<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
    <front>
        <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
            </publisher></journal-meta>
        <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PLCB-RA-0712R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390</article-id><article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
                    <subject>Cell Biology/Cell Signaling</subject>
                    <subject>Computational Biology/Signaling Networks</subject>
                    <subject>Developmental Biology/Cell Differentiation</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Computational Models of the Notch Network Elucidate Mechanisms of
                    Context-dependent Signaling</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Models of Notch Signaling</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Agrawal</surname>
                        <given-names>Smita</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
                        <sup>¤a</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Archer</surname>
                        <given-names>Colin</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">
                        <sup>¤b</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Schaffer</surname>
                        <given-names>David V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Department of Chemical Engineering, University of California Berkeley,
                    Berkeley, California, United States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Department of Bioengineering, University of California Berkeley,
                    Berkeley, California, United States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff3">
                <label>3</label>
                <addr-line>Helen Wills Neuroscience Institute, University of California Berkeley,
                    Berkeley, California, United States of America</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Miyano</surname>
                        <given-names>Satoru</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <role>Editor</role>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Tokyo, Japan</aff><author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">schaffer@berkeley.edu</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn1">
                    <label>¤a</label>
                    <p>Current address: Institute of Human Genetics, University of Minnesota Twin
                        Cities, Minneapolis, Minnesota, United States of America</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="current-aff" id="fn2">
                    <label>¤b</label>
                    <p>Current address: Australian Institute of Bioengineering and Nanotechnology,
                        The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="con">
                    <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SA DVS. Performed the experiments:
                        SA. Analyzed the data: SA. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SA
                        CA. Wrote the paper: SA.</p>
                </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict">
                <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
            </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2009</year>
            </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2009</year>
            </pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e1000390</elocation-id><history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2008</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2009</year>
                </date>
            </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Agrawal et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
                <p>The Notch signaling pathway controls numerous cell fate decisions during
                    development and adulthood through diverse mechanisms. Thus, whereas it functions
                    as an oscillator during somitogenesis, it can mediate an all-or-none cell fate
                    switch to influence pattern formation in various tissues during development.
                    Furthermore, while in some contexts continuous Notch signaling is required, in
                    others a transient Notch signal is sufficient to influence cell fate decisions.
                    However, the signaling mechanisms that underlie these diverse behaviors in
                    different cellular contexts have not been understood. <italic>Notch1</italic>
                    along with two downstream transcription factors <italic>hes1</italic> and
                        <italic>RBP-Jk</italic> forms an intricate network of positive and negative
                    feedback loops, and we have implemented a systems biology approach to
                    computationally study this gene regulation network. Our results indicate that
                    the system exhibits bistability and is capable of switching states at a critical
                    level of Notch signaling initiated by its ligand Delta in a particular range of
                    parameter values. In this mode, transient activation of Delta is also capable of
                    inducing prolonged high expression of Hes1, mimicking the
                    “ON” state depending on the intensity and duration of the
                    signal. Furthermore, this system is highly sensitive to certain model parameters
                    and can transition from functioning as a bistable switch to an oscillator by
                    tuning a single parameter value. This parameter, the transcriptional repression
                    constant of <italic>hes1</italic>, can thus qualitatively govern the behavior of
                    the signaling network. In addition, we find that the system is able to dampen
                    and reduce the effects of biological noise that arise from stochastic effects in
                    gene expression for systems that respond quickly to Notch signaling.</p>
                <p>This work thus helps our understanding of an important cell fate control system
                    and begins to elucidate how this context dependent signaling system can be
                    modulated in different cellular settings to exhibit entirely different
                    behaviors.</p>
            </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
                <title>Author Summary</title>
                <p>The Notch signaling pathway is an evolutionarily conserved signaling system that
                    is involved in various cell fate decisions, both during development of an
                    organism and during adulthood. While the same core circuit functions in various
                    different cellular contexts, it has experimentally been shown to elicit varied
                    behaviors and responses. On the one hand, it functions as a cellular oscillator
                    critical for somitogenesis, whereas in other situations, it can function as a
                    cell fate switch to pattern developing tissue, for example in the
                        <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye. Furthermore, malfunctioning of Notch
                    signaling is implicated in various cancers. To better understand the underlying
                    mechanisms that allow the network to function distinctly in different contexts,
                    we have mathematically modeled the behavior of the Notch network, encompassing
                    the Notch gene along with two of its downstream effector transcription factors,
                    which together form a network of positive and negative feedback loops. Our
                    results indicate that the qualitative and quantitative behavior of the system
                    can readily be tuned based on key parameters to reflect its multiple roles.
                    Furthermore, our results provide insights into alterations in the signaling
                    system that lead to malfunction and hence disease, which could be used to
                    identify potential drug targets for therapy.</p>
            </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Helen Wills Neuroscience Institute and LDRD
                    3668DS. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis,
                    decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
                <page-count count="14"/>
            </counts></article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="s1">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Cells continuously receive signals from their microenvironments – including
                factors present in the extracellular matrix, soluble media, and surrounding cells
                – which collectively influence cell function and behavior via activating
                intracellular signal transduction and gene regulation networks. These networks
                generally involve complex, nonlinear interactions of proteins, such as
                phosphorylation cascades (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Denhardt1">[1]</xref>) and second messenger
                signaling systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Keltner1">[2]</xref>, whose structures feature positive and negative
                feedback loops, feed-forward interactions, signal amplification, and cross-talk with
                other pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Weng1">[3]</xref>. Mathematical models of these interactions are
                therefore very insightful or even necessary avenues to analyze and understand the
                regulation of cell behavior, as the properties of these networks can exceed an
                intuitive understanding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Klipp1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Obrink1">[6]</xref>.</p>
            <p>Notch is a signaling system required for numerous critical cell fate specification
                events during the development of the nervous system, hematopoietic system, eye, and
                skin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Carthew1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Weinmaster1">[11]</xref>. The receptor for
                this pathway is the single pass transmembrane protein Notch that, when bound by its
                ligands Delta or Jagged, undergoes a series of cleavage events to release its
                intracellular domain (NICD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-ArtavanisTsakonas1">[9]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Greenwald1">[12]</xref>.
                This NICD then translocates into the nucleus and acts as a transcriptional
                upregulator of target genes, including members of the <italic>hes</italic> family,
                through its interaction with the transcription factor RBP-Jκ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lu1">[13]</xref>. In mammals
                there are four different Notch proteins (Notch1-4) and 5 ligands (Delta 1, 3, and 4
                and Jagged 1 and 2). For this study, we have focused primarily on the Notch1
                signaling pathway.</p>
            <p>In its role as a critical regulator of cell fate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Carthew1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Weinmaster1">[11]</xref>,
                Notch has been known to function via lateral inhibition and induction mechanisms to
                create fine-grained patterns in undifferentiated cells, a process required for
                proper boundary formation and differentiation of various tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Cornell1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Brooker1">[15]</xref>. It
                can also function as a binary cell fate switch, for example during differentiation
                of the epidermis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Blanpain1">[16]</xref> and endodermal epithelium of the gut <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Matsuda1">[17]</xref>, to
                promote differentiation of one cell type from precursor cells at the expense of
                another. Furthermore, in some cases continuous Notch activity is not required for
                cell fate specification. For example, transient Delta-Notch signaling has been shown
                to be sufficient to induce T-cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lefort1">[18]</xref> and NK cell differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Carotta1">[19]</xref> from their respective
                precursor cells, and can induce an irreversible switch to gliogenesis in neural
                crest stem cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Morrison1">[20]</xref>. Notch signaling also occurs only transiently in
                many instances during the development of <italic>Drosophila</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hooper1">[21]</xref>,
                zebrafish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Appel1">[22]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Appel2">[23]</xref>, and mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bettenhausen1">[24]</xref>. It was also
                recently shown that human embryonic stem cells (hESCs) require activation of Notch
                signaling to form the progeny of all three embryonic germ layers, and subsequent
                transient Notch signaling enhanced generation of hematopoietic cells from committed
                hESCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Yu1">[25]</xref>.
                The mechanisms by which a short Notch signaling pulse can permanently switch cell
                fate are not elucidated.</p>
            <p>The Notch system has also been shown to function as an oscillator. Specifically, the
                expression levels of members of the <italic>hes</italic> family, a group of
                downstream Notch target genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Pourquie1">[26]</xref>, have been shown to oscillate with a 2 hour
                periodicity in some systems during development, which for example aids in
                somitogenesis (i.e. the patterning of somites) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Saga1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jouve1">[29]</xref>. Hes1
                protein and mRNA concentrations have also been observed to oscillate with an
                approximate 2 hr time period upon serum starvation in various cultured cell lines
                including myoblasts, fibroblasts, and neuroblastoma cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>. Furthermore,
                oscillations in the Notch network have been proposed to be important in maintaining
                neural progenitor cells in an undifferentiated state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Shimojo1">[31]</xref>. Finally, there is
                evidence that such oscillations may also afford cells the opportunity to repeatedly
                test for the continued existence of a signal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lahav1">[32]</xref>, thereby increasing
                cellular response sensitivity and flexibility by allowing the cell to integrate the
                results of many periodical evaluations of the signal before making an ultimate cell
                fate decision.</p>
            <p>The Delta-Notch signaling system has been previously modeled to elucidate its role in
                fine-grained pattern formation through the action of lateral inhibition and
                induction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Collier1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Webb1">[35]</xref>. Collier <italic>et
                al.</italic> developed a simple 2-parameter model that focuses on pattern formation
                due to feedback inhibition between adjacent cells via Delta-Notch signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Collier1">[33]</xref>. Other
                models build upon this simple model by adding more molecular detail at the
                intercellular level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Wearing1">[34]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Webb1">[35]</xref>. In addition, several studies have focused on
                trying to understand the underlying mechanism of Notch system oscillations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lahav1">[32]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Monk1">[36]</xref>, where a
                Hes1 negative feedback loop composed of Hes1 protein repressing
                <italic>hes1</italic> transcription, likely plays a central role <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Takebayashi1">[37]</xref>.
                Delays related to transcription and translation were also proposed to be important
                for the observed oscillations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jensen1">[38]</xref>. However, while several models have thus been
                proposed and have yielded important insights into this system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Monk1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jensen1">[38]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Heron1">[40]</xref>, they
                have focused exclusively on Hes1 and not analyzed its interactions with other
                signaling proteins in the Notch system. Additionally, all these models focus on a
                particular aspect or mode of Notch signaling (e.g. lateral inhibition or
                oscillation) but do not yet address how complex, alternative behaviors could arise
                from the same network.</p>
            <p>Here we mathematically model the Notch signaling system to analyze how the same
                network is capable of functioning as a cell fate switch or an oscillator in
                different biological contexts. This model, which includes the regulation of the
                    <italic>notch1-RBP-Jk-hes1</italic> gene circuit, predicts that the Notch1-Hes1
                system acts as a bistable switch in certain regions of parameter space, where Hes1
                levels can change by 1–2 orders of magnitude as a function of the input
                Delta signal. In addition, it predicts that a transient pulse of a high level of
                Delta is capable of inducing high Hes1 expression levels for a duration that would
                be sufficient to induce a cell fate switch. Moreover, the model elucidates how the
                network can be ‘tuned’ to function in different regimes, either
                as an oscillator or a cell fate switch, by changing a key parameter. Finally, low
                numbers of reactants can lead to significant statistical fluctuations in molecule
                numbers and reaction rates, making cells intrinsically noisy biochemical reactors
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Rao1">[41]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Weinberger1">[42]</xref>. Stochastic
                simulations of the Notch system, which enable the analysis of the effect of
                biological noise in the system arising due to stochastic variations in gene
                expression, reveal that for systems that respond quickly to Notch signaling, the
                network is able to dampen the effects of this biological noise and function in a
                manner similar to what is predicted by the deterministic model. In summary, the
                model enables analysis of the different behavioral responses of the Notch signaling
                network observed over a broad spectrum of signaling inputs and parameter values and
                can be further expanded to study Notch signaling in numerous contexts.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>We developed a model of Notch signaling to investigate how this system can function
                as either an oscillator or as a simple binary switch capable of responding to steady
                state or transient inputs. Brief experimental work revealed that the
                <italic>notch1</italic> promoter is positively upregulated by its gene product and
                is downregulated by Hes1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s002">Fig. S1</xref>). We thus examined the behavior of the
                    <italic>notch1</italic>, <italic>RBP-Jκ</italic>, and
                <italic>hes1</italic> genes, which form a complex set of regulatory feedback loops
                    (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). A deterministic
                model composed of a system of differential equations was developed to analyze
                dynamic changes in the levels of the network constituents. However, since the
                concentrations of some of the species were low, stochastic simulations were also
                conducted to examine whether noise in the levels of the network components could
                significantly impact system behavior, as noise has the potential to undermine the
                fidelity of cell fate choices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Rao1">[41]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Gillespie1">[43]</xref>.</p>
            <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g001" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g001</object-id>
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Schematic of the Notch1-RBP-Jκ-Hes1 signaling network.</title>
                    <p>(A) Each arrow represents a term or event in the differential equation model
                        including transcription, translation, mRNA and protein degradation, nuclear
                        import, TF binding, receptor-ligand binding and receptor processing. (B)
                        Schematic of the positive and negative feedback loops of the
                        Notch1-RBP-Jk-Hes1 network. (-|) represents repression and (-&gt;)
                        represents activation of target genes.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <sec id="s2a">
                <title>Deterministic Model Development</title>
                <p>A set of differential equations was developed to track changes in the
                    concentrations of various species in the nucleus and cytoplasm of a cell as a
                    function of time following activation of Notch by its ligand. The cell is
                    modeled as a 10 µm diameter sphere with a 5 µm diameter
                    nucleus. Numerous processes were modeled as terms in the differential equation
                    system, including transcription, translation, transport, degradation or - in the
                    case of Notch - receptor cleavage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>). As examples, the three equations
                    tracking the Hes1 cytoplasmic mRNA, Hes1 cytoplasmic protein and Hes1 nuclear
                    protein concentrations are given by:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>The rate of change (in units of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) of the cytoplasmic mRNA concentration of Hes1 is given by the
                    difference in the rates of it transcription and degradation. R<sub>fHcm</sub> is
                    the transcription rate of <italic>hes1</italic> mRNA in the nucleus. We assume
                    instantaneous export of mRNA to the cytoplasm. A factor of 7 is included to take
                    into account the dilution due to export to the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>).
                        k<sub>dHcm</sub>, k<sub>dHcp</sub>, and k<sub>dHnp</sub> denote the
                    degradation constants for the <italic>hes1</italic> mRNA (Hcm), cytoplasmic
                    protein (Hcp), and nuclear protein (Hnp), respectively, which are assumed to
                    undergo first order degradation kinetics. k<sub>trHc</sub> denotes the
                    translation constant (min<sup>−1</sup>) for conversion of cytoplasmic
                        <italic>hes1</italic> mRNA into cytoplasmic protein. Transcriptional and
                    translational delay times are incorporated into the model, as these are
                    processes that inherently involve delays between initiation and the production
                    of a molecule of mRNA or protein, as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jensen1">[38]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Barrio1">[44]</xref>.
                    Thus, the translation of Hes1 protein is based on the delayed
                    <italic>hes1</italic> mRNA concentration H<sub>cmD</sub> (delayed by time TpHc,
                    the average time for translation of Hes1), which is the concentration of mRNA
                    present when the process of translation was initiated instead of the
                    concentration at the present time. k<sub>niHcp</sub> denotes the nuclear import
                    rate in units of min<sup>−1</sup>. A dilution factor of 7 is again
                    used to incorporate differences in nuclear and cytoplasmic volumes.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2b">
                <title>The <italic>hes1</italic> Promoter</title>
                <p>The transcription rates for <italic>notch1</italic>, <italic>hes1</italic>, and
                        <italic>RBP-Jκ</italic> are based on the states of their respective
                    promoters. Previous promoter analysis has been complemented with Genomatix Suite
                    Gene2Promoter transcription factor (TF) binding site prediction software to
                    identify potential TF binding sites in the promoters of the three genes in the
                    model.</p>
                <p>Takebayashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Takebayashi1">[37]</xref> observed that <italic>hes1</italic>
                    transcription is repressed by its own gene product through Hes1 protein binding
                    to sites in the <italic>hes1</italic> promoter termed N-boxes. Through a series
                    of binding and transcriptional activity assays, the study determined that Hes1
                    bound strongly to three N-boxes found upstream of the transcriptional start site
                    and repressed transcription of the <italic>hes1</italic> mRNA up to 40-fold.
                    Also, while the work concluded that there was a synergistic rather than an
                    additive effect of the N-box binding dependent repression of gene expression,
                    further mathematical analysis has indicated that there is no or very weak
                    synergy among the different binding sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">[45]</xref>. Several positive
                    regulatory regions were also found in the <italic>hes1</italic> promoter, and it
                    was also shown to have two adjacent RBP-Jκ binding sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jarriault1">[46]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Brou1">[47]</xref>. Thus, we have
                    modeled the <italic>hes1</italic> promoter to have three equivalent N-boxes
                    where the Hes1 protein can bind and repress transcription, as well as two
                    equivalent RBP-Jκ sites. The presence of all other positive regulators
                    of transcription is lumped into a constant basal rate of transcription.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2c">
                <title>The <italic>notch1</italic> Promoter</title>
                <p>As it has not been extensively investigated, the <italic>notch1</italic> promoter
                    sequence was analyzed in the Gene2Promoter software. One putative Hes1 site
                    (N-box) and two putative RBP-Jκ sites were found in the ∼1 kb
                        <italic>notch1</italic> promoter analyzed. This may imply that
                        <italic>notch1</italic> is both positively and negatively regulated by its
                    own gene product. To test this, a transcriptional activity experiment using the
                    dual luciferase assay system was conducted. The promoter of murine
                        <italic>notch1</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis1">[48]</xref>
                    was used to drive expression of hRluc cDNA (Renilla luciferase). Co-transfection
                    studies with plasmids expressing RBP-Jκ, NICD, Hes1, and dNHes1 (a
                    dominant negative form of Hes1) indeed demonstrated that the
                    <italic>notch1</italic> promoter is regulated negatively by Hes1 and
                    RBP-Jκ in the absence of NICD but is positively regulated by NICD in the
                    presence of RBP-Jκ (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s002">Fig. S1</xref>).
                    The <italic>notch1</italic> promoter was modeled with two RBP-Jκ sites
                    and one N-box.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2d">
                <title>The <italic>RBP-Jκ</italic> Promoter</title>
                <p>A 418 bp sequence upstream of the <italic>RBP-Jκ</italic> gene as
                    characterized by Amakawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Amakawa1">[49]</xref> was analyzed in
                    the Gene2Promoter software for TF binding sites of interest. Three potential
                    Hes1 binding sites and three potential RBP-Jκ sites were found. Thus,
                    the <italic>RBP-Jκ</italic> gene also potentially undergoes
                    autoregulation under Notch signaling, and a three N-box, three RBP-Jκ
                    site model was utilized.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2e">
                <title>Modeling the Transcription Term</title>
                <p>As discussed above, all three promoters have one or more binding sites for both
                    Hes1 (the N-box) and RBP-Jκ. It is assumed that Hes1 can bind and
                    repress transcription of the corresponding promoter only in its homodimer form,
                    and the dimerization reaction is assumed to be at steady state over timescales
                    of protein transcription, translation and import, driven by mass action kinetics
                    such that the concentration of the dimer is given by:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>Where, K<sub>aHp</sub> is the association equilibrium constant
                    for the dimerization reaction. Similarly, the time scales of transcription
                    factor binding to and dissociation from the promoter elements are also assumed
                    to be much faster than those of gene transcription and protein synthesis, such
                    that binding to the promoter is at pseudo steady state. In addition, it is
                    assumed that NICD can bind only when an RBP-Jk protein is bound to its site on
                    the promoter, and that this NICD binding converts RBP-Jκ from a
                    transcriptional repressor to an activator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lu1">[13]</xref>.</p>
                <p>The level of promoter activation (i.e. rate of mRNA synthesis) is modeled by an
                    approach termed BEWARE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Gilman1">[50]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lai1">[51]</xref>, in which the probabilities of a promoter
                    being in any one of its many possible states are calculated based on the
                    relative concentrations of the three transcription factors (Hes1, RBP-Jκ
                    and NICD), and their respective DNA binding affinities, using equilibrium
                    binding equations. The level of activation of the promoter is then given by: <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where, P[P<sub>i</sub>] is the probability
                    of the promoter being in state i, and v<sub>i</sub> is the activation rate of
                    gene transcription associated to the promoter being in that state i. When the
                    promoter is empty, the gene activation rate is assumed to be the basal
                    transcription rate (V<sub>b</sub>) for that promoter. When a Hes1 dimer is bound
                    to an N-box, the rate is reduced by a factor r<sub>N</sub> that takes into
                    account the repressive effect of the Hes1 transcription factor, and when
                    RBP-Jκ is bound, the rate is reduced by a factor r<sub>R</sub>.
                    Furthermore, when the promoter is in its maximally activated state with the NICD
                    bound to the RBP-Jκ and no Hes1 dimers bound, the activation rate is
                    assumed to be at its maximum and is given by
                    (V<sub>max</sub>+V<sub>b</sub>). In the case of multiple RBP-Jκ
                    binding sites, an additional factor t<sub>c</sub> (&lt;1) is used to account
                    for states where not all RBP-Jκ sites bind NICD to represent the
                    decrease from the maximum possible activation rate. For a detailed expression of
                    transcription rates please refer to Supplemental Materials (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>).</p>
                <p>Although explicit parameters have been included to account for cooperative
                    binding for Hes1 dimers to multiple N-boxes and for RBP-Jκ binding
                    (cooperativity factors C<sub>n</sub>, C<sub>r</sub> and C<sub>nr</sub> - please
                    refer to <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t001">Table 1</xref> for model
                    parameters), they have been set to 1 for these simulations, as recent work
                    suggests there is very little if any cooperative effect in Hes1 binding to
                    N-boxes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">[45]</xref>. Finally, it is assumed that each mRNA produces a
                    fixed number of proteins, i.e. mRNA dynamics have been neglected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Gilman1">[50]</xref>.</p>
                <table-wrap id="pcbi-1000390-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
                        <title>Parameter values used for the models.</title>
                    </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000390-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                        <colgroup span="1">
                            <col align="left" span="1" width="99*"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1" width="99*"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1" width="59*"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1" width="141*"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Symbol</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Degradation constant of Hes1 protein
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdHcp, kdHnp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0315</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Degradation constant of Hes1 mRNA
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdHcm</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.029</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Degradation constant of RBP-Jk protein
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdRcp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00231</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Meir1">[82]</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Degradation constant of RBP-JK mRNA
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdRcm</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0075</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Meir1">[82]</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Degradation constant of full-length Notch1 protein
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdNp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Logeat1">[54]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Degradation constant of NICD protein
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdNcp,kdNnp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0014 or 0.00385</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Foltz1">[55]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Degradation of Notch mRNA
                                    (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdNm</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0058</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Kessler1">[83]</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cooperativity factor for Hes1-DNA binding</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cn</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cooperativity factor for RBP-Jk DNA binding</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cr</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cooperativity factor for RBP-Jk Hes1 DNA binding</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cnr</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate of protein translation from Hes1 mRNA
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KtrHc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">[45]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate of protein translation from RBP-Jk mRNA
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KtrRc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate of protein translation from Notch1 mRNA
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KtrN</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RBP-Jk DNA association constant
                                    (M<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kr</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.23×10<sup>8</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lam1">[84]</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hes1 DNA association constant
                                    (M<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kn</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2×10<sup>8</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RBP-Jk NICD association constant
                                        (M<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ka</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1×10<sup>8</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hes1 dimer association constant
                                    (M<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KaHp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1×10<sup>9</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transcriptional time delay for Hes1 (min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TmHc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">[52]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Translational time delay for Hes1 (min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TpHc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.35</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">[52]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transcriptional time delay for RBP-Jk (min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TmRc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">[52]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Translational time delay for RBP-Jk (min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TpRc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">[52]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transcriptional time delay for Notch1 (min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TmNc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">[52]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Translational time delay for Notch1 (min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TpNc</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">[52]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Basal transcriptional rate for Hes1 (M/min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vbh</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14×10<sup>−10</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">[45]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Basal transcriptional rate for RBP-Jk (M/min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vbr</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3×10<sup>−11</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Basal transcriptional rate for Notch1 (M/min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vbn</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23×10<sup>−11</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maximal transcriptional rate for Hes1 (M/min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vmaxh</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5×10<sup>−10</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Cinquin1">[53]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maximal transcriptional rate for RBP-Jk (M/min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vmaxr</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2×10<sup>−10</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maximal transcriptional rate for Notch1 (M/min)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vmaxn</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5×10<sup>−11</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nuclear import rate of Hes1 protein
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kniHcp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Watai1">[85]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nuclear import rate of RBP-Jk protein
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kniRcp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Watai1">[85]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nuclear import rate of NICD protein
                                        (min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kniNcp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Watai1">[85]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NICD generation constant upon Delta binding
                                        (M<sup>−1</sup> min<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KfNcp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6×10<sup>7</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Repression constant of Hes1 bound to N-box</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rNbox</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>, Text</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Repression constant of RBP-Jk alone bound to
                                    promoter</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rR</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Text</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2f">
                <title>Parameter Determination</title>
                <p>Experimentally determined values for half-lives of proteins and mRNA, association
                    and dissociation constants of proteins to their respective DNA binding sites,
                    dimerization constants, and protein translation and transcription rates have
                    been used when possible (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t001">Table
                    1</xref>). These values are often not available for the exact species of
                    interest; however, the best available estimates based on similar protein classes
                    are used wherever applicable as the starting point. The time delays for
                    transcription and translation for each of the three genes are calculated as
                    previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">[52]</xref> and are detailed in the Supplemental
                    Materials (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text
                        S1</xref>). 4.5 transcripts per minute <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">[45]</xref> and 20 transcripts
                    per minute <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Cinquin1">[53]</xref> were used as initial estimates for
                        <italic>hes1</italic> basal and maximum transcription rates respectively.
                    The transcription rates for <italic>RBP-Jκ</italic> and
                    <italic>notch1</italic> were then determined from these estimates and the
                    estimates of their minimum transcription times (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>).</p>
                <p>The degradation rates for the Hes1 protein and mRNA were determined
                    experimentally by Hirata et al. in fibroblasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>. They observed
                    similar values in other cultured cell types including myoblasts, neuroblastomas,
                    and teratocarcinomas. Pulse chase experiments of Logeat et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Logeat1">[54]</xref>
                    were used to assess the degradation rates for the full-length Notch1 protein,
                    and an estimate of Notch1 protein half-life of ∼40 minutes was derived.</p>
                <p>GSK3β has been shown to affect the stability of NICD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Foltz1">[55]</xref>.
                    Although there are conflicting results as to whether GSK3β helps to
                    stabilize <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Foltz1">[55]</xref> or destabilize the cleaved NICD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Espinosa1">[56]</xref>,
                    our experimental results show that GSK3β is essential for the NICD
                    regulation of neural stem cell differentiation into astrocytes (Agrawal, Ngai,
                    and Schaffer, manuscript in preparation). Furthermore, we show that Notch1
                    signaling upregulates the expression of GSK3β in these cells. Thus, the
                    effect of GSK3β is incorporated into the model by increasing the
                    half-life of NICD from 3 to 8 hrs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Foltz1">[55]</xref> above a threshold
                    concentration of Hes1 (which is assumed to directly or indirectly regulate the
                    expression of GSK3β). This increased NICD half-life does not however
                    change the qualitative behavior of the Hes1 switch (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s004">Fig. S3A</xref>).</p>
                <p>The repression constant of Hes1 dimer bound to an N-box (r<sub>Nbox</sub>) is
                    estimated from the results of Takebayashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Takebayashi1">[37]</xref> that show that
                    in the presence of three N-boxes, transcription is repressed by ∼40
                    fold. This yields a repression value of ∼0.3 per N-box (Please refer to
                    Supplemental Materials (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>) for details). Since there are no
                    reliable estimates of the NICD generation constant upon Delta binding
                        (k<sub>fNcp</sub>), a lumped parameter of this constant with the Delta
                    concentration is used to report the strength of the Delta signal
                    (k<sub>fNcp</sub>*Delp). The initial parameters for which the
                    experimentally determined values are not accurately available were later
                    subjected to sensitivity analysis (See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">results</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2g">
                <title>Computational Methods and Initial Conditions</title>
                <p>The differential equations described in the model were solved (with parameter
                    values given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t001">Table 1</xref>)
                    using Berkeley Madonna 8.3.11 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.berkeleymadonna.com" xlink:type="simple">www.berkeleymadonna.com</ext-link>) with the Runge Kutta 4 module at a step
                    size of 1 min. To arrive at realistic initial conditions for the model, the
                    initial concentrations of all species were set to 0 with zero Delta signal, and
                    the simulations were run until the various species attained steady state
                    concentration levels. These steady state values (listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t002">Table 2</xref>) were then used as
                    the initial conditions for subsequent simulations. For the various experiments,
                    the system was run for 750 minutes without stimulation with the Delta ligand to
                    attain a basal steady state, and the Delta concentration was then increased to
                    different levels to initiate Notch1 signaling. Simulations were run either with
                    a constant Delta signal throughout or with varying duration pulses of the Delta
                    signal. The system was simulated for a duration of 5,000–10,000
                    minutes (∼3.5–7 days), as neural progenitor stem cells have
                    been previously shown to undergo differentiation upon Notch activation in
                    3–5 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Tanigaki1">[57]</xref>). Longer simulations up to 50,000 minutes
                    were conducted when required to confirm Hes1 had reached steady state levels.</p>
                <table-wrap id="pcbi-1000390-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
                        <title>Initial conditions for deterministic and stochastic models.</title>
                    </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000390-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                        <colgroup span="1">
                            <col align="left" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Species</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Deterministic Model (mol/l)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stochastic Model (# of molecules/cell)</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hcm (Hes1 mRNA)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.34 * 10<sup>−12</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hcp (cytoplasmic Hes1 protein)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.48 * 10<sup>−10</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hnp (nuclear Hes1 protein)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.30 * 10<sup>−9</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rcm (RBP-Jκ mRNA)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44 * 10<sup>−12</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rcp (cytoplasmic RBP-Jκ protein)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.53 * 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rnp (nuclear RBP-Jκ protein)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07* 10<sup>−8</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">422</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nm (Notch1 mRNA)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66 * 10<sup>−11</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Np (Notch1 protein)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.74 * 10<sup>−10</sup></td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">269</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ncp (cytoplasmic NICD)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nnp (nuclear NICD)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2h">
                <title>Stochastic Model Development</title>
                <p>Since the levels of several protein species in the deterministic model
                    simulations were very low (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t002">Table
                        2</xref>), at the level of tens of molecules per cell, assumptions of mass
                    action kinetics and pseudo steady state may not hold true, and stochastic
                    effects may play an important role in the dynamics of the signaling network
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Rao1">[41]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hasty1">[58]</xref>. To analyze whether
                    noise in protein and mRNA concentrations would impact the dynamics of the
                    system, a stochastic simulation of the model using the Gillespie algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Gillespie1">[43]</xref>
                    was implemented in C++ (code available upon request). To relax
                    the assumptions of mass action kinetics and pseudo steady state, we explicitly
                    simulated every reaction step, making a total of 299 reactions. For example,
                    every interaction between a transcription factor and a promoter was modeled as a
                    discrete reaction in the simulation. The τ-leap method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Gillespie2">[59]</xref>
                    was also incorporated into the algorithm to accelerate the stochastic
                    simulations and increase their efficiency.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec id="s3a">
                <title>The Notch1-Hes1 Network as a Bistable Switch</title>
                <p>The response of the Notch1-RBP-Jκ-Hes1 system to a step change in an
                    input Delta signal was analyzed. Simulations were initiated using the steady
                    state levels of the different species in the absence of any external Delta (also
                    listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t002">Table 2</xref>), and at
                    t = 750 minutes a Delta signal was applied.
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g002">Fig. 2A</xref> demonstrates
                    that when a low input Delta stimulus is applied, the Hes1 concentration settles
                    to a correspondingly low steady state value. However, when the input Delta
                    signal was increased (10-fold), Hes1 shows a rapid increase to a new, 20-fold
                    higher steady state value. Further steady state analysis at a range of input
                    Delta levels and initial conditions reveals that the system exhibits
                    bistability. At low levels of Delta signal, basal levels of Hes1 are maintained
                    in the cell (“OFF” state), but as the Delta signal strength
                    is increased beyond a threshold level, it stimulates the production of Hes1,
                    which is then maintained at high levels (“ON” state) through
                    the concerted regulation of the Notch1-RBP-Jκ-Hes1 network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Bistability
                    – which has previously been proposed as an advantageous mechanism to
                    mediate an unambiguous cell fate switch, including in stem cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lai1">[51]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Saha1">[60]</xref>
                    – is evident within an intermediate range of Delta signal values
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g002" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g002</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 2</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Bistability in Notch signaling.</title>
                        <p>(A) Deterministic Hes1 trajectories as a function of time for two
                            different strengths of Delta signals given as a product of the Delta
                            concentration and the rate constant of formation of NICD upon
                            Delta-Notch binding
                            (kfNcp*Delp = kDelp). These
                            deterministic simulations were initiated using steady state values of
                            the system under no Delta signal and at
                            t = 750 minutes (indicated by vertical
                            arrow) the input Delta signal was applied. (B) Hysteresis in the
                            Notch1-Hes1 network, where Hes1 concentration can attain two possible
                            steady states for an intermediate range of Delta inputs. The point of
                            switching depends on whether the Delta signal is increasing or
                            decreasing.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3b">
                <title>Network Sensitivity to Biological Noise</title>
                <p>The initial numbers of some protein and mRNA species in the system were in the
                    range of tens of molecules per cell (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t002">Table 2</xref>), such that stochastic fluctuations
                    in individual species may impact the dynamics of the network. In particular,
                    intracellular noise inherent in systems with small numbers of molecules and/or
                    slow biochemical reactions can randomize or undermine the
                    “accuracy” of cell fate choices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Rao1">[41]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hasty1">[58]</xref>. To analyze such
                    behavior, stochastic simulations based on the Gillespie algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Gillespie1">[43]</xref>,
                    distinct from the deterministic model, were developed. Steady state analysis
                    shows that at low, constant Delta signals, the Hes1 levels fluctuate about a low
                    mean value corresponding to the “OFF” state, as expected
                    (data not shown). However, if the Delta signal is increased to a level just
                    below the concentration at which the deterministic model would predict a switch
                    in state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>),
                    stochastic simulations reveal that noise in the network can induce some
                    trajectories to spontaneously switch states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). Analogous to results previously
                    observed in other systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lai1">[51]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Arkin1">[61]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hasty2">[62]</xref>,
                    noise thus undermines the bistable switch and induces spontaneous flipping
                    between states. Analysis of the time it takes the system to initially pass from
                    the lower to the upper state reveals that as the strength of the input signal is
                    increased, this average first passage time (FPT) decreases, and the percentage
                    of trajectories that change state increases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). However, this
                    “uncertainty” occurs within a narrow range of intermediate
                    Delta signal levels, and if this intermediate window is avoided, the system
                    effectively behaves deterministically.</p>
                <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g003" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g003</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 3</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Stochastic simulations demonstrate spontaneous
                            “OFF” to “ON” transitions.</title>
                        <p>(A) Representative stochastic Hes1 trajectories as a function of time
                            after application of a constant Delta stimulus at 750 min at levels just
                            below “ON” levels predicted by the deterministic
                            model. Some Hes1 trajectories remain at low levels
                            (“OFF” state) while others randomly switch state to
                            higher levels (“ON” state). (B) First passage time
                            (FPT) of stochastic trajectories for passage from
                            “OFF” to “ON” state as a
                            function of Delta signal strength in the bistable region. The mean and
                            standard deviation of 40–60 runs in each case are plotted. The
                            percentage of trajectories that switched to “ON”
                            state under the given Delta signal is indicated below each data point.
                            All points except those connected by the same letter (A) are
                            statistically distinct (p&lt;0.01, 2-tail t-test).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p>In addition, “ON” to “OFF” transitions
                    were simulated by first stimulating with a high Delta signal for 4000 minutes to
                    induce high Hes1 expression levels. When Delta was then reduced to levels that
                    were in the predicted bistable region based on the deterministic model, the
                    system maintained high expression levels of Hes1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>), as anticipated from the
                    deterministic results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g002">Fig.
                    2B</xref>). Contrary to what was expected based on the deterministic model,
                    however, when the Delta signal was instead reduced to zero, some trajectories
                    remained in the high Hes1 expression (“ON”) state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). This indicates the
                    role of stochastics in potentiating high Hes1 expression levels even in the
                    absence of continued signal.</p>
                <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g004" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g004</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 4</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>The Notch system exhibits bistability under stochastic simulations.</title>
                        <p>(A) Hes1 stochastic trajectories are shown during high Delta levels for
                            4000 minutes, following which the Delta signal is brought down to levels
                            that failed to switch the state to “ON” when
                            provided for a prolonged duration
                                (kDelp = 4×10<sup>−4</sup>)
                            in the deterministic model. All the trajectories remain in the
                            “ON” state – corresponding to the region
                            of bistability seen in the deterministic simulations. (B) Hes1
                            stochastic trajectories are shown after application of a high Delta
                            signal for 4000 minutes, after which the Delta signal is brought down to
                            0. Some trajectories persist in the “ON” state.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3c">
                <title>Response of the System to Transient Delta Activation</title>
                <p>It has been shown for neural crest stem cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Morrison1">[20]</xref> that a transient
                    Notch signal is sufficient to induce cell differentiation. Also, there are
                    numerous situations where transient Notch-Delta signaling determines the fates
                    of immature cells, both in tissue culture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lefort1">[18]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Carotta1">[19]</xref>
                    and during organismal development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hooper1">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bettenhausen1">[24]</xref>. Under continuous Delta stimulation, the system
                    can attain high steady-state Hes1 expression levels, thus acting as a switch,
                    but we next wanted to examine whether transient Delta activation was also
                    capable of eliciting high Hes1 expression. We thus examined the dynamic response
                    of the system to transient activation of the Notch1 pathway upon variation in
                    the strength and duration of an applied Delta signal.</p>
                <p>When the system is stimulated for a short duration (10 minutes) with a moderate
                    strength Delta signal, the deterministic model predicts a transient peak in the
                    Hes1 expression that eventually decays to its low steady state value (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). However, the peak
                    expression of Hes1 continually increases with increasing input signal duration
                    up to ∼800 minutes, beyond which the maximum expression levels of Hes1
                    attained remain the same but the duration of prolonged high expression levels
                    progressively increases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g005">Fig.
                    5A</xref>). Similarly, as the input Delta signal strength is increased for a
                    constant pulse duration, the peak Hes1 concentrations attained also increase up
                    to a maximum value, after which a further increase in the signal strength only
                    increases the duration of high Hes1 levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). The cell is thus able to attain
                    high Hes1 expression either under prolonged low intensity Delta signaling or a
                    short burst of high intensity Delta signaling.</p>
                <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g005" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g005</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 5</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Both input Delta signal strength and duration affect the output Hes1
                            expression levels.</title>
                        <p>(A) Effect of Delta signal duration on the Hes1 expression levels: a
                            transient Delta signal of
                                kfNcp*Delp = 5×10<sup>−3</sup>
                            was provided in the deterministic model for varying amounts of time
                            ranging from 10 minutes to 3000 minutes, and the resulting Hes1
                            trajectories were simulated up to 15000 minutes. (B) The effect of Delta
                            signal strength on Hes1 expression: a transient Delta signal of varying
                            strengths (expressed as
                            kDelp = kfNcp*Delp
                                (min<sup>−1</sup>)) was provided in the deterministic
                            model for 100 minutes, and the resulting Hes1 were simulated up to 20000
                            minutes.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3d">
                <title>Stochastic Effects on Transient Delta Signaling</title>
                <p>We also examined the effect of stochastics on transient activation of the
                    network. Simulations were run using the parameter values as in the deterministic
                    model for various Delta pulse durations ranging from 10 minutes to 3000 minutes
                    and &gt;40 trajectories per input duration value were analyzed. For Delta
                    pulse durations of less than 500 minutes, the stochastic simulations followed
                    the prediction of the deterministic model (data not shown). However, for a
                    500-minute Delta pulse, even though the deterministic model predicts a transient
                    Hes1 peak that does not attain the maximum possible expression level, a small
                    percentage of the stochastic trajectories in fact did switch to the
                    “ON” state (corresponding to high Hes1 expression levels)
                    (data not shown). Also, as the duration of the Delta pulse is increased, the
                    percentage of trajectories that remain in the “ON” state for
                    the simulated 15,000 minutes progressively increases even though the
                    deterministic model predicts that the system would revert back to the
                    “OFF” state within that time. Furthermore, the average first
                    passage time (FPT) of the trajectories that do switch state increases as the
                    Delta pulse duration increases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). It is likely that for shorter Delta pulse durations, if the
                    system is to undergo the spontaneous “OFF” to
                    “ON” transition, it does so early, soon after the
                    application of the Delta signal. However, in the case of longer duration input
                    signals, the continued presence of the signal allows trajectories to switch
                    state even much later in the simulation, resulting in an apparently longer first
                    passage time. Collectively, these results imply that even for very short signal
                    pulse, a small fraction of a population of cells receiving a pulse of Delta
                    signal could switch their state due to stochastic effects.</p>
                <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g006" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g006</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 6</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>First passage time (FPT) for passage from “OFF”
                            to “ON” state as a function of Delta signal duration
                            in stochastic simulations.</title>
                        <p>The mean and standard deviation of &gt;20 runs in each case are
                            plotted. The percentage of trajectories that switched to the
                            “ON” state under the given Delta signal is indicated
                            below each data point. All points except those connected by the same
                            letter (A,B,C) are statistically distinct (p&lt;0.01, 2-tail
                            t-test).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3e">
                <title>Bifurcation Analysis</title>
                <p>A number of parameters in the model have not been directly experimentally
                    measured and were estimated from data available for similar protein classes in
                    different contexts, and we thus performed sensitivity analysis for all such
                    parameters by varying them individually through a broad range of values in the
                    deterministic model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t003">Table
                    3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s003">Fig.
                        S2</xref>). Although in most cases the qualitative behavior of the system
                    remained unchanged, the system did exhibit considerable sensitivity to specific
                    parameters, which were then subjected to further analysis. These include: the
                    half-life of NICD, the equilibrium binding constant of NICD with RBP-Jκ
                        (K<sub>a</sub>), the maximal transcription rates (V<sub>max</sub>), and the
                    repression constant of Hes1 (r<sub>Nbox</sub>). NICD has a long half-life of a
                    few hours under normal physiological conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Foltz1">[55]</xref>. However, our model
                    indicates that if the NICD half-life is drastically reduced, the system fails to
                    function as a switch and cannot express high levels of Hes1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s004">Fig. S3</xref>).
                    In addition, the equilibrium binding constant (K<sub>a</sub>) of NICD to
                    RBP-Jκ in the model is 10<sup>8</sup> M<sup>−1</sup>, but as
                        K<sub>a</sub> increases – denoting stronger interactions of NICD
                    with the promoter – bifurcation analysis demonstrates that the OFF-ON
                    transition occurs at accordingly lower values of the Delta signal
                    (k<sub>Delp</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g007">Fig.
                    7A</xref>). Similarly, increasing the maximal transcription rate of Hes1
                        (V<sub>maxh</sub>) to indicate a stronger promoter shifts the OFF-ON
                    transitions to lower Delta signal strengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g007" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g007</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 7</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Bifurcation Analysis.</title>
                        <p>(A) Bifurcation analysis of how the switching points vary with the
                            equilibrium binding constant (K<sub>a</sub>) of NICD to RBP-Jk. Stronger
                            interaction between NICD and RBP-Jk lowers the threshold of Delta signal
                            required to turn the system ON. (B) Bifurcation analysis of how the
                            switching points vary with the maximal transcription rate of Hes1
                                (V<sub>maxh</sub>). A higher maximal transcription rate, indicating
                            a stronger Hes1 promoter, also slightly shifts the region of bistability
                            towards lower Delta signal strengths.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="pcbi-1000390-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
                        <title>Summary of results of sensitivity analysis documenting the effect of
                            increasing parameter values on the threshold of Delta signal strength
                            required to switch the system state from OFF to ON.</title>
                    </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000390-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                        <colgroup span="1">
                            <col align="left" span="1" width="98*"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1" width="47*"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1" width="59*"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1" width="192*"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameter</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range of variation</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect on threshold Kdelp (Delta signal strength)
                                    with increasing parameter value</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Results</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ka</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10<sup>7</sup>–10<sup>9</sup>
                                        (M<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Decrease over 2 orders of magnitude; no qualitative
                                    effect</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vmaxh</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3–0.9 nM/min</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Slight decrease; no qualitative effect</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rNbox</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–1</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drastic qualitative change in behavior of the
                                    system</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g008">Fig. 8</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kn</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10<sup>7</sup>–10<sup>9</sup>
                                        (M<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Slight increase; no qualitative effect</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s003">Fig. S2A</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KaHp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10<sup>8</sup>–10<sup>10</sup>
                                        (M<sup>−1</sup>)</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Slight increase; no qualitative effect</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s003">Fig. S2B</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rR</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–0.5</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Slight decrease; no qualitative effect</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s003">Fig. S2C</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kdNcp, kdNnp</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001–0.04</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Increase over 2 orders of magnitude</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s004">Fig. S3</xref>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
                        <fn id="nt101">
                            <p>The system exhibits a shift in the region of bistability, thus
                                changing the sensitivity of the system to the Delta signal, but the
                                qualitative nature of the gene network in most cases remains the
                                same for a broad range of the parameter values.</p>
                        </fn>
                    </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3f">
                <title>The Degree of Repression by Hes1 Determines the Qualitative Nature of the
                    Cellular Response to Delta Stimuli</title>
                <p>Interestingly, the response of the deterministic model was most sensitive to the
                    extent to which Hes1 binding reduced or repressed expression of target genes
                        (r<sub>Nbox</sub>). As the Hes1 repression constant (r<sub>Nbox</sub>) is
                    progressively decreased (or the repressive strength of Hes1 progressively
                    increased) from 0.3 to 0.1, the final steady state concentrations of Hes1
                    progressively decrease for a given level of Delta signaling (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s005">Fig. S4</xref>),
                    but the system continues to exhibit bistability. Intriguingly, as the value of
                        r<sub>Nbox</sub> is further decreased below 0.1, there is a dramatic
                    qualitative change in the response of the system. Specifically, the system
                    undergoes a bifurcation or transition from bistable to monostable behavior and
                    at such high repressive strengths is unable to attain high steady state Hes1
                    expression levels. Finally at very low values of r<sub>Nbox</sub>
                    (&lt;0.03), it once again undergoes a transition to a stable oscillatory
                    response where the Hes1 levels in the cell oscillate about a low mean steady
                    state value (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g008">Fig. 8A</xref>). A
                    phase plot of the response of the system with variable r<sub>Nbox</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g008">Fig. 8B</xref>) demonstrates how the
                    same gene network can transition from behaving as a bistable switch to being an
                    oscillator. The model thus elucidates the versatility of the system, where
                    tuning of a single key parameter can convert its behavior from a switch to a
                    clock. Previous <italic>hes1</italic> models showing sustained oscillations have
                    focused exclusively on the low r<sub>Nbox</sub> region (i.e.
                    r<sub>Nbox</sub> = 0) of such a phase plot
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Monk1">[36]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jensen1">[38]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bernard1">[39]</xref>.</p>
                <fig id="pcbi-1000390-g008" position="float">
                    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g008</object-id>
                    <label>Figure 8</label>
                    <caption>
                        <title>Effect of the repression constant of Hes1 (r<sub>Nbox</sub>) on the
                            Notch signaling network.</title>
                        <p>(A) At lower values or r<sub>Nbox</sub> (higher repression constants for
                            Hes1), the network predicts oscillations in Hes1 levels. As the value of
                                r<sub>Nbox</sub> is decreased to 0.03 and lower, the system exhibits
                            stable oscillations. (B) At a fixed Delta signal strength of
                                kDelp = 2×10<sup>−4</sup>,
                            as the r<sub>Nbox</sub> is progressively decreased, the response of Hes1
                            transitions from behaving as a bistable switch to a brief region of
                            monostability to an oscillator.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The Notch signaling system is an evolutionarily conserved network that functions in
                multiple organs to orchestrate cell fate specification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Maillard1">[63]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Beatus1">[65]</xref> in a
                context dependent manner. In some cases, it can function as a binary cell fate
                switch at the individual cell level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Blanpain1">[16]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Matsuda1">[17]</xref>, whereas in other
                situations cell-cell contact dependent Notch signaling can result in pattern
                formation in an array of cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Cornell1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Brooker1">[15]</xref>, and in yet other contexts it can function as a
                biological clock to govern pattern formation and differentiation during
                somitogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Saga1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jouve1">[29]</xref>. Although several
                additional components such as Fringe, Numb, and Presenilin can feed into and
                modulate the Notch signaling cascade, the core of the signaling pathway is
                relatively simple, where Notch acts as a membrane bound transcription factor that is
                activated by ligand binding and induces transcription of target <italic>hes</italic>
                genes via its interaction with the RBP-J<italic>k</italic> transcription factor
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Kopan1">[10]</xref>.
                However, the system can exhibit complex inter-regulation of its components. A better
                understanding of the functioning and regulation of this signaling system –
                and in particular how it exhibits diverse behaviors in different contexts
                – is valuable from a basic biology standpoint, in understanding how
                misregulation of the Notch signaling pathway can underlie disease, and from
                regenerative medicine viewpoint in therapeutic applications of stem cells.</p>
            <p>Mathematical modeling can provide valuable insights into the behavior of this gene
                regulatory circuit. Previous models have focused either on the level of cell-cell
                interactions to simulate the levels of Notch and Delta within adjacent cells and
                thereby analyze pattern formation based on levels of Delta and Notch levels in an
                array of cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Collier1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Webb1">[35]</xref>, or on the autoregulation
                of the <italic>hes</italic> genes in isolation to examine the oscillatory behavior
                of the gene circuit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Monk1">[36]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bernard1">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Heron1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Barrio1">[44]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">[45]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser2">[66]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser3">[67]</xref>. Here we have developed an integrative model that
                takes into account the intracellular signaling network downstream of Notch
                activation through its ligand Delta, leading to the activation of the
                <italic>hes1</italic> gene via interaction with RBP-Jκ. These three genes
                potentially regulate the transcription of one another (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s001">Text S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s002">Fig S1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Takebayashi1">[37]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Jarriault1">[46]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Brou1">[47]</xref>, forming
                a network of positive and negative feedback loops (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>). Our model begins to elucidate how a
                cell can potentially tune key system parameters in the resulting Notch1-Hes1 gene
                circuit to elicit diverse responses.</p>
            <p>The behavior of the system was most sensitive to the repression constant of Hes1,
                    r<sub>Nbox</sub>. The degree of Hes1 repression of a transcriptional target can
                be modulated by the presence of co-factors. For example, whereas Groucho can act as
                a transcriptional co-repressor for Hes1, Runx2 can act as a negative regulator of
                the repressive activity of Hes1 by interfering with the interaction of Hes1 with the
                TLE corepressors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-McLarren1">[68]</xref>. The repressive activity of Hes1 can also be
                further potentiated by its interaction with the winged-helix protein brain factor 1
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Yao1">[69]</xref>.
                Therefore, because different cells can express these factors to different extents,
                which can thereby modulate the value of r<sub>Nbox</sub>, the same gene circuit can
                be tuned to transduce an input Delta signal into qualitatively different responses
                – oscillation vs. switching.</p>
            <p>The model predicts that for low repressive strengths of Hes1
                (0.1&lt;r<sub>Nbox</sub>&lt;0.3), the Hes1 expression level functions as a
                bistable switch in response to varying the strength of the Delta signal, thereby
                providing an unambiguous fate switch that is insensitive to the presence of small
                fluctuations in input signal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g002">Fig.
                2</xref>). Hysteresis has been previously observed experimentally in other
                biological systems including the JNK signaling cascade <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bagowski1">[70]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bagowski2">[71]</xref> and the Cdc2 cell
                cycle regulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Pomerening1">[72]</xref>. Parameters such as K<sub>a</sub> (the
                association binding constant of NICD to RBP-Jκ) and V<sub>max</sub> (the
                maximal transcription rates) can shift the region of bistability, thus changing the
                sensitivity of the system to the Delta signal, but the qualitative nature of the
                gene network remains the same for a broad range of these parameter values. Positive
                feedback loops with nonlinearity can yield bistability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lai1">[51]</xref>, and both Notch1
                autoregulation and NICD-mediated conversion of RBP-Jκ into a transcriptional
                activator that in turn upregulates Notch1 expression constitute positive feedback
                loops that can drive this behavior.</p>
            <p>Since the numbers of some protein and mRNA species in the model were low (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000390-t002">Table 2</xref>), we developed a
                stochastic model to examine the effect of biological noise and cell-to-cell
                variability on the bistable response of the system to Delta signaling. Spontaneous
                OFF to ON switching of states was observed even in regions not predicted by the
                deterministic model. For example, as the Delta values are increased through the
                bistable range, the percentage of trajectories switching to the ON state increases,
                and the average FPT for these trajectories decreases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). These results are consistent with
                observations in other bistable systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hnggi1">[73]</xref>, and computationally in
                other signaling systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lai1">[51]</xref>, where noise has been shown to cause spontaneous
                switching of states. However, since the timescale of a system's downstream
                response to the Notch network's state varies from a few hours (for example
                during somitogenesis) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Giudicelli1">[74]</xref> to a few days (for example during stem cell
                differentiation) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Tanigaki1">[57]</xref>), the impact of stochastic noise on the fate
                switch will also be different in different contexts. Thus, for very low Delta
                signals, the average FPT is sufficiently high (&gt;110 hrs) such that the cell
                remains in the OFF state for prolonged periods of time and would be non-responsive
                to Delta signaling over timescales of a few hours, whereas in the case of a
                population of cells experiencing Notch signaling over a period of 4–6
                days, spontaneous switching could undermine the genetic switch and cause some cells
                to change fate at these low Delta input signals.</p>
            <p>While the system can behave as a switch in a particular range of parameters at steady
                state, there are also many situations in which Notch signaling is transient, yet is
                sufficient to induce a switch in cell fate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Lefort1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bettenhausen1">[24]</xref>.
                To simulate this, the model behavior was analyzed under transient Delta activation.
                The network response to a transient Delta stimulus was a strong function of both the
                signal intensity and duration, and either a high intensity signal for a short
                duration or a low intensity signal for a prolonged duration was capable of inducing
                transient increase in Hes1 expression levels for up to 2.5 days after withdrawal of
                the signal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g005">Fig. 5</xref>), a time
                sufficient to initiate a biological response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Tanigaki1">[57]</xref>.</p>
            <p>This prolonged expression of Hes1 upon transient Delta activation is due to the long
                half-life of NICD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Foltz1">[55]</xref>. The bistable switch is thus sensitive to the
                degradation constant of NICD. If the NICD half-life were for example drastically
                reduced, the model would predict that the system would fail to express high levels
                of Hes1 regardless of Delta levels (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000390.s004">Fig. S3</xref>). Hes1 is a repressive transcription
                factor that in some systems plays a crucial role in suppressing the activation of
                oncogenes. For example, in breast cancer cells, Hes1 can inhibit both estrogen- and
                heregulin-beta1-stimulated growth via downregulation of E2F-1 expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hartman1">[75]</xref>. Thus,
                a malfunction in the Notch system, such as a reduction in NICD half-life, could
                contribute to cell transformation. Indeed, aberrant Notch signaling is implicated in
                many cancers (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Harper1">[76]</xref>). For example, integrin-linked kinase (ILK),
                which is either activated or overexpressed in many types of cancers including breast
                cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Troussard1">[77]</xref>, can remarkably reduce the protein stability of
                Notch1 and thus decrease its half-life drastically <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Mo1">[78]</xref>. Interestingly, high ILK
                and low NICD levels are detected in basal cell carcinoma and melanoma patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Mo1">[78]</xref>.</p>
            <p>By increasing the repressive strength of the Hes1 dimer by 10-fold
                (r<sub>Nbox</sub>&lt;0.03), the cell can transition from being a bistable
                system, to a brief region of monostability, and finally to an oscillator (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000390-g008">Fig. 8B</xref>). Oscillations occur with
                a time period of approximately 2 hrs, similar to what Hirata et al. observed in cell
                culture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">[30]</xref>. This value also compares well with the various
                models that have been developed (for the Hes system in isolation) to explain
                oscillations in the <italic>hes</italic> family of genes and their homologues. These
                models assume complete repression in the presence of even a single Hes homodimer
                bound to the promoter region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Monk1">[36]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Bernard1">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">[45]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser2">[66]</xref>. This corresponds to an r<sub>Nbox</sub> value of
                0, in which case there would be no difference between the repressive strength of
                promoters with 1, 2 or 3 N-boxes. From the experimental observations of Takebayashi
                et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Takebayashi1">[37]</xref>, where the repressive strength of the promoter did in
                fact increase with the number of N-boxes, the estimated value of r<sub>Nbox</sub> is
                0.3. However, during somitogenesis, the factors expressed in the presomitic mesoderm
                (PSM) may enhance the repression due to Hes1 such that the value of r<sub>Nbox</sub>
                is very low.</p>
            <p>This current model represents the Notch signaling network core in a single cell, and
                it can readily be extended to a field of cells to analyze the role of Notch in
                patterning tissue formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Saha1">[60]</xref>. In addition, there are numerous cell-specific
                mechanisms and factors that feed into this important signaling core <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-CamposOrtega1">[79]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000390-Irvine1">[81]</xref>. Additional molecular
                species can be added to this model framework, or the parameter values of the current
                model can readily be modulated for example to simulate changes in DNA binding
                affinities, repressive constants, or the protein and mRNA stabilities as a function
                of cell-specific factors. This simple but versatile model can therefore be expanded
                by incorporation of additional molecular mechanism, specific to particular cell
                types, to make predictions on the role of Notch signaling in diverse cells and
                tissues.</p>
            <p>In summary, we have theoretically and computationally analyzed the
                Notch1-RBP-Jκ-Hes1 signaling network, which is responsible for cell fate
                specification in numerous contexts. Our results indicate that the network,
                consisting of both positive and negative feedback mechanisms, can be tuned to
                function either as a bistable cell fate switch or an oscillator based on relatively
                small changes in a key parameter value. Furthermore, the duration and strength of
                the Delta signal regulate either the peak or the final steady state levels of Hes1
                attained. Therefore, cells can readily tune the Notch system to regulate a variety
                downstream cell fates and functions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s5">
            <title>Supporting Information</title>
            <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000390.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.s001" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Text S1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Supplemental Materials</p>
                    <p>(0.09 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000390.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.s002" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Transcriptional analysis of the Notch1 promoter. Relative fold changes in the
                        activity of the Notch1 promoter in the presence of exogenous Hes1 (H),
                        dNHes1 (dN), RBP-Jκ(R) and NICD (N) are shown. Relative amounts of
                        plasmids used in each case encoding the respective cDNA are indicated. For
                        example H0.1dN1R0.5N0.5 indicates
                        Hes1 = 0.1 µg,
                        dNHes1 = 1 µg,
                        RBP-Jk = 0.5 µg and
                        NICD = 0.5 µg in a total of 4
                        µg transfection.</p>
                    <p>(2.52 MB TIF)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000390.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.s003" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S2</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Bifurcation Analysis. (A) Bifurcation analysis of how the switching points
                        vary with the Hes1 DNA association constant (Kn). Varying the association
                        constant over two orders of magnitude causes a slight shift in the strength
                        of the Delta signal required to switch the system state. Thus, stronger DNA
                        association of Hes1 (higher values of Kn) increases the threshold values of
                        Delta signal strength (Kdelp) required to turn the system ON. (B)
                        Bifurcation analysis of how the switching points vary with the Hes1
                        dimerization constant (KaHp). Varying the dimerization constant over two
                        orders of magnitude causes a slight increase in the strength of the Delta
                        signal required to switch the system state to ON. (C) Bifurcation analysis
                        of how the switching points vary with the repression constant of
                        RBP-Jκ (rR). Increasing the repression constant from 0 to 0.5
                        (corresponding to a decrease in the RBP-Jκ repressive strength), has
                        very little effect on the threshold of Delta signaling strength required to
                        turn the system ON.</p>
                    <p>(0.82 MB TIF)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000390.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.s004" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S3</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Effect of half-life of NICD on the Hes1 switch. (A) Changing the half life
                        from 3 hrs (kdNcp = 0.00385) to 8 hrs
                        (0.0014) due to the effect of GSK3β causes a slight increase in the
                        steady state Hes1 concentration in response to a Delta signal of
                            kDelp = 5×10<sup>−4</sup>,
                        but no qualitative change in the switch. Increasing the degradation constant
                        by 10-fold (kdNcp = 0.0014 to 0.014)
                        however, causes complete suppression of the switch. (B) Analysis of how the
                        threshold value of Delta signal required to switch the system from OFF to ON
                        increases with the increasing degradation constant of NICD (decreasing NICD
                        half life).</p>
                    <p>(0.52 MB TIF)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000390.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000390.s005" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Figure S4</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Effect of repression through Hes1 (r<sub>Nbox</sub>) on the high steady state
                        values of Hes1 expression.Decreasing r<sub>Nbox</sub> progressively
                        decreases the steady state concentrations of Hes1 in the r<sub>Nbox</sub>
                        range of 0.3 to 0.1.</p>
                    <p>(0.42 MB TIF)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <p>We would like to thank Dr. Wei-Qiang Gao, Dr. Diane Hayward, Dr. R. Kopan, Dr. R.
                Kageyama and Dr. C. Cepko for providing valuable plasmid constructs.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Denhardt1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Denhardt</surname>
                            <given-names>DT</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Signal-transducing protein phosphorylation cascades mediated by
                        Ras/Rho proteins in the mammalian cell: the potential for multiplex
                        signalling.</article-title>
                    <source>Biochem J</source>
                    <volume>318(Pt 3)</volume>
                    <fpage>729</fpage>
                    <lpage>747</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Keltner1">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Keltner</surname>
                            <given-names>NL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gorman</surname>
                            <given-names>AG</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Second messengers.</article-title>
                    <source>Perspect Psychiatr Care</source>
                    <volume>43</volume>
                    <fpage>60</fpage>
                    <lpage>64</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Weng1">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Weng</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bhalla</surname>
                            <given-names>US</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Iyengar</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Complexity in biological signaling systems.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>284</volume>
                    <fpage>92</fpage>
                    <lpage>96</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Klipp1">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Klipp</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Liebermeister</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Mathematical modeling of intracellular signaling pathways.</article-title>
                    <source>BMC Neurosci</source>
                    <volume>7</volume>
                    <supplement>Suppl 1</supplement>
                    <fpage>S10</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Barua1">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Barua</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Faeder</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Haugh</surname>
                            <given-names>JM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Computational models of tandem SRC homology 2 domain interactions
                        and application to phosphoinositide 3-kinase.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>283</volume>
                    <fpage>7338</fpage>
                    <lpage>7345</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Obrink1">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Obrink</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sawa</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Scheffrahn</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Singer</surname>
                            <given-names>BB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sigmundsson</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Computational analysis of isoform-specific signal regulation by
                        CEACAM1-A cell adhesion molecule expressed in PC12 cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
                    <volume>971</volume>
                    <fpage>597</fpage>
                    <lpage>607</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Carthew1">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Carthew</surname>
                            <given-names>RW</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Pattern formation in the Drosophila eye.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <fpage>309</fpage>
                    <lpage>313</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Ikawa1">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ikawa</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kawamoto</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Goldrath</surname>
                            <given-names>AW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Murre</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>E proteins and Notch signaling cooperate to promote T cell
                        lineage specification and commitment.</article-title>
                    <source>J Exp Med</source>
                    <volume>203</volume>
                    <fpage>1329</fpage>
                    <lpage>1342</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-ArtavanisTsakonas1">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Artavanis-Tsakonas</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rand</surname>
                            <given-names>MD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lake</surname>
                            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Notch signaling: cell fate control and signal integration in
                        development.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>284</volume>
                    <fpage>770</fpage>
                    <lpage>776</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Kopan1">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kopan</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Notch: a membrane-bound transcription factor.</article-title>
                    <source>J Cell Sci</source>
                    <volume>115</volume>
                    <fpage>1095</fpage>
                    <lpage>1097</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Weinmaster1">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Weinmaster</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Roberts</surname>
                            <given-names>VJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lemke</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1991</year>
                    <article-title>A homolog of Drosophila Notch expressed during mammalian
                        development.</article-title>
                    <source>Development</source>
                    <volume>113</volume>
                    <fpage>199</fpage>
                    <lpage>205</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Greenwald1">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Greenwald</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>Structure/function studies of lin-12/Notch proteins.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
                    <volume>4</volume>
                    <fpage>556</fpage>
                    <lpage>562</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Lu1">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lu</surname>
                            <given-names>FM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lux</surname>
                            <given-names>SE</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Constitutively active human Notch1 binds to the transcription
                        factor CBF1 and stimulates transcription through a promoter containing a
                        CBF1-responsive element.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>93</volume>
                    <fpage>5663</fpage>
                    <lpage>5667</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Cornell1">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Cornell</surname>
                            <given-names>RA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Eisen</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Notch in the pathway: the roles of Notch signaling in neural
                        crest development.</article-title>
                    <source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source>
                    <volume>16</volume>
                    <fpage>663</fpage>
                    <lpage>672</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Brooker1">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brooker</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hozumi</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lewis</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Notch ligands with contrasting functions: Jagged1 and Delta1 in
                        the mouse inner ear.</article-title>
                    <source>Development</source>
                    <volume>133</volume>
                    <fpage>1277</fpage>
                    <lpage>1286</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Blanpain1">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Blanpain</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lowry</surname>
                            <given-names>WE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pasolli</surname>
                            <given-names>HA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Fuchs</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Canonical notch signaling functions as a commitment switch in the
                        epidermal lineage.</article-title>
                    <source>Genes Dev</source>
                    <volume>20</volume>
                    <fpage>3022</fpage>
                    <lpage>3035</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Matsuda1">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Matsuda</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wakamatsu</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kohyama</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Okano</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Fukuda</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Notch signaling functions as a binary switch for the
                        determination of glandular and luminal fates of endodermal epithelium during
                        chicken stomach development.</article-title>
                    <source>Development</source>
                    <volume>132</volume>
                    <fpage>2783</fpage>
                    <lpage>2793</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Lefort1">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lefort</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Benne</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lelievre</surname>
                            <given-names>JD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dorival</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Balbo</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Short exposure to Notch ligand Delta-4 is sufficient to induce
                        T-cell differentiation program and to increase the T cell potential of
                        primary human CD34+ cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Exp Hematol</source>
                    <volume>34</volume>
                    <fpage>1720</fpage>
                    <lpage>1729</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Carotta1">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Carotta</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brady</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wu</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nutt</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Transient Notch signaling induces NK cell potential in
                        Pax5-deficient pro-B cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
                    <volume>36</volume>
                    <fpage>3294</fpage>
                    <lpage>3304</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Morrison1">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Morrison</surname>
                            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Perez</surname>
                            <given-names>SE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Qiao</surname>
                            <given-names>Z</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Verdi</surname>
                            <given-names>JM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hicks</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Transient Notch activation initiates an irreversible switch from
                        neurogenesis to gliogenesis by neural crest stem cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Cell</source>
                    <volume>101</volume>
                    <fpage>499</fpage>
                    <lpage>510</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Hooper1">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hooper</surname>
                            <given-names>SD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Boue</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Krause</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jensen</surname>
                            <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mason</surname>
                            <given-names>CE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Identification of tightly regulated groups of genes during
                        Drosophila melanogaster embryogenesis.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>72</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Appel1">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Appel</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Givan</surname>
                            <given-names>LA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Eisen</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Delta-Notch signaling and lateral inhibition in zebrafish spinal
                        cord development.</article-title>
                    <source>BMC Dev Biol</source>
                    <volume>1</volume>
                    <fpage>13</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Appel2">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Appel</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Eisen</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Regulation of neuronal specification in the zebrafish spinal cord
                        by Delta function.</article-title>
                    <source>Development</source>
                    <volume>125</volume>
                    <fpage>371</fpage>
                    <lpage>380</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Bettenhausen1">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bettenhausen</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hrabe de Angelis</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Simon</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Guenet</surname>
                            <given-names>JL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gossler</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Transient and restricted expression during mouse embryogenesis of
                        Dll1, a murine gene closely related to Drosophila Delta.</article-title>
                    <source>Development</source>
                    <volume>121</volume>
                    <fpage>2407</fpage>
                    <lpage>2418</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Yu1">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yu</surname>
                            <given-names>X</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zou</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ye</surname>
                            <given-names>Z</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hammond</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chen</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Notch signaling activation in human embryonic stem cells is
                        required for embryonic, but not trophoblastic, lineage commitment.</article-title>
                    <source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>461</fpage>
                    <lpage>471</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Pourquie1">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pourquie</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The vertebrate segmentation clock.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Anatomy</source>
                    <volume>199</volume>
                    <fpage>169</fpage>
                    <lpage>175</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Saga1">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Saga</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Takeda</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The making of the somite: molecular events in vertebrate
                        segmentation.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>835</fpage>
                    <lpage>845</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Palmeirim1">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Palmeirim</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Henrique</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ish-Horowicz</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pourquie</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Avian hairy gene expression identifies a molecular clock linked
                        to vertebrate segmentation and somitogenesis.</article-title>
                    <source>Cell</source>
                    <volume>91</volume>
                    <fpage>639</fpage>
                    <lpage>648</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Jouve1">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jouve</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Palmeirim</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Henrique</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Beckers</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gossler</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Notch signalling is required for cyclic expression of the
                        hairy-like gene HES1 in the presomitic mesoderm.</article-title>
                    <source>Development</source>
                    <volume>127</volume>
                    <fpage>1421</fpage>
                    <lpage>1429</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Hirata1">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hirata</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yoshiura</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ohtsuka</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bessho</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Harada</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Oscillatory expression of the bHLH factor Hes1 regulated by a
                        negative feedback loop.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>298</volume>
                    <fpage>840</fpage>
                    <lpage>843</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Shimojo1">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Shimojo</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ohtsuka</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kageyama</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Oscillations in notch signaling regulate maintenance of neural
                        progenitors.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuron</source>
                    <volume>58</volume>
                    <fpage>52</fpage>
                    <lpage>64</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Lahav1">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lahav</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>The strength of indecisiveness: oscillatory behavior for better
                        cell fate determination.</article-title>
                    <source>Sci STKE</source>
                    <volume>2004</volume>
                    <fpage>pe55</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Collier1">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Collier</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Monk</surname>
                            <given-names>NA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Maini</surname>
                            <given-names>PK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lewis</surname>
                            <given-names>JH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Pattern formation by lateral inhibition with feedback: a
                        mathematical model of delta-notch intercellular signalling.</article-title>
                    <source>J Theor Biol</source>
                    <volume>183</volume>
                    <fpage>429</fpage>
                    <lpage>446</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Wearing1">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wearing</surname>
                            <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Owen</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sherratt</surname>
                            <given-names>JA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Mathematical modelling of juxtacrine patterning.</article-title>
                    <source>Bull Math Biol</source>
                    <volume>62</volume>
                    <fpage>293</fpage>
                    <lpage>320</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Webb1">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Webb</surname>
                            <given-names>SD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Owen</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Oscillations and patterns in spatially discrete models for
                        developmental intercellular signalling.</article-title>
                    <source>J Math Biol</source>
                    <volume>48</volume>
                    <fpage>444</fpage>
                    <lpage>476</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Monk1">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Monk</surname>
                            <given-names>NA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Oscillatory expression of Hes1, p53, and NF-kappaB driven by
                        transcriptional time delays.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <volume>13</volume>
                    <fpage>1409</fpage>
                    <lpage>1413</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Takebayashi1">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Takebayashi</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sasai</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sakai</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nakanishi</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>Structure, chromosomal locus, and promoter analysis of the gene
                        encoding the mouse helix-loop-helix factor HES-1. Negative autoregulation
                        through the multiple N box elements.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>269</volume>
                    <fpage>5150</fpage>
                    <lpage>5156</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Jensen1">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jensen</surname>
                            <given-names>MH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sneppen</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tiana</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Sustained oscillations and time delays in gene expression of
                        protein Hes1.</article-title>
                    <source>FEBS Lett</source>
                    <volume>541</volume>
                    <fpage>176</fpage>
                    <lpage>177</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Bernard1">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bernard</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Cajavec</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pujo-Menjouet</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mackey</surname>
                            <given-names>MC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Herzel</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Modelling transcriptional feedback loops: the role of Gro/TLE1 in
                        Hes1 oscillations.</article-title>
                    <source>Philos Transact A Math Phys Eng Sci</source>
                    <volume>364</volume>
                    <fpage>1155</fpage>
                    <lpage>1170</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Heron1">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Heron</surname>
                            <given-names>EA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Finkenstadt</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rand</surname>
                            <given-names>DA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Bayesian inference for dynamic transcriptional regulation; the
                        Hes1 system as a case study.</article-title>
                    <source>Bioinformatics</source>
                    <volume>23</volume>
                    <fpage>2596</fpage>
                    <lpage>2603</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Rao1">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rao</surname>
                            <given-names>CV</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wolf</surname>
                            <given-names>DM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Arkin</surname>
                            <given-names>AP</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Control, exploitation and tolerance of intracellular noise.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>420</volume>
                    <fpage>231</fpage>
                    <lpage>237</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Weinberger1">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Weinberger</surname>
                            <given-names>LS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Burnett</surname>
                            <given-names>JC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Toettcher</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Arkin</surname>
                            <given-names>AP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Schaffer</surname>
                            <given-names>DV</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Stochastic gene expression in a lentiviral positive-feedback
                        loop: HIV-1 Tat fluctuations drive phenotypic diversity.</article-title>
                    <source>Cell</source>
                    <volume>122</volume>
                    <fpage>169</fpage>
                    <lpage>182</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Gillespie1">
                <label>43</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gillespie</surname>
                            <given-names>DT</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1977</year>
                    <article-title>Exact stochastic simulation of coupled chemical reactions.</article-title>
                    <source>J Phys Chem</source>
                    <volume>81</volume>
                    <fpage>2340</fpage>
                    <lpage>2361</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Barrio1">
                <label>44</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Barrio</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Burrage</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leier</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tian</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Oscillatory regulation of Hes1: Discrete stochastic delay
                        modelling and simulation.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>e117</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.0020117</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser1">
                <label>45</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zeiser</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Muller</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Liebscher</surname>
                            <given-names>V</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Modeling the Hes1 oscillator.</article-title>
                    <source>J Comput Biol</source>
                    <volume>14</volume>
                    <fpage>984</fpage>
                    <lpage>1000</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Jarriault1">
                <label>46</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jarriault</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brou</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Logeat</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Schroeter</surname>
                            <given-names>EH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kopan</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Signalling downstream of activated mammalian Notch.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>377</volume>
                    <fpage>355</fpage>
                    <lpage>358</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Brou1">
                <label>47</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brou</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Logeat</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lecourtois</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Vandekerckhove</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kourilsky</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>Inhibition of the DNA-binding activity of Drosophila suppressor
                        of hairless and of its human homolog, KBF2/RBP-J kappa, by direct
                        protein-protein interaction with Drosophila hairless.</article-title>
                    <source>Genes Dev</source>
                    <volume>8</volume>
                    <fpage>2491</fpage>
                    <lpage>2503</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Lewis1">
                <label>48</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lewis</surname>
                            <given-names>AK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Frantz</surname>
                            <given-names>GD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Carpenter</surname>
                            <given-names>DA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>de Sauvage</surname>
                            <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gao</surname>
                            <given-names>WQ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Distinct expression patterns of notch family receptors and
                        ligands during development of the mammalian inner ear.</article-title>
                    <source>Mech Dev</source>
                    <volume>78</volume>
                    <fpage>159</fpage>
                    <lpage>163</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Amakawa1">
                <label>49</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Amakawa</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jing</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ozawa</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Matsunami</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hamaguchi</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Human Jk recombination signal binding protein gene (IGKJRB):
                        comparison with its mouse homologue.</article-title>
                    <source>Genomics</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <fpage>306</fpage>
                    <lpage>315</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Gilman1">
                <label>50</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gilman</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Arkin</surname>
                            <given-names>AP</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Genetic “code”: representations and dynamical
                        models of genetic components and networks.</article-title>
                    <source>Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>341</fpage>
                    <lpage>369</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Lai1">
                <label>51</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lai</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Robertson</surname>
                            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Schaffer</surname>
                            <given-names>DV</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>The sonic hedgehog signaling system as a bistable genetic switch.</article-title>
                    <source>Biophys J</source>
                    <volume>86</volume>
                    <fpage>2748</fpage>
                    <lpage>2757</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Lewis2">
                <label>52</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lewis</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Autoinhibition with transcriptional delay: a simple mechanism for
                        the zebrafish somitogenesis oscillator.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <volume>13</volume>
                    <fpage>1398</fpage>
                    <lpage>1408</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Cinquin1">
                <label>53</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Cinquin</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Repressor dimerization in the zebrafish somitogenesis clock.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>e32</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030032</comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Logeat1">
                <label>54</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Logeat</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bessia</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brou</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>LeBail</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Jarriault</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>The Notch1 receptor is cleaved constitutively by a furin-like
                        convertase.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>95</volume>
                    <fpage>8108</fpage>
                    <lpage>8112</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Foltz1">
                <label>55</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Foltz</surname>
                            <given-names>DR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Santiago</surname>
                            <given-names>MC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Berechid</surname>
                            <given-names>BE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nye</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Glycogen synthase kinase-3beta modulates notch signaling and
                        stability.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <volume>12</volume>
                    <fpage>1006</fpage>
                    <lpage>1011</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Espinosa1">
                <label>56</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Espinosa</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ingles-Esteve</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Aguilera</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bigas</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Phosphorylation by glycogen synthase kinase-3 beta down-regulates
                        Notch activity, a link for Notch and Wnt pathways.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>278</volume>
                    <fpage>32227</fpage>
                    <lpage>32235</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Tanigaki1">
                <label>57</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tanigaki</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nogaki</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tashiro</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kurooka</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Notch1 and Notch3 instructively restrict bFGF-responsive
                        multipotent neural progenitor cells to an astroglial fate.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuron</source>
                    <volume>29</volume>
                    <fpage>45</fpage>
                    <lpage>55</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Hasty1">
                <label>58</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hasty</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McMillen</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Isaacs</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Collins</surname>
                            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Computational studies of gene regulatory networks: in numero
                        molecular biology.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>268</fpage>
                    <lpage>279</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Gillespie2">
                <label>59</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gillespie</surname>
                            <given-names>DT</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Approximate accelerated stochastic simulation of chemically
                        reacting systems.</article-title>
                    <source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source>
                    <volume>115</volume>
                    <fpage>1716</fpage>
                    <lpage>1733</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Saha1">
                <label>60</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Saha</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Schaffer</surname>
                            <given-names>DV</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Signal dynamics in Sonic hedgehog tissue patterning.</article-title>
                    <source>Development</source>
                    <volume>133</volume>
                    <fpage>889</fpage>
                    <lpage>900</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Arkin1">
                <label>61</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Arkin</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ross</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McAdams</surname>
                            <given-names>HH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Stochastic kinetic analysis of developmental pathway bifurcation
                        in phage lambda-infected Escherichia coli cells.</article-title>
                    <source>Genetics</source>
                    <volume>149</volume>
                    <fpage>1633</fpage>
                    <lpage>1648</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Hasty2">
                <label>62</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hasty</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pradines</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dolnik</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Collins</surname>
                            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Noise-based switches and amplifiers for gene expression.</article-title>
                    <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                    <volume>97</volume>
                    <fpage>2075</fpage>
                    <lpage>2080</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Maillard1">
                <label>63</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Maillard</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Adler</surname>
                            <given-names>SH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pear</surname>
                            <given-names>WS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Notch and the immune system.</article-title>
                    <source>Immunity</source>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                    <fpage>781</fpage>
                    <lpage>791</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Bolos1">
                <label>64</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bolos</surname>
                            <given-names>V</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Grego-Bessa</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>de la Pompa</surname>
                            <given-names>JL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Notch signaling in development and cancer.</article-title>
                    <source>Endocr Rev</source>
                    <volume>28</volume>
                    <fpage>339</fpage>
                    <lpage>363</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Beatus1">
                <label>65</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Beatus</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lendahl</surname>
                            <given-names>U</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Notch and neurogenesis.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurosci Res</source>
                    <volume>54</volume>
                    <fpage>125</fpage>
                    <lpage>136</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser2">
                <label>66</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zeiser</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Liebscher</surname>
                            <given-names>HV</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tiedemann</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rubio-Aliaga</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Przemeck</surname>
                            <given-names>GK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Number of active transcription factor binding sites is essential
                        for the Hes7 oscillator.</article-title>
                    <source>Theor Biol Med Model</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>11</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Zeiser3">
                <label>67</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zeiser</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rivera</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kuttler</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hense</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lasser</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Oscillations of Hes7 caused by negative autoregulation and
                        ubiquitination.</article-title>
                    <source>Comput Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>18</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-McLarren1">
                <label>68</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McLarren</surname>
                            <given-names>KW</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Theriault</surname>
                            <given-names>FM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Stifani</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Association with the nuclear matrix and interaction with Groucho
                        and RUNX proteins regulate the transcription repression activity of the
                        basic helix loop helix factor Hes1.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>276</volume>
                    <fpage>1578</fpage>
                    <lpage>1584</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Yao1">
                <label>69</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yao</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lai</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Stifani</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The winged-helix protein brain factor 1 interacts with groucho
                        and hes proteins to repress transcription.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                    <volume>21</volume>
                    <fpage>1962</fpage>
                    <lpage>1972</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Bagowski1">
                <label>70</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bagowski</surname>
                            <given-names>CP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ferrell</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                            <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Bistability in the JNK cascade.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>1176</fpage>
                    <lpage>1182</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Bagowski2">
                <label>71</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bagowski</surname>
                            <given-names>CP</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Besser</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Frey</surname>
                            <given-names>CR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ferrell</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                            <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>The JNK cascade as a biochemical switch in mammalian cells:
                        ultrasensitive and all-or-none responses.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <volume>13</volume>
                    <fpage>315</fpage>
                    <lpage>320</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Pomerening1">
                <label>72</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pomerening</surname>
                            <given-names>JR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sontag</surname>
                            <given-names>ED</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ferrell</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                            <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Building a cell cycle oscillator: hysteresis and bistability in
                        the activation of Cdc2.</article-title>
                    <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
                    <volume>5</volume>
                    <fpage>346</fpage>
                    <lpage>351</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Hnggi1">
                <label>73</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hänggi</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Talkner</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Borkovec</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1990</year>
                    <article-title>Reaction-rate theory: fifty years after Kramers.</article-title>
                    <source>Reviews of Modern Physics</source>
                    <volume>62</volume>
                    <fpage>251</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Giudicelli1">
                <label>74</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Giudicelli</surname>
                            <given-names>F</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lewis</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>The vertebrate segmentation clock.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
                    <volume>14</volume>
                    <fpage>407</fpage>
                    <lpage>414</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Hartman1">
                <label>75</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hartman</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Muller</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Foster</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wimalasena</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gustafsson</surname>
                            <given-names>JA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>HES-1 inhibits 17beta-estradiol and heregulin-beta1-mediated
                        upregulation of E2F-1.</article-title>
                    <source>Oncogene</source>
                    <volume>23</volume>
                    <fpage>8826</fpage>
                    <lpage>8833</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Harper1">
                <label>76</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Harper</surname>
                            <given-names>JA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yuan</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tan</surname>
                            <given-names>JB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Visan</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Guidos</surname>
                            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Notch signaling in development and disease.</article-title>
                    <source>Clin Genet</source>
                    <volume>64</volume>
                    <fpage>461</fpage>
                    <lpage>472</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Troussard1">
                <label>77</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Troussard</surname>
                            <given-names>AA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McDonald</surname>
                            <given-names>PC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wederell</surname>
                            <given-names>ED</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mawji</surname>
                            <given-names>NM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Filipenko</surname>
                            <given-names>NR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Preferential dependence of breast cancer cells versus normal
                        cells on integrin-linked kinase for protein kinase B/Akt activation and cell
                        survival.</article-title>
                    <source>Cancer Res</source>
                    <volume>66</volume>
                    <fpage>393</fpage>
                    <lpage>403</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Mo1">
                <label>78</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mo</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>MY</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Han</surname>
                            <given-names>SO</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kim</surname>
                            <given-names>IS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ann</surname>
                            <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Integrin-linked kinase controls Notch1 signaling by
                        down-regulation of protein stability through Fbw7 ubiquitin ligase.</article-title>
                    <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                    <volume>27</volume>
                    <fpage>5565</fpage>
                    <lpage>5574</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-CamposOrtega1">
                <label>79</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Campos-Ortega</surname>
                            <given-names>JA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Numb diverts notch pathway off the tramtrack.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuron</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>4</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Dierick1">
                <label>80</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dierick</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bejsovec</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Cellular mechanisms of wingless/Wnt signal transduction.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Top Dev Biol</source>
                    <volume>43</volume>
                    <fpage>153</fpage>
                    <lpage>190</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Irvine1">
                <label>81</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Irvine</surname>
                            <given-names>KD</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Fringe, Notch, and making developmental boundaries.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                    <fpage>434</fpage>
                    <lpage>441</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Meir1">
                <label>82</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Meir</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>von Dassow</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Munro</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Odell</surname>
                            <given-names>GM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Robustness, flexibility, and the role of lateral inhibition in
                        the neurogenic network.</article-title>
                    <source>Curr Biol</source>
                    <volume>12</volume>
                    <fpage>778</fpage>
                    <lpage>786</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Kessler1">
                <label>83</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kessler</surname>
                            <given-names>CB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Delany</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Increased Notch 1 expression and attenuated stimulatory G protein
                        coupling to adenylyl cyclase in osteonectin-null osteoblasts.</article-title>
                    <source>Endocrinology</source>
                    <volume>148</volume>
                    <fpage>1666</fpage>
                    <lpage>1674</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Lam1">
                <label>84</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lam</surname>
                            <given-names>LT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bresnick</surname>
                            <given-names>EH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Identity of the beta-globin locus control region binding protein
                        HS2NF5 as the mammalian homolog of the notch-regulated transcription factor
                        suppressor of hairless.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                    <volume>273</volume>
                    <fpage>24223</fpage>
                    <lpage>24231</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pcbi.1000390-Watai1">
                <label>85</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Watai</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sase</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Shiono</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nakano</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Regulation of nuclear import by light-induced activation of caged
                        nuclear localization signal in living cells.</article-title>
                    <source>FEBS Lett</source>
                    <volume>488</volume>
                    <fpage>39</fpage>
                    <lpage>44</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        
    </back>
</article>