<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PLCB-RA-1115R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Computational Biology/Computational Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Coding Efficiency of Fly Motion Processing Is Set by Firing Rate, Not Firing Precision</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Efficiency of Motion Processing Set by Firing Rate</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spavieri</surname><given-names>Deusdedit Lineu</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichner</surname><given-names>Hubert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>Department of Systems and Computational Neurobiology, Max-Planck-Institute of Neurobiology, Martinsried, Germany</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>Karl J.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University College London, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">aborst@neuro.mpg.de</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DLS AB. Performed the experiments: DLS. Analyzed the data: DLS HE. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AB. Wrote the paper: DLS HE AB.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e1000860</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date>
</history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Spavieri et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
<p>To comprehend the principles underlying sensory information processing, it is important to understand how the nervous system deals with various sources of perturbation. Here, we analyze how the representation of motion information in the fly's nervous system changes with temperature and luminance. Although these two environmental variables have a considerable impact on the fly's nervous system, they do not impede the fly to behave suitably over a wide range of conditions. We recorded responses from a motion-sensitive neuron, the H1-cell, to a time-varying stimulus at many different combinations of temperature and luminance. We found that the mean firing rate, but not firing precision, changes with temperature, while both were affected by mean luminance. Because we also found that information rate and coding efficiency are mainly set by the mean firing rate, our results suggest that, in the face of environmental perturbations, the coding efficiency is improved by an increase in the mean firing rate, rather than by an increased firing precision.</p>
</abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>How is information about the sensory world represented in the brain? How does this representation change, when the stimulus is contaminated by noise or the brain itself is perturbed by temperature variations? We address these questions by studying motion vision in the fly's visual system. Flies barely thermoregulate but behave normally within a large temperature range. Moreover, visual stimuli are naturally noisy at low intensities and might change considerably within short periods of time. To analyze how the fly's brain handles such perturbations, we recorded responses of a motion-sensitive neuron at different temperatures and light intensities. We analyzed how the responses change and how much information about the stimulus is lost due to noise. We found that response variability and delay are determined mainly by the light intensity, but are barely affected by temperature variations. The information content of the responses was weakly influenced by response noise or delay. The mean firing rate of the neuron, which was strongly influenced by temperature and light level, determined how much stimulus information was contained in response. Based on our results, we can say that over a wide range of environmental conditions, their influence on the efficiency of the system to process information is small.</p>
</abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Max-Planck-Society and by a grant of the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD) to DLS. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Several flying insects are able to partially control the temperature of (part of) their bodies during certain periods of time, by means of physiological or behavioral strategies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Heinrich1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-May1">[3]</xref>. Blowflies (<italic>Calliphora vicina</italic>) however, barely thermoregulate. During flight, when considerable amount of heat is produced by the flight muscles, the temperature of their thorax increases by about five degrees Celsius. The head temperature increases less - by just about two degrees above the temperature of environment in the same period of time. Head and thorax temperature reach the environment temperature around one hundred seconds after the flight stops <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Stavenga1">[4]</xref>. Therefore, their body temperature closely follows the temperature of the environment, which can easily vary more than ten degrees during the day. Within this range, the kinetics of biochemical reactions underlying neural information transmission might vary between three and tenfold <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Hille1">[5]</xref>, and indeed, a strong impact on several response properties of fly's photoreceptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Tatler1">[7]</xref> and other interneurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Hengstenberg1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Warzecha1">[9]</xref> has been observed. Despite the effect of temperature on their nervous system, blowflies show normal flight behavior over a wide temperature range (10–37°C) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Faucherre1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-ElWadawi1">[11]</xref>.</p>
<p>One of the processes influenced by temperature changes is the adaptation of the photoreceptors to light intensity variations. Adaptation to light intensity is necessary to match the limited dynamic range of the photoreceptor responses to encode the wide range of intensities found in natural conditions. Moreover, at low light intensities, the combination of the discrete nature of light and the high sensitivity of the photoreceptors introduces noise into the system, which seems to be responsible for around 50% of the noise measured in the response of postsynaptic cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Laughlin1">[12]</xref>. The consequences of this noise further downstream the visual pathway are still being debated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Borst1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Borst2">[17]</xref>.</p>
<p>Here, we determine to what extent temperature and luminance influence the firing rate and precision of the responses of an identified wide-field, motion-sensitive neuron in the fly's visual system called ‘H1-cell’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Hausen1">[18]</xref>, and how the response properties of H1 contribute to information transmission in the system. The H1-cell is located in the posterior part of the third neuropil of the fly's visual system, the so-called lobula plate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Strausfeld1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Borst3">[20]</xref>. It is excited by ipsilateral horizontal back-to-front motion, and inhibited by motion in the opposite direction, i.e. front-to-back. H1 is part of a network of about 60 neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Haag1">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Farrow2">[25]</xref> that supply the neck and flight motor system with motion information for flight stabilization and course control <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Gronenberg1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Wertz3">[31]</xref>. We recorded H1 responses from 84 flies to a square wave grating moving with a time-varying velocity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>) at 42 different combinations of temperature and luminance. The temperature range covered about half of the range flies face under natural conditions. The luminance range covered four orders of magnitude and includes intensities where photon noise effects are common, corresponding to dusk and dawn under natural conditions.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000860-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Time dependent-firing rate.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold> A segment of the image velocity as a function of time. <bold>B</bold> Raster plots of the same H1 at different experimental conditions of temperature and light intensity. <bold>C</bold> Respective average rates calculated using 137 trials for each condition. <bold>D</bold> Average rates of 325 acquisitions (84 flies) in a wider set of experimental conditions. Scales are the same as indicated in <bold>C</bold>. For each condition, firing rates of several flies were pooled - n is the sample size and the gray curves are bootstrap confidence intervals (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, 1000 replications).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results/Discussion</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Experimental Findings</title>
<p>The effects of temperature and luminance on H1 responses are dramatic, but strikingly different for the two parameters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1B, C</xref>). Under warm and bright conditions (red spikes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, red line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>), the cell's firing activity follows the time course of the stimulus velocity with a short delay, reaching maximum firing frequencies of about 300 Hz for velocities along the preferred direction of the cell. Compared to that, a temperature reduction decreases the mean firing rate but leaves the temporal structure of the response unaffected (blue spikes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, blue line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). In contrast, a luminance reduction reduces not only the mean firing rate, but additionally alters the temporal structure of the response (light red spikes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, light red line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). The full spectrum of responses for all parameter combinations is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>.</p>
<p>In order to quantify the effect of temperature and luminance on the various response properties like firing rate and reliability, we calculated for each luminance a temperature coefficient Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (the ratio of the respective response parameter at 25<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>C and 15<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>C). A strong influence of temperature expresses itself in a Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> value different from 1 at many different luminance levels. Furthermore, we calculated at each temperature a luminance coefficient, K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as the ratio of the response parameter at 100 cd m<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and at 0.1 cd m<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Again, a strong influence of luminance on a given response property is revealed by K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values different from 1 at many different temperatures. Both temperature and luminance have a strong effect on the mean firing rate of H1, with Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values of up to 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). However, temperature has almost no effect on the response reliability while luminance does (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2 B–D</xref>). We quantified the response reliability in two different ways: first, we measured the standard deviation (STD) of the occurrence times of the first spike after a velocity transition, i.e. a zero-crossing from an inhibitory to an excitatory direction of motion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>). This measure should, at least in principle, be independent of the mean firing rate. Second, we measured the response reliability 50 ms after a velocity transition using the ratio of the variance of the spike count and the mean spike count (Fano Factor) within a 20 ms time window (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). Here, a better response reliability can be achieved in two ways - a smaller variance or a higher firing rate associated with the refractory period of the neuron <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-BerryII1">[32]</xref>. The effect of temperature on the STD or on the Fano Factor is rather small: at almost all light intensities tested, the coefficients of temperature (Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) are not statistically different from 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2B,C</xref>). In contrast, the reliability of the response improves considerably for all measures of reliability (all p<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>0.001, Wilcoxon test) with increasing luminance. The coefficient of luminance (K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) reaches values smaller than 0.5 at several temperatures measured. These findings are summarized by the Spearman correlation coefficients between response properties and temperature and luminance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000860-t001">Table 1</xref>). In summary, we find that temperature does not significantly affect the response reliability, while higher luminance values increase the response reliability substantially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Figs. 2 B,C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000860-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Firing rate and precision as a function of temperature and light intensity.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold> Mean firing rate. <bold>B</bold> Spike jitter, measured as the standard deviation of the first spike after a velocity transient (from negative to positive). <bold>C</bold> Average Fano factors for transient responses 50 ms after a velocity transition, calculated in an interval of 50ms, using overlapping windows of 20 ms. Color code represents the linear interpolation of the mean values at the experimental points, indicated by the crosses. Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the temperature and luminance coefficients, respectively (for details see text). Error bars are bootstrap confidence intervals (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, 1000 replications) <bold>D</bold> Top: Segment of a stimulus waveform during a velocity transition from inhibitory to excitatory direction. Center: Raster plots of the responses in 20 trials at three different conditions, indicated in the legends. Each mark represents the occurrence of one spike. Bottom: Distributions of the arrival time of the first spike for the three different conditions shown above, obtained using a kernel density estimator with optimized width for Gaussian distributions.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1000860-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Correlation between response properties and temperature and light intensity.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000860-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Response properties</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Temperature</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light intensity</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean firing rate</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fano factor (transient)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">STD first spike</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.005 (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.55</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Spearman rank correlation. The p values not shown were smaller than 0.05 (n = 325).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>It is interesting to note that neither the increase of photoreceptor bandwidth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Tatler1">[7]</xref> nor the temperature dependent spontaneous activity of the system has a strong impact on the reliability of the responses. However, the effect of temperature on the firing rate depends on the mean luminance - the Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> coefficients decrease with increasing luminance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). We observed similar interdependent effects of temperature and luminance in the spontaneous firing rate of H1: The Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> value in the dark was around 6.4 and fell to 3.3 in the presence of a stationary image with a luminance of 84 cd m<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (n = 5 flies). This effect has also been measured in several response properties of the fly's photoreceptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Tatler1">[7]</xref> such as e.g. the bandwidth, which has a Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of 3 when the cells are dark adapted and 1.9 when they are light adapted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Tatler1">[7]</xref>. What consequences will such effects have on the amount of information about the stimulus in the H1 response? To what extent do the firing rate and firing precision determine the efficiency of the system to encode information?</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Information Theoretic Analysis</title>
<p>To answer these questions, we estimated the information rate and coding efficiency of H1 responses. To calculate these quantities, we discretized the response in bins of 2ms and represented the occurrence of a spike in a bin by ‘1’ and the absence by ‘0’. Probability distributions of binary words with lengths from 2ms up to 20 ms were estimated and information rates calculated. The temporal scale of the system (encoding window) was defined as the length of the binary words at which the information rate was maximal (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Materials and Methods</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000860.s001">Fig. S1</xref> for details). The behaviorally relevant temporal scales for flies, estimated from flight trajectories in which males flies pursued females, are about 40ms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Land1">[33]</xref>. This is the total delay of the system, from the detection of the female in the visual field up to the correction of the flight course. Therefore, it is reasonable to expect that the information transmission in the system occurs in shorter time-scales. Moreover, changes in the temporal scale of the response are known to be part of the mechanisms of adaptation - e.g., temperature and luminance alter the response time-scales of the photoreceptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Tatler1">[7]</xref> - and should thus be taken into account. We also analyzed the importance of the precise spike timing on the information rate by using two encoding modes to determine it: one which recognizes the exact positions of the spikes within the encoding window (‘timing’) to discriminate responses and one that just counts the number of spikes within it (‘count’).</p>
<p>In a similar way as the encoding window, the latency of the system was defined as the lag between the velocity and H1 responses that maximizes the mutual information between them. To calculate the mutual information, we estimate the joint probability distribution between binary response words and instantaneous velocity, both discretized in bins of 2ms. The velocity amplitude was discretized in bins of 1 degree per second and the length of the word used was the one that maximizes the information rate between stimulus and response (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Materials and Methods</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000860.s001">Fig. S1</xref> for details).</p>
<p>The dependence of the information rate on luminance and temperature is similar to the dependence of the mean firing rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Figs. 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g003">3A</xref>). Here again, temperature and luminance have interdependent effects on the information rate. The temporal precision of responses after velocity transitions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2B,D</xref>) is set mainly by the mean light level and does not have a great impact on the information rate, as previous work suggested <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Lewen1">[14]</xref>: as temperature increases, the information rate increases too (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>), although the firing precision remains the same. Indeed, the partial correlation coefficient between the information rate and the STD of the first spike, with the effect of the mean firing rate removed, is 0.23, whereas the correlation with the mean firing rate, with the effect of the STD removed, is 0.91 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000860-t002">Table 2</xref>). Thus, the information rate is determined mostly by the mean firing rate, rather than by the noise in the system or in the input signal. The information rate of the spike-timing mode at an optimal encoding window was on average only 1.06 bits s<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (n = 325) higher than of the count encoding mode.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000860-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Information rates, efficiencies and optimal time-scales as a function of temperature and luminance.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold>. Optimal information rates and <bold>B</bold>. respective coding efficiencies. <bold>C</bold>. Optimal encoding windows and <bold>D</bold>. latencies. Color code represents the linear interpolation of the mean values at the experimental points, indicated by the crosses. Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the temperature and luminance coefficients, respectively (for details see text). Error bars are bootstrap confidence intervals (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, 1000 replications).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1000860-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Correlation between fundamental and information theoretic response properties.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000860-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Response property</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>Precision</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>Rate</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Information rate</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.58</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Coding efficiency</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.37</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Encoding window</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.83</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.86</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Latency</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.71</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.45</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Spearman rank correlation. Firing precision is the standard deviation of the first spike after a velocity transition. All p values were smaller than 0.01 (n = 325).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The coding efficiency is more robust against changes on temperature or luminance than the information rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). Again, the effect of thermal fluctuations is reduced as the luminance increases. Observing the partial correlation coefficients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000860-t002">Table 2</xref>), we can see the temporal precision of the response does not contribute as much as the mean firing rate to the coding efficiency. Moreover, the sign of the correlation coefficient between coding efficiency and firing precision is reversed when the effect of the mean firing is removed. This means that the firing rate masked the real effect of the firing precision on the coding efficiency, mainly because both firing rate and precision vary when the light intensity changes. The count encoding mode was on average 15% more efficient to convey information than the timing encoding mode at the respective optimal encoding windows. These results suggest that the improvement of the information rate and coding efficiency is achieved by an increase of the mean firing rate, rather than the firing precision.</p>
<p>Why does the fly additionally increase the firing precision as the mean light level increases, if the efficiency of the system to convey information barely changes? The amount of information transmitted is not the only essential signal characteristic needed for survival - the temporal scale of the system is also fundamental. Here we estimated two response temporal scales - the optimal encoding window and the latency (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Materials and Methods</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000860.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). The encoding window decreases with luminance (p<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> 0.001) and temperature (p<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>) with similar mean values of temperature and luminance coefficients, Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, of around 0.7. The effect of the firing precision on the encoding window is remarkable (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000860-t002">Table 2</xref>), which might explain why its Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> weakly depends on luminance. Similarly, the response latency reduces with light or temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g003">Fig. 3D</xref>). There is a big difference in the amplitude of the temperature and luminance coefficients: whereas the mean Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is about 0.8, the mean K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is 0.33. The correlations between the latency and the mean firing rate and precision are similar (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000860-t002">Table 2</xref>), which suggests that the influence of the firing precision on the temporal scale of the system is as important as the impact of the mean firing rate.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Modeling</title>
<p>In order to gain insight how temperature and luminance affect the motion processing pathway from the photoreceptors up to H1, we implemented a model of the system under study (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Materials and Methods</xref>, Modeling). This model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">Fig. 4A, B</xref>) incorporates temperature and luminance dependent photoreceptor impulse responses taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1">[6]</xref>, an array of elementary motion detectors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Hassenstein1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Borst4">[35]</xref>, and an Integrate-and-Fire model cell that spatially integrates over the array of motion detector inputs. Our aim was to reproduce the measured firing rates and firing precision for the three stimulus conditions depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>. In particular, the model should be able to reproduce the temperature dependent effects - change of response strength, conservation of firing precision - and the luminance dependent effects - changes of both firing rate and firing precision. The model modifications necessary for reproducing the measurements depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2D</xref> thus should allow us to hypothesize what parameters of the motion processing pathway are influenced by the two different sources of perturbation, temperature and luminance, and in which way. The results of the simulation are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">Fig. 4D, E, G, H</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000860-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Model structure and simulation results.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold> Structure of the elementary motion detection circuit of the model. <bold>B</bold> Schematic of the Integrate-and-Fire neuron used for simulating H1 responses. <bold>C</bold> A segment of the image velocity as a function of time, same excerpt as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>. <bold>D</bold> Simulated raster plot and <bold>E</bold> Simulated average firing rates for each out of three stimulus conditions (averaged over 1500 trials) as indicated in the legend. <bold>F</bold> Segment of a stimulus waveform during a velocity transition from inhibitory to excitatory direction; same excerpt as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>. <bold>G</bold> Simulated raster plots of the responses in 20 trials at three different conditions. <bold>H</bold> Probability distribution of the arrival time of the first spike for the three different conditions shown above. Legend as in 4E.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We first fit the model to reproduce the results for the bright-warm stimulus condition (red traces in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">2</xref>). We then went on to modify as few parameters as possible to achieve proper fits for the bright-cold (blue traces) and dark-warm (light red traces) stimulus conditions. Our first finding is that changes at the output level, i. e. the Integrate-and-Fire neuron, alone are able to explain both the reduction in firing rate (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">4E</xref>) and the conservation of firing precision (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig 2D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">4H</xref>) under bright-cold conditions. To this end, we increased the time constant of an exponentially decaying outward current (called refractory current) following each spike. We could also reproduce the reduction of the firing rate by decreasing the output cell's sensitivity to synaptic input by increasing the threshold value <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for spike initiation. However, this modification also significantly reduced the firing precision of the cell. We, therefore, suggest that the observed temperature-dependent characteristics of the measured responses may be due solely to a modification of the spiking mechanism (e. g., changes in the kinetic rates of voltage-dependent ion channels), as opposed to a decrease of the synaptic input.</p>
<p>The response of H1 under dark-warm conditions, when compared to the bright-warm condition, is characterized by a decrease of the firing rate, a loss of temporal precision and an increased response latency. Based on the assumption that H1's biophysical properties remained unchanged during reduced brightness, we aimed to reproduce these effects by parameter changes in the motion detection pathway presynaptic to the H1 model. It is tempting to explain the change in response dynamics by known adaptations to low luminance in both photoreceptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1">[6]</xref> and their postsynaptic partners, the large monopolar cells (LMC) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Laughlin2">[36]</xref> of the lamina. Under these conditions, both cells increase their time constant leading to an increased low-pass filtering of the input signal. However, we found that these adaptations cannot explain the virtual absence of short term velocity modulations in the response under dark-warm conditions. From the viewpoint of a photoreceptor, different velocities of a periodic grating are encoded as membrane potential oscillations with varying frequencies set by the stimulus velocity. Applying a temporal filter to the photoreceptor input therefore merely affects how different frequencies (i. e., stimulus velocities) are attenuated, but does not influence how well the motion detector output follows the change in stimulus velocities.</p>
<p>Given the maximum stimulus velocity of about <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the spatial wavelength of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the maximum temporal frequency encoded by the photoreceptors is about 10Hz, which is way below the cut-off frequency of photoreceptors and LMCs under all conditions. An increased filter time-constant in the input lines to the motion detector can therefore not account for the temporally smeared out time-course of the H1 response under low light levels. Rather, these response characteristics suggest a filtering of the motion-sensitive signal, i. e. after the multiplicative interaction within the motion detector. We accounted for these observations by incorporating a low-pass filter with a luminance-dependent time constant at the output of the motion detection circuit. The decrease in firing precision (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g002">Fig 2D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">4H</xref>) is both due to a roughly hundred-fold increase of noise at the photoreceptors as well as the final low-pass filter. The decrease of the firing rate for dark stimuli is likely a consequence from smaller photoreceptor and LMC responses to dark stimuli as measured previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Laughlin2">[36]</xref>. We incorporated this effect into our model by scaling down the photoreceptor impulse response for dark stimuli.</p>
<p>The model, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>, is unable to reproduce the increase in the response latency for dark stimuli, in spite of using photoreceptor impulse responses measured under such circumstances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1">[6]</xref>. In order to fit the model parameters and produce the results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">Fig. 4E, H</xref>, we therefore manually introduced a delay of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as found by cross-correlation of the measurements with the simulated response.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Final Conclusions</title>
<p>In summary, the various response parameters can be grouped into three different classes according to whether or not they are affected by temperature and/or luminance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). The firing rate and the information rate are influenced by both temperature and luminance. The encoding window and the coding efficiency are barely affected by temperature and by luminance. Finally, the latency and spike jitter are mainly affected by luminance, but only weakly if at all by temperature.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000860-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Overview of the results.</title>
<p>The mean coefficient of temperature (Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) for luminances up to 1 cd m<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are represented by black squares, and for luminances above 1 cd m<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, by gray squares. The shaded region correspond to coefficient of 1. Coefficients smaller than 1 were inverted, for sake of comparison. Similarly, the blue squares represent the mean amplitudes of the coefficient of luminance (K<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) for temperatures up to 22<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>C, whereas red squares represent the mean amplitudes for higher temperatures.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.g005" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Our model could reproduce the decrease in firing rate and conservation of spiking precision for cold conditions by incorporating a refractory current following each spike with a temperature-dependent time constant. The decrease in temporal precision for dark stimuli was modeled by adding a higher amount of noise to the photoreceptor input and lowpass-filtering the motion-detector output with a luminance-dependent time constant. The decrease in firing rate for darker stimuli is likely a consequence of reduced photoreceptor response amplitudes and was modeled by a lowering the photoreceptor impulse response.</p>
<p>The near independence of latency and spike jitter from temperature is in contrast to the latency of photoreceptor responses for flash stimuli, which have Q<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values between 0.35 and 0.66 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Tatler1">[7]</xref>. Thus, it seems that the latency of the system depends less on temperature than the latency of the photoreceptors. Together with the remarkable correlation between H1's latency and firing precision, and with the fact that responses after velocity transitions are more delayed than in steady firing, this suggests that photoreceptors are not the bottleneck of the latency in the system: considerable amount of delay is introduced in the response during motion computation and possibly during H1's dendritic integration. This is in agreement with our model simulations, which required suitable parameter changes in later stages to mimick the experimental results. Moreover, faster responses in the first stage of the visual system do not improve firing precision in subsequent stages. The response property which seems to be used to control the information throughput when perturbations arise is the mean firing rate. This dominance of the mean firing relative to the firing precision is less pronounced in other sensory modalities like audition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Laughlin2">[36]</xref>, but has also been observed in other systems, like in the retina of guinea pigs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Rokem1">[37]</xref> or in the proprioceptive afferents in crustacean limbs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-DiCaprio1">[39]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Preparation, Recording and Temperature Control</title>
<p><italic>Calliphora vicina</italic> flies were maintained in the department stock at 19–22<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>C, 50–60% relative humidity and 12h-12h light-dark cycle. We recorded from 84 female flies, 7–14 days after eclosion. After immobilization with wax, a small hole was cut in the back of the head and the air sacs and fat tissues that cover the lobula plate were put aside. The fly was then transferred into a metallic case which enclosed its entire body except the head. To isolate the head thermally from the environment a soft airstream was blown frontally on it. Ringer's solution was added regularly to the brain to prevent dehydration. The temperature of the case, airstream and solution was regulated by a controlled Peltier device. Head temperature was measured using a microthermoprobe (AD instruments) and a thermometer (GMH3210, Greisinger electronics, Germany). Since the microthermoproble caused considerable tissue damage, temperature and electrophysiological recordings could not be done simultaneously. The head temperature was therefore inferred from the temperature of the metallic support. The relation between head and support temperatures was measured in pilot acquisitions for three different flies. Tungsten electrodes (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>1M<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) were used for recordings from the H1 neuron, which was identified by its position in the optic lobe and its characteristic response to visual stimuli. After amplification and filtering, H1 responses were processed on-line by a threshold unit which generated a pulse of 1.2 ms when a spike was detected. The pulses were then sampled at 1kHz and saved in a microcomputer for off-line analysis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Visual Stimulation</title>
<p>The visual stimulus was presented on CRT-monitor (M21LMAX, Image systems corp., USA) updated at 240 Hz. The visual field stimulation has a area of 72<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>×83<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, starting at head midline (azimuth = <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The image used was a square-wave grating with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> spatial wavelength and contrast of 67%. The image velocity <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was drawn from a Gauss-Markov process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Bartosch1">[40]</xref>, with mean of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, standard deviation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and correlation time of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>ms. For each acquisition, the stimulus, whose duration was ten seconds, was repeated 150 times, with a interval of two seconds between trials. The image was presented without motion for two minutes before the start of the acquisition, to adapt the photoreceptors to the mean luminance level. The first fifteen trials and the first second of each trial were discarded to avoid accommodation effects and transient responses.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>The response stationarity over trials was quantified by an accommodation index, defined as the ratio of spike count of the first and hundredth trials. Since a higher accommodation rate would overestimate the response variability, only acquisitions with accommodation indexes between 0.7 and 1.3 (338 from 359 acquisitions) were used for further analysis. These limits were determined based on an analysis of a surrogate data, with several different accommodation indexes. We estimate that a reduction of 0.3 in the index represents a reduction of 5% in the information rate, in relation to an acquisition with the same mean firing rate and approximately unitary index. The estimation of the response variability might also be compromised if the responses entrain with the refresh rate of the video monitor. The degree of entrainment was measured by the residual power of the mean time-dependent firing rate at 238–242Hz. Power spectra were calculated using the Welch-Bartlett method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Manolakis1">[41]</xref>, with sampling frequency of 1KHz, window length 512 ms, with an overlap of 256ms. Other window lengths and overlaps yielded similar results. The residual power was obtained by removing linear trends in the spectra. Acquisitions in which the averaged residual power within the interval 238–242 Hz was higher than 0.37 dB - three standard deviations of the residual power distribution for all acquisitions - were discarded (13 out of 359 acquisitions).</p>
<p>To calculate the information rate between stimulus and response, spike trains were discretized in bins of 2ms and the probability distribution of binary words <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of length <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was estimated. The information rate was then calculated as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the entropy of the response, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the entropy of the response given a particular time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> relative to the stimulus, averaged over <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The coding efficiency was then calculated as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>The optimal encoding window was defined as the word length in which the information rate was maximal<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>Similarly, the response latency was estimated as the lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between image velocity and response that maximized <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, that is<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>To calculate <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the image velocity <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was discretized in bins of 1<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>To reduce the bias of the entropy estimations, a combination of jackknife <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Quenouille1">[42]</xref> and shuffled response surrogates was applied. The corrected information rate was calculated as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Optican1">[43]</xref><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The jackknife estimator <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was calculated as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the estimation of the entropy <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> without using the trial <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the total number of trials. A pilot acquisition with 596 trials was used to determine the estimation error as a function of the number of trials. The <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that minimizes the mean bias for 137 trials was 1.13. The maximal difference between the information estimations using 100 and 596 trials was around 1%, for a binwidth <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of 2ms and word lengths <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between 2 and 20ms.</p>
<p>The contribution of the precise spike times to the information rate at the optimal encoding windows was determined by a comparison with a second encoding mode, in which only the number of spikes within the word was considered to discriminate different words.</p>
<p>Statistical significance was assessed by non-parametric statistical tests - Wilcoxon sign rank for single, Wilcoxon rank sum for double and Kruskal-Wallis for multiple comparisons. All tests were two-tailed. The sample size for each condition for double comparison was estimated as 8 independent measurements (detected difference of 10%, with size of 0.08 and power of 0.85) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Gibbons1">[44]</xref>. Error bars reported in the graphs are confidence intervals (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), calculated using non-parametric bootstrap with one thousand replications <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Zoubir1">[45]</xref>. To measure the correlation between random variables, zero and first order Spearman rank correlation coefficients were used.</p>
<p>The temperature coefficient <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of a determined response property <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was defined as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were obtained from a linear least-square fit of the data. The coefficient of luminance <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was defined as<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>and calculated in the same way as <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Modeling</title>
<p>Input signals ranging from −0.67 to 0.67 were computed from the velocity profile used for the experiments for an array of 80 photoreceptors spaced at <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> spatial resolution. We added Gaussian noise to each of these input signals (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and convolved them with photoreceptor impulse responses taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1">[6]</xref>. The photoreceptor output was fed through a further filter stage consisting of a high-pass filter (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and 25% of the unfiltered photoreceptor output. 60 pairs of photoreceptor outputs with a spatial distance of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were processed by an array of so-called Reichardt-Detectors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000860-Borst4">[35]</xref>. One such Reichardt Detector consisted of two mirror-symmetrical subunits, each multiplying the low-pass-filtered signal (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) of one input line by the high-pass-filtered signal (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) of the neighboring input line. The output signals of the detectors were further processed by a sigmoidal synaptic non-linearity (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and a low-pass-filter (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for bright stimuli, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for dark stimuli) before providing excitatory and inhibitory input to the output model neuron. The final stage was an Integrate-and-Fire neuron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>) integrating over all synaptic inputs. It also received a noise current (Gaussian distributed, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and a refractory current following each spike (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the warm and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the cold condition). Membrane currents are described by <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the outputs of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-th motion detector. This ordinary differential equation was simulated using the explicit Euler method. A spike was fired when the potential <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> crossed a threshold of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> above the resting potential. The firing rates depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">Fig. 4E</xref> and the distribution of the first spikes after a velocity transition in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000860-g004">Fig. 4H</xref> were computed by averaging over 1500 trials.</p>
<p>The parameters of the model were fit manually to minimize the distance between the measured firing rates and those produced by simulating the model for several hundred trials. We also used genetic algorithms to search for parameter sets that minimize this error but could not improve the results found before during manual search.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000860.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000860.s001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>Information rate as a function of the encoding window. a. The information rate between stimulus and a representative H1 response as a function of the encoding window, for timing and count encoding modes. Lr* is the encoding window where the information rate in the timing mode is maximal. b. Respective coding efficiencies. c. Information rates (timing mode) between the discretized velocity and the response, calculated at the optimal encoding window. Response latency was defined as the lag that maximizes the information rate.</p>
<p>(0.08 MB PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank R. Koberle, Y. Choe, Y. Elyada, T. Mrsic-Flogel, W. Hemmert, F. Theunissen and F. Weber for comments on the manuscript and helpful discussions, and W. Wintersberger for technical assistance.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Heinrich1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <source>The Hot-blooded Insects: Strategies and Mechanisms of Thermoregulation</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge, USA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Casey1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Biophysical ecology and heat exchange in insects.</article-title>             <source>Am Zool</source>             <volume>332</volume>             <fpage>225</fpage>             <lpage>237</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-May1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1979</year>             <article-title>Insect thermoregulation.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>313</fpage>             <lpage>349</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Stavenga1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stavenga</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwering</surname><given-names>PBW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tinbergen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>A three-compartment model describing temperature changes in tethered flying bowflies.</article-title>             <source>J Exp Biol</source>             <volume>185</volume>             <fpage>325</fpage>             <lpage>333</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Hille1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hille</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <source>Ion Channels of Excitable Membranes</source>             <publisher-loc>Sunderland, USA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates, Inc</publisher-name>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Roebroek1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roebroek</surname><given-names>JGH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Tjonger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stavenga</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Temperature dependence of receptor potential and noise in fly (<italic>Calliphora erythrocephala</italic>) photoreceptor cells.</article-title>             <source>J Insect Physiol</source>             <volume>36</volume>             <fpage>499</fpage>             <lpage>505</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Tatler1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tatler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>O'Carroll</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laughlin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Temperature and the temporal resolving power of fly photoreceptors.</article-title>             <source>J Comp Physiol [A]</source>             <volume>186</volume>             <fpage>399</fpage>             <lpage>407</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Hengstenberg1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hengstenberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1971</year>             <article-title>Das Augenmuskelsystem der Stubenfliege <italic>Musca domestica</italic> 1. Analyse der “clock-spikes” und ihrer Quellen.</article-title>             <source>Kybernetik</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>56</fpage>             <lpage>77</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Warzecha1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warzecha</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egelhaaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Temperature-dependence of neuronal performance in the motion pathway of the bowfly <italic>Calliphora erythrocephala</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Exp Biol</source>             <volume>202</volume>             <fpage>3161</fpage>             <lpage>3170</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Faucherre1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Faucherre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cherix</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Behavior of <italic>Calliphora vicina</italic> (Diptera, Calliphoridae) under extreme conditions.</article-title>             <source>J Insect Behav</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>687</fpage>             <lpage>690</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-ElWadawi1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>El-Wadawi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>The development of thermotolerance protects blowfly flight muscle mitochondrial function from heat damage.</article-title>             <source>J Exp Biol</source>             <volume>198</volume>             <fpage>2413</fpage>             <lpage>2421</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Laughlin1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laughlin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blakeslee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Synaptic limitation to contrast coding in the retina of the blowfly <italic>Calliphora</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source>             <volume>231</volume>             <fpage>437</fpage>             <lpage>467</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Borst1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Effects of mean firing on neural information rate.</article-title>             <source>J Comput Neurosci</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>213</fpage>             <lpage>221</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Lewen1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lewen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bialek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Ruyter van Steveninck</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Neural code of naturalistic motion stimuli.</article-title>             <source>Network: Comput Neural Syst</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>327</fpage>             <lpage>329</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Egelhaaf1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egelhaaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grewe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warzecha</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Outdoor performance of a motion-sensitive neuron in the blowfly.</article-title>             <source>Vision Res</source>             <volume>41</volume>             <fpage>3627</fpage>             <lpage>3637</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Grewe1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grewe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kretzberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warzecha</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egelhaaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Impact of photon noise on the reliability of a motion sensitive neuron in the fly's visual system.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>10776</fpage>             <lpage>10783</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Borst2"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Noise, not stimulus entropy, determines neural information rate.</article-title>             <source>J Comput Neurosci</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>23</fpage>             <lpage>31</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Hausen1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hausen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>The lobula-complex of the fly: structure, function and significance in visual behaviour.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>All</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source>Photoreception and vision in invertebrates</source>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Strausfeld1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Strausfeld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>Functional neuroanatomy of the blowfly's visual system.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <source>Photoreception and Vision in Invertebrates</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Plenum</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">483</size>           </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Borst3"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Neural networks in the cockpit of the fly.</article-title>             <source>J Comp Physiol [A]</source>             <volume>188</volume>             <fpage>419</fpage>             <lpage>437</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Haag1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Recurrent network interactions underlying flow-field selectivity of visual interneurons.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>5685</fpage>             <lpage>5692</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Haag2"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Dendro-dendritic interactions between motion-sensitive large-field neurons in the fly.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>3227</fpage>             <lpage>3233</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Haag3"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Orientation tuning of motion-sensitive neurons shaped by vertical-horizontal network interactions.</article-title>             <source>J Comp Physiol</source>             <volume>189</volume>             <fpage>363</fpage>             <lpage>370</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Farrow1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Input organization of multifunctional motion sensitive neurons in the blowfly.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>9805</fpage>             <lpage>9811</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Farrow2"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Nonlinear, binocular interactions underlying flow field selectivity of a motion-sensitive neuron.</article-title>             <source>Nature Neurosci</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>1312</fpage>             <lpage>1320</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Gronenberg1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gronenberg</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Strausfeld</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Descending neurons supplying the neck and flight motor of diptera: physiological and anatomical characteristics.</article-title>             <source>J Comp Neurol</source>             <volume>302</volume>             <fpage>973</fpage>             <lpage>991</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Hengstenberg2"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hengstenberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Gaze control in the blowfly <italic>Calliphora</italic>: a multisensory, two-stage integration process.</article-title>             <source>Neurosciences</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>19</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Haag4"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wertz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Integration of lobula plate output signals by dnovs1, an identified premotor descending neuron.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>1992</fpage>             <lpage>2000</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Wertz1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wertz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Nonlinear integration of binocular optic flow by dnovs2, a descending neuron of the fly.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>3131</fpage>             <lpage>3140</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Wertz2"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wertz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gaub</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Plett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Robust coding of ego-motion in descending neurons of the fly.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>14993</fpage>             <lpage>15000</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Wertz3"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wertz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Local and global motion preferences in descending neurons of the fly.</article-title>             <source>J Comp Physiol</source>             <volume>195</volume>             <fpage>1107</fpage>             <lpage>1120</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-BerryII1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berry-II</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Refractoriness and neural precision.</article-title>             <source>J Neurosci</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>2200</fpage>             <lpage>2211</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Land1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Land</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Collett</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1974</year>             <article-title>Chasing behavior of houseflies (<italic>Fannia canicularis</italic>) a. description and analysis.</article-title>             <source>J Comp Physiol</source>             <volume>89</volume>             <fpage>331</fpage>             <lpage>357</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Hassenstein1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hassenstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reichardt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1956</year>             <article-title>Systemtheoretische analyse der zeit-, reihenfolgen- und vorzeichenauswertung bei der bewegungsperzeption des rüsselkäfers chlorophanus.</article-title>             <source>Z Naturforsch</source>             <volume>11b</volume>             <fpage>513</fpage>             <lpage>524</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Borst4"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reisenman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Adaptation of response transients in fly motion vision. ii: Model studies.</article-title>             <source>Vision Research</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>1309</fpage>             <lpage>1322</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Laughlin2"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laughlin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blakeslee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1986</year>             <article-title>Synaptic limitations to contrast coding in the retina of the blowfly calliphora.</article-title>             <source>Proc R SocLond</source>             <volume>231</volume>             <fpage>437</fpage>             <lpage>467</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Rokem1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rokem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watzl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gollisch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stemmler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herz</surname><given-names>AVM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Spike-timing precision underlies the coding efficiency of auditory receptor neurons.</article-title>             <source>J Neurophysiol</source>             <volume>95</volume>             <fpage>2541</fpage>             <lpage>2552</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Koch1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Segev</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berry-II</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>How much the eye tells the brain.</article-title>             <source>Current Biology</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>1428</fpage>             <lpage>1434</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-DiCaprio1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>DiCaprio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Billimoria</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ludwar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Information rate and spike-timing precision of proprioceptive afferents.</article-title>             <source>J Neurophysiol</source>             <volume>98</volume>             <fpage>1706</fpage>             <lpage>1717</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Bartosch1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bartosch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Generation of colored noise.</article-title>             <source>Int J Mod Phys C</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>851</fpage>             <lpage>855</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Manolakis1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manolakis</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ingle</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kogon</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <source>Statistical and adaptive signal processing</source>             <publisher-loc>Boston, USA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Artech House, Inc</publisher-name>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Quenouille1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Quenouille</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1956</year>             <article-title>Notes on bias in estimation.</article-title>             <source>Biometrika</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>353</fpage>             <lpage>360</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Optican1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Optican</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gawne</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Unbiased measures of transmitted information and channel capacity from multivariate neuronal data.</article-title>             <source>Biol Cybern</source>             <volume>65</volume>             <fpage>305</fpage>             <lpage>310</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Gibbons1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <source>Nonparametric statistical inference, fourth edition</source>             <publisher-loc>New York, USA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Marcel Dekker Inc</publisher-name>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000860-Zoubir1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zoubir</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boashash</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The bootstrap and its application in signal processing.</article-title>             <source>IEEE Signal Proc Mag</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>56</fpage>             <lpage>76</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</article>