<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-12-01999</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sensitive Detection of Viral Transcripts in Human Tumor Transcriptomes</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Detection of Viral Transcripts in Human Tumors</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schelhorn</surname><given-names>Sven-Eric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>Matthias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolosi</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altmüller</surname><given-names>Janine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nürnberg</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>Herbert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lengauer</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berthold</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Max-Planck-Institute for Informatics, Campus E1.4, Saarbrücken, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Pediatric Oncology and Hematology, Children's Hospital, and Center for Molecular Medicine Cologne, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Cologne Center for Genomics, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Institute of Virology, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>Claus O.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Texas at Austin, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">sven@mpi-inf.mpg.de</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SES LT. Performed the experiments: MF JA PN. Analyzed the data: SES. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MF JA PN. Wrote the paper: SES. Designed the software used in analysis: SES. Provided guidance: HP TL FB.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003228</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Schelhorn et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In excess of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>% of human cancer incidents have a viral cofactor. Epidemiological studies of idiopathic human cancers indicate that additional tumor viruses remain to be discovered. Recent advances in sequencing technology have enabled systematic screenings of human tumor transcriptomes for viral transcripts. However, technical problems such as low abundances of viral transcripts in large volumes of sequencing data, viral sequence divergence, and homology between viral and human factors significantly confound identification of tumor viruses. We have developed a novel computational approach for detecting viral transcripts in human cancers that takes the aforementioned confounding factors into account and is applicable to a wide variety of viruses and tumors. We apply the approach to conducting the first systematic search for viruses in neuroblastoma, the most common cancer in infancy. The diverse clinical progression of this disease as well as related epidemiological and virological findings are highly suggestive of a pathogenic cofactor. However, a viral etiology of neuroblastoma is currently contested. We mapped <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transcriptomes of neuroblastoma as well as positive and negative controls to the human and all known viral genomes in order to detect both known and unknown viruses. Analysis of controls, comparisons with related methods, and statistical estimates demonstrate the high sensitivity of our approach. Detailed investigation of putative viral transcripts within neuroblastoma samples did not provide evidence for the existence of any known human viruses. Likewise, <italic>de-novo</italic> assembly and analysis of chimeric transcripts did not result in expression signatures associated with novel human pathogens. While confounding factors such as sample dilution or viral clearance in progressed tumors may mask viral cofactors in the data, in principle, this is rendered less likely by the high sensitivity of our approach and the number of biological replicates analyzed. Therefore, our results suggest that frequent viral cofactors of metastatic neuroblastoma are unlikely.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Many human cancers are caused by infections with tumor viruses and identification of these pathogens is considered a critical contribution to cancer prevention. Deep sequencing enables us to systematically investigate viral nucleotide signatures in order to either verify or exclude the existence of viruses in idiopathic human cancers. We have developed Virana, a novel computational approach for identifying tumor viruses in human cancers that is applicable to a wide variety of tumors and viruses. Virana firstly addresses several important biological confounding factors that may hinder successful detection of these pathogens. We applied our approach in the first systematic search for cancer-causing viruses in metastatic neuroblastoma, the most common form of cancer in infancy. Although the heterogeneous clinical progression of this disease as well as epidemiological and virological findings are suggestive of a pathogenic cofactor, the viral etiology of neuroblastoma is currently contested. We conducted an analysis of experimental controls, comparisons with related approaches, as well as statistical analyses in order to validate our method. In spite of the high sensitivity of our approach, analyses of neuroblastoma transcriptomes did not provide evidence for the existence of any known or unknown human viruses. Our results therefore suggest that frequent viral cofactors of metastatic neuroblastoma are unlikely.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The work of SES was partially supported by DFG grant Klinische Forschergruppe KFO 129. The work of SES and TL was partially supported by grant No. 01GS08103 (Oncogene) of the German Federal Science Ministry. The Children's Cancer Research Fund Neuroblastoma (Foerdergesellschaft Kinderkrebs-Neuroblastom-Forschung) supported the deep sequencing analysis (awarded to FB and MF). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="17"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>To date, pathogenic agents are known to be causally related to 20% of human cancer cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Moore1">[1]</xref> and significantly affect the global health burden of this disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Parkin1">[2]</xref>. The majority of these agents comprise oncogenic viruses such as human papilloma virus (HPV), Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), and hepatitis C virus (HCV) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Sarid1">[3]</xref>. Characterizing the oncogenic potential of viral pathogens has important consequences for prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of malignant neoplasms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Schiller1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen1">[5]</xref>. Tumor viruses in particular have received renewed attention in the context of recent global efforts to characterize the etiology of cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen2">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-International1">[7]</xref>. Consequently, viral cofactors for several idiopathic cancers are currently investigated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen3">[8]</xref> and epidemiological indicators suggest that additional human tumor viruses remain to be discovered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Javier1">[9]</xref>.</p>
<p>Neuroblastoma is a heterogeneous embryonal tumor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Brodeur1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Maris1">[11]</xref> that is accountable for 15% of deaths caused by malignant conditions in children <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-JanoueixLerosey1">[12]</xref>. The disease is associated with an exceptionally low median age of presentation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> months <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Kaatsch1">[13]</xref> and is often diagnosed <italic>in utero</italic>. Metastatic neuroblastoma has two biologically divergent subtypes. Stage 4S is characterized by an age of presentation between <italic>in utero</italic> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> months, metastases confined to liver, skin, lymph nodes and bone marrow, and its ability to regress spontaneously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-DAngio1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Shuangshoti1">[15]</xref>. In contrast, stage 4 tumors are presented at any age, demonstrate high infiltration rates in bone marrow and bone, and are most often progressive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Brodeur1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-JanoueixLerosey2">[16]</xref>. While genes related to neuronal differentiation have been described to be upregulated in stage 4S in comparison to stage 4 neuroblastoma, thereby indicating distinct levels of neuronal differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Fischer1">[17]</xref>, little is currently known about the differences between molecular etiologies of stage 4 and stage 4S neuroblastoma.</p>
<p>The variation of clinical outcomes between neuroblastoma subtypes indicates distinct genetic and environmental factors affecting the development of this malignancy. Interestingly, the early onset of the disease overlaps with periods of high susceptibility to viral infections and is reminiscent of acute lymphoblastic leukemia – another pediatric tumor with uncertain etiology for which an infective cofactor has long been suspected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Roman1">[18]</xref>. Furthermore, epidemiological studies have associated reduced neuroblastoma risk with immunologic indicators such as previous childhood infections, day care attendance, and breast feeding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Menegaux1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Heck1">[20]</xref> that are suggestive of an infective cofactor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen4">[21]</xref>. While transforming polyomaviruses such as JCV and BKV were previously identified within neuroblastoma samples and other pediatric embryonal tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Jrgensen1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Flaegstad1">[24]</xref>, newer studies seem to render these associations inconclusive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Stolt1">[25]</xref>. Therefore, the role of pathogenic cofactors of neuroblastoma oncogenesis remains unresolved.</p>
<p>In general, the search for suspected viral cofactors of idiopathic diseases requires systematic screening of human tissues for viral biomarkers such as virus-derived nucleotide sequences. Unfortunately, viruses are of polyphyletic origin and thus lack common universal marker genes as they are frequently exploited in metagenomics studies targeting cellular microorganisms. Consequently, it is not currently possible to specifically PCR-amplify viral nucleotide sequences within a given tissue without prior information about the infective agent being sought <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Rohwer1">[26]</xref>. As a result, several systematic assays for pathogen detection have been developed that do not rely on targeted PCR-amplification of viral factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Bexfield1">[27]</xref> and were employed to identify Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpes virus (KSHV) as a human tumor virus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Chang1">[28]</xref>. These systematic approaches were recently supplemented by sensitive deep sequencing technologies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Bexfield1">[27]</xref>. These technologies were recently applied to exclude several cancer-virus associations based on negative evidence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Feldhahn1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Arron1">[30]</xref> and aided in the identification of MCPyV, a human polyomavirus, as a cofactor of Merkel cell carcinoma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Feng1">[31]</xref>.</p>
<p>Deep sequencing technologies have enabled detection of both known and novel viruses with unprecedented sensitivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Lipkin1">[32]</xref>. However, the large numbers of sequence fragments (“reads”) generated by these methods necessitate data reduction approaches for filtering and condensing the list of putative viral transcripts. Two such approaches are currently represented in the literature: <italic>digital transcript subtraction</italic> that discards human sequence homologs from the sequence data and considers the remaining transcripts as potential viral signatures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Arron1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Feng1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Duncan1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Patowary1">[39]</xref>, and <italic>de-novo sequence assembly</italic> that aims to reconstruct whole viral genomes from overlapping reads <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Ma1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Wu1">[43]</xref>. Recently, variants of these of two approaches have been implemented in several computational pipelines such as PathSeq <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Kostic1">[44]</xref>, RINS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Bhaduri1">[45]</xref>, and CaPSID <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Borozan1">[46]</xref>.</p>
<p>Identification of tumor viruses in particular poses several important challenges to existing computational pipelines. Confounding factors such as loss of viral genetic material from progressed tumors as well as limited replication competence or latent replication strategies often result in low or selective transcription of tumor viruses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen1">[5]</xref>. In addition, viral oncogenes homologous to human factors and chimeric transcripts originating from proviral insertion sites may share significant sequence similarity with human transcripts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Butel1">[47]</xref>, thus making unequivocal identification of viral factors difficult. Last, high rates of viral sequence divergence from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (dsDNA viruses) up to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (ssRNA viruses) substitutions per site and year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Duffy1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Firth1">[49]</xref> hinder recognition of known viruses based on known reference sequences.</p>
<p>We have developed Virana, a novel computational approach specifically tailored to detecting low-abundance transcripts that diverge from known viral reference sequences or share significant sequence homology with human factors. In particular, our method maps sequence reads to a combined reference database comprising the human genome and all known viral reference sequences. The approach is configured to allow for high mismatch rates and mappings to multiple reference sequences (‘<italic>multimaps’</italic>). By using this combined and sensitive mapping strategy, our approach is especially well suited for detecting human-viral chimeric transcripts and viruses diverging from known references. In contrast to existing subtractive approaches for viral transcript discovery, our method abstains from discarding reads homologous to the human genome from further analysis. Instead, Virana exploits multimaps to assign sequence reads to a homologous context comprising human reference transcripts and viral reference genomes. These homologous regions retain the full, unfiltered information contained in the raw sequence data while also being amenable to further analyses by multiple sequence alignments, human-viral phylogenies, and orthogonal taxonomic annotations, thus greatly aiding in the interpretation of the results.</p>
<p>We applied our novel approach on an overall number of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> deep sequencing transcriptomes of stage 4 and stage 4S metastatic neuroblastoma in order to identify putative viral cofactors associated with this idiopathic disease.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Clinical samples and experimental deep sequencing data</title>
<p>Primary neuroblastoma samples from stage 4 (progressive) patients (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and stage 4S (regressive) patients (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were obtained prior to treatment from the central neuroblastoma tumor bank at the University Hospital of Cologne, Germany. None of the tumors harbored amplification of the MYCN proto-oncogene as determined by two independent laboratories for each case by fluorescence in situ hybridisation (FISH) and Southern blot <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Spitz1">[50]</xref>. Only neuroblastoma samples with a tumor cell content of above <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>% as assessed by a pathologist were selected for deep sequencing. Integrity of RNA was evaluated using the Bioanalyzer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (Agilent Technologies) and only samples with an RNA integrity number of at least <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were considered for further processing. Quality of all neuroblastoma samples and related deep sequencing data was additionally confirmed by an orthogonal computational analysis focusing on human gene expression in the context of differential splicing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Aschoff1">[51]</xref>.</p>
<p>All patients were enrolled in the German Neuroblastoma trials with informed consent. In order to validate our approach we additionally employed a positive control panel consisting of tumors with known viral cofactors. An EBV-positive B-cell-lymphoma (BCL) was received from the Pediatric Oncology and Hematology Department of the Hannover Medical School. Deep-sequencing reads obtained from full transcriptome libraries of two HPV18-positive HeLa samples (HeLa) and a HPV16-positive primary cervical squamous cell carcinoma (ceSCC) were downloaded from the Short Read Archive (SRA) and preprocessed as specified in the original publication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Arron1">[30]</xref>. Transcriptome data of a HBV-positive hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) HKCI-5<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> cell line with confirmed HBV integration events was downloaded from the SRA based on information in the original publication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Li1">[52]</xref>. A negative control panel consisting of a normal brain transcriptome generated as part of the Illumina BodyMap 2.0 project was obtained from the SRA at run accession number ERR030882.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Library preparation and sequencing</title>
<p>mRNA libraries of the EBV-positive B-cell lymphoma and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> neuroblastomas were prepared following the Illumina RNA Sample Preparation Kit and Guide (Part #<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Rev. A). For each sample, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>g high-quality total RNA was processed for mRNA purification, chemical fragmentation, first strand synthesis, second strand synthesis, end repair, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>′-end adenylation, adapter ligation, and PCR amplification. Validated libraries underwent gel size selection and final paired-end sequencing with an effective read length of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp on the Illumina Genome Analyzer IIx following Illumina standard protocols. Additionally, libraries for two of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> neuroblastoma samples were generated using the same protocols and sequenced with an effective paired-end read length of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp on a Illumina HiSeq <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. All libraries had insert size distributions approximating <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp as later confirmed by read mapping. The data were filtered according to signal purity by the Illumina Realtime Analysis (RTA) software.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Simulated sequencing data</title>
<p>In this study we employ simulated sequencing data from three viral genomes that are homologous to human factors. Reads originating from the ABL1-homologue of the Abelson murine leukemia virus (A-MuLV, GI:9626953, positions <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), from the the <italic>gag</italic> region of HERVK22I (obtained from Repbase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Jurka1">[53]</xref>, positions <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and from Bo17, a GCNT3-homolog of the bovine herpesvirus 4 (BoHV-4, GI:13095578, positions <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) were generated <italic>in silico</italic> by dwgsim, a read simulator based on wgsim <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Li2">[54]</xref>. In addition, we produced simulated chimeric transcripts by fusing each of the aforementioned sequence regions to the human TP53 gene, a known proto-oncogene (UCSC build hg19, GRCh37, chr17, positions 7572926–7579569). These artificial fusion transcripts were generated using Fusim <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Bruno1">[55]</xref> based on TP53 exon models obtained from the UCSC refGene database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Pruitt1">[56]</xref>. Fusion transcripts were then used as templates for generating simulated data sets with dwgsim. In all cases, dwgsim was applied using the default empirical error model. Paired-end read lengths and insert size distributions were chosen according to the neuroblastoma sequencing data (see above). Additional simulated sequencing data generated by a related publication were analyzed as described in Section “Estimation of read mapping sensitivity”.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Sample data notation</title>
<p>Sample panels containing neuroblastoma transcriptomes sequenced at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp effective read lengths are denoted as NB1 and NB2, respectively. While the NB1 panel contains seven transcriptomes of neuroblastoma stages 4 and 4S each, the NB2 panel contains one sample of stages 4 and 4S each (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003228-t001">Table 1</xref>). Positive control panels of human cancer transcriptomes with known viral cofactors (BCL, HeLa, ceSCC, and HCC) are denoted as POS. The negative control panel consisting of a normal human brain transcriptome is denoted as NEG.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1003228-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Sequencing panel characteristics.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003228-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample ID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Read length</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequencing depth (Gbp)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Read pairs (million)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HeLa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ceSCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.527</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ceSCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.400</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.527</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.547</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.351</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.513</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.184</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.439</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.695</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.881</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.236</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.744</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.345</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.207</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.759</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.050</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.581</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.829</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.527</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.031</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.317</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.172</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.282</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.868</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.065</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.890</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.368</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.845</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.737</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.174</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.300</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.847</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.772</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.284</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.863</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.748</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.041</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Sequencing characteristics of neuroblastoma (NB), positive control (POS), and negative control (NEG) panels.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Reference genomes</title>
<p>The current assembly of the human reference genome (UCSC build hg19, GRCh37) as well as corresponding refGene splice-site annotations were obtained from UCSC. Splice variant annotations and cDNA sequences for the human genome were downloaded from Ensembl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Flicek1">[57]</xref>. A set of all <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> available complete viral reference genomes and their taxonomic lineages were obtained from NCBI via the E-utilities web service <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Maglott1">[58]</xref> and the database query: “Viruses[Organism] AND srcdb_refseq[PROP] NOT cellular organisms [ORGN]”. In addition, we obtained consensus reference sequences for all human endogenous retroviruses (HERV-K/HML-2) represented in Repbase (Primate HERV, HERVK11DI, HERVK11I, HERVK13I, HERVK22I, HERVK3I, HERVK9I, HERVKC4)) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Jurka1">[53]</xref>. All reference genomes were combined into a single human-viral reference database for Virana. Since RINS and CaPSID cannot use such a combined database, human and viral reference sequences were collected within two separate databases for these approaches.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Quality control, mapping, and assembly</title>
<p>Paired-end reads from the neuroblastoma panels and positive control panels were quality-controlled with an in-house sequence analysis framework in order to identify sample contamination, adapter contamination, and batch effects. After quality control, the sequence data consisted of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Gbp (NB1), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Gbp (NB2), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Gbp (POS), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Gbp (NEG) of sequence reads, respectively (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003228-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>All data were mapped against a combined human-viral reference database with the splicing-aware and gapped read mapper STAR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Dobin1">[59]</xref> in paired-end mode. While Virana considers the read mapper to be a replaceable component, in principle, we decided to employ STAR due to its mapping speed, high sensitivity settings, and its consideration of putative chimeric transcripts. We configured the mapper for high sensitivity by following recommendations of the author of STAR (personal communication). In particular, we set the rate of acceptable mismatches to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> times the length of each read and the <italic>seedSearchStartLmax</italic> and <italic>winAnchorMultimapNmax</italic> parameters to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively. The minimum length of chimeric segments (<italic>chimSegmentMin</italic>) was reduced to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in order to detect fusion transcripts at short read lengths. Known splice sites from splice annotations of the human reference genome as well as canonical splice sites were considered in the mapping. For each read, multiple mapping locations with alignment score distances of up to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ranks relative to the best score were permitted (‘multimaps’). Read alignments were stored in standardized BAM files. STAR supports detection of chimeric transcripts by reporting discordant read pairs whose ends map to different chromosomes. These discordant read pairs were employed in further analyses as detailed in the next section.</p>
<p>In order to identify putative new viral transcripts, read pairs with at least one unmapped read end were extracted from BAM files by the Samtools suite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Li2">[54]</xref> and assembled into longer contigs by the <italic>de-novo</italic> transcriptome assemblers Trinity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Grabherr1">[60]</xref> and Oases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Schulz1">[61]</xref> using default parameters. Oases was configured for using different k-mer values in order to facilitate reconstruction of low-abundance viral transcripts. Contigs of length less than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp were considered to be spurious assemblies and excluded from further processing.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Detection of chimeric transcripts</title>
<p>Virana supports detection of human-viral chimeric transcripts in two different manners. First, the read mapper employed in our study is able to partially align reads that contain a human-viral chimeric breakpoint to multiple reference sequences. Consequently, these partially aligned reads can be detected by Virana within the generic analysis of homologous regions (see below). The second, more sensitive approach to detecting chimeric transcripts is based on paired-end read information. Since the STAR mapper assigns reads to a combined reference database comprising both human and viral reference sequences, ends of paired-end reads whose inserts span the breakpoint of a chimeric transcript will be aligned to different reference sequences. These discordant read pairs are reported by STAR during read mapping (see above) and can further be filtered by mismatch score or sequence complexity in order to yield a high-confidence list of chimeric transcripts.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Generation of homologous regions</title>
<p>A distinguishing feature of Virana is its ability to automatically reconstruct the homologous context of reads that map to both viral and human reference sequences. This homologous context is constructed in four steps:</p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item>
<p>First, reads that map to at least one viral reference are extracted from the mapping together with their primary (highest alignment score) and secondary (up to ten ranks of alignment scores below the highest score) mapping positions (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Since viruses of the same taxonomic family often exhibit significant sequence similarity, reads that map to one family member often also map to related family members as well as to homologous loci in the human reference. Based on these primary and secondary mapping locations, Virana obtains overlapping human reference transcripts, viral genomic references, and viral taxonomic information pertaining to the location. For each sequence read, information obtained in this manner is collected in a data structure denoted as HIT. HITs originating from the same analysis panel are pooled for further analysis.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Second, pooled HITs originating from the same analysis panel are assigned to viral taxonomic families based on the viral genomic references they refer to (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pcbi-1003228-box001">Box 1</xref> Algorithm 1). Sets of HITs assigned to the same viral taxonomic family are denoted as the <italic>homologous group</italic> (HOG) of that family. The same HIT may, in principle, be assigned to several HOGs.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Third, since reads and references generally share local rather than global sequence similarity, sequences in HOGs cannot conveniently be aligned in a multiple sequence alignment. This circumstance considerably complicates interpretation of homologous relationships between multiple reads and references. Virana therefore applies a three-step greedy clustering approach to split HOGs into manageable and alignable clusters denoted as homologous regions (HORs, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pcbi-1003228-box002">Box 2</xref> Algorithm 2):</p>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>3a</label>
<p>The set of all reads within a HOG is re-aligned to the set of all references (human reference transcripts and viral reference genomes) within the HOG using a highly sensitive BLASTN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Altschul1">[62]</xref> alignment (word size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Since all possible mapping locations are required for further processing, BLAST is configured for high permissiveness (E-value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
</list-item><list-item><label>3b</label>
<p>Each HIT is assigned to a singleton cluster. Clusters containing reads that map to the same reference are merged if their reference mapping locations (as determined by BLASTN) are less or equal than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> basepairs apart (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-gaps). Optimal values for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are determined empirically, see Section “Estimation of required sequencing coverage for detection of a homologous region” for a robustness analysis. Merging continues until the number of clusters converges. Subsequently, all clusters with fewer than an empirically chosen cutoff of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reads are discarded in order to remove spurious hits. After filtering, each remaining cluster represents a candidate HOR. Since cluster membership is defined by reads mapping to common references, each pair of references within the candidate HOR shares one or more regions of high local sequence similarity (e.g., the loci the read mapped to) connected by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-gaps.</p>
</list-item><list-item><label>3c</label>
<p>For each HOR, parts of reference sequences that are neither covered by a read mapping location nor by an <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-gap between read mapping locations are trimmed.</p>
</list-item></list>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Last, due to the high mutual similarity of sequences within trimmed HORs, sequences within each HOR are now amenable to sequence alignment against the longest reference sequence within that HOR using LASTZ, the successor of BLASTZ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Schwartz1">[63]</xref>. The resulting star-shaped multiple sequence alignment is then used for construction of per-sample (for reads) and per-gene (for human reference transcripts) consensus sequences. Aligned consensus sequences retain information on non-consensus nucleotides due to the usage of IUPAC ambiguous nucleotide codes. Consensus sequences can then be manually inspected in order to determine single nucleotide permutations and indels up to length <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that distinguish sequence reads, viral references, and human reference transcripts.</p>
</list-item></list>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Virana's approach to identifying viral transcripts in human tumors.</title>
<p>a) Transcriptome sequence samples are first mapped to a combined set of human and viral reference sequences in a splicing-aware fashion. b) Unmapped or discordantly mapped read pairs are further processed by assembly methods to detect novel viruses or transcript chimeras that may indicate proviral integration events. c) Reads mapping to one or more viral genomes (HITs) are analyzed in an integrated fashion by considering human homologous mapping locations and viral taxonomies. This process results in a number of homologous regions (HOR) for each viral family. HORs are represented as multiple sequence alignments incorporating a wealth of sequence information. Alignments are further enriched by taxonomic annotations and phylogenetic analyses.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><boxed-text id="pcbi-1003228-box001" position="float">
<p><bold>Algorithm 1.</bold> Construction of homologous groups.</p>
<p> <bold>Data</bold>: Reads</p>
<p> <bold>Result</bold>: Homologous groups</p>
<p> Initialise: homologous_groups;</p>
<p> <bold>for</bold> <italic>read in mapping</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p>  obtain all mapped references of read;</p>
<p>  <bold>if</bold> <italic>mapped against viral reference</italic> <bold>then</bold></p>
<p>   Initialize: read_hit;</p>
<p>   add read to read_hit;</p>
<p>   <bold>for</bold> <italic>viral reference the read maps to</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p>    add alignment positions of viral reference to     read_hit;</p>
<p>   <bold>end</bold></p>
<p>   <bold>for</bold> <italic>human cDNA reference the read maps to</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p>    add alignment positions of cDNA to read_hit;</p>
<p>   <bold>end</bold></p>
<p>   <bold>for</bold> <italic>viral reference of a viral taxonomic family thus      added</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p>    add read_hit to the homologous group for that     family;</p>
<p>   <bold>end</bold></p>
<p>  <bold>end</bold></p>
<p> <bold>end</bold></p>
</boxed-text><boxed-text id="pcbi-1003228-box002" position="float">
<p><bold>Algorithm 2.</bold> Construction of homologous regions.</p>
<p><bold>Data</bold>:Homologous groups</p>
<p><bold>Result</bold>: Homologous regions</p>
<p>Initialise: homologous_regions;</p>
<p><bold>for</bold> <italic>homologous_group in homologous_groups</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p> Initialize: homologous_regions;</p>
<p> <bold>for</bold> <italic>read_hit in homologous_group</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p>  <bold>for</bold> <italic>homologous_region in homologous_regions</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p>   <bold>if</bold> <italic>read_hit and homologous_region share a reference</italic>     <bold>then</bold></p>
<p>    <bold>if</bold> <italic>alignment positions of shared reference are      within l basepairs</italic> <bold>then</bold></p>
<p>     merge read_hit into homologous_region;</p>
<p>     extend all reference aligment positions within      homologous_region;</p>
<p>    <bold>end</bold></p>
<p>   <bold>end</bold></p>
<p>  <bold>end</bold></p>
<p> <bold>end</bold></p>
<p> <bold>if</bold> <italic>read_hit not merged</italic> <bold>then</bold></p>
<p>  Initialize: homologous_region;</p>
<p>  merge read_hit into homologous_region;</p>
<p>  add homologous_region to homologous_regions;</p>
<p> <bold>end</bold></p>
<p><bold>end</bold></p>
<p><bold>while</bold> <italic>mergeable_pair_of_homologous_regions exists</italic> <bold>do</bold></p>
<p> <bold>for</bold> <italic>pair_of_homologous_regions in homologous_regions</italic>   <bold>do</bold></p>
<p>  <bold>if</bold> <italic>pair_of_homologous_regions shares a reference</italic>     <bold>then</bold></p>
<p>   <bold>if</bold> <italic>alignment positions of shared reference are within l     basepairs</italic> <bold>then</bold></p>
<p>    merge pair_of_homologous_regions;</p>
<p>    extend all reference aligment positions within     new homologous_region;</p>
<p>   <bold>end</bold></p>
<p>  <bold>end</bold></p>
<p> <bold>end</bold></p>
<p><bold>end</bold></p>
</boxed-text>
<p>Consensus sequences can be further processed by phylogenetic analyses. For generating phylogenies, Virana employs the software PhyML <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Guindon1">[64]</xref> following the maximum likelihood approach and using default parameters recommended by the HIV sequence database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hiv.lanl.gov" xlink:type="simple">http://hiv.lanl.gov</ext-link>, GTR model of nucleotide substitution, transition/transversion ratio: 4, gamma shape parameter: 1, number of substation rate categories: 4, approximate Likelihood Ratio Test (aLRT) using SH-like supports where applicable). We note that the topology of the phylogenetic trees constructed in this manner is stable with regard to the model choice; while more complex model parameters may yield better likelihoods in some instances, these differences do not influence interpretation of our results.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2i">
<title>Taxonomic annotation</title>
<p>In this study, we additionally compare consensus sequences of aligned HOGs as well as <italic>de-novo</italic> assembled sequence contigs to nucleotide (NCBI NT) and protein (NCBI NR) reference archives in order to assign transcripts to a taxonomic origin. To this end, we employ several BLAST <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Maglott1">[58]</xref> search strategies (BLASTN, BLASTX, and TBLASTX) with sensitive word sizes (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively). TBLASTX bypasses synonymous mutations during similarity search and is particularly suited for detecting functionally conserved homologs. This approach is therefore recommended for discovering remote similarities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Kunin1">[65]</xref> and is widely used in environmental metagenomics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Mokili1">[66]</xref>. A permissive E-value threshold of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is used for all comparisons in order to reduce the possibility of missing true viral hits. For each query transcript and search strategy, the three highest-scoring reference sequences are extracted from the BLAST results. Subsequently, descriptions, taxonomic information, and available gene annotations for high-scoring reference hits are pooled and query transcripts are assigned a putative viral, human, or ambiguous origin based on the pooled information. In order to limit the search space of the computationally intensive TBLASTX procedure, we constrain the allowed taxonomic origin of reference sequences to only viral (NCBI taxon ID <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) or human (NCBI taxon ID <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) hits while excluding artificial sequences (NCBI taxon ID <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) using the NCBI database query “(((txid10239 [ORGN]) OR (txid9606 [ORGN]) OR (human [ORGN])) NOT (txid81077 [ORGN]))”.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2j">
<title>Estimation of read mapping sensitivity</title>
<p>We quantify the ability of our novel method Virana and the related methods RINS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Bhaduri1">[45]</xref> and CaPSID <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Borozan1">[46]</xref> at detecting diverged viral transcripts among human sequence data by employing a recently published validation data set <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Borozan1">[46]</xref>. This data set consists of a negative control background set of reads simulated from the human reference genome that is spiked with four sets of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reads simulated from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> viral reference genomes. Nucleotide positions within reads of each of the four viral spike-in data sets are mutated randomly independently and uniformly with a set-specific probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> before being merged with the background data set. The set of viral reference sequences represents <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> different viral families that infect plants (Cherry green ring mottle virus, Cestrum yellow leaf curling virus, Elm mottle virus, East African cassava mosaic virus), birds (Gallid herpesvirus 1), insects (Cotesia congregata bracovirus), bacteria (Guinea pig Chlamydia phage), amphibians (Frog adenovirus 1), and mammals (Rat coronavirus Parker, Banna virus).</p>
<p>All five data sets (non-spiked human negative control and four human-viral spike-in sets) are analyzed by Virana, RINS, and CaPSID using identical reference sequences as described in Section “Reference genomes”. Sensitivity (fraction of correctly identified viral reads among all viral reads) and specificity (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fraction of falsely identified human reads among all human reads) of viral read detection are determined for each method and data set. Analyses are performed with either default parameters (Virana), parameters published in the original validation data set (CaPSID), or settings adapted by us in order to maximize sensitivity (RINS: minimal contig length decreased to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, read lengths and insert size distributions according to input data).</p>
<p>Since all methods map to the same complete viral reference set, reads from a particular viral genome of the validation data set may be distributed across several closely related reference genomes, all of which may be considered valid mappings. For this reason, we added post-processing steps to CaPSID and RINS and performed this validation on the level of viral taxonomic families rather than on the level of single viral species. We note, however, that results of all tested methods including Virana retain information on single viral species throughout the analysis. In particular, sensitivity and specificity of the methods change only minimally if data is analyzed on the single species level.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2k">
<title>Analysis of human-viral homologous and chimeric transcripts</title>
<p>Analysis of the human-viral homologous regions and chimeric transcripts based on simulated read data (see Section “Simulated sequencing data”) was conducted by configuring CaPSID, RINS, and Virana analogous to the previous section. For the validation of fusion transcript detection, the number of true positives is set to the number of all reads originating from the human-viral fusion transcript. Since all detection methods in this validation are configured to only report reads mapping to the viral part of the fusion transcript, sensitivity estimates are scaled down equally for all methods in this particular validation. Analysis of discordant read ends in order to detect the origins of chimeric transcripts was performed as described before (see Section “Detection of chimeric transcripts”).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2l">
<title>Estimation of required sequencing depth</title>
<p>Expanding on related work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Feng2">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Moore2">[35]</xref>, we quantify the theoretical sensitivity of Virana by estimating the number of viral transcripts per cell that are required for achieving a certain minimal sequencing coverage at a probability of at least 95%. Based on human genome annotations obtained from UCSC, we determined an average length of human coding sequences (CDS) of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp. By conservatively assuming that an idealized cell contains <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> mRNAs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Feng2">[34]</xref> of average length <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fragmented at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp as a result of library preparation, an expected number of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> cDNA fragments are generated per cell. For a given viral transcript of length <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a viral transcript abundance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> per cell, we expect a number of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> viral transcript fragments. Assuming a theoretical, unbiased sequencing process, the probability of sequencing a viral transcript fragment among the overall <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transcript fragments is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Given a single-end read length of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, a number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reads are required to achieve a sequence coverage <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of that viral transcript. The probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of observing at least <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reads during sequencing with a sequencing depth <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is specified by the cumulative binomial distribution function with parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Due to numerical instabilities of computing the cumulative binomial distribution for large values <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we exploit the Central Limit Theorem and estimate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> by the Camp-Paulson normal approximation to the binomial distribution. This approach has a negligible approximation error of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Lesch1">[67]</xref>. Our approach further depends on successfully reconstructed homologous regions, each requiring an empirically determined minimum number of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> transcripts separated by no more than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> base pairs.</p>
<p>Although the probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of a homologous region being successfully constructed from viral transcripts at a given sequence coverage can be derived analytically for a special case <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Breitbart1">[68]</xref>, this solution neither considers edge effects occurring for small transcripts nor takes into account the distribution of insert sizes of paired-end reads. We therefore approach the problem empirically by <italic>in silico</italic> simulation of paired-end reads that are assigned randomly independently and uniformly to transcripts of different lengths and at varying coverages. This simulation process addresses the aforementioned confounding factors by considering transcript boundaries and sampling insert sizes from a normal distribution parametrized according to neuroblastoma sequence data employed in this study (see Section “Library preparation and sequencing”). An mean estimator for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and its standard error <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were derived by averaging the success rates of homologous region constructions across <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> simulations for each transcript length, read length, region linkage, and read coverage.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2m">
<title>Availability</title>
<p>All sequence data generated in this study are publicly available in the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) at study accession number PRJEB4441. Software implementations of our method and all validation procedures are available at http://mpi-inf.mpg.de/∼sven/virana.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>This study presents a novel approach to detecting viral transcripts in human tumor transcriptomes. In contrast to related approaches such as RINS and CaPSID that rely on subtracting reads homologous to human transcripts from the analysis, our novel method Virana assigns sequence reads to a combined human-viral reference database without discarding homology information (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g001">Figure 1</xref>). By employing a particularly fast and sensitive read mapper, Virana gains sensitivity at discovering highly divergent and chimeric viral transcripts. In addition, this configuration allows for exploitation of multimaps (e.g., sequence reads mapping to several reference genomes with varying mismatch rates) to discover the homologous context of sequence reads with regard to viral and human reference sequences. Last, Virana employs chimeric alignments as well as <italic>de-novo</italic> assembly of unmapped sequence reads followed by taxonomic annotation in order to discover proviral integration events and novel viruses, respectively.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Detection of divergent viruses</title>
<p>In order to compare Virana and the two subtractive approaches CaPSID and RINS in a controlled environment we rely on a previously published simulated data set consisting of a negative control data set free of viral reads, here denoted as background set. The background set is used to construct four additional validation data sets spiked with viral reads at increasing rates of sequence divergence (0%, 5%, 10%, 25%, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>). Performance is quantified in terms of sensitivity and specificity (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>). Applying all three viral detection methods on the validation data sets reveals comparatively high rates of correctly detected viral reads for CaPSID and RINS at low sequence divergences between 0% and 5%. Specifically, the two subtractive methods achieve <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fold higher sensitivities compared to Virana (sensitivities of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for subtractive approaches and Virana, respectively, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g002">Figure 2</xref>). In contrast, Virana substantially surpasses subtractive approaches at higher rates of viral sequence divergence (10–25%), offering comparatively stable sensitivities between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-fold and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-fold higher than Capsid and RINS, respectively (sensitivities of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for subtractive approaches and Virana, respectively, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g002">Figure 2</xref>, left panel). Notably, while subtractive approaches fail to identify 20–90% of viruses in settings of high sequence divergence, Virana is the only approach able to reliably detect the full set of viruses in all validation scenarios (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g002">Figure 2</xref>, right panel). As a result of Virana's ability to detect human-viral transcript homologs, reads originating from several human endogenous retroviruses (HERVs) that are part of the human reference genome but technically also belong to the viral family <italic>Retroviridae</italic> are detected in validation data at all levels of sequence divergence. Since the detected HERV reads originate from the human rather than from the viral part of the validation data, these reads classified as false positive (FP) hits for the purpose of this validation. As a result of this artifact, Virana exhibits a slightly lowered specificity compared to subtractive approaches (0.99985 versus 1.0 for Virana and CaPSID/RINS, respectively). However, we note that HERV reads are correctly classified by Virana during homologous region construction and by optional BLAST-based taxonomic annotation. These reads can therefore be safely and automatically ignored in subsequent analyses if HERV expression is of no interest to the researcher.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Detection of divergent viruses.</title>
<p>Performance comparison of Virana, CaPSID, and RINS at detecting viral reads at different rates of simulated sequence divergence among a background set comprising human genomic reads. The background set without any spike-ins of viral reads serves as negative control. Left panel: stacked bars represent absolute numbers of detected reads grouped by sequence divergence, correctness of classification (TP: true positive, FP: false positive), and detection method. Falsely classified reads not assigned to any of the viral families present in the validation are labeled as false positives (FP). Colored segments indicate to which viral families the reads were assigned. Each condition allowed for the correct detection of up to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reads. Right panel: color coded markers for each condition and detection method indicating which viral families were identified. A maximum number of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> viral families could be correctly identified in each condition.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In spite of the involved construction process of homologous regions, Virana is fastest among the three viral detection approaches, requiring only about half an hour per sample analyzed. In contrast, RINS and CaPSID require two to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> times longer per sample, respectively (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Interestingly, the majority of time spend by CaPSID is lost on subtraction, indicating that this step is a limiting factor of subtractive approaches. We note than reported times are based on analyses using a single compute core. Since all evaluated methods benefit from multithreading, dedicating additional compute cores to the analysis allows for further reduction in processing time.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Time required for data analysis.</title>
<p>Cumulative time in minutes required for analysis of the divergence validation set. Times are reported for the negative control without viral spike-ins as well as for four mixed data sets consisting of negative control background set with viral spike-ins at different divergence rates. Segments within bar plots represent different analysis processes employed by the three viral detection methods Virana, CaPSID, and RINS. All measurements are based on a single CPU Intel(R) Xeon(R) E5-4640 clocked at 2.40 GHz.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Detection of low-coverage, homologous, and chimeric viral transcripts</title>
<p>Having established Virana's ability to detect reads sampled at comparatively high coverage from viral genomes with low or no human-viral sequence similarity, we next test the sensitivity of the viral detection methods in a more challenging scenario involving gene regions of animal viruses that have close human homologs and are sampled at low sequencing coverages. Three such human-viral homologs are used in the analysis: V-ABL of the acutely transforming retrovirus A-MuLV, Bo17 of herpesvirus BoHV-4 (a model virus for oncogenic gammaherpesviruses such as EBV and KSHV and implied in several animal cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Thiry1">[69]</xref>) and <italic>gag</italic> of HERV-K(HML2)22I, a class of human endogenous retroviruses associated with some forms of breast cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-WangJohanning1">[70]</xref>). Validation is based on simulated sequencing data and split into two scenarios (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref> for details). Within the first scenario, simulated sequencing reads are sampled directly from human-viral homologs while in the second scenario reads are generated from artificial fusion transcripts that each involve one of the three homologs fused to the human TP53 proto-oncogene. The resulting human-viral fusion transcripts mimic transcriptional signals indicating retroviral integration or homologous recombination of viral DNA next to a human gene which may result in activation of the latter by insertional mutagenesis.</p>
<p>We apply the viral detection methods Virana, CaPSID, and RINS on these two validation data sets in order to evaluate sensitivity at detecting viral genes that are similar to human factors either due to natural sequence homology or due to gene fusions. Performance is quantified by detection sensitivity, specificity, as well as by the absolute number of reads correctly detected. While all methods performed at a perfect specificity of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, only Virana detects viral transcripts at all coverages and with two to three-fold higher sensitivities compared to competing methods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In particular, sequence reads originating from endogenous retroviruses were almost always subtracted from the analysis by RINS and CaPSID. In addition, RINS seemed to be confounded by low sequencing coverage, a fact most probably resulting from its heavy reliance on <italic>de-novo</italic> transcript assembly. Subsequent analysis of discordantly mapped read pairs by Virana (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>) correctly identified the TP53 gene as fusion partner of both V-ABL and Bo17, indicating that detection of human-viral chimeras is reliable even at low twofold coverage. Due to the repeat nature of the HERV-K sequence in the human genome and the resulting re-occurrence of HERV-K homologs at multiple loci in the human reference it was not possible to unambiguously identify the fusion partner of the HERV-K <italic>gag</italic> gene.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Detection of low-coverage, homologous, and chimeric viral transcripts.</title>
<p>Displayed are performances of Virana, CaPSID, and RINS at detecting the three human-viral homologous gene regions Bo17, gag, and vABL. Performance is quantified in terms of sensitivity (right panel) and absolute number of reads correctly identified (left panel) at differing sequencing coverages (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fold). Methods are validated at detecting both isolated gene regions (upper part) as well as at detecting human-viral fusion transcripts involving each of the three gene regions fused to the human TP53 proto-oncogene (lower part). Specificity of detection is 1.0 (100%) for all detection methods (not displayed).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Estimation of optimal sequencing depth</title>
<p>Due to a variety of factors (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Discussion</xref>) human tumor viruses often replicate at very low levels within the infected cell. Determining the required sequencing depth for detecting viral transcripts present at specific cellular abundances is therefore crucial for planning transcriptome experiments designed to identify tumor viruses. Based on statistical arguments and average mRNA sizes (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>), we inferred the minimal abundances of viral transcripts required in an average cell required for detection depending (1) on the length of the transcript being sought and (2) on the sequencing depth employed in the experiment. Here we report results for an average viral cDNA-transcript (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp), an average viral transcript region analyzed in the validation of human-viral homologs (Bo17 and vABL, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp, see previous section), an average length human CDS (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp), and the genome size of a small tumor virus (A-MuLV, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp). Based on these estimates and given an average sequencing depth as employed in the NB1 analysis panel, Virana requires a minimum twofold sequence coverage of an average viral cDNA transcript in order to detect the transcript within a homologous region with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>% probability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g005">Figure 5</xref>, upper left quadrant, dashed blue vertical line). This sequence coverage is produced with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>% probability if at least one viral transcript is present per cell, on average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g006">Figure 6</xref>, upper left quadrant, dashed blue vertical line). The number of viral transcripts per cell required for detection is inversely related to transcript length and sequencing depth, in principle: at a transcript length corresponding to a small viral genome (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp) and a per-sample sequencing depth of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>% of the sequencing depth generated in the NB1 panel, a transcript coverage of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and at least <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> viral transcripts per cell are required for reliable detection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g006">Figure 6</xref>, upper right panel, dotted black vertical line).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Estimation of required sequencing coverage for detection of a homologous region.</title>
<p>Probability of successful region construction by Virana depending on the lengths of the transcripts being sought, the region linkage parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as well as characteristics of the sequencing platform employed. Colored areas represent overlapping standard error bands of the mean, denoting the uncertainties of the estimations. The probability of Virana to detect a homologous region depends on the length of the viral transcript being sought, the linkage parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the homologous region, as well as the transcript coverage and read length of the sequencing platform employed. Given characteristics of the sequencing process applied for NB1 sample panel, an average viral cDNA of length <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp requires a minimal transcript coverage of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in order to be reliably detected using a linkage parameter of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as employed in this study (upper left quadrant, dashed blue vertical line). Technologies affording longer read length as used for the NB2 panel typically also afford higher sequencing depths. However, at a fixed coverage these technologies generate a more highly fragmented region linkage due to a smaller number of longer reads, resulting in lower probability of generating contiguous homologous regions (lower left quadrant). Lower transcript coverage is sufficient for longer transcripts transcribed from a complete A-MuLV genome (upper right panel, dotted black vertical line) or smaller values of the region linkage parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pcbi-1003228-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Estimation of required cellular transcript abundances for achieving a given transcript coverage.</title>
<p>Sequencing coverage of viral transcripts is depending on the average number of transcript copies per cell in the sequenced sample, on the length of the viral transcript being sought, and on characteristics of the sequencing process. In order to better visualize the optimal sequencing depth required for detection of viral factors, we estimated the required number of transcript copies per cell for different sequencing depths. These sequencing depths are expressed as factors relative to the depths employed for the NB1/NB2 panel generated in this study (which are here reported as a relative sequencing depth of 1).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Analysis of positive and negative experimental controls</title>
<p>In order to evaluate Virana on experimental data we conducted an analysis of several positive and negative control samples with a cumulative size of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Gbp. The negative control sequencing data originates from a normal brain transcriptome that is suitable as a control for neuroblastoma data. Positive controls span a range of cancer transcriptomes that are associated with several viral cofactors such as a hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) cell line with proviral integration of Hepatitis B virus, a cervical squamous cell carcinoma (ceSCC) and two HeLa cell line samples with associated human papillomavirus (HPV), and a Ebstein-Barr virus (EBV) positive B-cell lymphoma (BCL).</p>
<p>As displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g007">Figure 7</xref> (upper part), analysis of the brain negative control sample demonstrates that viral transcription is ubiquitous even in normal (non-cancerous) samples. Specifically, several bacteriophages of the taxonomic families <italic>Microvirodae</italic>, <italic>Myoviridae</italic>, <italic>Podoviridae</italic>, and <italic>Siphovoridae</italic> indicate sample contamination with bacteria as well as technical spike-ins (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://res.illumina.com/documents/products/technotes/technote_phixcontrolv3.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://res.illumina.com/documents/products/technotes/technote_phixcontrolv3.pdf</ext-link>). Remarkably, the Coliphage phi-X174 genome of the family <italic>Microvirodae</italic> could be fully assembled by Virana's homologous region construction, yielding a single fragment of 99% sequence identity and 100% coverage compared to the phi-x174 reference genome. In addition, several retroviral and flaviviral hits at low abundances of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reads per million reads mapped (RPMM) highlight human factors such as HERV-Ks (endogenous retroviruses) as well as human proto-oncogenes SRC/ABL and DNAJC14/RP11 that have close homologs in the viral families <italic>Retroviridae</italic> and <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>, respectively. The taxonomic ambiguity of these regions is automatically identified during Virana's homologous region construction and confirmed by optional BLAST-based annotation compared to NCBI nt and nr databases (as indicated by thinner bars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g007">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Overview of identified homologous regions in positive and negative experimental controls.</title>
<p>Left panel: cumulative numbers of reads assigned to viral taxonomic families (log-scale). Each bar represents a homologous group (HOG) colored according to viral taxonomic family. Bars comprise several segments, each representing a homologous region (HOR). Heights of segments indicate the putative origin of reads assigned to this region (human, viral, or ambiguous). Viral families of bacteriophages are marked accordingly. Right panel: Analogous to left panel, but the lengths of bars represent relative rather than absolute abundances quantified in cumulative reads per million reads mapped (RPMM).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Analysis of positive control samples resulted in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> homologous regions (HORs)spanning five viral families (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g007">Figure 7</xref>, lower part). Viral cofactors associated with each of the cancer samples are correctly recovered at a high dynamic range of read abundances between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> RPMM (HCC with integrated HBV provirus) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> RPMM (HeLa cell line associated with HPV18). In addition, several viral fragments were successfully reconstructed within HORs of the positive control samples, such as a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp long EBV segment containing latency-associated factors EBNA 3b, 3c, and 4a (80% sequence identity with the wild type genome) as well as a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bp long HBV fragment containing the oncogenic HBV-X gene (98% sequence identity compared with Hepatitis B virus isolate HK1476). Similar to results on the negative control brain sample, several HORs with lower abundances assigned to the taxonomic families <italic>Retroviridae</italic> and <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> represent human-viral sequence homologies that are automatically flagged to be of ambiguous taxonomic status by Virana.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the HCC sample was also investigated in recent work focusing on detecting viral integration events <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Li1">[52]</xref>. In this recent study, the authors confirmed one integration event by Sanger sequencing while alluding to two additional events still awaiting experimental validation. By analyzing discordantly mapped read ends, Virana could correctly identify all three HBV fusion events involving human genes TRRAP (11 read pairs), ZNF48 (11 read pairs), and PLB1 (6 read pairs) as part of the primary mapping procedure.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Analysis of neuroblastoma samples</title>
<p>Deep-sequencing of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> neuroblastoma samples on two sequencing platforms yielded <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Gbp (NB1) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Gbp (NB2) of mapped read pairs (including multimaps), respectively (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003228-t002">Table 2</xref>). While samples were sequenced independently and marked with unique identifiers to allow for sample tracking at each step of the analysis, reads from each sample panel and each tumor stage (4 or 4S) were pooled for analysis. Processing the pooled sample panels with Virana resulted in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> homologous regions representing four viral families (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g008">Figure 8</xref>). All HORs were associated with low relative read abundances of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> RPMM compared to confirmed viral signatures of experimental positive controls (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> RPMM, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Several homologous regions assigned to bacteriophage viral families <italic>Baculoviridae</italic> and <italic>Myoviridae</italic> are attributable to sample contamination.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Overview of identified homologous regions in neuroblastoma samples.</title>
<p>Left panel: cumulative numbers of reads assigned to viral taxonomic families (log-scale). Each bar represents a homologous group (HOG) colored according to viral taxonomic family. Bars comprise several segments, each representing a homologous region (HOR). Heights of segments indicate the putative origin of reads assigned to this region (human, viral, or ambiguous). Viral families of bacteriophages are marked accordingly. Right panel: Analogous to left panel, but the lengths of bars represent relative rather than absolute abundances quantified in cumulative reads per million mapped (RPMM).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003228-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Mapping rates.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003228-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample ID</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pairs mapped</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both ends mapped</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uniquely mapped</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depth (Gbp)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HeLa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.900%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.900%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.422%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ceSCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.803%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.803%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.561%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.264</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ceSCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.629%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.629%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.921%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.612%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.612%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.528%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.424</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.693%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.693%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.500%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.924</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.481%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.481%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.515%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.234</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.878%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.878%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.422%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.275</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.062%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.062%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.342%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.385%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.385%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.938%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.641</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.749%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.749%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.012%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.503</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.057%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.057%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.203%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.652</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.819%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.819%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.856%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.597%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.597%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.107%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.635</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.952%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.952%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.681%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.093</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.242%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.242%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.009%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.223</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.854%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.854%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.756%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.651</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.819%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.819%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.256%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.668</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.710%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.710%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.899%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.539</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.344%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.344%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.326%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.110%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.110%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.829%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.225%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.225%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.552%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.243</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NB2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4S</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.280%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.280%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.538%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.517</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Mapping ratios and depths of neuroblastoma (NB), positive control (POS), and negative control (NEG) panels. Mapped reads are relative to the number of sequenced read pairs that have passed quality control. Depths include reads with multiple mapping locations (‘multimaps’).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Reads assigned to viral families <italic>Retroviridae</italic> and <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> were determined to originate from either endogenous elements (HERVs) or from human proto-oncogenes that have close homologs in pestiviruses and acutely transforming retroviruses. HORs associated with these viral families were automatically assigned human or ambiguous taxonomic origin by Virana, as indicated by narrower bars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g008">Figure 8</xref>. We undertook manual investigation of homologous relationships within each ambiguous HOR by analyzing multiple sequence alignments and phylogenetic trees of the respective regions. These analyses revealed unambiguous clusterings of neuroblastoma sequence reads near human or endogenous factors in all cases (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g009">Figure 9</xref> for an example phylogeny).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>Human-viral phylogeny based on a HOR.</title>
<p>Phylogenetic tree of HOR #16 of the NB1 stage 4 panel. Viral reference sequences are indicated with red branches and associated tip labels (‘Virus’) while human factors are labeled with green branches. Blue branches represent consensus sequences of neuroblastoma reads (‘Sample’). The tree was generated by the maximum likelihood approach PhyML using the multiple sequence alignment of the HOR as input (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>). Distances between nodes are quantified as substitutions per site. As can be derived from the tree, neuroblastoma consensus sequences are tightly clustered in close proximity to the endogenous retrovirus HERVK9I and two human factors, thereby unambiguously indicating the human origin of these neuroblastoma reads. Clusters of other sequences represent well known sequence homologies, as for example between human ABL1/SRC genes and acutely transforming retroviruses.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>No significant differences in viral expression signatures between neuroblastoma 4 and 4S stages could be detected except for HERV-K endogenous retroviruses which display <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> higher abundances in stage 4S (NB1: 56 RPMM, NB2: 28 RPMM) than in stage 4 (NB1: 41 RPMM, NB2: 15 RPMM) neuroblastomas. All reads assigned to homologous regions were further analyzed for evidence of chimeric transcription (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>). While several read pairs with putative chimeric mappings could be identified, all viral chimeric read ends were clustered within low-complexity regions of the viral genomes. Analyses revealed that these putative chimeric mappings represent sequencing errors and low-complexity templates that non-specifically attracted reads of similarly low sequence complexity. No cluster of chimeric reads located at a specifically viral genome location and representing a human-viral breakpoint could be identified.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3f">
<title>Reconstruction of novel transcripts by <italic>de-novo</italic> assembly</title>
<p>In order to identify transcripts of novel viruses that do not map to known references, we generated <italic>de-novo</italic> transcriptome assemblies of all unmapped reads. We applied the two <italic>de Bruijn</italic> graph based assembly methods Oases<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Schulz1">[61]</xref> and Trinity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Grabherr1">[60]</xref> that demonstrated best-in-class performance in recent evaluations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Zhao1">[71]</xref> on sequencing data of the NB2 panel. This sequencing data is especially amenable to assembly due to its long read length (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003228-t001">Table 1</xref>). Assembly resulted in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reconstructed neuroblastoma 4S contigs for Oases, and Trinity, respectively (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003228-g010">Figure 10</xref>). Assembly of the neuroblastoma 4 sample yielded <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e159" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> contigs from the same methods. Results of Oases and Trinity assemblies are comparable in terms of contig length. All contigs were subjected to taxonomic annotation using high-sensitivity TBLASTX annotation based on human and viral content of the NCBI nt and nr databases (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>). Overall, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> contigs (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of contigs of any specific assembly) were identified to be of putative viral origin. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> contigs were assigned to bacteriophage references and excluded from further analysis. Based on searches against the full NCBI nr and nt databases followed by manual inspection, all remaining <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> contigs were determined to display higher similarities to bacterial or human sequences than to any viral reference.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003228-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>Reconstruction of novel transcripts by <italic>de-novo</italic> assembly.</title>
<p>Histograms display lengths of reconstructed sequence contigs assembled from unmapped reads of NB2 stage 4 and stage 4S samples (y-axis in log-space). Two independent assembly methods, Trinity and Oases, were used in the reconstruction. The grand total number of contigs reconstructed within each assembly is displayed in the rightmost column. Reconstructed contigs are annotated with their putative taxonomic origin as inferred by comparison with NCBI nucleotide (nt) and protein (nr) archives using TBLASTX database searches.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Neuroblastoma is a pediatric tumor of the sympathetic nervous system that represents the most common form of cancer in infancy. It is characterized by a striking diversity in biology and clinical behaviour of its subtypes. This heterogeneity as well as supporting epidemiological findings are highly suggestive of infectious cofactors involved in genesis and maintenance of the disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Menegaux1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Heck1">[20]</xref>. While several studies utilizing technologies with lower sensitivity compared to our approach have identified human polyomaviruses in neuroblastoma and pediatric embryonal tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Jrgensen1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Flaegstad1">[24]</xref>, newer investigations seem to render these associations inconclusive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Stolt1">[25]</xref>. However, viral commensals of the families <italic>polyomaviridae</italic> and <italic>adenoviridae</italic> are indeed suspected to acquire rare transforming properties as a consequence of viral latency or defective replication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen5">[72]</xref> and to encode oncogenes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Berk1">[73]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Eash1">[74]</xref> whose carcinogenic potential in human is currently investigated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen3">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-ElguideOliveira1">[75]</xref>. We undertook the first systematic search for known and unknown viruses in transcriptomes of metastatic neuroblastoma by analyzing deep sequencing RNA-Seq data of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> metastatic neuroblastomas from two tumor stages as well as positive and negative experimental controls.</p>
<p>Several high-throughput methods for detecting viral sequence reads among human RNA-Seq data have been developed. Among these methods, PathSeq, CaPSID and RINS are most prominent due to their design as reusable computational pipelines. In this study we selected CaPSID and RINS due to their high performance and public availability and compared their detection performance with that of our novel method Virana. Both CaPSID and RINS follow a subtractive approach, e.g. they separately map input data to viral and human reference sequences and subtract viral read mappings that are similar to the human genome from the analysis. While CaPSID is conceptualised as a generalised framework that supports the subtraction process by means of a database and a web server, RINS features an integrated pipeline that splits input reads into shorter fragments in order to increase mapping sensitivity, followed by transcriptome assembly of putative viral reads into full length transcripts.</p>
<p>Both RNA and DNA viruses may share considerable sequence homology to human factors due to reasons such as lateral gene transfer, oncogene capture, ancestral endogenization, or insertional mutagenesis leading to chimeric transcripts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Butel1">[47]</xref>. Such homologous transcripts may display human-viral sequence similarities of 86% (Bovine Herpes virus) and up to 92% (acutely transforming retroviruses). Subtractive approaches silently discard these transcript from the analysis due to their similarity to the human reference genome. In contrast, our novel method Virana follows a radically different approach. Instead of separate mapping to viral and human reference database followed by digital subtraction, Virana undertakes a particularly sensitive read mapping to a combined set of human and viral references. By allowing for multimaps, this mapping strategy facilitates discovery of viral transcripts regardless of their similarity to human factors. Apart from being conceptually simpler by relying on only one mapping step and discarding the subtraction procedure that is both possibly erroneous and computationally costly, this approach empowers the mapper to make informed decisions about relative alignment quality by weighing different human and viral reference positions against each other. As a direct consequence of this increased mapping quality, paired-end reads can be mapped across human and viral references, allowing for detection of human-viral chimeric transcription and proviral integration events.</p>
<p>We quantitatively validated Virana's approach both in settings involving simulated reads as well as in real-world scenarios involving experimental positive and negative controls. In these validations, Virana displays significantly higher detection sensitivities than competing approaches especially at high rates of viral sequence divergence exceeding <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003228.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>% that are common for tumor viruses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-deVilliers1">[76]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Karlin1">[78]</xref>. As a consequence, Virana was the only method able to detect all viral families independent of sequence divergence in the validation data set. In spite of the additional processing undertaken by our method, Virana features between and two and three times faster execution speeds compared to related methods.</p>
<p>Interestingly, viral reads analyzed in the sequence divergence validation originate from a broad array of viral species, only two of which infect mammalian hosts and none of which display significant human-viral sequence homology. As a consequence, this validation favors subtractive approaches by reducing the danger of erroneous subtraction of viral reads that are similar to the human genome. In addition, the sequence divergence validation contained reads sampled at high coverage. However, transcripts of tumor viruses are often expressed at only low cellular abundances and are thus expected to have low sequence coverage. We therefore next validated the ability of viral detection approaches to detect viral transcripts homologous to human factors at varying levels of sequence coverage. Virana, by virtue of not relying on digital subtraction, demonstrated superior sensitivity at this validation both in settings of natural sequence homology as well as in cases of human-viral chimeric transcription. Specifically, Virana was the only method able to detect evidence for all viruses even at low twofold coverages. We observed that both RINS and CaPSID discarded a substantial amount of human-viral homologous transcripts due to their high similarity to the human reference genome, a fact that explains the lower performance of these methods in this validation scenario.</p>
<p>Analysis of positive and negative experimental controls further reveals that Virana is able to detect viral transcripts associated with four types of cancer at a high dynamic range of relative abundances. While Virana displays a slightly reduced specificity in simulated and experimental evaluations, these false positive hits are limited to only two viral families (<italic>Flaviviridae</italic> and <italic>Retroviridae</italic>) that display high sequence similarity to human factors. These hits are additionally annotated with an ambiguous taxonomic origin by Virana. In addition, Virana provides extensive support for investigating such ambiguous viral hits by analyzing the homologous context of putative viral reads in a context of multiple sequence alignments and phylogenies.</p>
<p>In principle, several biological confounding factors may hinder detection of viral transcripts by any sequence-based method. Low concentration and extratumoral location of viral producer cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen3">[8]</xref> or selection of growth-autonomous cells in progressed tumors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Voisset1">[79]</xref> can significantly dilute the number of viral transcripts in a sample. Additionally, known tumor viruses such as high-risk HPV strains, EBV, and MCPyV selectively transcribe their genome during viral latency (HPV: E6/7 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Dyson1">[80]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Scheffner1">[81]</xref>, EBV: EBNA1/2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Young1">[82]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Klein1">[84]</xref>, MCPyV: large T antigen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Feng1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Houben1">[85]</xref>), thus generating only low abundances of tens (MCPyV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Feng1">[31]</xref>) to hundreds (KSHV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Cornelissen1">[86]</xref>, EBV <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Metzenberg1">[87]</xref>) of transcripts per cell. Last, transcription of human oncogenic factors modulated by viral <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Coffin1">[88]</xref> or endogenous <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Ono1">[89]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Tomlins1">[90]</xref> retroviral promoters as well as ‘hit-and-run’ mechanisms of viral oncogenesis that imply loss of viral material <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Si1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-McLaughlinDrubin1">[92]</xref> may predispose cells to transformation without requiring maintenance of viral transcripts.</p>
<p>Our approach aims to counteract these confounding factors by two strategies: first by sequencing neuroblastoma transcriptomes at comparatively high depth in order to detect rare transcripts and second by using several biological replicates at different tumor stages, thus reducing the probability of total loss of viral material from all analyzed samples. Based on statistical estimations concerning Virana's homologous region construction process and the sequencing depth of our experimental data, we can conclude that our approach requires minimal abundances of only two average-length viral transcripts per cell even under adverse conditions such as high viral divergence or extensive human-viral sequence homology. While representing a theoretical sensitivity that may be altered by sequencing biases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Fang1">[93]</xref>, these copy numbers compare very favorably with related estimates reporting minimal abundances of one to several complete viral genomes per cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Bexfield1">[27]</xref>, .</p>
<p>After applying Virana to several positive control panels of human cancers with known viral cofactors and accurately reconstructing large fragments of viruses that are causally related to the respective tumors, we analyzed neuroblastoma transcriptomes at high sequencing depth and using two different sequencing platforms. Analyses of neuroblastoma transcriptomes resulted in the detection of putative viral transcripts with high local sequence similarity to several viral families. However, automatic taxonomic annotation as well as detailed manual inspection of homologous regions pertaining to these families revealed the human or bacteriophage origin of all transcripts. While we could find differences in the abundance of HERV-K transcripts between neuroblastoma stages 4 and 4S, the causative role of HERV transcription with regard to oncogenesis is currently unclear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-Bannert1">[94]</xref> and, as to our knowledge, only tentative associations with specific cancers have been made as to date <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003228-WangJohanning1">[70]</xref>. Apart from these tentative differences in HERV-K abundances, no quantitative difference between neuroblastoma stages 4 and 4S could be identified with regard to viral transcription.</p>
<p>In conclusion, our observations provide negative evidence regarding the contested question of putative viral cofactors of metastatic neuroblastoma by suggesting that viruses are unlikely to be frequent cofactors in the maintenance of metastatic neuroblastoma.</p>
</sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Moore1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Why do viruses cause cancer? Highlights of the first century of human tumour virology</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>878</fpage>–<lpage>889</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Parkin1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The global health burden of infection-associated cancers in the year 2002</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>3030</fpage>–<lpage>3044</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Sarid1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Viruses and human cancer: from detection to causality</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Schiller1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowy</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Vaccines to prevent infections by oncoviruses</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">zur Hausen H (2006) Infections Causing Human Cancer. Weinheim: Wiley-VCH.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen2"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>zur Hausen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Red meat consumption and cancer: reasons to suspect involvement of bovine infectious factors in colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>2475</fpage>–<lpage>2483</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-International1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">International Cancer Genome Consortium</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Artez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>International network of cancer genome projects</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>464</volume>: <fpage>993</fpage>–<lpage>998</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen3"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>zur Hausen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The search for infectious causes of human cancers: where and why</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> <volume>392</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Javier1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javier</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The History of Tumor Virology</article-title>. <source>Cancer Research</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>7693</fpage>–<lpage>7706</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Brodeur1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodeur</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Neuroblastoma: biological insights into a clinical enigma</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Maris1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogarty</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bagatell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Neuroblastoma</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source> <volume>369</volume>: <fpage>2106</fpage>–<lpage>2120</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-JanoueixLerosey1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janoueix-Lerosey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schleiermacher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delattre</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular pathogenesis of peripheral neuroblastic tumors</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1566</fpage>–<lpage>1579</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Kaatsch1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaatsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology of childhood cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Treat Rev</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-DAngio1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Angio</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koop</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Special pattern of widespread neuroblastoma with a favourable prognosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1046</fpage>–<lpage>1049</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Shuangshoti1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuangshoti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shuangshoti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nuchprayoon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanjanapongkul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marrano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Natural course of low risk neuroblastoma</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>690</fpage>–<lpage>694</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-JanoueixLerosey2"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janoueix-Lerosey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schleiermacher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosseri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Overall genomic pattern is a predictor of outcome in neuroblastoma</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1026</fpage>–<lpage>1033</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Fischer1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oberthuer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brors</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahlert</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skowron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of neuronal genes defines subtypes of disseminated neuroblastoma with favorable and unfavorable outcome</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>5118</fpage>–<lpage>5128</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Roman1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ansell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kinsey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia and infections in the first year of life: a report from the United Kingdom Childhood Cancer Study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>496</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Menegaux1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menegaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olshan</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neglia</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bondy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Day care, childhood infections, and risk of neuroblastoma</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>851</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Heck1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hashibe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boffetta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The epidemiology of neuroblastoma: a review</article-title>. <source>Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen4"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>zur Hausen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Childhood leukemias and other hematopoietic malignancies: interdependence between an infectious event and chromosomal modifications</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>1764</fpage>–<lpage>1770</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Jrgensen1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponthan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kogner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flaegstad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Human polyomavirus BK (BKV) and neuroblastoma: mechanisms of oncogenic action and possible strategy for novel treatment</article-title>. <source>Med Pediatr Oncol</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Krynska1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krynska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Valle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Croul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katsetos</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Detection of human neurotropic JC virus DNA sequence and expression of the viral oncogenic protein in pediatric medulloblastomas</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>11519</fpage>–<lpage>11524</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Flaegstad1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaegstad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andresen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asomani</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A possible contributory role of BK virus infection in neuroblastoma development</article-title>. <source>Cancer Research</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1160</fpage>–<lpage>1163</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Stolt1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stolt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kjellin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sasnauskas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luostarinen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koskela</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Maternal human polyomavirus infection and risk of neuroblastoma in the child</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Rohwer1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohwer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Phage Proteomic Tree: a genome-based taxonomy for phage</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>4529</fpage>–<lpage>4535</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Bexfield1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bexfield</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kellam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Metagenomics and the molecular identification of novel viruses</article-title>. <source>Vet J</source> <volume>190</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Chang1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cesarman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pessin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Culpepper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Identification of herpesvirus-like DNA sequences in AIDS-associated Kaposi's sarcoma</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>266</volume>: <fpage>1865</fpage>–<lpage>1869</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Feldhahn1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldhahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menzel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weide</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meckbach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>No evidence of viral genomes in whole-transcriptome sequencing of three melanoma metastases</article-title>. <source>Exp Dermatol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>766</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Arron1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arron</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dybbro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganem</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome sequencing demonstrates that human papillomavirus is not active in cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1745</fpage>–<lpage>1753</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Feng1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Clonal integration of a polyomavirus in human Merkel cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>319</volume>: <fpage>1096</fpage>–<lpage>1100</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Lipkin1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipkin</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Microbe hunting</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Duncan1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JCH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Identification of microbial DNA in human cancer</article-title>. <source>BMC medical genomics</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Feng2"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benos</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Human transcriptome subtraction by using short sequence tags to search for tumor viruses in conjunctival carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>11332</fpage>–<lpage>11340</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Moore2"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gustavsen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chénard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The sensitivity of massively parallel sequencing for detecting candidate infectious agents associated with human tissue</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e19838</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Xu1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stange-Thomann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dodge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Pathogen discovery from human tissue by sequence-based computational subtraction</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Weber1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shendure</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanenbaum</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Identification of foreign gene sequences by transcript filtering against the human genome</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Isakov1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isakov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Modai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shomron</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Pathogen detection using short-RNA deep sequencing subtraction and assembly</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2027</fpage>–<lpage>2030</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Patowary1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patowary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kv</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Periwal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>De novo identification of viral pathogens from cell culture hologenomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Res Notes</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Ma1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Discovery of DNA Viruses in Wild-Caught Mosquitoes Using Small RNA High throughput Sequencing</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e24758</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Kreuze1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreuze</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Untiveros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quispe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Complete viral genome sequence and discovery of novel viruses by deep sequencing of small RNAs: a generic method for diagnosis, discovery and sequencing of viruses</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> <volume>388</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Palacios1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Druce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A new arenavirus in a cluster of fatal transplant-associated diseases</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>358</volume>: <fpage>991</fpage>–<lpage>998</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Wu1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Virus discovery by deep sequencing and assembly of virus-derived small silencing RNAs</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>1606</fpage>–<lpage>1611</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Kostic1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostic</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ojesina</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedamallu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhaak</surname><given-names>RGW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>PathSeq: software to identify or discover microbes by deep sequencing of human tissue</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Bhaduri1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhaduri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ungewickell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khavari</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Rapid identification of non-human sequences in high-throughput sequencing datasets</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1174</fpage>–<lpage>1175</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Borozan1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borozan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchette</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laamme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>CaPSID: A bioinformatics platform for computational pathogen sequence identification in human genomes and transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Butel1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Viral carcinogenesis: revelation of molecular mechanisms and etiology of human disease</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Duffy1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shackelton</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Rates of evolutionary change in viruses: patterns and determinants</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Firth1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Using time-structured data to estimate evolutionary rates of double-stranded DNA viruses</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2038</fpage>–<lpage>2051</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Spitz1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spitz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hero</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ernestus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berthold</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>FISH analyses for alterations in chromosomes 1, 2, 3, and 11 define high-risk groups in neuroblastoma</article-title>. <source>Med Pediatr Oncol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Aschoff1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aschoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hotz-Wagenblatt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glatting</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eils</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>SplicingCompass: differential splicing detection using RNA-Seq data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1141</fpage>–<lpage>1148</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Li1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Co</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>ViralFusionSeq: accurately discover viral integration events and reconstruct fusion transcripts at single-base resolution</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>649</fpage>–<lpage>651</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Jurka1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kapitonov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlicek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klonowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohany</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Repbase Update, a database of eukaryotic repetitive elements</article-title>. <source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Li2"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2078</fpage>–<lpage>2079</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Bruno1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miecznikowski</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>FUSIM: a software tool for simulating fusion transcripts</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Pruitt1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatusova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klimke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maglott</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>NCBI Reference Sequences: current status, policy and new initiatives</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>D32</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Flicek1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flicek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amode</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ensembl 2012</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>D84</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Maglott1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maglott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatusova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Entrez Gene: gene-centered information at NCBI</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>D52</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Dobin1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drenkow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaleski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Grabherr1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Fulllength transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>652</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Schulz1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zerbino</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vingron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Oases: robust de novo RNA-seq assembly across the dynamic range of expression levels</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1086</fpage>–<lpage>1092</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Altschul1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>215</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Schwartz1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baertsch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Human-mouse alignments with BLASTZ</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Guindon1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufayard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lefort</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anisimova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hordijk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>New algorithms and methods to estimate maximum-likelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of PhyML 3.0</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Kunin1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lapidus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mavromatis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hugenholtz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A bioinformatician's guide to metagenomics</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Mokili1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mokili</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohwer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dutilh</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Metagenomics and future perspectives in virus discovery</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Virology</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Lesch1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lesch</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeske</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Some Suggestions for Teaching About Normal Approximations to Poisson and Binomial Distribution Functions</article-title>. <source>The American Statistician</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Breitbart1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitbart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salamon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andresen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahaffy</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Segall</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genomic analysis of uncultured marine viral communities</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>14250</fpage>–<lpage>14255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Thiry1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiry</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bublot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubuisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Bressem</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lequarre</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Molecular biology of bovine herpesvirus type 4</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-WangJohanning1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang-Johanning</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Epp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Quantitation of HERV-K env gene expression and splicing in human breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1528</fpage>–<lpage>1535</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Zhao1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Optimizing de novo transcriptome assembly from short-read RNA-Seq data: a comparative study</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source> <volume>12 Suppl 14</volume>: <fpage>S2</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-zurHausen5"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>zur Hausen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Oncogenic DNA viruses</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>7820</fpage>–<lpage>7823</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Berk1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Recent lessons in gene expression, cell cycle control, and cell biology from adenovirus</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>7673</fpage>–<lpage>7685</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Eash1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gasparovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Querbes</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atwood</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The human polyomaviruses</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>865</fpage>–<lpage>876</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-ElguideOliveira1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elgui de Oliveira</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>DNA viruses in human cancer: an integrated overview on fundamental mechanisms of viral carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source> <volume>247</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-deVilliers1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Villiers</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fauquet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broker</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>zur Hausen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Classification of papillomaviruses</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> <volume>324</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Simmonds1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Combet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deleage</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Consensus proposals for a unified system of nomenclature of hepatitis C virus genotypes</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>962</fpage>–<lpage>973</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Karlin1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaisdell</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schachtel</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Contrasts in codon usage of latent versus productive genes of Epstein-Barr virus: data and hypotheses</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>4264</fpage>–<lpage>4273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Voisset1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voisset</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Human RNA “rumor” viruses: the search for novel human retroviruses in chronic disease</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Dyson1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Münger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The human papilloma virus-16 E7 oncoprotein is able to bind to the retinoblastoma gene product</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>243</volume>: <fpage>934</fpage>–<lpage>937</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Scheffner1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werness</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huibregtse</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The E6 oncoprotein encoded by human papillomavirus types 16 and 18 promotes the degradation of p53</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>1136</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Young1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rickinson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Epstein-Barr virus: 40 years on</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Kelly1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stylianou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>An Epstein-Barr virus anti-apoptotic protein constitutively expressed in transformed cells and implicated in burkitt lymphomagenesis: the Wp/BHRF1 link</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000341</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Klein1"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kis</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Epstein-Barr virus infection in humans: from harmless to life endangering virus-lymphocyte interactions</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1297</fpage>–<lpage>1305</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Houben1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houben</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinkam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schrama</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Merkel cell polyomavirus-infected Merkel cell carcinoma cells require expression of viral T antigens</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>7064</fpage>–<lpage>7072</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Cornelissen1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelissen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Kuyl</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Burg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zorgdrager</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Noesel</surname><given-names>CJM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Gene expression profile of AIDS-related Kaposi's sarcoma</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Metzenberg1"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Levels of Epstein-Barr virus DNA in lymphoblastoid cell lines are correlated with frequencies of spontaneous lytic growth but not with levels of expression of EBNA-1, EBNA-2, or latent membrane protein</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Coffin1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Coffin JM, Hughes SH, Varmus HE, Rosenberg N, Jolicoeur P (1997) Retroviral Pathogenesis. Retroviruses. Cold Spring Harbor (NY): Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Ono1"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasunaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ushikubo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide sequence of human endogenous retrovirus genome related to the mouse mammary tumor virus genome</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>598</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Tomlins1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomlins</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laxman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helgeson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Distinct classes of chromosomal rearrangements create oncogenic ETS gene fusions in prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>448</volume>: <fpage>595</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Si1"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus-encoded latencyassociated nuclear antigen induces chromosomal instability through inhibition of p53 function</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>697</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-McLaughlinDrubin1"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin-Drubin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Viruses associated with human cancer</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1782</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Fang1"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Design and validation issues in RNA-seq experiments</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003228-Bannert1"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bannert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Retroelements and the human genome: new perspectives on an old relation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>101 Suppl 2</volume>: <fpage>14572</fpage>–<lpage>14579</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>