<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-12-01649</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary modeling</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Evolutionary Capacitance and Control of Protein Stability in Protein-Protein Interaction Networks</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Evolutionary Capacitance and Protein Networks</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dixit</surname>
            <given-names>Purushottam D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Maslov</surname>
            <given-names>Sergei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Biology, Brookhaven National Laboratory, Upton, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Physics and Astronomy, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Laufer Center for Physical and Quantitative Biology, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, New York, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Liberles</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Wyoming, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">maslov@bnl.gov</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: PDD SM. Performed the experiments: PDD. Analyzed the data: PDD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PDD. Wrote the paper: PDD SM.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id>e1003023</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article, free of all copyright, and may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. The work is made available under the Creative Commons CC0 public domain dedication.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In addition to their biological function, protein complexes reduce the exposure of the constituent proteins to the risk of undesired oligomerization by reducing the concentration of the free monomeric state. We interpret this reduced risk as a stabilization of the functional state of the protein. We estimate that protein-protein interactions can account for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of additional stabilization; a substantial contribution to intrinsic stability. We hypothesize that proteins in the interaction network act as <italic>evolutionary capacitors</italic> which allows their binding partners to explore regions of the sequence space which correspond to less stable proteins. In the interaction network of baker's yeast, we find that statistically proteins that receive higher energetic benefits from the interaction network are more likely to misfold. A simplified fitness landscape wherein the fitness of an organism is inversely proportional to the total concentration of unfolded proteins provides an evolutionary justification for the proposed trends. We conclude by outlining clear biophysical experiments to test our predictions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="summary">
        <title>Author Summary</title>
        <p>The folded form of proteins is only marginally stable <italic>in vivo</italic> and constantly faces the risk of aggregation, unfolding/misfolding, and other aberrant interactions. For most proteins, the folded form is also the functionally relevant one and forces of natural selection strongly modulate its stability. <italic>In vivo</italic>, proteins interact with each other on a genome-wide scale. Usually, the interaction of a protein and its binding partners requires both the proteins to be in the folded form and as a result, the interactions tend to shift the population of a protein towards the folded form. Consequently, protein-protein interactions interfere with the evolution of protein stability. Here, we present empirical evidence and theoretical justification for proteins' ability to stabilize the folded form of their interaction partners and allow them to explore the region of the sequence space that corresponds to proteins with less stable structure. We argue that the ‘evolutionary capacitance’ – previously thought to be a property of the chaperone HSP90, a special class of proteins – is a property of all proteins, albeit to a different degree.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was funded by the DOE Systems Biology KBase university-led project “Tools and Models for Integrating Multiple Cellular Networks” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genomicscience.energy.gov/compbio/kbaseprojects.shtml" xlink:type="simple">http://genomicscience.energy.gov/compbio/kbaseprojects.shtml</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The toxicity due to protein misfolding and aggregation has a considerable effect on the viability of living organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Drummond1">[1]</xref>–. Consequently, cells are under strong selection pressure to evolve thermodynamically stable <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Zeldovich1">[6]</xref> and aggregation-free protein sequences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Monsellier1">[7]</xref>. The internal region of stable proteins has a tightly packed core of hydrophobic residues. A mutation in the core may disrupt the entire protein structure. Consequently, the core residues are strongly conserved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Alberts1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Branden1">[9]</xref>. In contrast, mutations on the surface contribute weakly to the thermodynamic stability of proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Tokuriki1">[10]</xref> yet surfaces show significant level of conservation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Pazos1">[11]</xref> owing to protein-protein interactions.</p>
      <p>Recent high throughput experiments have established that proteins interact with each other on a genome-wide scale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Wagner1">[12]</xref>. Such ‘small world’ networks are thought to facilitate biological signaling and ensure that cells remain robust even after a random failure of some of its components <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Jeong1">[13]</xref>. It is thought that evolutionarily, multi-protein complexes are favored over larger size of individual proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Lynch1">[14]</xref> since large proteins are difficult to fold and expensive to synthesize while small interacting proteins can fold independently and then efficiently assemble into large complexes. Individual interaction between proteins can give rise to cooperativity and allostery which results in a finer control over the functional task the protein complex performs. Protein-protein interactions (PPI) are also thought to prevent protein aggregation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Masino1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Pechmann1">[16]</xref>. Lastly, many proteins can perform promiscuous function in that they can partake in multiple protein complexes. Interestingly, proteins in higher organisms are involved in more interactions and form larger protein complexes compared to more primitive life forms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Fernndez1">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Here, we hypothesize an additional biophysical advantage for protein-protein interactions. Proteins bound to their interaction partners <italic>effectively</italic> present a lower monomer concentration inside the cell. Since free monomers are susceptible to misfolding/unfolding and toxic oligomerization, interacting proteins may face a reduced risk towards the same. This reduced risk can be interpreted as interaction-induced stabilization <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> — stabilization due to the protein-protein interaction network — of an otherwise monomeric protein (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003023-g001">Fig. 1</xref> for a cartoon). We propose that by giving proteins an additional stability, each protein in the interaction network acts as an <italic>evolutionary capacitor</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford2">[19]</xref> in the evolution of its binding partners: proteins are allowed to explore the less stable regions (regions of low intrinsic stability) of the sequence space as long as they are stabilized by their interaction partners. Inversely, unstable proteins are expected to receive significant additional stability from the interaction network.</p>
      <fig id="pcbi-1003023-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The equilibrium between the folded state of protein A (blue protein) and its unfolded/insoluble state (blue coil) is affected by the interactions of the folded state with its interaction partner B (red).</title>
          <p>The formation of the AB dimer lowers the population of the unfolded/insoluble state of protein A and effectively stabilizes the folded state.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Below we outline the empirical evidence for our hypothesis and suggest clear biophysical and evolutionary experiments to test it further.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>We present our estimates of the interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>) and explore the evolutionary interplay between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and protein stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> using a simplified fitness model for a toy proteome. We test the predictions of the toy model on the proteome of baker's yeast. The fitness model also sheds light on the interplay between protein stability and protein abundance.</p>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is comparable to inherent stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></title>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003023-g002">Fig. 2</xref> shows the histogram of the estimated interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> cytoplasmic yeast proteins for whom abundance, interaction, and localization data is available (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> for the details of the calculations). Note that the average PPI induced stability is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and can be as high as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This stabilization is dependent not only on the number of interaction partners of a given protein or the strengths of those interactions but also on the relative abundances of the interaction partners. In fact, the interaction-induced stability of a protein correlates strongly with the relative concentration of its binding partners<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e012"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>(Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This suggests a plausible mechanism of stabilization of a protein without changing its sequence viz. via adjusting the expression levels of its interaction partners (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref> below).</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1003023-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The histogram of estimated PPI-induced stabilities for the yeast cytoplasmic proteome (See main text).</title>
            <p>While the average stability is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, some proteins can receive as much as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of stability from their binding partners. Note that the peak near <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is due to proteins which have no interaction partners and are by definition not stabilized by the PPI network.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The estimated <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values are of the same order of magnitude as the inherent stabilities of proteins, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Branden1">[9]</xref>. Given that random mutations are more likely to destabilize proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Zeldovich1">[6]</xref>, we expect protein-protein interactions to act as secondary mechanisms to stabilize proteins and to interfere with the evolution of protein stability.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Simplified fitness model explores the interplay between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></title>
        <p>To explore the evolutionary consequences of the interaction-induced stability, we investigate a simplified fitness model of a toy proteome consisting of 15 proteins (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s005">Table S1</xref>). Briefly, the fitness of the cell depends only on the total concentration of unfolded proteins in it <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Geilersamerotte1">[20]</xref>. During the course of evolution, each protein acquires random mutations that change either a) its inherent stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or b) the dissociation constant of its interaction with a randomly selected interaction partner. Even though protein abundance and protein-protein interactions evolve at the same time scale as protein stability, the former are dictated largely by the biological function of the involved proteins. Incorporating the fitness effects of changes in expression levels and interaction partners in our simple model is non-trivial. Thus, in order to specifically probe the relation between stability and interactions, we do not allow proteins to change their abundance and interaction partners.</p>
        <p>In the model, the concentration of unfolded proteins and thus the fitness of the proteome depends on the total stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of individual proteins. While random mutations are more likely to make proteins unstable, protein-protein interactions increase the total stability. In the canonical ensemble description of the evolution of fitness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Sella1">[21]</xref>, the inverse effective population size (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), the <italic>evolutionary temperature</italic> quantifies the importance of genetic drift. The <italic>effective</italic> population size modulates the competition between destabilizing random mutations and stabilizing protein-protein interactions.</p>
        <p>We find that at higher effective populations, proteins are inherently stable and only the least stable proteins (small <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) receive high stabilization from the interaction network (high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). At low effective population, due to genetic drift, proteins are inherently destabilized and protein-protein interactions serve as the primary determinant of the <italic>effective</italic> stability of proteins. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003023-g003">Fig. 3</xref> shows the dependence of average inherent stability (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), average interaction-induced stability (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and average total stability (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with effective population size. Interestingly, the total stability (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) of proteins remains relatively insensitive to changes in population size.</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1003023-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The average of inherent stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (triangles) and the interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (squares) as a function of effective population size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the toy proteome.</title>
            <p>The curves are fitted to the data only to highlight trends, blue curve represents the total stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Population size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is in arbitrary units. The shaded area roughly represents the region of the red and the black curve that correspond to the empirically observed folding free energies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Branden1">[9]</xref> and the estimated interaction-induced free energy <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We observe that the correlation coefficient between the inherent stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> itself varies with the effective population size. Even though its magnitude decreases, interaction-induced stability becomes more and more correlated with inherent stability as population size increases (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003023-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). In real life organisms, interaction-induced stability acts on a need basis for proteins and serve as a secondary stabilization mechanism. In the drift-dominated regime, which is unlikely to be realized in real life organisms (except probably in parasitic microbes with low population sizes), interaction-induced stability becomes the dominant player in the evolution of total stability of proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Fernndez1">[17]</xref>. We next examine if this prediction from the toy model holds for real organisms.</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1003023-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The spearman correlation coefficient between interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and inherent stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of effective population size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (See supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref>).</title>
            <p>Population size is in arbitrary units. The blue region identifies the location of real life proteomes (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003023-g003">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Induced stability correlates with aggregation propensity</title>
        <p>Proteome-wide information about the inherent stability of proteins <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is currently unavailable. Previously, <italic>in silico</italic> estimates of protein aggregation propensity have been used as proxy for protein stability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Yang1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Niwa1">[23]</xref>. We use the TANGO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">[24]</xref> algorithm to estimate protein aggregation propensity. It is known that TANGO aggregation propensity correlates strongly and negatively with protein stability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">[24]</xref>. TANGO has been verified extensively with experiments on peptide aggregation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">[24]</xref> and has been previously used to study the evolutionary aspects of protein-protein interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Yang1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Yang2">[25]</xref>. Similar analysis for Aggrescan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-ConchilloSole1">[26]</xref> can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s007">Table S3</xref>. We find that the aggregation propensity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is correlated positively with the interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). As expected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Drummond2">[2]</xref>, the aggregation propensity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is negatively correlated with protein abundance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The correlation between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> does not depend on this underlying dependence and persists even after controlling for total abundance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (partial Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s006">Table S2</xref>). This result suggests in the proteome of baker's yeast, protein stability correlates negatively with interaction-induced stability.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Aggregation propensity correlates <italic>principally</italic> with free monomer abundance</title>
        <p>The fitness cost of protein aggregation is directly proportional to the amount of aggregate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Geilersamerotte1">[20]</xref>. Thus, the selection forces that make protein sequences aggregation-free act more strongly on highly expressed proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Drummond1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Drummond2">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Yang1">[22]</xref>. Our hypothesis suggests that the proteins that are bound to their interaction partners present a lower concentration of the <italic>free monomeric</italic> state <italic>in vivo</italic> (low <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and automatically lower the misfolding/aggregation induced fitness cost, even if highly abundant (high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The selection forces to evolve an aggregation-free sequence may be weaker for such proteins. Consequently, the aggregation propensity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> should be principally correlated with the free monomer concentration <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> rather than the total abundance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>Indeed, we observe that the estimated monomer concentration <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the aggregation propensity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are correlated negatively (Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Importantly, this correlation is not an artifact of the underlying correlation between the aggregation propensity and total abundance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (partial Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). At the same time, the partial correlation coefficient between the aggregation propensity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the total protein abundance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> controlling for the estimated monomer concentration <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is minimal (partial Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). In short, the total free monomer concentration <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of a protein (rather than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, its total abundance) might be a better variable to relate to evolutionary and biophysical constraints on the protein.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Interacting proteins as evolutionary capacitors</title>
        <p>We have thus far shown that a protein's interaction partners can significantly stabilize its folded state and this stabilization interferes with the evolution of the inherent stability of the protein. We now explore the reverse viz. the evolutionary consequences of the ability of each protein to impart stability to its interaction partners.</p>
        <p>The concept of evolutionary capacitor has been previously introduced for the heat shock protein HSP90 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford2">[19]</xref>, which is also a molecular chaperone and a highly connected hub in the PPI network (70 interaction partners in the current analysis). An elevated concentration of HSP90 buffers the potentially unstable variation in proteins, which may allow proteins to sample a wider region of the sequence space, which may often lead to functional diversification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Khersonsky1">[27]</xref>. Similar to HSP90, each protein in the interaction network has some ability to stabilize its interaction partners to a certain extent. Consequently, we study the evolutionary <italic>capacitance</italic> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of individual proteins in the context of the interaction network by estimating the effect of protein knockout on ppi-induced stability <italic>in silico</italic>. Proteins with higher evolutionary capacitance are defined as those with the higher cumulative destabilizing effect on the proteome. We write,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e073"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e073" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>For each protein <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the sum in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e073">Eq. 1</xref> is carried out over all proteins <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that are destabilized due to its knockout. Here, we assume that the potential of a given protein knockout to generate multiple phenotypes depends on the loss of stability of its interaction partners caused by its knockout. We hypothesize that, similar to unstable proteins requiring HSP90 to fold, the interaction partners of proteins with high capacitance should be unstable. In fact, the capacitance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of a protein and the mean aggregation propensity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of its interaction partners are strongly correlated (Spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The capacitance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is significantly correlated with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> even after controlling for the abundance of the protein (partial spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the number of its interaction partners (partial spearman <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). This suggests that a protein needs to be present in sufficient quantity and should interact with a large number of proteins in order to effectively act as a capacitor.</p>
        <p>We have presented evidence that all proteins can act as an <italic>evolutionary capacitor</italic>, albeit with variable effectiveness, for their interaction partners. Traditionally, evolutionary capacitors are understood to be chaperones that buffer phenotypic variations by helping misolding-prone proteins fold in a proper structure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford2">[19]</xref>. Not surprisingly, when we carried out functional term enrichment analysis using gene ontology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Carbon1">[28]</xref>, we found that approximately half of the top 20 capacitors have ‘chaperone’ in their name. The top 20 are also over represented in the chaperone-like molecular function of <italic>protein binding</italic> and <italic>unfolded protein binding</italic> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the biological process of <italic>protein folding</italic> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). These findings validate our definition of capacitors that were previously identified as chaperones. Interestingly, some of the predicted capacitors do not currently have a protein folding-related functional annotation. These need more experimental investigation (see supplementary File S1 for the list). This suggests that previously identified <italic>evolutionary capacitor</italic> HSP90 may in fact only be one among the broader set of <italic>evolutionary capacitors</italic>. Every protein in the interaction network is an <italic>evolutionary capacitor</italic> for its interaction partners and <italic>evolutionary capacitor</italic> is a quantitative distinction rather than a qualitative one.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Recently, Fernández and Lynch <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Fernndez1">[17]</xref> showed that random genetic drift is the chief driving force behind thermodynamically less stable yet densely interacting proteins in higher organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Fernndez1">[17]</xref>. Additionally, protein complexes in higher organisms have more members than in lower organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Lynch1">[14]</xref>. Recently, it was observed that a destabilizing mutation in the enzyme DHFR in <italic>E. coli</italic> leads to functional tetramerization of the otherwise monomeric enzyme <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Bershtein1">[29]</xref> suggesting that protein-protein interactions can at least partially compensate the effect of protein destabilization. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> lactoglobulin is an aggregation-prone protein generally found as a dimer. It was shown that the specific interactions responsible for the formation of the dimer considerably reduce the risk of protein aggregation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Pechmann1">[16]</xref>. Ataxin-3 is a protein implicated in polyglutamine expansion diseases wherein the functional interactions of the protein reduce the exposure of its aggregation prone interface and thereby decrease its aggregation propensity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Masino1">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Here, we have quantified the interaction-induced stability on a proteome wide scale and hypothesized that the PPI-induced stabilization is a secondary evolutionary advantage of the PPI network; alleviating the selection pressure on proteins in functional multi-protein complexes to evolve a stable folded. A simple model for the fitness of the proteome provided a fundamental justification for the co-evolution of protein stability and protein-protein interactions and made predictions that were tested on the proteome of baker's yeast. In the model, when the effects of natural selection are weak, proteins acquire stability mainly via protein-protein interactions. At a higher population size — in the absence of genetic drift — proteins are intrinsically stable and protein-protein interactions stabilize only those proteins that fail to evolve inherent stability.</p>
      <p>We have also presented evidence that <italic>all</italic> interacting proteins stabilize their binding partners to a certain extent and act as the evolutionary capacitance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford2">[19]</xref> for their evolution. Interestingly, though some of the top 20 capacitors predicted in this study are known chaperones and are over-represented in GO ontology terms such as <italic>protein binding</italic>, <italic>unfolded protein binding</italic>, and <italic>protein folding</italic>; others do not have any protein folding-related functional annotation and need experimental investigation.</p>
      <p>The importance of disordered proteins, especially in the proteomes of higher organisms, cannot be neglected. The proteome of baker's yeast does not have many completely disordered proteins but <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the amino acids in the proteins of yeast are predicted to be in a disordered state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Ward1">[30]</xref> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the proteins considered in this study, see supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s004">Fig. S4</xref>). Even though the development presented above applied only to an equilibrium between folded and unfolded/misfolded/aggregated protein, it can be easily generalized to disordered proteins. This is because even though the folded <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> unfolded equilibrium is not well defined, similar to well structured proteins, disordered proteins also exist either in a soluble monomeric (instead of the folded state), a misfolded/aggregated, and a complexed state. Many disordered proteins acquire a definite structure when bound to their interaction partners and seldom dissociate to the soluble monomeric <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Dyson1">[31]</xref>. These serve as even stronger candidates for the beneficiaries of interaction-induced stability compared to folded proteins. Consequently, we include both partially disordered proteins and structured proteins in the current analysis of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> cytoplasmic proteins.</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Suggested experimental tests</title>
        <sec id="s3a1">
          <title>Modulation of protein stability by overexpression of its partners</title>
          <p>We predict that the measured free energy of protein folding in vivo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Ignatova1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Guo1">[33]</xref> will be lower than the in vitro measurement. Moreover, this free energy can be modulated by overexpressing the interaction partners of the protein that increases the equilibrium constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between the folded monomer and the generic complexed state. Recently, it was observed that the measured stability of phosphoglycerate kinase was higher by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Guo1">[33]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a2">
          <title>Overexpression-instability epistasis</title>
          <p>Does the PPI-induced stabilization have evolutionary advantages? We propose the following experimental test. Consider two mutated phenotypes for an isolated interacting pair of proteins A and B in an organism 1) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, a destabilized mutant of protein A and 2) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> where B is overexpressed. We predict that lowering of the organismal fitness due to destabilization of protein A (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) can be at least partially rescued by the overexpression of the protein B (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) i.e. the combination of two penalizing mutations may perhaps be advantageous to the organism.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Law of mass action and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></title>
        <p>In cellular homeostasis, the total concentration <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of any protein <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be written as the sum of its free folded monomer concentration <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, a fraction comprising of insoluble oligomers and unfolded peptide <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and as part of all protein complexes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> containing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003023-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). In our computational model, for simplicity and owing to the nature of the large scale data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Stark1">[34]</xref>, we restrict protein complexes to dimers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Maslov1">[35]</xref>, thus for all proteins <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that interact with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e105"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e105" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>Conservation of mass implies,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e106"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e106" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>The concentration <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of each dimer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> satisfies the law of mass action,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e109"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e109" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>We can write the balance between the three states of the protein, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003023-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), as two <italic>equilibrium</italic> equations<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e111"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e111" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e112"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e112" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>Note that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> comprises of a collection of biologically unusable states of the protein viz. the misfolded/unfolded and the oligomerized state any of which may convert to/interact with the folded monomeric state <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Consequently, the first equilibrium <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a collection of <italic>thermodynamic equilibriums</italic>. The equilibrium constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> will thus depend not only on the temperature <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> but also on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. If among the unfolded, misfolded, and the oligomerized states the former dominates the population comprising <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> then, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the thermodynamic stability of the free monomeric state. Similarly, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e124"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e124" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>and depends not only on the dissociation constants <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> but also the free concentrations <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the interacting partners of protein <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and on the topology of the interaction network in the organism. Here too, we assume that a) only the folded monomeric forms of proteins interact with each other and b) there is no appreciable interaction between the collective unfolded state <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of protein <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and any state of any other protein <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We have also neglected the role of chaperones in actively reducing the concentration of the unfolded/misfolded/aggregated state by turning it over to the folded state. In fact, some of the chaperones are included in of our mass action equilibrium model and prevent unfolding by sequestering the folded state (see below and the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">discussion</xref> section).</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1003023-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>At steady state, protein A can be present either as a mixture of misfolded monomers and insoluble oligomers (U<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), a folded monomer F<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, or in a complex with its interaction partners (D<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>By combining mass conservation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e106">Eq. 3</xref>) with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e111">Eq. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e112">Eq. 6</xref>,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e134"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e134" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>In the above development, we have made a crucial assumption that only.</p>
        <p>Note that in the absence of interactions, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We identify <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as the additional decrease in the insoluble fraction due to protein-protein interactions. We define the interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e138"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e138" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Identification of proteins and the mass action model</title>
        <p>We downloaded the latest set of interacting proteins in baker's yeast from the BIOGRID database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Startk1">[36]</xref>. To filter for non-reproducible interactions and experimental artifacts, we retained only those interactions that were confirmed in two or more separate experiments. For the sake of simplicity, we only considered cytoplasmic proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Huh1">[37]</xref> with known concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Ghaemmaghami1">[38]</xref>. This lead to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> proteins connected by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> interactions.</p>
        <p>The <italic>in vivo</italic> stability of a protein is a combination of its thermodynamic stability, resistance to aggregation or oligomerization, and resistance to degradation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Tokuriki2">[39]</xref>. Note that the interaction-induced stability of a protein depends on the stability of its interaction partners (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e112">Eq. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e124">Eq. 7</xref>, and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e138">Eq. 9</xref>). Unfortunately, the exact dependence of the <italic>in vivo</italic> protein stability on its sequence is unclear and there exist no reliable data or sequence dependent computational estimates for the thermodynamic stability of proteins. Moreover, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and thus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e112">Eq. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e124">Eq. 7</xref>, and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e138">Eq. 9</xref>), can be estimated even in the absence of the knowledge of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In our estimates of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we assume that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given simply by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e146"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>Here, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is obtained by solving the mass action equations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Maslov1">[35]</xref> iteratively (see below). This is equivalent to assuming that all the proteins are equally and highly stable (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for all proteins <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> thus calculated serves as the upper limit of interaction-induced stability. In the supplementary materials (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s001">Fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s002">Fig. S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s008">Tables S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s009">S5</xref>), we show that different assignments of the equilibrium constants including a simple model of protein stability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Ghosh1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Ghosh2">[42]</xref> do not change the qualitative nature of our observations.</p>
        <p>The dissociation constants <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for protein-protein interactions follow a lognormal distribution with a mean <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> nM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Maslov1">[35]</xref>. The majority of interactions between proteins are neither too weak nor unnecessarily strong. Common sense dictates that it does not make sense to decrease the dissociation constant between two proteins beyond the point where the abundance limiting protein spends all of its time in the bound state. Motivated by these evolutionary arguments to minimize unnecessary protein production and to avoid unnecessarily strong interactions, Maslov and Ispolatov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Maslov1">[35]</xref> devised a recipe to assign dissociation constants to individual protein-protein interactions. viz. for interacting proteins <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the dissociation constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We also explore a few other assignment rules for dissociation constants (see supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s003">Fig. S3</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s010">Table S6</xref>).</p>
        <p>We solve for free concentrations <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> iteratively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Maslov1">[35]</xref>. We start by setting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for all proteins and iteratively calculate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e159"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e159" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>till two consecutive estimates of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fall within <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of each other for all proteins.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Simplified fitness model for cellular proteomes</title>
        <p>As noted above, the toxic effects of misfolding and aggregation may be the chief determinant of protein sequence evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Drummond2">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Wilke1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Olzscha1">[5]</xref>. The dosage dependent fitness effect of misfolded proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Geilersamerotte1">[20]</xref> motivates us to introduce a simple biophysical model for fitness <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the proteome (See <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003023.e163">Eq. 11</xref>),<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003023.e163"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e163" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the scaling factor. Potentially, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be estimated from fitness experiments by introducing measured quantities of unfolded protein in the cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Geilersamerotte1">[20]</xref>. We explore the evolution of a hypothetical proteome to investigate the interplay between protein stability and protein-protein interactions.</p>
        <p>We believe that protein abundances and the topology of the interaction network are largely dictated by biological function. It is non-trivial to incorporate the fitness effect of changes in gene expression level and the network topology in our simplified model. Thus, to specifically probe the relation between stability and interactions, we concentrate on the effect of toxic gain of function due to misfolding and aggregation on cellular fitness and not include changes in gene expression levels and network topology. In this aspect, our model is in the same spirit as previously proposed models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Zeldovich1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Dill1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Heo2">[48]</xref>. The effect of random mutations on average destabilizes proteins and the dynamics of the evolution of thermodynamic stability of proteins can be modeled as a random walk with negative average velocity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Zeldovich1">[6]</xref>. We consider the thermodynamic stability as a proxy for the <italic>in vivo</italic> stability of proteins. We construct the cytoplasm of a hypothetical organism with 15 proteins. The number of proteins is low due to computational restrictions. The proteome is evolved by sampling the dissociation constants from the lognormal distribution while introducing random mutations in proteins that change their stability. At each generation, the fitness is evaluated and the progeny is accepted at a certain <italic>evolutionary temperature</italic> (defined as the inverse of the effective population size, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Sella1">[21]</xref>. We run a total of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> generations for each <italic>evolutionary temperature</italic> and analyze the organism in the latter half of the evolutionary run (details of the model and a brief description of the population genetics terminology is in supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Aggregation propensity</title>
        <p>The notion of protein stability relevant to this study is the propensity of a protein to avoid structural transformations that may render it unemployable for biological function. For example, for a small and highly soluble protein, this stability corresponds to the thermodynamic stability of the native state while for a large multi domain protein, it may correspond to the thermodynamic stability of one of its domains against the partially unfolded state. In short, thermodynamic stability of the folded state with respect to the unfolded, partially folded state, and the misfolded state all contribute to the <italic>in vivo</italic> stability of proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Tokuriki2">[39]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Though there is a lack of proteome-wide estimates of thermodynamic stability of proteins, the aggregation propensity can be estimated from the sequence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-ConchilloSole1">[26]</xref> and is known to be correlated with protein stability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">[24]</xref>. In our correlation analysis, we use the estimated aggregation propensity as a proxy for <italic>in vivo</italic> protein stability and explore the relationship between interaction-induced stability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and protein stability. The aggregation propensity was estimated for the same <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> proteins used in the mass action calculation to estimate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We tested the TANGO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">[24]</xref> and Aggrescan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-ConchilloSole1">[26]</xref> to estimate the aggregation propensity of proteins. Previously, TANGO has been used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Yang1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Niwa1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-Chen3">[49]</xref> to understand the relation between protein abundance and instability. We show results for TANGO in the main text. Aggrescan results (supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s011">Text S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003023.s007">Table S3</xref>) are quite similar.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The histogram of interaction-induced stabilities <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when protein stabilities depend on their chain length.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The histogram of interaction-induced stabilities <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when protein stabilities are set at their minimum.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The histogram of interaction-induced stabilities <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when all dissociation constants are set at 5 nM.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The histogram of estimated disorder in the proteins of the yeast proteome.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A table for the parameters and topology of the toy proteome.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A table reporting correlations between stability and interaction using TANGO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">[24]</xref>.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s007" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A table reporting correlations between stability and interaction using AGGRESCAN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003023-ConchilloSole1">[26]</xref>.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s008" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s008" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A table reporting correlations between stability and interaction when protein stabilities depend on their chain length.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s009" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s009" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A table reporting correlations between stability and interaction when protein stabilities are set to their minumum.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s010" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s010" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A table reporting correlations between stability and interaction when all dissociation constants are set at 5 nM.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003023.s011" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003023.s011" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>An inventory of population genetics terms, additional information about the toy model, and misc. information about the analysis.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank Prof. Ken Dill, Dr. Adam de Graff, Prof. Dilip Asthagiri, and Ms. Shreya Saxena for valuable discussions and a critical reading of the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Drummond1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Why highly expressed proteins evolve slowly</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>14338</fpage>–<lpage>14343</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Drummond2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mistranslation-induced protein misfolding as a dominant constraint on coding-sequence evolution</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-GeilerSamerotte1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geiler-Samerotte</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dion</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budnik</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Misfolded proteins impose a dosage-dependent fitness cost and trigger a cytosolic unfolded protein response in yeast</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>680</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Wilke1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Signatures of protein biophysics in coding sequence evolution</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struc Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Olzscha1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olzscha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schermann</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woerner</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinkert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Amyloid-like Aggregates Sequester Numerous Metastable Proteins with Essential Cellular Functions</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Zeldovich1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeldovich</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Protein stability imposes limits on organism complexity and speed of molecular evolution</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>16152</fpage>–<lpage>16157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Monsellier1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monsellier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Prevention of amyloid-like aggregation as a driving force of protein evolution</article-title>. <source>EMBO reports</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>742</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Alberts1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Alberts B, Bray D, Lewis J, Raff M, Roberts K, et al. (2002) Molecular biology of the cell. New York: Garland Science.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Branden1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Branden C, Tooze J (1998) Introduction to protein structure. New York: Garland Science.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Tokuriki1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokuriki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stricher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schymkowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tawfik</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Stability Effects of Protein Mutations Appear to be Universally Distributed</article-title>. <source>J Mol Bio</source> <volume>369</volume>: <fpage>1318</fpage>–<lpage>1332</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Pazos1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pazos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helmer-Citterich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ausiello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valencia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Correlated mutations contain information about protein-protein interaction</article-title>. <source>J Mol Bio</source> <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>523</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Wagner1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The yeast protein interaction network evolves rapidly and contains few redundant duplicate genes</article-title>. <source>Mol Bio Evol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1283</fpage>–<lpage>1292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Jeong1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barabási</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Lethality and centrality in protein networks</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>411</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Lynch1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The evolution of multimeric protein assemblages</article-title>. <source>Mol Bio Evol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1353</fpage>–<lpage>1366</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msr300" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msr300</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Masino1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicastro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vendruscolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pastore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional interactions as a survival strategy against abnormal aggregation</article-title>. <source>The FASEB journal</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Pechmann1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pechmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tartaglia</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vendruscolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Physicochemical principles that regulate the competition between functional and dysfunctional association of proteins</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>10159</fpage>–<lpage>10164</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Fernndez1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Non-adaptive origins of interactome complexity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>474</volume>: <fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Hsp90 as a capacitor for morphological evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>396</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>342</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Rutherford2">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swalla</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Hsp90 Capacitor, Developmental Remodeling, and Evolution : The Robustness of Gene Networks and the Curious Evolvability of Metamorphosis</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Biochemistry</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Geilersamerotte1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geiler-samerotte</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dion</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budnik</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Misfolded proteins impose a dosage-dependent fitness cost and trigger a cytosolic unfolded protein response in yeast</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>680</fpage>–<lpage>685</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Sella1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirsh</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The application of statistical physics to evolutionary biology</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>9541</fpage>–<lpage>9546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Yang1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Impact of translational error-induced and error-free misfolding on the rate of protein evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Sys Bio</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Niwa1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Bimodal protein solubility distribution revealed by an aggregation analysis of the entire ensemble of escherichia coli proteins</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>4201</fpage>–<lpage>4206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-FernandezEscamilla1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Escamilla</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schymkowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Prediction of sequence-dependent and mutational effects on the aggregation of peptides and proteins</article-title>. <source>Nature Biotech</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1302</fpage>–<lpage>1306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Yang2">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Protein misinteraction avoidance causes highly expressed proteins to evolve slowly</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>–<lpage>840</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-ConchilloSole1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conchillo-Sole</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aviles</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vendrell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daura</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Aggrescan: a server for prediction and evaluation of “hot spots” of aggregation in polypeptides</article-title>. <source>Bioinfo</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Khersonsky1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khersonsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roodveldt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tawfik</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Enzyme promiscuity : evolutionary and mechanistic aspects</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Chem Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>508</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Carbon1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carbon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mungall</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>AmiGO: online access to ontology and annotation data</article-title>. <source>Bioinfo</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Bershtein1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bershtein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Soluble oligomerization provides a beneficial fitness effect on destabilizing mutations</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>4857</fpage>–<lpage>4862</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Ward1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGuffin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Prediction and functional analysis of native disorder in proteins from the three kingdoms of life</article-title>. <source>Journal of molecular biology</source> <volume>337</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>645</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Dyson1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Coupling of folding and binding for unstructured proteins</article-title>. <source>Current opinion in structural biology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Ignatova1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ignatova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Monitoring protein stability and aggregation in vivo by real-time fluorescent labeling</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>528</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Guo1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruebele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Temperature dependence of protein folding kinetics in living cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Stark1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breitkreutz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reuly</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breitkreutz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>BioGRID: a general repository for interaction datasets</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Maslov1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maslov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ispolatov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Propagation of large concentration changes in reversible proteinbinding networks</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>13655</fpage>–<lpage>13660</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Startk1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Startk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Breitkreutz</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chatr-Aryamontri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oughtred</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The biogrid interaction database: 2011 update</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>698</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Huh1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falvo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerke</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Global analysis of protein localization in budding yeast</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>425</volume>: <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>691</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Ghaemmaghami1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaemmaghami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Global analysis of protein expression in budding yeast</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>425</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>741</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Tokuriki2">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokuriki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tawfik</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Stability effects of mutations and protein evolvability</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struc Biol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>596</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Ghosh1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Computing protein stabilities from their chain lengths</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>10649</fpage>–<lpage>10654</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Dill1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmit</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Physical limits of cells and proteomes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>17876</fpage>–<lpage>17882</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Ghosh2">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cellular proteomes have broad distributions of protein stability</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>3996</fpage>–<lpage>4002</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Chen1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Thermal adaptation of viruses and bacteria</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>1118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Zeldovich2">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeldovich</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A first-principles model of early evolution: Emergence of gene families, species, and preferred protein folds</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comp Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e139</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Heo1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maslov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Topology of protein interaction network shapes protein abundances and strengths of their functional and nonspecific interactions</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>4258</fpage>–<lpage>4263</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Chen2">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Thermal adaptation of viruses and bacteria</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>1118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Wylie1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A biophysical protein folding model accounts for most mutational fitness effects in viruses</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>9916</fpage>–<lpage>9921</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Heo2">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakhnovich</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Emergence of species in evolutionary “simulated annealing”</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1869</fpage>–<lpage>1874</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1003023-Chen3">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dokholyan</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Natural selection against protein aggregation on self-interacting and essential proteins in yeast, fly, and worm</article-title>. <source>Mol Bio Evol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1530</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>