<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-13-01293</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Proteomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular complexes</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Theoretical biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Computer and information sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Computing methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical computing</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Applied mathematics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Micellar On-Pathway Intermediate Step Explains the Kinetics of Prion Amyloid Formation</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Micellar Intermediate in Prion Amyloid Formation</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hingant</surname><given-names>Erwan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontes</surname><given-names>Pascaline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Martinez</surname><given-names>Maria Teresa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnaud</surname><given-names>Jacques-Damien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liautard</surname><given-names>Jean-Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pujo-Menjouet</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>CI<sup>2</sup>MA, Universidad de Concepción, Concepción, Chile</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>INSERM U710, Université Montpellier 2, Place E. Bataillon, 3eme étage, Montpellier, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Etablissement Confiné d’Expérimentation, Plateforme RAM, UMS 3426-BioCampus, Place E. Bataillon, UM2, Montpellier, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Centre de Recherche sur les Pathogènes et Biologie pour la Santé, CPBS UMR5236, Université Montpellier 2, Place E. Bataillon, Montpellier, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Université de Lyon, CNRS, Université Lyon 1, Institut Camille Jordan UMR5208, Villeurbanne, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>INRIA Team Dracula, Inria Center Grenoble Rhône-Alpes, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markel</surname><given-names>Scott</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Accelrys, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ehingant@ci2ma.udec.cl</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JPL LPM. Performed the experiments: PF MTAM JDA. Analyzed the data: EH JPL LPM. Wrote the paper: EH JPL LPM. Developed the mathematical model: EH LPM.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003735</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Hingant et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In a previous work by Alvarez-Martinez <italic>et al.</italic> (2011), the authors pointed out some fallacies in the mainstream interpretation of the prion amyloid formation. It appeared necessary to propose an original hypothesis able to reconcile the <italic>in vitro</italic> data with the predictions of a mathematical model describing the problem. Here, a model is developed accordingly with the hypothesis that an intermediate on-pathway leads to the conformation of the prion protein into an amyloid competent isoform thanks to a structure, called micelles, formed from hydrodynamic interaction. The authors also compare data to the prediction of their model and propose a new hypothesis for the formation of infectious prion amyloids.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Understanding the mechanism of prions is an important issue. Indeed, it involves a mechanism modifying the structure of the proteins that are of high interest in theoretical biology. Knowing the underlying mechanism that leads to prion disease could help further investigations in the world of amyloid disease and for example the so-called Alzheimer's disease. The theory of prion, also known as Protein-Only, has been widely studied. Nevertheless no mathematical models are able to reproduce the phenomena <italic>in silico</italic>. This suggests a lack of information in the theory. Here we propose a new model, built with a new approach theory that fits experimental data in a very satisfactory way. This model, together with experiments, maintains the idea that an intermediate conformation of the protein helps the disease to spread. Besides, this work is an excellent example of a strong interaction between mathematical modelling and biological approach. Indeed, because of a strong discrepancy between theoretical results of the early original model and biological data on pathological prion formation, the team of biologists decided to investigate more closely their experiments. They came out with a new discovery: the crucial role of micelles in the pathological conformation of the prion protein.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work has been supported by ANR grant MADCOW no. ANR-08-JCJC-0135-01 (France). EH has been partially supported by FONDECYT postdoctoral grant no. 3130318 (Chile). The authors thank INRIA for its financial support. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Transmissible spongiform encephalopathies, or prion diseases, are a group of fatal neurodegenerative disorders of humans and animals. The pathogenic process is typically associated with conformational conversion of a cellular protein, called prion or PrP<sup>C</sup>, to a misfolded isoform, called PrP<sup>Sc</sup>. The “protein-only” model asserts that this rogue PrP<sup>Sc</sup> represents the infectious prion agent, self-propagating by binding PrP<sup>C</sup> and inducing its conversion to the abnormal PrP<sup>Sc</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Prusiner1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Prusiner2">[2]</xref>. This scenario was quantitatively described as a nucleation-dependent amyloid polymerization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Come1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Masel1">[4]</xref>. It is now generally accepted that the prion development process results from an amyloid polymerization after an initial nucleus formation in the very early phase of protein aggregation. Models based on nucleation-dependent polymerization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Ferrone1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Powers1">[7]</xref> describe a molecular mechanism at the origin of the formation of large protein aggregates, by involving thermodynamically unfavourable steps that become favourable when the nucleation kinetic barrier is reached. As a striking consequence of these models, the unfavourable first steps can be bypassed by seeding with preformed polymers. However, due to the transient nature of the initial nucleus, our understanding of the interactions that form this initial structure is very sparse and thus the understanding of species allowing the prion proteins to overcome the strong kinetic barrier to form a specific amyloid conformation is highly limited <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Serio1">[8]</xref>. This may have led to one of the most notable persisting fallacy claiming that the Lag phase of prion proliferation, defined as the required phase for the nucleus formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Come1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Harper1">[9]</xref>, reflects the unfavourable nucleation phase. This idea was challenged by experimental results obtained by numerous authors who revealed a linear dependence of the lag time (denoted by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) to monomer concentration not exceeding a nucleus size of about 2 monomers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Baskakov1">[11]</xref>. This result, also found for some other spontaneous amyloid-forming proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Collins1">[12]</xref>, was generally attributed to an accumulation of large off-pathway species whose formation is competitive with the on-pathway processes that lead to amyloid <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Baskakov1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Powers2">[13]</xref>. However, in the case of hamster rPrP (Recombinant Syrian Hamster Prion Protein 90–231) polymerized <italic>in vitro</italic>, we previously found no kinetic evidence for an off-pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1">[10]</xref>. Consequently, we propose that an additional on-pathway step is necessary to explain the results observed. We hypothesize that this new stage stands very likely for a first step. It would occur before nucleation, because experimentally, we were able to show that seeded polymerization always begins after a time delay that can be interpreted as the time needed to generate active monomers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1">[10]</xref>. We show indeed that micelles are formed, which leads to an amyloid competent isoform of the prion protein (denoted by PrP*) considered as a necessary step to induce nucleation and amyloid polymerization. This hypothesis is supported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lee2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lhrs1">[15]</xref> where it is found that lipid interactions play a key role in the conformation of PrP<sup>C</sup> into PrP<sup>Sc</sup> by β-sheet enrichment, see Sec. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref>. We assume here that a similar interaction occurs in our experimental condition by pure PrP<sup>C</sup> interaction with the help of micelles formation. To analyse the consequences of this hypothesis, we develop a quantitative model with an explicit description of the microscopic processes, and we compare experimental data with the results predicted by the model.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Micelles characterization</title>
<p>In order to find out what types of structures could be involved as an on-pathway, we have performed a time dependent electron microscopic analysis during polymerization of hamster rPrP. Few minutes after dilution into polymerization buffer, we observed spherical structures looking like rigid micelles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g001">Fig. 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003735.s006">Fig. S6</xref> in Supporting Information). The size distribution fits well with a log normal distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>). The size of these spheres was heterogeneous with a mean around 30 nm. A sphere of 30 nm diameter reaches a surface area of around 30 nm<sup>2</sup>, the rPrP have a diameter (thanks to Protein Workshop v1.0 and PDB ID 1B10) of about 1.5 to 2 nm thus the sphere contains about 1000 proteins on its surface. In order to ensure that these structures are formed of rPrP, we decided to label them with antibodies. This method clearly identified spheres consisting of rPrP (details in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003735.s001">Fig. S1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003735-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Micelle-like structures.</title>
<p>A. Electron microscopy view of the rPrP<sup>C</sup> few minutes after solubilisation (see Materials and Methods). Samples were adsorbed on carbon/formvar film and negatively stained by 2% uranyl-acetate, and examined on a Jeol 1200 EX. B. Diameter measurement of the micelles observed on one sample as described in item A.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Micelles quantity correlates with fibrils in a precursor relationship</title>
<p>In a previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1">[10]</xref>, we showed that polymerization kinetics could not be explained by the existence of an off-pathway. Thus an important question remains: what exactly is the role of micelles in the polymerization mechanism? To answer this, we decided to analyse the evolution of the micelle quantity during polymerization kinetics. Qualitative analysis using electron microscopy revealed that the number of micelles is important a few minutes after dilution into polymerization buffer, and then rapidly decreases when fibrils are formed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). A semi-quantitative analysis of the amount of round shape structures suggested a precursor relationship between the micelles and fibrils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). This was established in two different buffers exhibiting very different lag phase and thus showing that it is very likely a common feature of <italic>in vitro</italic> prion polymerization.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003735-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Micelle-like structures precede amyloid fibril formation.</title>
<p>Comparison of the dynamics of micelles and amyloids. Amyloid formation was measured by fluorescence of ThT (in black circle) and micelles number (in red circle) counted directly on arbitrarily selected grids observed at the same magnification (top in buffer B and down in buffer C).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Quantitative model of polymerization including on-pathway micelles</title>
<p>To quantitatively analyse the consequences of an on-pathway micelle intermediate, we built an <italic>a priori</italic> model describing the different steps with the microscopic processes involved and their contributions to the whole system. From this microscopic model it is then possible to quantify macroscopic data, such as micelles, polymers and monomers concentration. The model can be detailed into four main parts.</p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item>
<p><bold>Phase 1:</bold> Formation of dependent PrP micelles through a growth phase with addition and loss of monomers as a cluster dynamics. It corresponds to the early phase in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref> where micelle quantity increases (curve with red circles) while the PrP<sup>Sc</sup> still remains constant (curve with black circles).</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Phase 2:</bold> Micelles help the transition towards a new structure (PrP*) that is stabilized in the micelle itself and is released as an isoform monomer. This is the main hypothesis of our work. Production of PrP* occurs all along the process until the stabilization of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> is reached.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Phase 3:</bold> The free isoform (PrP*) is able to reach the nucleation barrier and then nucleates. It corresponds to the phase in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref> where micelles (red circles) start to decrease while the quantity of polymers (black circles) remains constant.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Phase 4:</bold> Nucleation promotes polymerization of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> and fibrils split when size increases, leading to a rapid polymer (black circles) growth phase. Here, it corresponds to the fast growth phase of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref>.</p>
</list-item></list>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Microscopic description of the model and kinetic equations</title>
<p>A standard approach to formalize particle interactions between monomers, micelles and polymers, is to describe the transition rates between the states of the system through kinetic schemes. Well-known in chemistry, such a modelling is also used for polymerization models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Masel1">[4]</xref> and according to this method, it is then possible to write the differential equations of the concentration describing the dynamics of each quantity involved in the system.</p>
<p>In order to give the clearest insight as possible of the model elaboration process both for biologists and mathematicians, let us consider the 4 phases listed in the last section and progressively introduce the microscopic processes involved together with their kinetic schemes and the corresponding equations.</p>
<sec id="s2d1">
<title>Phase 1: Formation of dependent PrP micelles</title>
<p>We denote by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the PrP<sup>C</sup> monomer population (blue pentagons in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) and by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the micelles consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers (orange spherical aggregate in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). We assume that micelles grow by addition of PrP<sup>C</sup> one after the other, <italic>i.e.</italic> a PrP<sup>C</sup> monomer will aggregate to a micelle consisting of <italic>i</italic> monomers to form a larger one consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers. The rate at which this reaction occurs is given by a non-negative number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that depends on the size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of micelles. We also assume that this reaction is reversible and a micelle of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can release a PrP<sup>C</sup> monomer to form a micelle of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The rate of this reaction is given by the non-negative number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, also depending on the size. Both reactions are represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g003">Fig. 3</xref> by the interaction between the blue pentagon and the spherical aggregate. The kinetic scheme of these two reactions is given by <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e011"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula></p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003735-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Schematic representation of a micelle and interactions with monomers.</title>
<p>The blue pentagons represent the PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers, the big orange spherical structure stands for a micelle consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers, and the orange spheres (out of micelle) are the PrP* monomers stabilized by micelles. Both types of monomers, PrP<sup>C</sup> and PrP*, interact with the micelles by association-dissociation with rates given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> depending on the number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of monomers that form the micelle.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The differential equation describing the quantity change rates are written in function of the concentration of each particle type. We introduce then <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the concentrations, respectively of, monomers <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and micelles <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The flux associated to reaction (1), also called net rate, is then given by <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e024"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e024" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p>
</sec><sec id="s2d2">
<title>Phase 2: Transition to PrP*</title>
<p>We assume that the reaction, between PrP* monomers (orange spheres in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) denoted by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and micelles <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, follows the same dynamics as the PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers. Thus, the kinetic equation writes, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e029"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e029" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>The rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> play the same role as in (1). They respectively stand for, the rate at which a micelle <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> releases a PrP* monomer after having stabilized it and the rate at which a micelle <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> associates a PrP* monomers. If we denote by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the concentration of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we obtain the net rate for reaction (3), <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e037"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e037" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>To summarize, reactions (1)–(3) can be combined and written as <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e038"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e038" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>This shows how micelles help the transition from PrPC monomers to PrP*. Both depletion rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represent, in some sense, the probability that a monomer released by a micelle of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is stable in one of the two free isoforms, PrP<sup>C</sup> or PrP*. The way we choose these coefficients in the model will strongly depend on the structure of the micelles: we assume here a 3D spherical micelle structure in agreement with <italic>in vitro</italic> observation, see Sec. General assumptions and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d3">
<title>Phase 3: Nucleation</title>
<p>In this phase, we denote by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> a small aggregate consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> PrP* monomers up to a size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Here, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> corresponds to the size required to form a so-called nucleus. We name these intermediate aggregates oligomers. The reactions involved in the formation of a nucleus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e047"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e047" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Coefficient <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the rate at which a small aggregate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> will bind a PrP* monomer to form an aggregate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Here again, the reaction is reversible and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the rate of the reverse reaction. The net rate associated to reaction (6) is written as follows: <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e052"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e052" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>This process is called the nucleation because small aggregates are still assumed to be composed of PrP* (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). And these oligomers are unstable because the reaction is energetically unfavourable, namely <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Thus, oligomers can easily release PrP* until their reach the critical nucleus size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Once this size is reach, a so-called the nucleation barrier is crossed, <italic>i.e.</italic> an aggregate of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is formed, and monomers become attached to the newly created PrPSc isoform polymers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g004">Fig 4B</xref>). An important hypothesis here, is that the PrP<sup>C</sup> cannot reach this barrier which would be energetically to high while PrP* isoform would decrease considerably this level of energy necessary to reach the nucleus. This is the reason why the micelle role of converting PrP<sup>C</sup> into PrP* is crucial here.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003735-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Schematic representation of the nucleation.</title>
<p>A. The PrP* monomers form small aggregates called oligomers. B. When the oligomer reach a size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the oligomer structure becomes stable and forms a PrP<sup>Sc</sup> polymer.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d4">
<title>Phase 4: Polymers growth phase</title>
<p>After PrP* monomers have formed a nucleus of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, that is the minimal stable structure of PrP<sup>Sc</sup>, it polymerizes to form what we call polymers of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> and denoted by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when it consists in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> PrP* monomers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). In this model, we assume that polymers only polymerize with PrP* monomers and not with the PrP<sup>C</sup>. Indeed, we assume that energy necessary to pass from PrP<sup>C</sup> to the PrP<sup>Sc</sup> isoform is much more important than the one to pass from the PrP* (stabilized by micelles) to the PrP<sup>Sc</sup>. Thus, similarly to the nucleation steps, we define <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, now for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively the polymerization rates and depolymerization rates such that <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e063"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e063" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula></p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003735-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Schematic representation of the polymers dynamics.</title>
<p>A. The PrP<sup>Sc</sup> polymers <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers) bind (or loose) PrP* at its ends. It is the polymerization (or de-polymerization process). B. Polymers split into two smaller pieces. A polymer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> gives rise to two new polymers <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at a rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>This step is thermodynamically favourable and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The net rate of reaction (8) reads as (7), <italic>i.e.</italic> <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e071"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e071" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Finally, we assume that under our experimental conditions (agitation) both oligomers and polymers are subjected to a binary fragmentation, namely they can split into two smaller polymers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). This phenomenon contributes to the growth phase by multiplying the possible polymerization sites and explains why the mass of polymers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) seems to increase exponentially after the lag time. Thus, we define a splitting rate, given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, of a polymer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the associate distribution kernel <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This latter gives the probability that a polymer consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers, when it splits, gives rise to two polymers: one consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers and another of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The reaction is <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e078"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e078" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>and the net rate is <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e079"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e079" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>All these considerations give us the material to write evolution equations introduced in next section. These equations are the ones used for simulation in the next sections.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d5">
<title>Derivation of the model</title>
<p>The kinetic schemes and fluxes derived in the previous section are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003735-t001">Table 1</xref>. Using the reaction fluxes notations, it is then now possible to derive differential equations describing the dynamics of monomer, micelles and polymer formation at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> through their concentrations <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We recall that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup> monomer, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the concentration of micelles consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the concentration of PrP* monomers, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the concentration of PrP* oligomers, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the concentration of nucleus and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the concentration of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> polymers consisting of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> monomers.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1003735-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Reaction scheme and their related fluxes.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003735-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction scheme</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction fluxes</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Micelle formation and PrP* released</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amyloid polymerization</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amyloid splitting</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>We denote <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the respective concentrations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>We assume that the coefficient rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are non negative. Moreover, for any <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the kernel <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is non-negative such that for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This latter equality means that a polymer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> cannot split into bigger polymers, but only in two smaller pieces. We assume that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for any <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This symmetry assumptions means that we cannot distinguish between the fragmentation of a polymer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> into two polymers <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or two other <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it is the same reaction. Finally, it is a probability kernel, for any <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, that is<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e124"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e124" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>We are able now to write the differential equations associated to each concentration. First, the PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers is involved in all the reactions (1) and its dynamics is given by summing all the flux set up in (2): <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e125"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e125" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(13)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>The flux <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> appears twice because there is two monomers involved in the first reaction. Then, the evolution of micelles concentration is given by <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e127"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e127" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(14)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Indeed, there are four reactions that affects a micelle <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Two are of type (1) with the PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers associated to the net rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> while the two others are of type (3) with the PrP* monomer associated to the net rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Reactions (3), (6), (8) and (10) involve PrP* monomers. The dynamics of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is written as follows: <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e134"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>In particular, if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> accounts for all fragmentations such that a polymer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> leads to a polymer of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a monomer. The reactions are counted twice because of the symmetry of the reaction. Finally, oligomers and polymers follows the same dynamics, given by reactions (6), (8) and (10) with their associated fluxes. It is written as follows: <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e138"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e138" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(15)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>The fragmentation terms account for all the splitting of a polymer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to give two smaller ones of size less than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the creation of a new polymer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the fragmentation of a bigger one.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the model we developed can be summarized as as a set of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003735.e125">equations (13</xref>) to (15). The system has to be completed with initial conditions that depend on the experimental conditions, that is:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e142"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e142" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(16)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Before we analyse the system, we would like to emphasize the fact that this model describes the concentration of all micelles and polymers according to their size (number of monomers). Nevertheless it is possible to compute macroscopic quantity such as, <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e143"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>respectively the concentration of micelles and the <italic>mass</italic> of micelles which is the concentration of monomers in all the micelles. Similarly, <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e144"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>stands for the concentration of polymers and the <italic>mass of polymers</italic> that is the number of monomers in all the polymers. Finally, as we consider a closed system, with neither degradation nor production of monomers, it is then expected that the model preserves the total mass of monomers which is written as follows: <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e145"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e145" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(17)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Indeed, summing all the equations of the system, and particularly thanks to the properties of the probability kernel <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, this conservation holds.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Analysis of the experimental results based on this model</title>
<p>A qualitative analysis of the dynamics of micelles and polymers given by our model (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g006">Fig. 6</xref>) is consistent with the one observed in experiments (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). As expected, the correlation between polymers formation and the decreasing of micelles concentration is connected with the PrP* formation. For this purpose, we assume in our simulations that PrP* monomers originate from micelles and do not exist before, <italic>i.e.</italic> their initial concentration is null. Furthermore, this model was built to analyse the lag phase and be compared to data. Several definitions of the lag time exist but they are mostly related to the half-time (denoted by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), which is the time when half of the final polymerized mass is reached. One of the definitions links the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to the lag time by the relation: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the maximal slope of the sigmoid <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lee1">[6]</xref> describing polymer dynamics with respect to time. This formula makes sense for a genuine sigmoidal equation, but here we cannot have any explicit solution to the model. Since the half-time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is better defined and more tractable on our data, we choose to use it to analyse our results. It is the possible to focus ourselves on four main results provided by the model:</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003735-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Qualitative behaviour of the model.</title>
<p>Evolution normalized of the quantity: PrP<sup>C</sup>, PrP*, the <italic>mass</italic> of micelles and the <italic>mass</italic> of polymers. The dynamics are consistent with the experimental data shown in Fig. 2.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<list list-type="order"><list-item>
<p>We perform an analysis of the delay before polymerization starts when experiments are seeded with preformed PrP<sup>Sc</sup> polymers at different concentrations. Note that nucleation steps are bypassed in this case since PrP<sup>Sc</sup> already exists at the beginning of our experiment. Previous works <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Masel1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Greer1">[16]</xref> predicted the disappearance of the lag phase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003735.s002">Fig. S2</xref>) and expected the half-time to go to zero. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>, we can see that these phenomena are absolutely not observed experimentally while, on the other hand, the model we introduced confirm perfectly these observations and fit the data correctly. Moreover, as expected the half time computed in our model does not converge to zero when the seeding concentration of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> polymers increases.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g007">Fig. 7A</xref> show that the lag phase persists with an increasing concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers considering the nucleation case (without seeding). That fact is consistent with the generation of active monomers in the system. The shape of dependency to the initial condition is preserved, <italic>i.e.</italic> a linear log-log shape, but it remains independent of the nucleus size (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003735.s005">Fig. S5</xref>). It comforts the idea that the Lag time does not depend on a nucleation barrier. We emphasize that, for low concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup>, the dispersion becomes higher, this phenomenon could be explained by the stochasticity involved in the system and by-passed at high concentration when the interactions between proteins are facilitated. This has been studied in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Yvinec1">[17]</xref>.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>In the conventional model of nucleation, if the seeding is postponed, an increase of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> equal to the delay time before seeding should be observed (at least in the very first hours when the experiment takes place far enough from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). However, this dependency was not observed experimentally and the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is less than the one expected. This suggests that a phenomenon occurs during the early phase without seeding, which accelerates polymerization when nucleus is introduced. Our model explains this phenomenon by formation of the amyloid competent isoform and results are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003735.s004">Fig. S4</xref>.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>In the next step, we analyse the shape of the maximal speed distribution of polymerization (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) as a function of initial concentration. Our simulations appear to be qualitatively consistent with the experimental data, with concave shape of dependency (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003735.s003">Fig. S3</xref>).</p>
</list-item></list>
<fig id="pcbi-1003735-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Half-time correlation between the model and experimental results.</title>
<p>A. Diamonds are the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (in hours) obtain by fitting experimental data with a sigmoid (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1">[10]</xref>) for initial concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup> equal to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e159" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Squares are the mean value of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> while continuous line is the value obtain by the model for a concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup> varying from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. B. Squares stand for the mean <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (in hours) with standard error of the mean <italic>vs</italic> the seeding concentration of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> (in log-scale), obtained for a series of experiments. In each experiment the concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup> was fixed to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> mg/ml while the seeding concentration of PrP<sup>Sc</sup> given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (mass of polymers) ranges from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The result here gives the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <italic>vs</italic> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The continuous line corresponds to the simulations obtained with the model.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Taken together, these four points, allow us to conclude that experimental data corroborate our model. Furthermore, it suggests a simple explanation for the weak dependency of the lag time with initial concentration and it proposes a new interpretation of the overcoming kinetic barrier of the prion protein. <italic>A posteriori</italic>, the microscopic processes involving prion proliferation, built here, describe the observed <italic>in vitro</italic> macroscopic facts.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Evidences for the existence of micelle as an on-pathway during the formation of amyloid <italic>in vitro</italic> leads then to the question of the existence of such intermediate <italic>in vivo</italic>. Indeed, the concentrations of rPrP used to study the <italic>in vitro</italic> polymerization are far above those observed <italic>in vivo</italic> and buffers involved are not compatible with life. But, in the view presented here, micelles play the important role to sustain the conformation that is eligible for the amyloid formation. This suggests that the PrP<sup>C</sup> should reach a specific conformation to be able to polymerize into amyloid. What happens <italic>in vivo</italic>? It was recently shown that:</p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item>
<p>the conformational structure and stability of the recombinant human PrP in a membrane environment are substantially different from those of the free protein in solution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Morillas1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Sanghera1">[19]</xref></p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>anionic lipids bicelles converted α-helix-rich rPrP to a β-sheet conformation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lhrs1">[15]</xref>,</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>lipid is necessary to convert PrP<sup>C</sup> to infectious PrP<sup>Sc</sup> under physiological conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Wang1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Wang2">[21]</xref>,</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>the hydrophobic highly conserved middle region of PrP is involved in the interaction with lipid membranes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Wang3">[22]</xref>, and deletion in this part of the molecule impaired PrP<sup>Sc</sup> induced conversion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Wang4">[23]</xref>. This phenomenon was also observed for other amyloid forming peptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lee2">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Tsai1">[24]</xref>.</p>
</list-item></list>
<p>Thus our hypothesis is the formation of mixed-micelles containing phospholipids and rPrP reducing the concentration necessary to reach CMC (Critical Micellar Concentration) under physiological conditions. We believe that it is consistent with the appearance of nucleation, <italic>in vivo</italic>, at low concentration of proteins.</p>
<p>The main characteristic of the <italic>in vivo</italic> formed amyloids is infectiosity and this property is related to the amyloid structure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Chien1">[25]</xref>. It is important to remind that most of the amyloids produced <italic>in vitro</italic> are not infectious. However, recently it was shown that addition of phospholipids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Wang2">[21]</xref> during <italic>in vitro</italic> polymerization leads consistently to infectious amyloids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Wang1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Deleault1">[26]</xref>. Furthermore, it was proven that rPrP proteins interact with membrane phospholipids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Sanghera1">[19]</xref> and this interaction precedes conformational changes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Morillas1">[18]</xref>, a phenomenon also observed for other amyloid forming peptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lee2">[14]</xref>. Our hypothesis of formation of mixed-micelles containing phospholipids and rPrP, in such mixed-micelles, as in pure prion micelles, allow the protein to reach the PrP* conformation competent to generate infectious amyloids.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>General assumptions on the model</title>
<p>This model is used to fit data, that is why we have to give assumptions on rates to obtain a physical and biological relevant model. In the case of micelles(or 3D spherical structures as it is observed experimentally here), we assume as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Billingham1">[27]</xref> that assimilation rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are constant for any <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and we denote them by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> respectively, both of them being positive constants. Indeed, we assume that both types of proteins have the same affinity with respect to micelles of any size. The depletion rate needs to take the spherical structure of a micelle into account, which radius linked to the number of monomers that composes it. In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Billingham1">[27]</xref>, this term is given under the form <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e175"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e175" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(18)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>which is derived from chemical potential for one species of monomers. However, for the sake of simplicity we interpret differently this form and adapt it to one model. First, we suppose that in the smallest size, micelles do not transconformed PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers into amyloid competent isoform. We justify this assumption by thermodynamic constraints, assumed to be stronger in the greatest size. As the term in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e176" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is dominant for small micelles, we let <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e177"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e177" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(19)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>The term in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is dominant in the greatest size, thus this part is taken into account for the depletion of PrP*, <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e179"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e179" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(20)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Now, for polymerization, we consider a constant polymerization rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e180" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, such that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e181" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is equal to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for any <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e183" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and a depolymerization rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e184" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> equal to a constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the nucleus size and equal to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for longer polymer, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e189" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <italic>i.e.</italic> polymerization becomes an irreversible process after the nucleus is reached. Moreover, a linear splitting rate is taken, that is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e190" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a uniform kernel given by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003735.e192"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e192" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(21)</label></disp-formula></p>
</sec><sec id="s4b" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s4b1">
<title>Expression and purification of recombinant prion protein</title>
<p><bold>Recombinant</bold> 90–231 prion protein (rPrP) was produced as described previously, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1">[10]</xref>. Protein concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically (Beckman spectrophometer) using an extinction coefficient of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e193" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a molecular mass of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Purity of the protein preparation was assessed by phase reverse HPLC. The protein was stored lyophilized at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b2">
<title>Transmission electron microscopy</title>
<p>Samples were absorbed on carbon/formvar-coated copper grids (300 mesh) (Agar scientific, Saclay, France) and stained by negative contrast with 2% (w/v) uranyl acetate for one minute. Labelled samples are observed after negative contrast with uranyl acetate 2% on a JEOL 1200 EX II transmission electron microscope (Service commun de microscopie électronique de l’université Montpellier II, Montpellier, France) at 80KV of voltage. Number of micelles were counted directly on images and size of micelles as well as length and width of fibrils were measured using ImageJ software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" xlink:type="simple">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b3">
<title>Kinetics measurements of polymerization</title>
<p>Kinetics of amyloid formation was monitored in SpectraMax Gemini XS (Molecular Devices). Samples containing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e198" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the oxidized form of HaPrP90-231 (rPrP) were incubated in Buffer A, Buffer B or Buffer C (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1">[10]</xref> for more details on the buffers composition) upon continuous shaking at 1350 rpm in 96-well plates and in the presence of ThT (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The kinetics was monitored by bottom-reading of fluorescence intensity using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> excitation and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e201" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e202" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> emission. Every set of measurements was performed in triplicates, and the results were averaged. Previously prepared amyloid were used to performed the seeding and the w/w per cent were calculated assuming that suspension was homogeneous.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b4">
<title>Numerical simulation</title>
<p>A code was developed to simulate the equations and compared to data. It is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ci2ma.udec.cl/ehingant/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ci2ma.udec.cl/ehingant/</ext-link>.</p>
</sec></sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003735.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Characterization by antibodies of micelles.</bold> Transmission electron microscopy view of micelles occurring as spherical structures while PrP<sup>Sc</sup> polymers appear as rigid-rod. The method used: 1. Samples absorption on carbon/formvar-coated copper grids (300 mesh) (Agar scientific, Saclay, France) 2. Labelling with antibodies: 1/antibody 3F4 (Covance, Berkeley, California; 1/100e in PBS 1% BSA), 2/antibody Rabbit anti Mouse (1/400e in PBS 1%BSA), 3/antibody Goat anti Rabbit-10 nm gold (1/100e in PBS BSA 1%) 3. Negative contrast staining with 2% (w/v) uranyl acetate for one minute.</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003735.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Numerical simulation of the model in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lee2">[14]</xref>.</bold> <bold>a</bold>, The normalized polymerization shape of the mass of polymers <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The simulation is done for a range of seeding (initial mass of PrP<sup>Sc</sup>) given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ranges from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with a concentration of monomers PrP<sup>C</sup> given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e207" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> mg/ml. In this model there are no micelles, PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers directly polymerize with PrP<sup>Sc</sup>. <bold>b</bold>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e208" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <italic>vs.</italic> seeding associated to the polymerization shape in (a), seeding is presented in log-scale. Both show the Lag time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e209" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> together with half time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e210" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> disappear when seeding increase.</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003735.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Dependency of slope to the initial concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup>.</bold> Comparison of our model and the model in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lee2">[14]</xref> with experimental results. The slope <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e211" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the apparent polymerization rate at the inflexion point or with the model: the number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e212" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e213" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the inflexion time such that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e214" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. <bold>a</bold>, Experimental data obtained in different buffers. The slope is obtained by fitting them with a sigmoidal shape. Red dot or the mean obtained through the experiments. <bold>b</bold>, Result obtained with the nucleation-dependent model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003735-Lee2">[14]</xref> and <bold>c</bold>, with the micelle-dependent model presented in the paper. The micelle-dependent model, item (c), appears in a better agreement as a convex function.</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003735.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Dependency of the Half-time to a postpone seeding.</bold> Circle is the mean with standard deviation of the half-time over 3 experiments. Meanwhile, the solid line is the result provided by the micelle-dependent model and the dashed line is the theoretical Half-time when pure nucleation-dependent polymerization is considered. This experiment consists in 4 test tubes containing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e215" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of PrP<sup>C</sup> monomers in the same buffer at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e216" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Then, at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e217" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the first tube is seeded with preformed polymers this leads to a half-time set as the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e218" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The second test tube is seeded 1 hour later (the seeding time) with the same concentration of polymers and so forth. The <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.e219" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is supposed to be linearly brought forward (dashed line) according to the seeding time, in the case where nothing happens between the beginning of the experiments and the time when polymers are introduced. Experimentally this time is less than the one expected (circle). The formation of micelles and transconformed monomers at the early phase explains this situation. Indeed, the process had already started with the micelles formation and active monomers PrP* in the buffer, before seeding. Thus, polymerization starts earlier than expected.</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003735.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p><bold>The half-time vs initial concentration of PrP<sup>C</sup>.</bold> It appears that the decreasing rate in log scale of the half-time remains independent on the nucleus size <italic>n</italic> for the micelle-dependent model which is not consistent with the nucleation-dependent model.</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003735.s006" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003735.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S6</label><caption>
<p><bold>Transmission electron microscopy's views of the experiments at different times.</bold> The images represent an arbitrary selection among many ones selected from the beginning to the end of experiments in two different buffers corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003735-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, top (Buffer C) and bottom (Buffer B).</p>
<p>(TIFF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Prusiner1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prusiner</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Novel proteinaceous infectious particles cause scrapie</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>216</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Prusiner2"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prusiner</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Prions</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>13363</fpage>–<lpage>13383</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Come1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Come</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lansbury</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>A kinetic model for amyloid formation in the prion diseases: importance of seeding</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>5959</fpage>–<lpage>5963</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Masel1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Quantifying the kinetic parameters of prion replication</article-title>. <source>Biophys Chem</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Ferrone1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Analysis of protein aggregation kinetics</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Lee1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sethuraman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belfort</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McRae</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A three-stage kinetic model of amyloid fibrillation</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>3448</fpage>–<lpage>3458</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Powers1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The kinetics of nucleated polymerizations at high concentrations: amyloid fibril formation near and above the “supercritical concentration”</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Serio1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cashikar</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kowal</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sawicki</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moslehi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Nucleated conformational conversion and the replication of conformational information by a prion determinant</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>289</volume>: <fpage>1317</fpage>–<lpage>1321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Harper1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lansbury</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Models of amyloid seeding in alzheimer's disease and scrapie: mechanistic truths and physiological consequences of the time-dependent solubility of amyloid proteins</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-AlvarezMartinez1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez-Martinez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fontes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zomosa-Signoret</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnaud</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hingant</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of polymerization shed light on the mechanisms that lead to multiple amyloid structures of the prion protein</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1814</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>–<lpage>1317</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Baskakov1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baskakov</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bocharova</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>In vitro conversion of mammalian prion protein into amyloid fibrils displays unusual features</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2339</fpage>–<lpage>2348</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Collins1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douglass</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mechanism of prion propagation: amyloid growth occurs by monomer addition</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e321</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Powers2"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of protein fibril formation: nucleated polymerization with competing off-pathway aggregation</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Lee2"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Membrane-mediated peptide conformation change from alphamonomers to beta-aggregates</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>2236</fpage>–<lpage>2245</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Lhrs1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lührs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wüthrich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Amyloid formation by recombinant full-length prion proteins in phospholipid bicelle solutions</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>357</volume>: <fpage>833</fpage>–<lpage>841</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Greer1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pujo-Menjouet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A mathematical analysis of the dynamics of prion proliferation</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source> <volume>242</volume>: <fpage>598</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Yvinec1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Yvinec R (2012) Modélisation probabiliste en biologie moléculaire et cellulaire. Ph.D. thesis, Université Claude Bernard - Lyon I.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Morillas1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morillas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swietnicki</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gambetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surewicz</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Membrane environment alters the conformational structure of the recombinant human prion protein</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>274</volume>: <fpage>36859</fpage>–<lpage>36865</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Sanghera1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanghera</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>TJT</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Binding of prion protein to lipid membranes and implications for prion conversion</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>1241</fpage>–<lpage>1256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Wang1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Generating a prion with bacterially expressed recombinant prion protein</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>1132</fpage>–<lpage>1135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Wang2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Lipid interaction converts prion protein to a prpsc-like proteinase k-resistant conformation under physiological conditions</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>7045</fpage>–<lpage>7053</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Wang3"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Conversion of bacterially expressed recombinant prion protein</article-title>. <source>Methods</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Wang4"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zha</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sy</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Role of the highly conserved middle region of prion protein (prp) in prp-lipid interaction</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>8169</fpage>–<lpage>8176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Tsai1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>HHG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Y-C</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Folding and membrane insertion of amyloidbeta (25–35) peptide and its mutants: implications for aggregation and neurotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>1909</fpage>–<lpage>1925</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Chien1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DePace</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Emerging principles of conformation-based prion inheritance</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>–<lpage>656</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Deleault1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deleault</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Supattapone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Formation of native prions from minimal components in vitro</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>9741</fpage>–<lpage>9746</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003735-Billingham1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billingham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>On modelling the formation of micelles in the presence of a slow influx of monomer</article-title>. <source>The Quarterly Journal of Mechanics &amp; Applied Mathematics</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>