<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-13-01556</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Theoretical biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Evolution of Multivariate Maternal Effects</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Multivariate Maternal Effects</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuijper</surname><given-names>Bram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>Rufus A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Townley</surname><given-names>Stuart</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Environment and Sustainability Institute, University of Exeter, Penryn, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Behaviour and Evolution Group, Department of Zoology, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>CoMPLEX, Centre for Mathematics and Physics in the Life Sciences and Experimental Biology, University College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Genetics, Evolution and Environment, University College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salathé</surname><given-names>Marcel</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Pennsylvania State University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">a.kuijper@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BK RAJ ST. Performed the experiments: BK RAJ ST. Analyzed the data: BK ST. Wrote the paper: BK ST.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003550</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Kuijper et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>There is a growing interest in predicting the social and ecological contexts that favor the evolution of maternal effects. Most predictions focus, however, on maternal effects that affect only a single character, whereas the evolution of maternal effects is poorly understood in the presence of suites of interacting traits. To overcome this, we simulate the evolution of multivariate maternal effects (captured by the matrix <bold>M</bold>) in a fluctuating environment. We find that the rate of environmental fluctuations has a substantial effect on the properties of <bold>M</bold>: in slowly changing environments, offspring are selected to have a multivariate phenotype roughly similar to the maternal phenotype, so that <bold>M</bold> is characterized by positive dominant eigenvalues; by contrast, rapidly changing environments favor <bold>M</bold>s with dominant eigenvalues that are negative, as offspring favor a phenotype which substantially differs from the maternal phenotype. Moreover, when fluctuating selection on one maternal character is temporally delayed relative to selection on other traits, we find a striking pattern of cross-trait maternal effects in which maternal characters influence not only the same character in offspring, but also other offspring characters. Additionally, when selection on one character contains more stochastic noise relative to selection on other traits, large cross-trait maternal effects evolve from those maternal traits that experience the smallest amounts of noise. The presence of these cross-trait maternal effects shows that individual maternal effects cannot be studied in isolation, and that their study in a multivariate context may provide important insights about the nature of past selection. Our results call for more studies that measure multivariate maternal effects in wild populations.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>In numerous organisms, mothers influence the phenotype of their offspring by transmitting hormones, antibodies and nutrients to the embryo. Evolutionary studies that make predictions about the evolution of these maternal effects typically focus, however, on single maternal characters only, in isolation of other traits. This contrasts with insights from quantitative genetics where reliable predictions about evolutionary change can only be made when measuring multiple traits simultaneously. The current study is therefore the first to make formal predictions about the evolutionary properties of multiple maternal effects. We show that maternal phenotypic characters generally give rise to developmental interactions in which one maternal character affects multiple offspring characters. In turn, such interactions can give rise to correlations between different traits in parent and offspring, which constrain evolutionary responses to sudden change. In addition, we find that the rate of environmental change directly affects some of the measurable properties of maternal effects: in rapidly changing environments, multivariate maternal effects are negative, so that offspring attain phenotypes that are different from their mothers, whereas positive maternal effects where offspring are more similar to their mothers occur in slowly changing environments. Hence, multivariate maternal effects provide a clear signature of the past selective environment experienced by organisms.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by EPSRC grant EP/H031928/1. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Since selection often varies both over space and time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Grant1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Siepielski1">[3]</xref>, evolutionary mechanisms that increase adaptation to changing environments are considered to be highly advantageous <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Meyers1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-WestEberhard1">[5]</xref>. Conventional studies focus on mechanisms such as bet-hedging <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Seger1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Starrfelt1">[8]</xref> and, in particular, within-generational phenotypic plasticity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-WestEberhard1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Pigliucci1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Chevin1">[11]</xref> as major adaptations to changing environments. However, a growing number of recent studies suggest that nongenetic effects provide an additional way of adaptation to changing environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Bossdorf1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Bonduriansky1">[14]</xref>. Here, nongenetic effects refer to any effect on the offspring phenotype that is brought about by the transmission of factors (other than sequences of DNA) from parents or more remote ancestors to the offspring <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Danchin1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka1">[15]</xref>. Nongenetic effects can be realized through a variety of mechanisms, such as social learning <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Richerson1">[16]</xref>, the transmission of DNA methylation variants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Youngson1">[17]</xref> or the transmission of maternal factors such as antibodies or hormones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Mousseau1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Badyaev1">[19]</xref>. Importantly, when nongenetic effects are present in a population, an individual's phenotype becomes a function of the phenotypes (or the environment) of its parents or previous ancestors, giving rise to a form of transgenerational plasticity that is suggested to allow for increased flexibility when coping with environmental change <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Agrawal1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Uller1">[22]</xref>.</p>
<p>Theoretical studies indeed predict that nongenetic effects are selectively favored in fluctuating environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka2">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hoyle1">[25]</xref>, particularly when the parental phenotype provides information about selective conditions encountered by future generations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Shea1">[24]</xref>. The role of parental information has been particularly well studied in the context of maternal effects, whereby the maternal phenotype or environment affects the offspring's phenotype through the provisioning of resources, antibodies or hormones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Marshall1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kuijper1">[29]</xref>. However, most studies on maternal effects focus mainly on univariate scenarios, in which a single maternal factor influences a single offspring character. By contrast, studies in plants and animals suggest that maternal effects typically have a multivariate nature, involving suites of interacting parental and offspring characters (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Thiede1">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Postma1">[33]</xref>). Indeed, this multivariate nature has long been appreciated by those models that assess the consequences of (non-evolving) nongenetic effects to phenotypic evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Day1">[38]</xref>. As yet, however, no theoretical predictions exist about the evolution of these multivariate maternal effects themselves.</p>
<p>We believe that taking a multivariate view on the evolution of maternal effects is insightful for at least two different reasons. First, as stated before, the main prediction of univariate models is that maternal effects evolve when the parental phenotype correlates with selective conditions encountered by offspring <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Shea1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kuijper1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lachmann1">[39]</xref>. It is currently unclear how these predictions play out when offspring are not influenced by a single, but multiple components of a parental phenotype, raising the question how offspring should weigh information that results from the presence of multiple maternal effects (e.g., the presence of multiple maternal hormones and immonoglobulins in avian eggs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Postma1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Groothuis1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Gil1">[41]</xref>). A second reason for considering the evolution of nongenetic effects in a multivariate context is the finding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Townley1">[42]</xref> that the multivariate configuration of all maternal effects (here assumed to be captured in the matrix <bold>M</bold>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Cowley1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hadfield1">[43]</xref>) plays an analogous role in determining the course of evolution as the genetic variance-covariance matrix <bold>G</bold> that describes the scope for correlated selection between traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande3">[44]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Walsh1">[46]</xref>. The role of the <bold>G</bold>-matrix in multivariate evolution has been the focus of a vast body of research for the last 40 years, and a substantial set of predictions exists on the ecological and social contexts that give rise to specific configurations of <bold>G</bold> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hansen1">[47]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jones1">[49]</xref>) and ensuing evolutionary constraints <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Walsh1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande4">[50]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Futuyma1">[54]</xref>. By contrast, there are yet no studies which investigate the selective conditions that lead to different configurations of <bold>M</bold>, which may similarly constrain phenotypic evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hoyle1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Townley1">[42]</xref>. As a first step towards a more inclusive theory that aims to incorporate both nongenetic and genetic constraints on evolution, the current study therefore aims to investigate which structures of <bold>M</bold> are likely to evolve across different ecological contexts.</p>
<p>To this end, we develop a formal model to make predictions about the evolution of multiple maternal effects in a periodically fluctuating environment. In the current model, a maternal effect reflects any causal influences of the maternal phenotype on the offspring's phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Mousseau1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Wolf2">[55]</xref>. Prominent examples of maternal effects are the modulation of offspring phenotypes by the maternal adjustment of a variety of egg hormones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Gil1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Groothuis2">[56]</xref> or the transmission of maternal antibodies to the embryo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Boulinier1">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Garnier1">[58]</xref>. In the current study, we focus on the evolution of multivariate maternal effects in the context of fluctuating selection. Specifically, we are interested in scenarios where the nature of selective fluctuations diverges between different maternal characters. For example, different maternal traits endure selection at different timepoints, because some maternal traits endure selection at different seasons than others, or because some selection on some characters may be more predictable (i.e., less stochastic noise) than selection on other characters. The current study thereby investigates whether such contexts lead to the interaction among different maternal characters, which cannot be inferred from studying the evolution of single traits in isolation.</p>
<p>We study the evolution of multivariate maternal effects in a fluctuating environment using individual-based evolutionary simulations. Although analytical approaches would be preferred to provide a general evolutionary model of multivariate phenotypes, an analytical assessment of multivariate evolution quickly becomes prohibitively difficult, even when only the evolution of the genetic variance-covariance matrix <bold>G</bold> is considered (while maternal effects are absent). It is thus no surprise that individual-based simulations have been the method of choice when considering more complicated scenarios of multivariate evolution (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jones1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jones2">[59]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Revell1">[61]</xref>). Moreover, maternal effects involve the additional complexity that phenotypic evolution depends on past generations, so that an analytical description requires a number of strong equilibrium assumptions (such as a constant covariance between genotypes and phenotypes, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hadfield1">[43]</xref>). Here, however, we use the flexibility of individual-based, evolutionary simulations to study the evolution of maternal effects in a dynamical fashion without these limiting assumptions.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Models</title>
<p>Our model assumes a sexually reproducing population of <italic>N</italic> = 5000 randomly mating hermaphrodites having discrete, nonoverlapping generations. A graphical summary of the life cycle is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g001">Figure 1A</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003550-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Graphical description of the model (panel A) and an example scenario in which fluctuating selective optima <italic>θ</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>θ</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) fluctuate over time (panel B).</title>
<p>In this particular scenario, optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is delayed relative to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with phase shift <italic>φ</italic> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> contains noise (indicated by noise parameter <italic>d</italic>). The amount of noise in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is proportional to the disturbance parameter <italic>d</italic>. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><sec id="s2a">
<title>Gene loci</title>
<p>To assess the evolution of multiple maternal effects, we study the simplest possible case, in which an individual that breeds in generation <italic>t</italic> expresses two phenotypic traits, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (where T denotes transposition). Each individual bears six unlinked, diploid loci: two of which correspond to the breeding values of both phenotypic characters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, that determine the baseline elevation of both phenotypic traits. The remaining four loci code for the entries of the 2× maternal effect matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, of which the entry <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reflects the maternal influence from maternal phenotype <italic>j</italic> to offspring phenotype <italic>i</italic> (see eq. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Grant1">[1]</xref> below). For all six loci, the two alleles at each locus interact additively (i.e., dominance effects are absent) and inheritance is biparental. During each generation, each allele mutates with probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, upon which a value drawn from a normal distribution with mean 0 and variance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is added to the current allelic value (i.e., a continuum of alleles model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kimura1">[62]</xref>). Each individual simulation run started from the initial values <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> continued for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> generations. Throughout, we found that values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> attained stable values after approximately a tenth of this total timespan (e.g., see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s004">Figure S4</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Phenotypes</title>
<p>Extending seminal quantitative genetics models that focus on non-evolving multivariate maternal effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande2">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hadfield1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Dickerson1">[63]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Falconer1">[65]</xref>, the phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of an individual in generation <italic>t</italic> is then given by the following recursion:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003550.e018"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e018" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>Here, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the breeding value of trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, while <italic>ε</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) reflects the contribution of environmental noise, which is normally distributed with mean 0 and variance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as in classical quantitative genetics models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande3">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande5">[66]</xref>. The starred value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the value of the maternal phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> after selection. As noted before, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the evolving maternal effect coefficient, describing how maternal character <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> influences offspring phenotype <italic>i</italic>. Note that we assume that the maternal effect loci are controlled by the offspring, representing a scenario in which entry <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of <bold>M</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) reflects the offspring's sensitivity to maternal trait <italic>z<sub>j</sub></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Mller1">[67]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Uller3">[68]</xref>. For example, the vector <bold>z</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) may reflect titers of different offspring hormones, and the entry <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> specifies how the maternal titer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of hormone <italic>j</italic> (e.g., measured during pregnancy or added to the egg) affects the titer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of offspring hormone <italic>i</italic> (e.g., mediated by the number of hormone binding sites present in the offspring endocrine cells). Indeed, studies indicate that maternal hormone and protein titers affect offspring hormone concentrations, often in a multivariate fashion (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Postma1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Groothuis2">[56]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Tschirren1">[69]</xref>).</p>
<p>While multivariate maternal effects <bold>M</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) are assumed to be genetically expressed by the offspring, they still give rise to nongenetic effects on the multivariate phenotype <bold>z</bold>(<italic>t</italic>). This is because the offspring's phenotype is not merely influenced by <bold>M</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) itself, but the product <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of maternal effects and the parental phenotype. Consequently, the involvement of the maternal phenotype gives rise to the well-known ‘cascading nature’ of maternal effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande2">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin1">[70]</xref>, whereby the maternal phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is itself a function of the multivariate grandmaternal phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which in turn is a function of the phenotypes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of previous ancestors. As the offspring's phenotype <bold>z</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) is thus not only a function of DNA sequences it received from its ancestors (i.e., genes coding for <bold>a</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) and <bold>M</bold>(<italic>t</italic>)), but also of the phenotypes of its ancestors, <bold>M</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) gives rise to nongenetic effects on the offspring phenotype (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Day1">[38]</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Fluctuating survival selection</title>
<p>After birth and phenotype determination (as in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003550.e018">eq. 1</xref>), each newborn enters a survival stage during which it endures survival selection. The survival probability <italic>w<sub>s</sub></italic> decreases nonlinearly with a displacement of the character <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> away from the selective optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, according to the Gaussian function<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003550.e036"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e036" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>where all individuals are assumed to have a baseline survival probability of <italic>c</italic>, while the strength of stabilizing selection on both phenotypes is proportional to the remainder <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. <italic>α</italic><sup>2</sup> measures the width of the selection function and is therefore inversely proportional to the strength of selection. Throughout, we assume that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<sec id="s2c1">
<title>Periodic fluctuations</title>
<p>Throughout the main part of the paper, optima <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are assumed to fluctuate according to a discrete-time sinusoid<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003550.e040"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e040" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where the optimum <italic>θ<sub>i</sub></italic> of trait <italic>z<sub>i</sub></italic> fluctuates periodically with amplitude <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub>, mimicking, for example, a seasonal environment or periodic environmental forcing on longer timescales (e.g., ‘El Niño,’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Wells1">[71]</xref>). The rate at which the selective environment fluctuates is given by <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub>. In addition, both fluctuating optima can either be <italic>φ</italic> time steps delayed relative to each other, or fluctuations in one optimum can be characterized by a certain degree of disturbance (<italic>d</italic>&gt;0), through the presence of additional (stochastic) fluctuations with a frequency of <italic>ω</italic><sub>2</sub>, where values of <italic>ω</italic><sub>2</sub> are chosen from a uniform distribution between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g001">Figure 1</xref> for an example). Note that discrete-time sinusoids give rise to more complicated periodic behaviors in comparison to their continuous-time counterparts, since they typically lack strict periodicity. Consequently, timeseries of selective optima generally look more erratic and variable over short-term periods (e.g., see insets in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2</xref>), which is likely to more closely correspond to temporal variation observed in natural timeseries.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003550-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>The evolution of univariate maternal effects for different frequencies <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub> of periodically fluctuating selection.</title>
<p>Each dot represents the average maternal effect<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> measured over ten replicate simulations (at generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), while the shaded areas depict corresponding standard deviations. Boxes on the top of the graph depict the a snapshot in time of the fluctuations in the selective optimum <italic>θ</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) over the course of 20 generations. Note that any fluctuations are absent whenever <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub> is a multiple of <italic>π</italic>, as the environment then fluctuates back towards the same state (i.e., Δ<italic>θ</italic> = 0) before selection takes place in the next generation. Black lines depict the autocorrelation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of selective conditions between the parental and offspring generations. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Finally, because selective optima fluctuate around 0 (i.e., no directional selection), we found no significant evolutionary change in the breeding values <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> underlying each phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande6">[72]</xref> (e.g., see Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s004">Figure S4A</xref>). We therefore only focus on the evolved values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the main part of this study.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c2">
<title>Stochastic fluctuations</title>
<p>In addition to the periodic fluctuations, the Supplementary Figures consider a scenario in which <italic>θ<sub>i</sub></italic> fluctuates according to a stochastic process rather than a sinusoid function. Simulations are identical to the periodic case, except that <italic>θ<sub>i</sub></italic> is now drawn from a Gaussian autocorrelated time series with mean 0 and variance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, whilst varying the value of the autocorrelation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or cross-correlation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in selective conditions between two subsequent generations (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Results</xref> and Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s001">Figures S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s002">S2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s003">S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s005">S5</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Reproduction</title>
<p>After survival selection, the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> surviving individuals reproduce: each surviving individual produces a number of <italic>n</italic> = 10 ova, which are all fertilized by a randomly chosen other survivor that acts as a sperm donor. From the zygotes, new individuals are sampled with replacement to maintain a population of constant size <italic>N</italic>. Subsequently, the cycle starts anew with mutation and phenotype determination, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g001">Figure 1A</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Result 1: The shape of the maternal effects matrix M is determined by the rate of environmental change</title>
<sec id="s3a1">
<title>The evolution of a single maternal effect, <italic>m</italic></title>
<p>To understand the evolution of multiple maternal effects in a fluctuating environment, it proves illustrative to first investigate the evolution of a single phenotypic trait <italic>z</italic> that is influenced by single a maternal effect, <italic>m</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2</xref>). When selective conditions fluctuate at a slow rate (small rate of change, <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub>), selection between two consecutive generations is likely to be positively correlated (autocorrelation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, black line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Consequently, offspring are selected to develop a phenotype of a similar sign as their mother, leading to the evolution of positive values of the maternal effect <italic>m</italic>. Faster fluctuations, however, (i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) lead to negative autocorrelations (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) in selective conditions between mother and offspring. As a result, offspring are selected to have phenotypes of a different sign in comparison to the maternal phenotype, selecting for negative maternal effects (<italic>m</italic>&lt;0, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
<p>When environmental change is effectively absent (i.e., when the frequency of change is <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub> = 0 or when exactly half a period of fluctuations has passed before selection takes place in the next generation: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), we find that <italic>m</italic> evolves to negative values. The evolution of <italic>m</italic>&lt;0 in the absence of environmental fluctuations is in line with previous findings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hoyle1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Ezard1">[73]</xref>, which predict that slightly negative values of <italic>m</italic> are optimal in stable environments, as a means to reduce the amount of phenotypic variance. It also explains why <italic>m</italic> has a smaller absolute magnitude when it evolves to positive values in comparison to cases where <italic>m</italic> evolves to negative values (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2</xref>), as positive <italic>m</italic> are more likely to increase, rather than decrease the phenotypic variance around the selective optimum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hoyle1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>.</p>
<p>So far, we have only studied a periodic environment, which raises the question whether these conclusions can be generalized to stochastic environments. In Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s001">Figure S1</xref>, we study the evolution of <italic>m</italic> when fluctuations in the selective optimum <italic>θ</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) are given by a Gaussian time series. Because the frequency parameter <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub> does not apply to stochastic environments, here we therefore vary the autocorrelation <italic>ρ</italic> between two subsequent time steps directly. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s001">Figure S1</xref> shows that positive values of <italic>m</italic> occur when fluctuations are characterized by positive autocorrelations <italic>ρ</italic>, while negative values of <italic>m</italic> evolve when <italic>ρ</italic>&lt;0. Hence, a marked correspondence exists between the degree of environmental autocorrelation and the sign and magnitude of <italic>m</italic> in both periodic and stochastic environments (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3a2">
<title>The evolution of multiple maternal effects, M</title>
<p>When extending our model to allow for multiple, coevolving maternal effects, we first focus on the simplest possible case in which fluctuations in selective conditions are identical for both phenotypic characters <italic>z</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub>. When only those maternal effects that affect the same trait in offspring (i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) are allowed to evolve, we find an identical outcome as in the previously discussed case with a single maternal effect (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s002">Figure S2A</xref>): both entries <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> evolve to positive values in slowly changing environments (that are characterized by positive autocorrelations), and to negative values in rapidly changing environments (characterized by negative autocorrelations). <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s002">Figure S2B</xref> shows that also in a stochastic environment, negative and positive maternal effects evolve dependent on the value of the autocorrelation between selective optima in parents and offspring.</p>
<p>When all entries of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are able to evolve, outcomes differ from the univariate case depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figures 3A and 3B</xref> show that all maternal effects either attain positive or negative values (of a substantial magnitude) for a broad range of rates of change <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub>. Moreover, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3</xref> shows that entries of <bold>M</bold> evolve to two alternatively stable, evolutionary outcomes: despite identical starting conditions, half of all replicate simulations result in <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> having negative values (while <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> are positive, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3A</xref>), whereas the other replicates result in <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> having positive values (with <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> being negative, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003550-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>The evolution of multivariate maternal effects for different frequencies <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub> of environmental change, when periodically fluctuating selection is identical across traits (i.e., <italic>θ</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>θ</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)).</title>
<p>Panels A, B: entries of the multivariate maternal effects matrix <bold>M</bold> evolve towards two alternatively stable outcomes (outcome 1 and outcome 2). Panel C: real and imaginary parts of the eigenvalue <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the maternal effects matrix are identical for both outcomes. For the sake of clarity, a value of 0.01 was subtracted from the eigenvalues of outcome 2, to prevent overlap with the eigenvalues in outcome 1. Each point in panels A and B depicts values of the maternal effect <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (at generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) averaged over ten replicate generations, while shading depicts corresponding standard deviations. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Both these alternatively stable outcomes result, however, in a similar overall ‘shape’ of the maternal effects matrix <bold>M</bold>, when measured in terms of its dominant eigenvalue <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3C</xref> shows that real (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and imaginary (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) parts of the eigenvalue are the same for alternative evolutionary outcomes. Indeed, it is this shape of <bold>M</bold> that determines how the maternal phenotype influences offspring phenotypes. For example, a positive real part of the eigenvalue implies that offspring will have a multivariate phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of a similar sign as the maternal phenotype, which is advantageous when selective optima are unlikely to change much between generations (left part of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). By contrast, negative values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> imply that offspring favor phenotypes that are different in sign to the maternal phenotype, which is beneficial when the selective environment changes rapidly between consecutive generations (right part of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). Since the real part of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, interchanging <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> gives rise to identical values, hence explaining why the two alternatively stable states lead to similar consequences.</p>
<p>Whereas the value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> informs whether maternal effects give rise to switches in sign between offspring and maternal phenotypes, the imaginary parts <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indicate changes in phenotypic values that span a larger number of generations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-EdelsteinKeshet1">[74]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Otto1">[75]</xref>. Although a full assessment of the dynamical consequences of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is beyond the scope of the current paper, we highlight the role of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when it attains its largest magnitude, at the point <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). At this point, the autocorrelation between selective conditions experienced by mother and offspring is nearly absent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), while the autocorrelation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between selective conditions experienced by grandmothers and offspring is, in fact, at a minimum: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In other words, offspring would benefit substantially from a phenotype that is opposite in sign to that of their grandparents. Using results from standard calculus (e.g., p. 355 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Otto1">[75]</xref>), it can be shown that the real and imaginary parts in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3C</xref> at the point <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> give rise to fluctuations in phenotypic values with a full period of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> timesteps. A period of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> implies that it takes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> timesteps for a phenotype to change sign, which matches the change in environmental conditions between grandparental and offspring generations. Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s004">Figure S4</xref> confirms this finding, by highlighting that the presence of all four entries of <bold>M</bold> leads to a substantial increase in mean fitness relative to scenarios in which only both diagonal entries of <bold>M</bold> are evolving (and where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is necessarily 0).</p>
<p>Alternatively stable outcomes are also found when selective fluctuations are stochastic rather than periodic (Supplementary <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s003">Figure S3</xref>), at least when selective optima are identical for both traits (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as previously considered for the periodic environment) (see Figures S3A–B). However, the eigenvalues of <bold>M</bold> (in particular their imaginary parts) are more modest in comparison to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g002">Figure 2C</xref>, as longer term fluctuations in a stochastic environment are inherently less predictable in comparison to a deterministic environment.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Result 2: Temporally advanced selective conditions result in positive cross-trait maternal effects</title>
<p>So far, we have assumed that fluctuations in both selective optima <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are identical, whereas different forms of fluctuating selection may act on each maternal trait, dependent on the ecological context that each trait experiences. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g004">Figure 4A</xref> shows, for example, how delays between the selective optima of both phenotypes impact on the evolution of multivariate maternal effects matrix <bold>M</bold>. First, the presence of a delay of <italic>φ</italic> timesteps between the two selective optima leads to a collapse from the two alternatively stable outcomes observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3</xref> to a single evolutionary outcome, unless both optima fluctuate in an exactly opposing fashion (depicted by the large error bars when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Second, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g004">Figure 4A</xref> shows that both cross-trait maternal effects (<italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> or <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub>, which reflect maternal influences from one maternal trait to a different offspring character) evolve to opposing positive and negative values, dependent on the delay <italic>φ</italic> between both optima. The maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> is positive (and <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> negative) when fluctuating selection on trait <italic>z</italic><sub>1</sub> is advanced relative to selection on <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub> (grey region in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g004">Figure 4A</xref>), whereas <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> is negative (and <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> positive) when fluctuating selection on trait <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub> is advanced relative to selection on <italic>z</italic><sub>1</sub>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003550-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>The evolution of multivariate maternal effects (panel A) when the evolutionary optimum <italic>θ</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) lags <italic>φ</italic> timesteps behind the evolutionary optimum <italic>θ</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>t</italic>).</title>
<p>Grey area: fluctuations in optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> precede those of optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. White area: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> precedes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Insets on the top of the panel depict the fluctuating selective optima <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (blue line) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (red line) over time. Panel B: selective cross-correlations that result from varying the time-lag between both selective optima. Note that each point in panel A depicts the maternal effect <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (at generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) averaged over ten replicate generations, while error bars depict corresponding standard deviations. Error bars are large when time lags are small, as evolution then leads to alternatively stable states observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figures 3A,B</xref>. The results in this figure also extend to a periodic environment in which the time delay <italic>φ</italic> is stochastically distributed according to a normal distribution <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with mean <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and variance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> varying from 0.1 to 4 (results not shown). Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Insights on the adaptive significance of cross-trait maternal effects can be derived from the cross-correlations <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of selective conditions between different traits in parents and offspring, which reflect to what extent one maternal phenotype is able to predict future selection on a different offspring phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Focusing on the grey region in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g004">Figure 4B</xref> where the selective optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is advanced relative to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we find that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In other words, selection on maternal phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is overall positively associated to selection on offspring phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (or when it attains negative values these are always smaller in magnitude than the other cross-correlation). Since the evolving maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> reflects the influence of maternal trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to offspring trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it evolves to positive values so that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> matches its future environment. By contrast, selection on the maternal phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is overall negatively associated to selection on offspring phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (or when it attains positive values these are always smaller in magnitude than the other cross-correlation). Hence, the maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> evolves to negative values instead. The reverse scenario applies for the white region in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3B</xref>, where selective optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is advanced relative to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Indeed, we find that <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> then evolves to positive values, while <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> evolves to negative values. In other words, those maternal traits enduring fluctuating selection that is advanced relative to selection on other maternal traits are more likely to develop positive cross-trait maternal effects, whereas delayed fluctuating selection on maternal traits is more likely to lead to negative cross-trait maternal effects.</p>
<p>Lastly, we investigated whether such cross-trait maternal effects also evolve in multivariate stochastic environments. As cross-correlations are easily measurable in time series analyses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Wei1">[76]</xref>, we chose to vary the cross-correlation directly in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s003">Figure S3</xref> (although results are similar when adjusting the time-lag between both optima). In a stochastic environment without any cross-correlation between both selective optima, we find that cross-trait maternal effects <italic>m<sub>ij</sub></italic> generally do not evolve, while the within-trait maternal effects <italic>m<sub>ii</sub></italic> track the autocorrelation of its associated selective optimum <italic>θ<sub>i</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s003">Figure S3D</xref>,E). By contrast, when selective cross-correlations are nonzero, cross-trait maternal effects evolve to substantial values (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s005">Figure S5</xref>). For example, when varying the cross-correlation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from −1 to +1, we find that the associated cross-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> evolves from strongly negative to strongly positive (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003550.s005">Figure S5A</xref>). Instead, when varying the cross-correlation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we find a similar pattern for the other cross-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub>. Similar to the periodic environment in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g004">Figure 4</xref>, we find that cross-trait maternal effects evolve in concordance to the prevailing cross-correlations between both fluctuating selective optima.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Result 3: The strongest maternal effects evolve from maternal traits that endure little selective noise</title>
<p>Next, we assess the combined influence of environmental stochasticity and periodicity, by considering a scenario in which selection on trait <italic>z</italic><sub>1</sub> fluctuates only periodically whereas selection on trait <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub> fluctuates both stochastically and periodically (e.g. see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Such a scenario reflects, for example, a case in which some traits (e.g., <italic>z</italic><sub>1</sub>) are associated with more predictable selective conditions than other traits (e.g., <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub>).</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g005">Figure 5A</xref> we vary the degree of stochastic noise <italic>d</italic> in selection acting on character <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub>. Increasing levels of noise lead to the evolution of substantial cross-trait maternal effects <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> from maternal character <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to offspring character <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. By contrast, the value of the other cross trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> (from maternal character <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to offspring character <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) evolves towards zero. Both the same-trait maternal effects <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> evolve towards positive and negative values respectively, corresponding to a positive dominant eigenvalue <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that is expected when the frequency of noise-free periodic fluctuations is relatively low (e.g., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003550-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>The evolution of multivariate maternal effects when varying the degree of noise in selective optimum <italic>θ</italic><sub>2</sub> while selective optimum <italic>θ</italic><sub>1</sub> remains noise-free.</title>
<p>Panel A: evolving maternal effects. Panel B: corresponding phenotypic variances <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of each phenotypic trait, showing that phenotype <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub> exhibits increased phenotypic variance (resulting in bet-hedging) when compared to <italic>z</italic><sub>1</sub>. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In order to explain the marked evolution of the cross-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub>, note that selection on maternal trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is characterized by white noise, while noise is absent on maternal trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Consequently, maternal trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a less reliable source of information about future selective conditions experienced by offspring. As a result, offspring are selected to obtain their information about periodic fluctuations from the other maternal trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, thereby evolving large, positive values of the cross trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> while its counterpart <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> evolves towards a value of 0. Hence, asymmetries in information content between both maternal characters favor the evolution of cross-trait maternal effects from the most reliable maternal character, phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>When the degree of noise in <italic>θ</italic><sub>2</sub> increases to ever larger levels, we find that <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> attains either positive or negative values of a large absolute magnitude, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). In line with analytical models that show that values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are associated with very large phenotypic variances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>, we find indeed that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> results in a large phenotypic variance of trait <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, while the variance of the other trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is generally small (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Large phenotypic variances are selectively favored in unpredictable environments, since a large diversity of phenotypes among siblings warrants the survival of at least a subset of them in the event of environmental change (bet-hedging: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Seger1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Starrfelt1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Bull1">[77]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Svardal1">[78]</xref>).</p>
<p>Given that maternal effects may thus drive the evolution of large phenotypic variances, large values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> relative to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can only be realized by evolving a large cross-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub>. By contrast, evolving a large within-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> would also generate large values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, but also gives rise to highly detrimental carry-over effects in which extreme values of the maternal phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> will lead to values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> an even larger magnitude in the next generation. Such detrimental carry-over effects are absent for the cross-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub>, since it has the more constant maternal phenotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as its input. Hence, cross-trait maternal effects may facilitate the evolution of large phenotypic variances without giving rise to deleterious carry-over effects that are associated with large absolute values of within-trait maternal effects <italic>m<sub>ii</sub></italic>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Maternal effects give rise to an interaction between parental and offspring phenotypes that is considered to be an important adaptation to changing environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Badyaev1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Uller1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hoyle1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Rsnen1">[79]</xref>. Yet, few formal models predict how selection shapes the strength and sign of maternal effects in different ecological contexts (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kazancolu1">[80]</xref> for similar remarks in the context of social interactions). The current study is therefore the first to show that different forms of environmental fluctuations can have a profound impact on the evolution of multivariate maternal effects.</p>
<p>When fluctuating selection acts in an identical fashion on all maternal traits, we find that the shape of the maternal effects matrix <bold>M</bold> (measured by its eigenvalues) evolves to be closely aligned with the degree of autocorrelation between parental and offspring phenotypes. Hence, we expect that slow fluctuations (leading to a positive autocorrelation) select for positive real parts of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, while rapid fluctuations select for negative real parts of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This finding corroborates a number of univariate models which showed that the rate of environmental fluctuations corresponds to the degree with which offspring should copy or diverge from their parent's phenotype in the case of discrete phenotypic variation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lachmann1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kussell1">[81]</xref>. Interestingly, our multivariate model shows that the same shape of <bold>M</bold> can sometimes be achieved in multiple ways, thereby leading to alternatively stable states in which entries of <bold>M</bold> can differ substantially in sign and magnitude between different subpopulations. Consequently, hybrid crosses between subpopulations are likely to lead to suboptimal values of maternal effects, potentially leading to postzygotic reproductive isolation. Nonetheless, as alternatively stable states collapse to a single outcome when fluctuating selection diverges between both traits, it remains to be seen whether maternal effects can indeed contribute to reproductive isolation across a broad range of contexts.</p>
<p>The most important result of the current study is that cross-correlations between selective fluctuations acting on different traits can select for striking configurations of cross-trait maternal effects. One way in which such cross-correlations can arise is due to time lags between selection acting on one trait and selection acting on another trait. Essentially, lag-times between fluctuating optima create asymmetries in the information content between both maternal characters, so that characters which endure selective fluctuations which are ‘advanced’ (relative to selective fluctuations on other traits) are more informative about future selective conditions than other characters. As a consequence, cross-trait maternal effects from such maternal traits should evolve to positive values, whereas cross-trait maternal effects based on traits enduring delayed selection should evolve to negative values. Hence, our study suggests that pairs of positive and negative maternal effects are indicative of lag-times (or cross-correlations in the action of fluctuating selection between different traits.</p>
<p>Another context in which asymmetries in information content occur between both maternal traits is when fluctuating selection on one character contains more stochastic noise relative to selection on other characters. In this case, we expect that offspring characters benefit from information contained in those maternal traits that endure the most predictable form of fluctuating selection, whereas offspring are selectively favored to ignore information from maternal characters with more selective noise when alternative maternal traits are available. Henceforth, we may expect cross-trait maternal effects to evolve that rely on those maternal traits which endure the most predictable forms of fluctuating selection. In addition, when stochastic noise in selective conditions acting on one particular trait is substantial, cross-trait maternal effects of large absolute magnitude may give rise to increased phenotypic variance in the trait that experiences noisy selection (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Such increased phenotypic variation is selectively advantageous in fluctuating environments, as it gives rise to bet-hedging <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Seger1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Starrfelt1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Gillespie1">[82]</xref>. Following the seminal model of Kirkpatrick and Lande <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref> our study indeed shows that large phenotypic variances are associated with relatively large magnitudes of maternal effects coefficients, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Henceforth, such ‘large’ maternal effects may provide an efficient means to increase phenotypic variation among offspring, which is in line with a number of studies that have identified maternal effects as a mechanism that gives rise to bet-hedging <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Marshall2">[83]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Crean1">[84]</xref>. On the other hand, large maternal effects will also imply that any fluctuations in current trait values resonate to future generations, generating ever larger mismatches to future environmental conditions. To use maternal effects to increase phenotypic variance, individuals are selectively favored to use other maternal traits, which are less affected by stochastic fluctuations in selective conditions. Consequently, cross-trait maternal effects used in the context of bet-hedging are expected to rely on maternal characters that are stably inherited across generations.</p>
<p>While numerous empirical studies have measured nongenetic effects in animal and plant populations (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Mousseau1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Rsnen1">[79]</xref>), almost all of these studies have taken a univariate perspective and measured only single maternal effects coefficients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Janssen1">[85]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-McAdam1">[86]</xref>, or alternatively, measured different maternal traits lumped into a single ‘maternal performance’ character (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Thiede1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Wolf3">[87]</xref>). Consequently, it is currently premature to assess whether our predictions correspond to any empirical measurements of maternal effects matrix <bold>M</bold>. The current study indicates, however, that overlooked components of <bold>M</bold>, such as cross-trait maternal effects, could potentially be an important adaptation to fluctuating selection, and may provide a signature of past selective differences between traits. We therefore hope that the current model provides an incentive for future studies to assess maternal effects in a multivariate context. Such measurements of <bold>M</bold> are facilitated by the recent advent of multivariate methods developed within the context of indirect genetic effects (IGEs, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Wolf3">[87]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin2">[90]</xref>) that allow for the estimation of <bold>M</bold> using variance components <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin3">[91]</xref>. To our knowledge, only a single study so far has used these multivariate methods to measure <bold>M</bold>: Galloway and coworkers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Galloway2">[32]</xref>, see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin1">[70]</xref>) measured maternal effects across four different life history traits in the plant <italic>Campanulastrum americanum</italic>, finding that some cross-trait maternal effects have magnitudes similar to or sometimes even larger than any within-trait maternal effects on similar characters. Moreover, cross-trait maternal effects often differ considerably in magnitude and even in sign, suggesting that observed variability among components in <bold>M</bold> is present and might be matched to past selective conditions to test our hypotheses. Moreover, a follow-up study in the same population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin1">[70]</xref> highlights another distinctive feature of maternal effects, namely that evolutionary change in phenotypes in a given generation is the result of both current and past selection gradients. We therefore hope that more studies follow the example by Galloway, McGlothlin and coworkers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Galloway2">[32]</xref> and measure maternal effects in multivariate contexts.</p>
<p>The current model has made a number of limiting assumptions that suggest possible directions for future work. The current study considers the simplest possible genetic architecture, where the breeding values <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and maternal effects <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are represented by single, diploid loci. It is well established that the relative number of loci coding for each trait may affect the magnitudes of the additive genetic (co)variances (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande7">[92]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Houle2">[93]</xref>), which in turn may either enhance or constrain adaptation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Walsh1">[46]</xref>. Apart from the potential effects of additive genetic (co)variances, however, we note that previous comparisons of multilocus and single-locus approaches (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Charlesworth1">[94]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kuijper2">[97]</xref>) have shown that evolutionary endpoints are often remarkably similar regardless of the approach taken, so we expect the evolution of <bold>M</bold> to be robust to more complicated genetic architectures. Future studies should assess whether this prediction indeed bears out.</p>
<p>In addition, we exclusively focus on the evolution of cross-trait maternal effects due to temporal cross-correlations, thereby generating interactions between two different characters in a transgenerational context. By contrast, conventional studies on multivariate evolution focus exclusively on genetic correlations as the main (within-generational) signature of interactions between traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande8">[98]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Pavlicev1">[102]</xref>. It would therefore be interesting to investigate whether those selective contexts that give rise to genetic correlations, such as trade-offs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-VanNoordwijk1">[103]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Roff1">[104]</xref>, phenotypic plasticity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Via1">[105]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Via2">[106]</xref>, developmental interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Cheverud1">[99]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Slatkin1">[100]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Pavlicev1">[102]</xref> or sexual selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kuijper2">[97]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Barton1">[101]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande9">[107]</xref> also affect the evolution of cross-trait maternal effects.</p>
<p>In turn, the potential role of cross-trait maternal effects as constraints on phenotypic evolution is currently virtually unexplored <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande2">[35]</xref>, as conventional studies have focused almost exclusively on genetic correlations that constrain the multivariate response to selection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Arnold1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Walsh1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Futuyma1">[54]</xref>. When cross-trait maternal effects are present, however, past selection on a particular character in the previous generation may lead to a correlated selective response on other characters even when genetic correlations themselves are absent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Lande2">[35]</xref>. In addition, a recent study on univariate maternal effects shows that maternal effects expose populations to stronger transient perturbations in response to sudden environmental shifts than populations without maternal effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Hoyle1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003550-Ezard1">[73]</xref>. More work is therefore needed to single out those ecological conditions in which significant cross-trait maternal effects are expected to evolve, as well assessing their consequences to phenotypic adaptation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003550.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p>The evolution of a single maternal effect <italic>m</italic> when fluctuations in <italic>θ</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) are stochastic rather than periodic. Instead of varying the frequency of environmental change <italic>ω</italic><sub>1</sub> (which is only relevant to periodic environments), we now vary the autocorrelation <italic>ρ</italic> between selective conditions experienced by mother and offspring. Maternal effects evolve to be positive when <italic>ρ</italic> attains large, positive values. By contrast, negative values evolve for smaller values of <italic>ρ</italic>. Each dot represents the average maternal effect <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> measured over ten replicate simulations (at generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), while the shaded areas depict corresponding standard deviations. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003550.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p>The evolution of the multivariate maternal effects matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when fluctuations in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are periodic (panel A) or stochastic (panel B). Panel A: Similar to the univariate scenario depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g001">Figure 1</xref>, we find that <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> evolve to positive values when periodic fluctuations are slow, whereas maternal effects evolve to be negative when fluctuations occur rapidly. Panel B: when the autocorrelation in selective conditions is positive (negative) between two subsequent timesteps, <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> again evolve to positive (negative) values, although magnitudes are more modest relative to panel A. Note that both selective optima are identical <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the periodic environment, whereas both optima are uncorrelated in the stochastic environment. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (panel A), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (panel B).</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003550.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p>The evolution of multivariate maternal effects in a stochastically fluctuating environment, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are Gaussian random variables. Panels A–C: when both optima are identical (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e159" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) we find alternative stable states, similar to the ones found in the periodic environment in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figure 3</xref>. Panel D–E: both optima are uncorrelated, yet identically distributed. Consequently, the alternative stable states collapse to a single outcome. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003550.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p>An example simulation showing the selective advantage of evolving maternal effects in a periodically fluctuating environment, when the rate of environmental change is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003550-g003">Figures 3A,B</xref>). At first, only the genetic values <bold>a</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) that code for phenotypes <italic>z</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>z</italic><sub>2</sub> are allowed to evolve, to obtain a baseline measure of adaptation to a fluctuating environment in terms of the number of surviving individuals <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (panel C). From generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> onwards, the two same-trait maternal effects <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> are allowed to evolve in addition to both genetic values. However, panels B and C show that <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> do not enhance adaptation to a fluctuating environment. This is unsurprising, as the two same-trait maternal effects <italic>m</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>22</sub> can only lead to fluctuations in which phenotypes change sign at every generation (i.e., when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). However, for the rate of environmental change <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> considered here, the optimal phenotype would need to change sign every second generation (see main text). When also both cross-trait maternal effects <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> are allowed to evolve (from generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> onwards), increased flexibility allows for phenotypic adaptation to the fluctuating environment (panel B), thereby eliminating the deep troughs of the fitness landscape in panel C. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003550.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p>The evolution of multivariate maternal effects in a stochastically fluctuating environment, where the selective optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the parental generation is cross-correlated with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the offspring generation. Panel A: the cross-correlation between optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is varied from −1 to 1, while the other cross-correlation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is constrained between values 0 and −0.1. As a consequence, the cross-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>12</sub> from maternal trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to offspring trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> evolves from negative to positive values, in line with the dominant cross-correlation. Panel B: now, the cross-correlation between optimum <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e176" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is varied from −1 to 1, while the other cross-correlation is constrained to much smaller values. Again, we find that the corresponding cross-trait maternal effect <italic>m</italic><sub>21</sub> from maternal trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to offspring trait <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> evolves from negative to positive, in line with the cross-correlation. In both panels, the within-trait autocorrelations <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e179" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are set at <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.1. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003550.e180" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Jonathan Wells, Rebecca Hoyle and Thomas Ezard for valuable discussions within the Transgen group, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://transgenerational.zoo.cam.ac.uk" xlink:type="simple">http://transgenerational.zoo.cam.ac.uk</ext-link>. We thank the Lorentz Centre in Leiden, the Netherlands and the Dutch Royal Academy of Arts and Sciences (KNAW) for funding of a workshop on nongenetic effects that contributed to the results presented in this paper. In addition, the Coop discussion group at the University of Exeter (Penryn Campus, Cornwall) is thanked for discussion of this work and Chris Guiver for valuable comments on the manuscript. This work has made use of the resources provided by the University of Exeter Science Strategy and the resulting Systems Biology initiative. Primarily these include HPC facilities managed by Konrad Paszkiewicz of the College of Environmental and Life Sciences and Pete Leggett of the University of Exeter Academics services unit. In addition, the authors acknowledge the use of the UCL Legion High Performance Computing Facility (<email xlink:type="simple">Legion@UCL</email>), and associated support services, in the completion of this work.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Grant1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Unpredictable evolution in a 30-year study of Darwin's finches</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>296</volume>: <fpage>707</fpage>–<lpage>711</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kawecki1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawecki</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Conceptual issues in local adaptation</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1225</fpage>–<lpage>1241</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Siepielski1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siepielski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiBattista</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>It's about time: the temporal dynamics of phenotypic selection in the wild</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1261</fpage>–<lpage>1276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Meyers1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Fighting change with change: adaptive variation in an uncertain world</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>557</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-WestEberhard1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">West-Eberhard MJ (2003) Developmental Plasticity and Evolution. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Seger1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brockmann</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>What is bet-hedging?</article-title> <source>Oxf Surv Evol Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Childs1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>CJE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary bet-hedging in the real world: empirical evidence and challenges revealed by plants</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>3055</fpage>–<lpage>3064</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Starrfelt1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Starrfelt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kokko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Bet-hedging – a triple trade-off between means, variances and correlations</article-title>. <source>Biol Rev</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>742</fpage>–<lpage>755</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Pigliucci1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Pigliucci M (2001) Phenotypic Plasticity: Beyond Nature and Nurture. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Leimar1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leimar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammerstein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dooren</surname><given-names>TJM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A new perspective on developmental plasticity and the principles of adaptive morph determination</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Chevin1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chevin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Adaptation, plasticity, and extinction in a changing environment: towards a predictive theory</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1000357</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Bossdorf1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossdorf</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pigliucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Epigenetics for ecologists</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Danchin1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danchin</surname><given-names>É</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charmantier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mesoudi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Beyond DNA: integrating inclusive inheritance into an extended theory of evolution</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Bonduriansky1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonduriansky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crean</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The implications of nongenetic inheritance for evolution in changing environments</article-title>. <source>Evol Appl</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jablonka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transgenerational epigenetic inheritance: prevalence, mechanisms, and implications for the study of heredity and evolution</article-title>. <source>Q Rev Biol</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Richerson1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Richerson PJ, Boyd R (2005) Not by Genes Alone: How Culture Transformed Human Evolution. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Youngson1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Youngson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitelaw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Transgenerational epigenetic effects</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genom Hum Genet</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Mousseau1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Mousseau T, Fox CW (1998) Maternal Effects as Adaptations. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Badyaev1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badyaev</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Maternal effects as generators of evolutionary change</article-title>. <source>Ann NY Acad Sci</source> <volume>1133</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Agrawal1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laforsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tollrian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Transgenerational induction of defences in animals and plants</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>401</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Galloway1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Etterson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Transgenerational plasticity is adaptive in the wild</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>318</volume>: <fpage>1134</fpage>–<lpage>1136</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Uller1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Developmental plasticity and the evolution of parental effects</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>438</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Jablonka2"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jablonka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oborny</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molnár</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kisdi</surname><given-names>É</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofbauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The adaptive advantage of phenotypic memory in changing environments</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>350</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Shea1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shea</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Three epigenetic information channels and their different roles in evolution</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1178</fpage>–<lpage>1187</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Hoyle1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ezard</surname><given-names>THG</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The benefits of maternal effects in novel and in stable environments</article-title>. <source>J Roy Soc Interface</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>2403</fpage>–<lpage>2413</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Marshall1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>When is a maternal effect adaptive?</article-title> <source>Oikos</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>1957</fpage>–<lpage>1963</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Uller2"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Uller T (2012) Parental effects in development and evolution. In: Royle NJ, Smiseth PT, Kölliker M, editors. The Evolution of Parental Care. New York: Oxford University Press. pp. 247–267.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Fischer1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taborsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kokko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>How to balance the offspring quality-quantity tradeoff when environmental cues are unreliable</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kuijper1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuijper</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>How should mothers adjust the size of their offspring to local environmental cues?</article-title> <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1488</fpage>–<lpage>1498</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Thiede1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiede</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Maternal inheritance and its effect on adaptive evolution: a quantitative genetic analysis of maternal effects in a natural plant population</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>998</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Genetic correlations and maternal effect coefficients obtained from offspring-parent regression</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>–<lpage>922</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Galloway2"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Etterson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGlothlin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Contribution of direct and maternal genetic effects to life-history evolution</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>826</fpage>–<lpage>838</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Postma1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siitari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwabl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tschirren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The multivariate egg: quantifying within- and among-clutch correlations between maternally derived yolk immunoglobulins and yolk androgens using multivariate mixed models</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>631</fpage>–<lpage>638</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The evolution of maternal characters</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande2"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Selection response in traits with maternal inheritance</article-title>. <source>Genet Res</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Cowley1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atchley</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Quantitative genetic models for development, epigenetic selection, and phenotypic evolution</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Wolf1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>ED</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The coadaptation of parental and offspring characters</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Day1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonduriansky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A unified approach to the evolutionary consequences of genetic and nongenetic inheritance</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>E18</fpage>–<lpage>E36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lachmann1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jablonka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The inheritance of phenotypes: an adaptation to fluctuating environments</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source> <volume>181</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Groothuis1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Groothuis</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwabl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hormone–mediated maternal effects in birds: mechanisms matter but what do we know of them?</article-title> <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>363</volume>: <fpage>1647</fpage>–<lpage>1661</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Gil1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hormones in avian eggs: physiology, ecology and behavior</article-title>. <source>Adv Stud Behav</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Townley1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Townley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ezard</surname><given-names>THG</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A G matrix analogue to capture the cumulative effects of nongenetic inheritance</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1234</fpage>–<lpage>1243</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Hadfield1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Hadfield J (2012) The quantitative genetic theory of parental effects. In: Royle N, Smiseth PT, Kölliker M, editors. The Evolution of Parental Care. New York: Oxford University Press. pp. 267–284.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande3"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Quantitative genetic analysis of multivariate evolution, applied to brain:body size allometry</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Arnold1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Constraints on phenotypic evolution</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>S85</fpage>–<lpage>S107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Walsh1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blows</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Abundant genetic variation + strong selection = multivariate genetic constraints: a geometric view of adaptation</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Hansen1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The evolution of genetic architecture</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Arnold2"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bürger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenlohe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ajie</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Understanding the evolution and stability of the G-matrix</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>2451</fpage>–<lpage>2461</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Jones1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bürger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenlohe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uyeda</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The effects of stochastic and episodic movement of the optimum on the evolution of the G-matrix and the response of the trait mean to selection</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2210</fpage>–<lpage>2231</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande4"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>The measurement of selection on correlated characters</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1210</fpage>–<lpage>1226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Houle1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Comparing evolvability and variability of quantitative traits</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Blows1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blows</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A reassessment of genetic limits to evolutionary change</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1371</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kirkpatrick2"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Patterns of quantitative genetic variation in multiple dimensions</article-title>. <source>Genetica</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Futuyma1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Futuyma</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary constraint and ecological consequences</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1865</fpage>–<lpage>1884</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Wolf2"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>What are maternal effects (and what are they not)?</article-title> <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>364</volume>: <fpage>1107</fpage>–<lpage>1115</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Groothuis2"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Groothuis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eising</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blount</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apanius</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Multiple pathways of maternal effects in black-headed gull eggs: constraint and adaptive compensatory adjustment</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1304</fpage>–<lpage>1313</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Boulinier1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boulinier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staszewski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Maternal transfer of antibodies: raising immuno-ecology issues</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Garnier1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staszewski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Militó</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobato</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Maternal antibody persistence: a neglected life-history trait with implications from albatross conservation to comparative immunology</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>2033</fpage>–<lpage>2041</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Jones2"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bürger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Stability of the G-matrix in a population experiencing pleiotropic mutation, stabilizing selection, and genetic drift</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1747</fpage>–<lpage>1760</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Guillaume1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Effects of migration on the genetic covariance matrix</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>2398</fpage>–<lpage>2409</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Revell1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Revell</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The G matrix under fluctuating correlational mutation and selection</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1857</fpage>–<lpage>1872</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kimura1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>The number of alleles that can be maintained in a finite population</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>738</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Dickerson1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickerson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1947</year>) <article-title>Composition of hog carcasses as influenced by heritable differences in rate and economy of gain</article-title>. <source>Iowa Agr Exp Sta Res Bull</source> <volume>354</volume>: <fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Willham1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willham</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>The covariance between relatives for characters composed of components contributed by related individuals</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Falconer1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Falconer D (1965) Maternal effects and selection response. In: Geerts SJ, editor. Genetics Today, Proceedings of the XI International Congress on Genetics. Volume <volume>3</volume> . Oxford: Pergamon. pp. 763–774.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande5"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Natural selection and random genetic drift in phenotypic evolution</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Mller1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lessells</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korsten</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Von Engelhardt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Manipulative signals in family conflict? On the function of maternal yolk hormones in birds</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>E84</fpage>–<lpage>E96</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Uller3"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A theoretical model of the evolution of maternal effects under parent-offspring conflict</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2075</fpage>–<lpage>2084</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Tschirren1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tschirren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sendecka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groothuis</surname><given-names>TGG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doligez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Heritable variation in maternal yolk hormone transfer in a wild bird population</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlothlin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The contribution of maternal effects to selection response: an empirical test of competing models</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Wells1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JCK</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ecological volatility and human evolution: a novel perspective on life history and reproductive strategy</article-title>. <source>Evol Anthropol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande6"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Expected relative fitness and the adaptive topography of fluctuating selection</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1835</fpage>–<lpage>1846</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Ezard1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezard</surname><given-names>THG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prizak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The fitness costs of adaptation via phenotypic plasticity and maternal effects</article-title>. <source>Funct Ecol</source> <comment>In press. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.12207" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/1365-2435.12207</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-EdelsteinKeshet1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Edelstein-Keshet L (1988) Mathematical models in Biology. New York: McGraw-Hill.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Otto1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Otto SP, Day T (2007) A Biologist's Guide to Mathematical Modeling in Ecology and Evolution. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Wei1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Wei WWS (1994) Time Series Analysis – Univariate and Multivariate Methods. Redwood City: Addison-Wesley.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Bull1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Evolution of phenotypic variance</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Svardal1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Svardal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rueffler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Comparing environmental and genetic variance as adaptive response to fluctuating selection</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2492</fpage>–<lpage>2513</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Rsnen1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Räsänen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kruuk</surname><given-names>LEB</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Maternal effects and evolution at ecological time-scales</article-title>. <source>Funct Ecol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>421</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kazancolu1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazancıoğlu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonzo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The evolution of social interactions changes predictions about interacting phenotypes</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>2056</fpage>–<lpage>2064</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kussell1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kussell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leibler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic diversity, population growth, and information in fluctuating environments</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>2075</fpage>–<lpage>2078</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Gillespie1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Natural selection with varying selection coefficients? A haploid model</article-title>. <source>Genet Res</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Marshall2"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonduriansky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bussière</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Offspring size variation within broods as a bet-hedging strategy in unpredictable environments</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>2506</fpage>–<lpage>2517</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Crean1"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crean</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Coping with environmental uncertainty: dynamic bet hedging as a maternal effect</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>364</volume>: <fpage>1087</fpage>–<lpage>1096</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Janssen1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joosse</surname><given-names>ENG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scharloo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>A negative maternal effect in springtails</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>828</fpage>–<lpage>834</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-McAdam1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McAdam</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boutin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Maternal effects and the response to selection in red squirrels</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Wolf3"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>ED</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheverud</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary consequences of indirect genetic effects</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Moore1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>ED</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Interacting phenotypes and the evolutionary process. I. Direct and indirect genetic effects of social interactions</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1352</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Wolf4"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>ED</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Interacting phenotypes and the evolutionary process. II. Selection resulting from social interactions</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>153</volume>: <fpage>254</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin2"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlothlin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>ED</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Interacting phenotypes and the evolutionary process. III. Social evolution</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>2558</fpage>–<lpage>2574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-McGlothlin3"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlothlin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>ED</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>How to measure indirect genetic effects: the congruence of trait-based and variance-partitioning approaches</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1785</fpage>–<lpage>1795</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande7"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>The maintenance of genetic variability by mutation in a polygenic character with linked loci</article-title>. <source>Genet Res</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Houle2"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Genetic covariance of fitness correlates: what genetic correlations are made of and why it matters</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Charlesworth1"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Optimization models, quantitative genetics, and mutation</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>520</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Taper1"><label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taper</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Models of character displacement and the theoretical robustness of taxon cycles</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>333</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Taylor1"><label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The selection differential in quantitative genetics and ESS models</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>2106</fpage>–<lpage>2110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Kuijper2"><label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuijper</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissing</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A guide to sexual selection theory</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande8"><label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>The genetic covariance between characters maintained by pleiotropic mutations</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Cheverud1"><label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheverud</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutledge</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atchley</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Quantitative genetics of development: genetic correlations among age-specific trait values and the evolution of ontogeny</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Slatkin1"><label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Quantitative genetics of heterochrony</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>811</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Barton1"><label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Natural and sexual selection on many loci</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Pavlicev1"><label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlicev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheverud</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evolution of adaptive phenotypic variation patterns by direct selection for evolvability</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source> <volume>278</volume>: <fpage>1903</fpage>–<lpage>1912</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-VanNoordwijk1"><label>103</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Noordwijk</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Acquisition and allocation of resources: their influence on variation in life history tactics</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Roff1"><label>104</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roff</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The evolution of genetic correlations: an analysis of patterns</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1392</fpage>–<lpage>1403</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Via1"><label>105</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Via</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Genotype-environment interaction and the evolution of phenotypic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Via2"><label>106</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Via</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Evolution of genetic variability in a spatially heterogeneous environment: effects of genotype-environment interaction</article-title>. <source>Genet Res</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003550-Lande9"><label>107</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Models of speciation by sexual selection on polygenic traits</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>3721</fpage>–<lpage>3725</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>