<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PBIOLOGY-D-13-00621</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme classes</subject><subj-group><subject>Transferases</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Enzyme regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Lipids</subject><subj-group><subject>Fatty acids</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Chemical biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Model organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Yeast and fungal models</subject><subj-group><subject>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell division</subject><subj-group><subject>Meiosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Quantitative Control of Protein <italic>S</italic>-Palmitoylation Regulates Meiotic Entry in Fission Yeast</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Quantitative Control of Protein Palmitoylation</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Mingzi M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Pei-Yun Jenny</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¤a</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>Felice D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>¤b</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>Howard C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Laboratory of Chemical Biology and Microbial Pathogenesis, The Rockefeller University, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Laboratory of Yeast Genetics and Cell Biology, The Rockefeller University, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Nicholas G.</given-names></name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Wayne State University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">hhang@rockefeller.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>The author(s) have made the following declarations about their contributions: Conceived and designed the experiments: MMZ. Performed the experiments: MMZ PYW. Analyzed the data: MMZ PYW PN HCH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MMZ FDK. Wrote the paper: MMZ PYW HCH.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤a</label><p>Current address: Institute of Genetics and Development of Rennes, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique Unité Mixte de Recherche 6290, Rennes, France.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤b</label><p>Current address: The Royal Society, London, United Kingdom.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e1001597</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Zhang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="RA1" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="uri" vol="" page="e1001598" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001598"> <article-title>Palmitoylation: A New Regulatory Role in Meiosis</article-title></related-article>
<abstract abstract-type="toc">
<p>Transcriptional control of DHHC palmitoyltransferase activity levels shapes cellular palmitoylation patterns and influences meiotic entry in fission yeast.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Protein <italic>S</italic>-palmitoylation, a lipid modification mediated by members of the palmitoyltransferase family, serves as an important membrane-targeting mechanism in eukaryotes. Although changes in palmitoyltransferase expression are associated with various physiological and disease states, how these changes affect global protein palmitoylation and cellular function remains unknown. Using a bioorthogonal chemical reporter and labeling strategy to identify and analyze multiple cognate substrates of a single Erf2 palmitoyltransferase, we demonstrate that control of Erf2 activity levels underlies the differential modification of key substrates such as the Rho3 GTPase in vegetative and meiotic cells. We show further that modulation of Erf2 activity levels drives changes in the palmitoylome as cells enter meiosis and affects meiotic entry. Disruption of Erf2 function delays meiotic entry, while increasing Erf2 palmitoyltransferase activity triggers aberrant meiosis in sensitized cells. Erf2-induced meiosis requires the function of the Rho3 GTPase, which is regulated by its palmitoylation state. We propose that control of palmitoyltransferase activity levels provides a fundamental mechanism for modulating palmitoylomes and cellular functions.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Palmitoylation is a fatty acid modification, which increases the hydrophobicity of proteins, known to control the membrane trafficking and function of many proteins important for cellular homeostasis and disease. Being a reversible process, palmitoylation is proposed to be a major cellular regulator. While changes in global protein palmitoylation patterns are often associated with different physiological states, the mechanisms that regulate this posttranslational modification and their functional consequences have been elusive. Using improved methods for protein palmitoylation analysis in the genetically tractable fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>, we discovered that the global protein palmitoylation pattern is significantly altered and correlates with entry into meiosis, a major developmental transition. We further showed that the precise level of a palmitoylating enzyme is important to shape the subset of lipid-modified proteins and influence the start of this cellular transition. As palmitoylated proteins are involved in eukaryotic cellular pathways, our results provide a crucial insight into how the quantitative control of palmitoylating enzymes may impact human physiology and disease.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>MMZ was supported by a fellowship from A*STAR, Singapore. This work was supported by grants from the Breast Cancer Research Foundation, The Wellcome Trust, and The Rockefeller University to PN, and Ellison Medical Foundation and NIH/NIGMS (R01 GM087544) to HCH. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In eukaryotic cells, posttranslational protein <italic>S</italic>-palmitoylation (hereafter referred to as palmitoylation) regulates protein-membrane associations as well as protein targeting and trafficking. The covalent addition of palmitic acid to cysteine residues is vital for the function of key signaling factors in diverse cellular processes including immune and neuronal signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Fukata1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Linder1">[3]</xref>. With its potential for reversibility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Martin1">[4]</xref>, which is unique among the characterized lipid modifications, palmitoylation allows both spatial and temporal control of protein function.</p>
<p>Given its versatility, palmitoylation is poised to be a major cellular regulator akin to phosphorylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Salaun1">[5]</xref>. Indeed, growing evidence suggests that protein palmitoylation is actively regulated. For example, receptor activity-regulated palmitate turnover of PSD-95 modulates synaptic strength and plasticity in postsynaptic neurons by mediating receptor clustering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Noritake1">[6]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-ElHusseiniAel1">[7]</xref>. Other extracellular signals have also been shown to alter the palmitoylation state or palmitate turnover rate of individual proteins in different cell types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Zhang1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mouillac1">[11]</xref>. Additionally, a broader level of control is suggested by global changes in palmitoylomes associated with specific physiological states of the cell or organism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mundy1">[12]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Kang1">[13]</xref>. While protein interactions that affect substrate accessibility have been shown to affect the palmitoylation state of specific substrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Ahearn1">[14]</xref>, the biochemical and genetic mechanisms that globally shape cellular palmitoylomes in response to physiological cues have remained elusive.</p>
<p>Protein palmitoylation is catalyzed by the Asp-His-His-Cys (DHHC)-containing palmitoyltransferases (hereafter referred to as palmitoyltransferases) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Roth1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Lobo1">[17]</xref>. One of the first palmitoyltransferases discovered, ERF2 (Effectors of Ras Function 2), was identified from a budding yeast screen designed to uncover cellular regulators of Ras palmitoylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Bartels1">[16]</xref>. Together, ERF2 (YLR246W) and its accessory protein ERF4 (YOL110W) form a functional palmitoyltransferase complex that catalyzes palmitate transfer to Ras <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Lobo1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Zhao1">[19]</xref>. Members of this palmitoyltransferase family are responsible for most protein palmitoylation events <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Roth2">[20]</xref>, and orthologs of these integral membrane enzymes with their characteristic DHHC motif that is required for palmitoyltransferase activity have been found in all examined eukaryotic genomes. In addition to having both distinct and overlapping substrate specificities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Roth2">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Huang1">[22]</xref>, palmitoyltransferases exhibit varying intracellular localization and tissue-specific expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Bannan1">[23]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Ohno1">[24]</xref>. Misregulated expression of specific palmitoyltransferases in mammals is associated with various developmental defects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Saleem1">[25]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mill1">[26]</xref>, neurological disorders <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Singaraja1">[27]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mukai1">[28]</xref>, and cancers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Draper1">[29]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Ducker1">[30]</xref>. Yet despite their central roles in transferring palmitate to proteins, to date there is little evidence for regulation of palmitoyltransferases, and the roles of these enzymes in shaping global protein palmitoylation in physiological contexts remain largely unexplored.</p>
<p>To investigate how palmitoyltransferase regulation affects global protein palmitoylation in a physiological context, we integrated genetic and chemical tools in the fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> and show that quantitative control of protein palmitoylation by varying Erf2 palmitoyltransferase activity levels shapes the palmitoylome during meiosis. We further demonstrate that palmitoyltransferase level-mediated changes in substrate palmitoylation affect meiotic entry in fission yeast cells, highlighting the physiological relevance of this regulatory mechanism for global protein palmitoylation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Changes in Global Protein Palmitoylation Are Associated with Meiosis</title>
<p>Fission yeast cells normally proliferate in the haploid state, but when nutrients become limiting, cells may enter an alternate meiotic differentiation pathway: cells of opposite mating types conjugate to form a diploid zygote, which replicates its genome and then undergoes two successive nuclear divisions to yield four haploid nuclei that mature into spores (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s001">Figure S1A</xref>). We took advantage of a well-characterized system in fission yeast for inducing synchronous meiosis that uses a temperature-sensitive allele of the Pat1 meiotic repressor (SPBC19C2.05), <italic>pat1-114</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Iino1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Nurse1">[33]</xref>. Diploid cells harboring this mutation can be induced to undergo meiosis in a timely and predictable manner by shifting the cultures from a permissive to restrictive temperature, resulting in the formation of viable spores (Figures S1B and 1A,B).</p>
<p>To analyze global changes in the palmitoylome during meiosis, we employed an alkyne-functionalized palmitate chemical reporter, alk-16, which together with bioorthogonal labeling offers significantly improved fluorescent detection of the modification compared to conventional radiolabeled lipids (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s002">Figure S2A</xref>–D) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Martin1">[4]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Zhang1">[8]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Charron1">[34]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Martin2">[35]</xref>. Using this system in diploid cells undergoing synchronous meiosis, we observed a distinct meiotic palmitoylome with a prominent band at approximately 23 kDa, which was absent in vegetative cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). This prompted us to focus on identifying the enzymes responsible for these modifications. Given that appearance of the meiotic palmitoylome followed the striking increase in Erf2 protein levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g001">Figure 1C</xref>), which reflects the reported <italic>erf2</italic> transcription profile during meiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wilhelm1">[36]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mata1">[37]</xref>, we postulated that the DHHC-containing Erf2 protein (SPBC3H7.09) plays a critical role in orchestrating meiosis-specific protein palmitoylation.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001597-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Use of chemical reporter strategy reveals changes in global protein palmitoylation during meiosis in fission yeast.</title>
<p>(A) Schematic representation of fission yeast sexual differentiation. Haploid cells conjugate to form a diploid zygote, which undergoes meiosis to yield four haploid nuclei that matures into spores. Pat1 kinase is a general repressor of meiosis. For more details on <italic>S. pombe</italic> meiosis, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s001">Figure S1</xref>. (B) Percentage of cells with 1, 2, or &gt;2 nuclei were determined by counting ≥200 DAPI-stained cells of the indicated strains at hourly intervals after meiotic induction (top). Representative DAPI images of cells at indicated times (bottom). Scale bars, 10 µm. Synchronous meiosis in diploid <italic>pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells was induced by shifting nitrogen-starved cultures to restrictive temperature (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Indicated times refer to the elapsed time after temperature shift. (C) Fluorescence profile of palmitoylated substrates in <italic>erf2-HA<sub>3</sub>/erf2-HA<sub>3</sub> pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> and <italic>erf2Δ/erf2Δ pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells undergoing synchronized meiosis (top panel). At the indicated times after meiotic induction, aliquots of the culture were pulse-labeled with alk-16. Western blots were probed for tubulin and HA (middle and bottom panels). (D) qPCR analysis of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> transcripts, normalized to <italic>act1</italic> mRNA levels, in vegetative (Veg) and meiotic (Mei, 8 h after meiotic induction) <italic>pat1-114/pat1-11</italic>4 cells. Data represent mean values of three biological repeats ± SD.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>The Erf2 Palmitoyltransferase Drives Changes in the Palmitoylome During Meiosis</title>
<p>Of the five open reading frames in the fission yeast genome that encode for proteins containing the DHHC motif, a characteristic feature of palmitoyltransferases (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s003">Figure S3A</xref>), we focused on Erf2 whose strongly elevated expression during meiosis precedes the appearance of the meiotic palmitoylome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g001">Figures 1D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s003">S3B</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wilhelm1">[36]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mata1">[37]</xref>. By in-gel fluorescence, we showed that Erf2 and its cofactor Erf4 (SPAC3F10.07c), and not the other DHHC-containing proteins examined, are specifically required for the incorporation of alk-16 onto Ras1 (SPAC17H9.09c) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g002">Figure 2A</xref>), the only reported palmitoylated protein in <italic>S. pombe</italic> whose modification is important for pheromone signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Onken1">[38]</xref>. Incorporation of alk-16 directly requires Erf2 palmitoyltransferase activity, as the Ras1 palmitoylation defect in <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells is rescued by re-introduction of Erf2, but not a catalytically inactive DHHC→DHHA mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g002">Figure 2B</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mitchell2">[39]</xref>. Collectively, these experiments demonstrate that Erf2 and Erf4 are functional orthologs of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> ERF2 and ERF4 palmitoyltransferase subunits, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Lobo1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Zhao1">[19]</xref>, and that this method can be used to profile Erf2-Erf4 substrates in fission yeast.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001597-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>The Erf2–Erf4 palmitoyltransferase drives major changes in the meiotic palmitoylome during meiosis.</title>
<p>(A–B) Alk-16-associated fluorescence of immunopurified Ras1 from vegetatively growing cells with the indicated palmitoyltransferase deletions (top panels). Western blots are probed for Ras1 (bottom panels). Wild-type (<italic>DHHC</italic>) or catalytically inactive (<italic>DHHA</italic>) Erf2 was expressed from a thiamine-repressible promoter in <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells (B). (C) Fluorescence detection of palmitoylated substrates (top panel) and Ras1 palmitoylation (bottom panel) in homozygous diploid <italic>pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells with the indicated palmitoyltransferase deletions 8 h after meiotic induction. Ctrl, DMSO control; Veg, vegetative cells.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To determine whether Erf2-Erf4 palmitoyltransferase function has an impact on the meiotic palmitoylome, we profiled palmitoylated proteins in mutant diploid cells undergoing synchronous meiosis. The distinct meiotic palmitoylome requires Erf2 activity, as modification of those prominent substrates was not observed in either meiotic <italic>erf2Δ</italic> or <italic>erf4Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). Ras1 was also palmitoylated in an Erf2-Erf4-dependent manner in this context (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g002">Figure 2C</xref>), suggesting a role for Ras1 in meiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Dudler1">[40]</xref>. Since salient features of the meiotic palmitoylome were still observed in the absence of two other putative palmitoyltransferases examined, we concluded that Erf2-Erf4 is the primary palmitoyltransferase driving changes in protein palmitoylation during meiosis.</p>
<p>This system, in which palmitoyltransferase regulation is linked to a highly coordinated biological process, provides an excellent model for studying how control of palmitoyltransferase expression affects global protein palmitoylation and its functional consequences.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Differential Palmitoylation of Erf2 Substrates in Distinct Cellular States</title>
<p>To study how control of palmitoyltransferase expression affects palmitoylation of its substrates, we sought to identify the Erf2 substrates that are preferentially palmitoylated during meiosis by comparative proteomics. We affinity purified alk-16-labeled proteins in meiotic <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup></italic>, vegetative <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup></italic>, and meiotic <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells using a cleavable azido-biotin affinity tag (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s004">Figure S4A</xref>–C) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Yang1">[41]</xref>. Recovered proteins were subsequently identified by gel-based proteomics, and those with ≥2-fold spectral counts in alk-16 samples compared to the corresponding DMSO controls were further analyzed. Proteins enriched in meiotic <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup></italic> cells were subjected to two filter criteria, excluding those also enriched in (1) meiotic <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells and (2) vegetative <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup></italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Notably, Ras1 was excluded because it was equally recovered in both meiotic and vegetative <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup></italic> cells, consistent with our biochemical analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g002">Figure 2B,C</xref>). Of the 238 remaining candidates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s011">Table S2</xref>), we focused on Isp3 (SPAC1F8.05) and Rho3 (SPAC23C4.08) as they were the most highly enriched proteins with molecular weights matching the prominent ∼23 kDa band we previously observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figures 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s004">S4D</xref>). Isp3, an abundant protein involved in spore formation with meiosis-specific expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figure 3D</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Shimoda1">[42]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Sato1">[43]</xref>, was the most heavily modified species: the ∼23 kDa band was lost in <italic>isp3Δ</italic> cells, and HA<sub>3</sub>-tagging of Isp3 reduced the electrophoretic mobility of the major fluorescent band (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). We further confirmed that Rho3, a Rho GTPase involved in polarized growth in vegetative cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Nakano1">[44]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wang1">[45]</xref>, is also an Erf2 substrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figure 3E</xref>) that is differentially modified between meiotic and vegetative cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figure 3F</xref>). These results suggest a novel mechanism by which changes in the palmitoylome can be mediated by the regulation of a single palmitoyltransferase activity. Given that Erf2 expression is low in vegetative cells and high in meiotic cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g001">Figure 1D</xref>), we reasoned that the differential modification of Rho3 and Ras1 could be a consequence of palmitoyltransferase levels.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001597-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Erf2 substrates are differentially modified in vegetative and meiotic cells.</title>
<p>(A) Filter criteria for candidate substrates that are palmitoylated by Erf2 during meiosis. (B) Each of the 238 candidates obtained is represented as a data point reflecting its molecular weight and enrichment (net spectral counts) in alk-16 over DMSO labeled <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup></italic> meiotic cells. Isp3 and Rho3 are the top two candidates with molecular weights ∼23 kDa (shaded). (C) Fluorescence profiles of meiotic cells with indicated gene deletions or expressing endogenous or tagged Isp3 (top panels). Western blot is probed for HA (bottom panels). Ctrl, DMSO control. (D) Isp3-HA<sub>3</sub> expression as determined by anti-HA blot of lysates from cells in distinct cellular states. Veg, vegetative cells. Mei, meiotic cells. (E) Rho3-HA<sub>3</sub> palmitoylation in meiotic <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup></italic> and <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells (top panel). Western blot is probed for HA (bottom panel). (F) Ras1 and Rho3 palmitoylation states in vegetative and meiotic cells (top panels). Western blots were probed for Ras1 and HA (bottom panels). Synchronous meiosis in indicated diploid <italic>pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells was induced by shifting nitrogen-starved cultures to restrictive temperature (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Meiotic cells refer to cells 8 h after the temperature shift.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Quantitative Control of Protein Palmitoylation by Varying Palmitoyltransferase Levels</title>
<p>To test this hypothesis, we first reduced <italic>erf2</italic> expression in diploid cells undergoing synchronized meiosis, achieving intermediate and low expression levels relative to wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). Although all three substrates require Erf2 for palmitoylation, Ras1, Rho3, and Isp3 were differentially modified as a consequence of altering <italic>erf2</italic> levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). Ras1 was efficiently palmitoylated at low <italic>erf2</italic> expression levels, and its palmitoylation was unaltered at higher levels. In contrast, reducing <italic>erf2</italic> expression decreased Rho3 and Isp3 palmitoylation with different sensitivities. The fact that palmitoylation of Rho3 and Isp3 are greatly attenuated at low <italic>erf2</italic> levels suggests that the strong upregulation of <italic>erf2</italic> expression during meiosis is needed to establish the distinctive features of the meiotic palmitoylome. In addition, these results demonstrate that modulation of palmitoyltransferase levels can differentially alter palmitoylation of individual substrates.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001597-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Quantitative control of protein palmitoylation by varying palmitoyltransferase levels affects meiotic entry.</title>
<p>(A) Labels are indicated in box. qPCR analysis of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> transcripts normalized to <italic>act1</italic> mRNA levels in indicated <italic>pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> strains 8 h into synchronous meiosis (top panel). Data represent mean values of experimental triplicates ± SD Palmitoylation of cognate Erf2 substrates were analyzed from the same lysate of each strain (bottom panels). Ras1 and Rho3-HA<sub>3</sub> were immunopurified and their levels were determined by Ras1 and HA immunoblots, respectively. Isp3 palmitoylation was monitored at the lysate level since it accounts for most of the fluorescence at ∼23 kDa. (B) Labels are indicated in box. Overexpression of <italic>erf2</italic> and/or <italic>erf4</italic> from thiamine-repressible <italic>nmt</italic> promoters in the indicated vegetatively growing <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells was achieved by switching them into thiamine-free medium for 24 h. qPCR analysis (top panel) as well as palmitoylation of Ras1 and Rho3 (bottom panels) were performed as described in (A). Isp3 is not expressed in vegetative cells. Cells were maintained at permissive temperature throughout this experiment. (C, D) DAPI (left) and DIC (right) images of indicated cells 96 h after <italic>erf2</italic> and/or <italic>erf4</italic> overexpression. The DHHC→DHHA catalytic <italic>erf2</italic> mutant was co-overexpressed with <italic>erf4</italic> from <italic>nmt1</italic> promoters. Scale bars, 10 µm.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>If physiological control of Erf2–Erf4 abundance accounts for the palmitoylome changes observed upon meiotic induction, we predicted that increasing Erf2–Erf4 levels in haploid vegetative cells would yield a palmitoylation profile similar to meiotic cells. To test this, we focused on Ras1 and Rho3 as model substrates since <italic>isp3</italic> expression is restricted to meiotic cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). Ras1 palmitoylation was insensitive to increases in Erf2–Erf4 levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4B</xref>), consistent with our previous results in meiotic cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). In contrast, while overexpression of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> individually had no impact on Rho3 modification, we observed a striking increase in Rho3 palmitoylation when the effective Erf2–Erf4 palmitoyltransferase concentration was increased by co-overexpression of both subunits of the palmitoyltransferase complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Intermediate <italic>erf2–erf4</italic> expression resulted in a modest increase in Rho3 palmitoylation, indicating a dose-dependent function of palmitoyltransferase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Importantly, although <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> were expressed from heterologous promoters, their levels were in fact within physiological range, with the highest and lowest levels being comparable to those attained by meiotic and vegetative cells, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). These results demonstrate the control of palmitoyltransferase levels as a mechanism by which cells can finely shape palmitoylomes, with an impact on cellular processes such as meiosis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>High Erf2 Activity Induces Meiosis in Cells Through Ectopic Rho3 Palmitoylation</title>
<p>If palmitoyltransferase-level-mediated changes in the global protein palmitoylation are important for meiotic entry, then increasing Erf2–Erf4 levels in vegetative cells may be sufficient to promote this process. While no obvious phenotype was observed for <italic>pat1<sup>+</sup></italic> cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s007">Figure S7</xref>), overexpression of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> in proliferating haploid cells induced a striking meiotic phenotype under normal vegetative growth conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4C</xref>). In these cells, we observed a significant reduction in growth rate and proportion of dividing cells with time, accompanied by a reduction in cell length at division and a transient G1 delay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g005">Figures 5A–C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s005">S5A</xref>–C). In addition to being disrupted for vegetative growth, these <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> co-overexpressing cells subsequently underwent aberrant meiosis-like reductive cleavages, with a significant proportion of cells having &gt;2 nuclei and containing spore-like structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g005">Figures 5D,E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s005">S5D</xref>,E). These cells were indeed undergoing a meiotic program as deletion of <italic>mei4</italic>, which is required for meiotic but not mitotic divisions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Horie1">[46]</xref>, suppressed the appearance of these multinucleated cells, resulting in misshapen cells arrested with a single nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g005">Figure 5E</xref>). This meiotic phenotype was dependent on high palmitoyltransferase levels, since cells maintained vegetative growth when <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> are expressed at low or intermediate levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figures 4C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g005">5E</xref>). Critically, this meiotic phenotype was not observed in cells co-overexpressing a catalytically inactive Erf2 mutant and Erf4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4D</xref>) or in cells overproducing either Erf2 or Erf4 alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4C</xref>), highlighting the requirement for a functional and active palmitoyltransferase complex. Together with the delay in meiotic entry observed in <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s006">Figure S6A</xref>,B), these results demonstrate that coordinated regulation of Erf2–Erf4 activity through changes in the expression of each subunit contributes to meiotic entry in fission yeast.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001597-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Overproduction of Erf2 and Erf4 in proliferating cells disrupts vegetative growth and induces aberrant meiosis and sporulation in<bold><italic>pat1-114</italic></bold><bold> cells.</bold></title>
<p><italic>erf2 OE erf4 OE</italic> refers to strain 7 from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4B</xref> that co-overexpresses <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> at high levels. These cells were grown in the presence of nutrients at permissive temperature, and co-overexpression of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> was induced by switching cells to thiamine-free medium (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Indicated times or time intervals refer to time after induction of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> co-overexpression. (A) Fold change in OD<sub>595</sub> of cultures during indicated 12 h intervals. OD<sub>595</sub> was maintained &lt;0.6. (B) DNA content analysis. (C) Blankophor staining of cells (top panels). Dimensions of septated cells (cell length and width, <italic>n</italic> = 20) and percentage of septated cells (septation index, <italic>n</italic>≥200) were determined by measuring and counting blankophor-stained cells (bottom panels, left to right). Error bars, SD. (D) Percentage of cells with 1, 2, or &gt;2 nuclei (<italic>n</italic>≥200) was determined by DAPI staining. (E) DAPI (top) and DIC (bottom) images of cells under conditions where <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> overexpression were repressed (+Thiamine) as well as 96 h postinduction of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> co-overexpression. Scale bars, 10 µm. (F) Left panel, percentage of cells with spores (<italic>n</italic>≥200) at indicated times postinduction. Right panel, DIC images of cells 96 h postinduction before (top) and after (bottom) β-glucuronidase digestion, which specifically kills vegetative cells but not spores. Nonoverexpressing <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells continue vegetative growth under the same conditions (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s005">Figure S5</xref>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>As the meiotic phenotype can be induced by Erf2–Erf4 overproduction, we reasoned that the Erf2–Erf4 substrates involved in triggering meiosis would have to be present in vegetative cells and sensitive to Erf2–Erf4 levels for their palmitoylation state. One such substrate is Rho3, whose palmitoylation state depends on <italic>erf2</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4A,B</xref>). We found that Rho3, but not Ras1, is required for the meiotic phenotype triggered by Erf2–Erf4 overexpression in haploid cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). This is clearly dependent on Rho3 palmitoylation, as cells expressing palmitoylation-deficient Rho3 failed to undergo Erf2-induced meiosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g006">Figure 6A,B</xref>). Genetic interaction between <italic>erf2</italic>, <italic>erf4</italic>, and <italic>pat1</italic>, which encodes the general inhibitor of meiosis, further supports the meiotic role of Erf2–Erf4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s007">Figure S7</xref>). Expression of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> is upregulated in cells undergoing normal meiosis when encountering low nitrogen conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wilhelm1">[36]</xref>, which normally initiates mating and subsequent meiosis, supporting our conclusion that high <italic>erf2/erf4</italic> levels promote meiotic entry. Overall, our results suggest that palmitoyltransferase-level-mediated modulation of the palmitoylome is a determinant of meiotic entry, likely via Rho3 function that is regulated by its palmitoylation state, closely interacting with the Pat1 kinase.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001597-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Palmitoylation-dependent Rho3 function is required for the Erf2-induced meiotic phenotype.</title>
<p>(A) DAPI (top) and DIC (bottom) images of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> co-overexpressing cells with indicated genotypes at 96 h postinduction. Vectors expressing internally tagged wild-type and mutant (Cys4→Ala) Rho3-HA<sub>3</sub> proteins from the <italic>nmt41</italic> promoter were integrated into the chromosome of <italic>rho3Δ</italic> cells. Scale bars, 10 µm. (B) Alk-16-associated fluorescence of Rho3 and palmitoylation-deficient Rho3(C4A) (top panel). Western blots were probed for HA (bottom panel).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>By analyzing multiple cognate substrates of a single palmitoyltransferase in a physiological context, our work offers a new perspective of how global protein palmitoylation can be regulated. We showed that modulation of Erf2–Erf4 activity levels underlies the differential modification of its cognate substrates in distinct cellular states, demonstrating the quantitative control of single or multiple palmitoyltransferase activities as a fundamental mechanism by which cells shape their palmitoylomes, with potentially important consequences on cellular function.</p>
<p>Our results uncover an intriguing possibility that a single palmitoyltransferase can regulate different cellular processes through distinct substrates depending on its levels. Indeed, high Erf2–Erf4 palmitoyltransferase levels promote or reinforce the meiotic state in fission yeast cells, consistent with the delay in meiotic entry observed for <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells. The fact that <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> overexpression induces the meiotic phenotype in <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells where there is lower Pat1 kinase activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Davey1">[47]</xref> but not in <italic>pat1<sup>+</sup></italic> cells suggests that a sensitized background is needed to reveal the meiotic role of Erf2–Erf4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s007">Figure S7</xref>). This is not unexpected since in fission yeast, exit from vegetative growth and activation of the meiotic differentiation program are tightly regulated by a multilayered network of factors with many feedback loops, each contributing to stepwise inactivation of Pat1 and sequential derepression of meiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Harigaya1">[48]</xref>. It is unlikely that the induced meiotic phenotype is a result of nonspecific or general cellular stress since a variety of nutritional or environmental stresses alone failed to trigger meiosis in <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s008">Figure S8</xref>). Moreover, despite the large number of genes that are shown to be regulated during meiosis or implicated in meiotic function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mata1">[37]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mata2">[49]</xref>, only a few gene products have been shown to induce ectopic meiosis in vegetatively growing haploid wild type and/or <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells, and many have been demonstrated to be major meiotic determinants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s009">Figure S9</xref>). Given that increasing a single palmitoyltransferase activity is sufficient to stimulate meiosis in <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells and that <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> expression is upregulated in wild-type cells undergoing normal meiosis in low nitrogen conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wilhelm1">[36]</xref>, it is likely that Erf2–Erf4 modulates meiotic entry by contributing to Pat1 inactivation and derepression of meiosis. On the other hand, we cannot exclude the possibility that high Erf2–Erf4 levels reinforce the meiotic state once cells enter the meiotic program via positive feedback loops. It has been shown in budding yeast that commitment in meiosis does not occur until induction of middle genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Winter1">[50]</xref>.</p>
<p>Quantitative control of Rho3 palmitoylation by the Erf2–Erf4 palmitoyltransferase activity reveals a role for this family of small GTPases in meiosis. Rho3 in <italic>S. pombe</italic> regulates polarized cell growth and exocytosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Nakano1">[44]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wang1">[45]</xref> and is involved in Golgi/endosome trafficking <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Kita1">[51]</xref>. Delivery of cytoplasmic vesicles to discrete plasma-membrane domains is critical for establishing and maintaining cell polarity, neurite differentiation, and regulated exocytosis. Interestingly, Anastasia and co-workers showed in budding yeast that blocking membrane traffic causes a mitotic checkpoint, suggesting a link between mitotic entry and membrane growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Anastasia1">[52]</xref>. If palmitoylation-dependent Rho3 function affects membrane trafficking, signals that are coupled to membrane growth may explain how Rho3 regulates meiotic entry in fission yeast. These signals may increase the concentration of receptors and effectors at the plasma membrane due to changes in membrane trafficking or cytoskeletal organization.</p>
<p>Our work has established the fission yeast <italic>S. pombe</italic>, with its relatively simple palmitoyltransferase network, as a robust and complementary model for understanding the basic control mechanisms and the function of protein palmitoylation. Palmitoylome analysis of various palmitoyltransferase-deficient mutants in budding yeast has provided clear evidence for enzyme-substrate specificity, with individual palmitoyltransferases showing a preference for substrates with common features; for example, ERF2–ERF4 substrates tend to be heterolipidated (e.g., prenylated or myristoylated) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Roth2">[20]</xref>. With Isp3 having an <italic>N</italic>-myristoylation motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004">Figure 4D</xref>) and Ras1/Rho3 being prenylated, it appears that the orthologous Erf2–Erf4 palmitoyltransferase in fission yeast has the same substrate preference. Notably, the Erf2–Erf4:Ras1 palmitoyltransferase:substrate pairing in fission yeast is reminiscent of the ERF2–ERF4:RAS1/RAS2 and DHHC9-GCP16:H-/N-Ras pairs in budding yeast and human, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Bartels1">[16]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Lobo1">[17]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Swarthout1">[53]</xref>. This suggests an evolutionary selection for specific cognate palmitoyltransferase:substrate pairs, which would be unlikely if palmitoyltransferases have extensive overlapping substrate preferences and were able to freely substitute for one another. The fact that ERF2–ERF4 also palmitoylates RHO3 in budding yeast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Roth2">[20]</xref> raises the possibility that in mammals, DHHC9-GCP16 may modify the large number of Rho GTPases with cysteines close to the N- or C-terminus that serve as potential palmitoylation sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Heasman1">[54]</xref>. If DHHC9-GCP16 indeed does palmitoylate Rho proteins, it would be interesting to determine if, like Erf2–Erf4, the palmitoyltransferase complex in mammals can discriminate between and differentially modify Ras and Rho proteins, potentially coordinating small GTPase function.</p>
<p>It remains to be determined how levels of a palmitoyltransferase affect its substrate specificity. One possibility is a difference in catalytic efficiency (<italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub>), and this is supported by the discovery of specificity determinants on both the palmitoyltransferases and their substrates that dictate enzyme-substrate interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Huang1">[22]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Nadolski1">[55]</xref>. In addition, level-dependent changes in palmitoyltransferase localization might alter substrate availability. For example, DHHC2 translocates to postsynaptic membranes upon neuronal stimulation, where it increases palmitoylation and synaptic targeting of PSD-95 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Noritake1">[6]</xref>. In our study, however, changes in palmitoyltransferase localization are unlikely to account for the difference in Ras1 and Rho3 palmitoylation since both substrates are localized to the same compartments in vegetative cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Onken1">[38]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Nakano1">[44]</xref>. Alternatively, it may be a result of titration by competing cellular factors that target substrates differentially <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Martin1">[4]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Ahearn1">[14]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Ho1">[56]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Siegel1">[58]</xref>.</p>
<p>As global proteomic studies rapidly expand the known list of proteins that are reversibly modified with this lipid moiety <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Kang1">[13]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Roth2">[20]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Martin2">[35]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wilson1">[59]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Yount1">[60]</xref>, palmitoylation is poised to be a major cellular regulator. This is supported by expression profiling experiments in flies and humans in which transcript levels of specific palmitoyltransferases vary widely across tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Bannan1">[23]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Ohno1">[24]</xref>. Neuronal differentiation signals were found to induce palmitoyltransferase degradation through the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Li1">[61]</xref>. In addition, palmitoyltransferase overexpression is associated with a variety of human cancers and induces cellular transformation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Draper1">[29]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Ducker1">[30]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mansilla1">[62]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Yamamoto1">[63]</xref>. To our knowledge, our study provides the first evidence that differential protein palmitoylation as a result of regulated palmitoyltransferase levels can influence cellular behavior. Although the palmitoylation machinery is more elaborate in multicellular eukaryotes, the fact that Ras and Rho GTPases are essential for cellular differentiation and development in mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Heasman1">[54]</xref> as well as the conservation of palmitoyltransferase function and specific palmitoyltransferase:substrate pairs between yeast and humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Lobo1">[17]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Roth2">[20]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Swarthout1">[53]</xref> indicate that our conclusions provide fundamental insights for regulatory roles of palmitoylation in major developmental transitions in metazoa.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Strains and Growth Conditions</title>
<p>Standard media and methods were used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Hayles1">[64]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Moreno1">[65]</xref>. Strains used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s010">Table S1</xref>. All experiments were carried out in minimal medium (EMM) and minimal medium plus supplements (EMM4S) for prototrophic and auxotrophic strains, respectively, at 25°C unless otherwise noted. When applicable, strains were generated by tetrad dissection and validated by marker segregation or PCR. Deletion strains, strains expressing <italic>erf2-HA<sub>3</sub></italic>, <italic>isp3-HA<sub>3</sub></italic>, and those expressing <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> from <italic>nmt</italic> promoters were constructed by PCR integration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Bahler1">[66]</xref>. For Rho3, the HA<sub>3</sub>-tag sequence was inserted in-frame 42 bp upstream of its termination codon by PCR integration. Functional rescue in <italic>erf2Δ</italic> cells was performed using the pDUAL plasmid (RIKEN BRC, Japan) expressing <italic>YFP-FLAG-His<sub>6</sub>-erf2</italic> under the <italic>nmt41</italic> promoter, which was linearized and integrated into the <italic>leu1</italic> locus. The Quikchange XL II kit (Stratagene) was used for site-directed mutagenesis of the <italic>erf2 DHHC</italic> motif. Homozygous diploids were obtained by incubating midlog cultures of haploid cells with 20 µg/ml Carbendazim (Sigma) for 4.5 h at 25°C and screening colonies on YES+phloxin B plates.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Synchronized Pat1-Driven Meiosis</title>
<p>Pat1-driven meiosis in homozygous diploid <italic>h-/h- pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells was carried out as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mata1">[37]</xref>. Midlog cultures grown in EMM, which contains 0.5% NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, were filter-washed three times with nitrogen-free minimal medium (EMM-N) using the Microfil filtration system (Millipore), and resuspended in EMM-N for 14 h at 25°C. Meiosis was induced by shifting the cultures to the restrictive temperature of 34°C in the presence of 0.05% NH<sub>4</sub>Cl. t = 0 is defined as the time of the temperature shift.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title><italic>erf2</italic> and/or <italic>erf4</italic> Overexpression From Thiamine-Repressible <italic>nmt</italic> Promoters</title>
<p>Cultures were grown to midlog in EMM plus 10 mg/ml thiamine at 25°C. All cells proliferate normally under these conditions. <italic>erf2</italic> and/or <italic>erf4</italic> expression from <italic>nmt</italic> promoters was induced by filter-washing the cells three times with EMM as described above. The cells were resuspended in EMM and growth was maintained at 25°C. The cultures were diluted with EMM approximately every 12 h for the duration of each experiment to keep OD<sub>595</sub>&lt;0.6 and in the presence of nutrients. t = 0 h is defined as the time of thiamine removal.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Flow Cytometry</title>
<p>DNA content was analyzed by flow cytometry using ethanol-fixed and propidium iodide-stained cells (2 µg/mL propidium iodide in 50 mM sodium citrate) on a BD FACS Calibur and analyzed using FlowJo software.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Cell Size Measurements and DNA Staining</title>
<p>For cell size measurements, live cells were stained with Blankophore (MP Biomedicals). For DNA staining, ethanol-fixed cells were stained with DAPI. Images were acquired in Metamorph (MDS Analytical Technologies) using an Axioplan 2 microscope (Carl Zeiss) and a CoolSNAP HQ camera (Roper Scientific). Cell size measurements were obtained using the Pointpicker plug-in of Image J (National Institute of Health).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Quantitative RT-PCR</title>
<p>Total RNA was extracted using acidic phenol, DNase I-treated, and purified with the RNeasy kit (Qiagen). RNA concentration was quantified and its integrity was determined by agarose gel electrophoresis. cDNA was synthesized using random hexamers and the SuperScriptIII First Strand Synthesis SuperMix (Invitrogen). Relative quantification of cDNA was carried out in triplicate for each independent experiment using qPCR MasterMix Plus for SYBR Green (Applied Biosystems) on an ABI 7900 Real-Time PCR system. Primers used for quantitative PCR are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s012">Table S3</xref>. Standard curves were generated using at least six 2-fold serial dilutions of a control sample and values within the linear exponential phase were used to calculate relative concentrations after normalization to the endogenous actin controls.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4g">
<title>Metabolic Labeling and Preparation of Cell Lysates</title>
<p>Cells were labeled with 10 µM of alk-16 (20–50 mM DMSO stock) for 15 min, washed once with PBS prior to liquid nitrogen freezing and storage at −80°C. For inhibitor experiments, cells were preincubated for 30 min with either 200 µg/mL CHX or 200 µM 2BP, which were maintained in the cultures during alk-16 labeling. Competition experiments were carried out with various palmitate concentrations in the cultures during metabolic labeling. To prepare cell lysates, Brij lysis buffer (1% (v/v) Brij-97, 150 mM NaCl, 50 mM triethanolamine pH 7.4, 5× concentration of Roche EDTA-free protease inhibitor cocktail, 10 mM PMSF) and acid-washed glass beads (Sigma) were added to the frozen yeast cell pellets, which were lysed (3×20 s) using the Fastprep homogenizer (Thermo Scientific) at 4 min intervals to avoid overheating. Lysates were spun at 1,000 g for 5 min to remove cellular debris. Typical lysate protein concentrations of 5–10 mg/mL were obtained, as quantified using the BCA assay (Pierce).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4h">
<title>Immunoprecipitations and Bioorthogonal Labeling</title>
<p>For analyses of whole cell lysates, 50 µg of protein was diluted with Brij lysis buffer to a final volume of 44.5 µL, to which 5.5 µL of freshly mixed Cu<sup>I</sup>-catalyzed azide-alkyne cycloaddition (CuAAC) reagents were added. The CuAAC reagents consisted of 1 µL az-Rho (5 mM stock solution in DMSO), 1 µL tris(2-carboxyethyl)phosphine hydrochloride (TCEP) (50 mM freshly prepared stock solution in deionized water), 2.5 µL tris[(1-benzyl-1<italic>H</italic>-1,2,3-triazol-4-yl)methyl]amine (TBTA) (2 mM stock solution in 1∶4 DMSO∶t-butanol), and 1 µL CuSO<sub>4</sub>·5H<sub>2</sub>O (50 mM freshly prepared stock solution in deionized water). After 1 h at room temperature, proteins were methanol-chloroform precipitated to remove excess CuAAC reagents. The protein pellets were air-dried and resuspended in SDS buffer (4% (w/v) SDS, 150 mM NaCl, 50 mM triethanolamine pH 7.4) by sonication before SDS-PAGE. For Ras1 and HA immunoprecipitations, 1–3 mg of cell lysate was added to 4 µg anti-Ras antibody (Ras10, Millipore) with 25 µL Protein A agarose (Roche) or to 15 µL of anti-HA antibody–conjugated agarose (3F10, Roche), respectively. After 2 h incubation with rocking at 4°C, the beads were washed three times with ice-cold RIPA buffer (1% (v/v) Triton X-100, 1% (w/v) sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% (w/v) SDS, 50 mM triethanolamine pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl). The washed beads were resuspended in 20 µL of PBS and 2.25 µL freshly mixed CuAAC reagents described above. The beads were then washed three times with ice-cold RIPA buffer prior to boiling in SDS buffer for SDS-PAGE.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4i">
<title>In-Gel Fluorescence Scanning and Western Blots</title>
<p>Fluorescence gels were visualized on a Typhoon 9400 variable mode imager (GE Healthcare) at excitation 532 nm/emission 580 nm. For Western blotting, proteins separated by SDS-PAGE were transferred to nitrocellulose membranes and probed with the following antibodies: anti-Ras (Ras10, Millipore), anti-tubulin (Tat1, gift from Keith Gull), and anti-HA (3F10, Roche). To avoid visualizing the light chain band in anti-Ras1 immunoblots of Ras1 immunopurifications, an Fc-specific anti-mouse-HRP secondary antibody (A2544, Sigma) was used. Blots were developed using the enhanced chemiluminescence kit (GE Healthcare). Images were processed using Image J.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4j">
<title>Affinity Enrichment and Mass Spectrometry</title>
<p>CuAAC reagents (az-azo-biotin) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Yang1">[41]</xref> were added to 10 mg cell lysate at the same concentrations described above. Proteins were methanol-precipitated and resulting air-dried protein pellets were resuspended in 1 mL SDS buffer containing 10 mM EDTA by sonication. The mixture was diluted 1∶3 with Brij lysis buffer and incubated with 100 µL of washed streptavidin agarose resin (Pierce) for 1 h on a nutating mixer at room temperature. The beads were then washed once with 0.2% (w/v) SDS in PBS, three times with PBS, and twice with 250 mM ammonium bicarbonate (ABC). Beads were resuspended in 500 µL 8 M urea, and reactive cysteines were alkylated by addition of 25 µL 200 mM TCEP and 25 µL 400 mM iodoacetamide for 30 min. The beads were washed twice with 50 mM ABC. Two sequential elutions of proteins from the resin were performed by incubating the beads with 250 µL of 25 mM sodium dithionite in 50 mM ABC with 0.1% (w/v) SDS for 30 min each. Proteins were concentrated using YM-10 Centricons (Millipore), dried in a speed vac, and separated by SDS-PAGE. Upon staining with Coomassie blue, each lane was cut into 10 slices for trypsin digestion and peptide extraction. Extracted peptides were dried and resuspended in 0.1% (v/v) trifluoroacetic acid for mass spectrometry identification. Acquired MS/MS spectra were analyzed using the Sequest search engine to identify proteins from the primary sequence database obtained from the <italic>S. pombe</italic> GeneDB. Exported Sequest results were analyzed using Scaffold (Proteome Software).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold><italic>S. pombe</italic></bold><bold> meiosis is a specialized and tightly regulated process.</bold> (A) Fission yeast cells normally proliferate as haploids through the mitotic cell cycle (right cycle, shaded), replicating their genome (S phase) and dividing the genetic material equally between two daughter cells during mitosis (M phase). When nutrients such as nitrogen become limiting, cells may enter an alternate meiotic differentiation pathway that is distinct from the mitotic cycle (left cycle). Haploid cells transiently arrest in G1 and conjugate with cells of opposite mating types to form a diploid zygote. These diploids replicate their genome (meiotic S phase) and then undergo two successive nuclear divisions (Meiosis I and II) to yield four haploid nuclei that mature into spores, completing meiosis. Each of these haploid spores germinates into normally dividing cells when favorable conditions return. (B) In <italic>S. pombe</italic>, the Mei2 master regulator governs the switch from the mitotic to meiotic cycle. Mei2 integrates extracellular cues (stress, nutrients, and pheromones) primarily through Ste11, and drives meiosis. Mei2 function is tightly regulated by the Pat1 kinase, which inactivates both Mei2 and Ste11, thereby preventing meiotic entry during the mitotic cell cycle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Watanabe1">[67]</xref>. Together, Pat1 and Mei2 constitute the core mitosis-meiosis switch in fission yeast. Working in concert, these key cellular factors integrate environmental cues and control entry into meiosis. The temperature-sensitive <italic>pat1-114</italic> allele of Pat1 allows the induction of synchronous meiosis regardless of normal biological cues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Beach1">[32]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Nurse1">[33]</xref>. Haploid and diploid cells harboring this mutation can be induced to undergo meiosis in a timely and predictable manner that facilitates characterization of the process by shifting the cultures from permissive to restrictive temperatures. At permissive temperature, Pat1 is active in homozygous diploids. As such, Mei2 is inactivated and cells do not enter meiosis. Although <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells are more sensitive to pheromones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Davey1">[47]</xref>, they proliferate normally and require the normal biological cues to enter meiosis at permissive temperature. On the other hand, at restrictive temperature, Pat1 is inactivated and derepression of Mei2 function induces spontaneous meiosis in <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Specific and sensitive bioorthogonal detection of protein palmitoylation and palmitoyltransferase activity </bold><bold><italic>in vivo</italic></bold><bold> in fission yeast.</bold> (A) Schematic representation of the bioorthogonal detection protocol. Alk-16, alkyne-functionalized palmitate reporter; Az-rho, azide-functionalized rhodamine fluorophore; CuAAC, copper-catalyzed azide-alkyne cycloaddition. (B) In-gel fluorescent detection of alk-16-labeled proteins in lysates and immunopurified Ras1 (Ras1 IP). Protein load was determined by Coomassie blue staining of the gel. (C, D) Fluorescent detection of immunopurified Ras1, a known palmitoylated protein, from alk-16-labeled cells (top panels). Western blots were probed for Ras1 (bottom panels). Palmitate competed with alk-16 labeling in a dose-dependent manner (C). Ras1-associated fluorescence was greatly diminished by pre-incubating cells with a general palmitoylation inhibitor 2-bromopalmitate (2BP) or by selective post-CuAAC cleavage of palmitoylation-specific thioester linkages with hydroxylamine (NH<sub>2</sub>OH). Pretreatment of cells with protein synthesis inhibitor cycloheximide (CHX) had little effect on posttranslational Ras1 labeling by alk-16 (D).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Erf2 and Erf4 expression is selectively regulated during sexual differentiation in fission yeast.</bold> (A) Partial amino acid sequence alignments and consensus sequence of <italic>S. pombe</italic> palmitoyltransferases and phenotypes of null mutants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Wood1">[68]</xref>. (B) qPCR analysis of palmitoyltransferase transcripts in vegetative and meiotic <italic>pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells. <italic>y</italic>-axis, fold change, meiotic/vegetative levels. All transcript levels were normalized to <italic>act1</italic> mRNA. Error bars, SD.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Enrichment and identification of Erf2 substrates that are selectively palmitoylated during meiosis.</bold> (A) Schematic representation of the selective enrichment protocol of alk-16-modified proteins from cell lysates. Az-azo-biotin, Azide-functionalized biotin probe with an azobenzene cleavable linker; CuAAC, copper-catalyzed azide-alkyne cycloaddition. (B) Selective enrichment of Ras1 in Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> elutions from lysates of cells metabolically labeled with alk-16 (bottom panel) over input lysates (top panel). Western blots were probed for Ras1. (C) Coomassie blue stain of proteins before (input, top panel) and after affinity enrichment/elution (bottom panel). Slices of the bottom gel were processed for gel-based mass spectrometry. (D) Amino acid sequences of Rho3 and Isp3, both of which were validated to be Erf2 substrates that are selectively palmitoylated in meiotic cells in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g003">Figure 3</xref>. Yellow, identified peptides; Green, modified amino acids in identified peptides (e.g., oxidation, carbamidomethylation).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p><bold>Ectopic meiosis in haploid </bold><bold><italic>pat1-114</italic></bold><bold> cells co-overexpressing </bold><bold><italic>erf2</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>erf4</italic></bold><bold>. </bold><bold><italic>erf2 OE erf4 OE:</italic></bold><bold> strain 7 from</bold> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001597-g004"><bold>Figure 4C</bold></xref> <bold>that co-overexpresses </bold><bold><italic>erf2</italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>erf4</italic></bold><bold> at high levels.</bold> These cells were grown at permissive temperature, and co-overexpression of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> was induced by switching cells to thiamine-free medium (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Nonoverexpressing <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells (<italic>erf2 erf4</italic>) continue vegetative growth under these conditions. Indicated times or time intervals refer to time after the switch to thiamine-free medium. (A) Fold change in OD<sub>595</sub> of cultures during indicated 12 h intervals. OD<sub>595</sub> was maintained &lt;0.6. (B) DNA content analysis. (C) Blankophor staining of cells (left panels). Scale bars, 10 µm. Dimensions of septated cells (cell length and width, <italic>n</italic> = 20, middle panels) and percentage of septated cells (septation index, <italic>n</italic>≥200, right panel) were determined by measuring and counting blankophor-stained cells. Error bars, SD. (D) Percentage of cells with 1, 2, or &gt;2 nuclei (<italic>n</italic>≥200) was determined by DAPI staining of the indicated strains. (E) Percentage of cells with spores at indicated times postinduction (<italic>n</italic>≥200).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s006" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S6</label><caption>
<p><bold><italic>erf2Δ</italic></bold><bold> cells are delayed in meiotic entry.</bold> (A) Schematic representation of fission yeast sexual differentiation. Haploid cells conjugate to form a diploid zygote, which undergoes meiosis to yield four haploid nuclei that matures into spores. Pat1 kinase is a repressor of meiosis. For more details on <italic>S. pombe</italic> meiosis, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001597.s001">Figure S1</xref>. (B) DNA content analysis of indicated strains after meiotic induction by thermal inactivation of Pat1. (C) Percentage of cells with 1, 2, or &gt;2 nuclei were determined by counting ≥200 DAPI-stained cells of the indicated strains at hourly intervals after meiotic induction (left panel). Representative DIC (middle panel) and DAPI (right panel) images of cells at indicated times. Scale bars, 10 µm. Synchronous meiosis in the indicated diploid <italic>pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells was induced by shifting nitrogen-starved cultures to a restrictive temperature (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Indicated times refer to the elapsed time after temperature shift.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s007" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S7</label><caption>
<p><bold>Erf2-Erf4 function in meiotic control is revealed in </bold><bold><italic>pat1-114</italic></bold><bold> cells.</bold> DAPI and DIC staining of haploid cells at 96 h after induction of <italic>erf2</italic> and <italic>erf4</italic> co-overexpression. Cells were grown in the presence of nutrients at permissive temperature. Scale bars, 10 µm. Erf2–Erf4-induced meiosis is observed in <italic>pat1-114</italic> (top panels) but not <italic>pat1<sup>+</sup></italic> cells (bottom panels). Our data suggest that Erf2–Erf4 function in meiotic control is unmasked in <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells where there is lower Pat1 kinase activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Davey1">[47]</xref>. It is likely that high Erf2–Erf4 activity induces ectopic meiosis by either activating the Ste11-Mei2 pathway or inactivating Pat1.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s008" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S8</label><caption>
<p><bold><italic>pat1-114</italic></bold><bold> cells do not enter meiosis when exposed to nutritional and other stresses.</bold> DAPI and DIC images of <italic>pat1-114</italic> cells upon exposure to indicated stresses. Scale bars, 10 µm. (A) Nutritional stress. Cells were grown at high densities for 7 d at 25°C in minimal medium containing the indicated sole nitrogen source (NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, glutamate, proline) or in nitrogen-free minimal medium (N-free). Proline is considered to be a poor nitrogen source. (B) Osmotic stress. Cells were grown in minimal medium containing 1 M sorbitol, 0.4 M NaCl, or 1 M KCl for 5 d at 25°C. No meiotic cells were observed in these experiments.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s009" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S9</label><caption>
<p><bold>Gene products that induce ectopic meiosis in haploid </bold><bold><italic>S. pombe</italic></bold><bold> cells.</bold> (A) Of the thousands of genes that significantly regulated during meiosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mata1">[37]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Mata2">[49]</xref>, the listed gene products are demonstrated to induce meiosis in haploid cells, highlighting their regulatory roles in the important cellular transition. The exact molecular mechanisms by which some of these gene products modulate meiotic entry remain to be elucidated. Unless otherwise stated, cells are <italic>pat1<sup>+</sup></italic>. (B) Signaling network that regulates fission yeast meiotic entry. In <italic>S. pombe</italic>, the Mei2 master regulator governs the switch from the mitotic to meiotic cycle. Mei2 integrates extracellular cues (stress, nutrients, and pheromones) primarily through Ste11, and drives meiosis. Mei2 function is tightly regulated by the Pat1 kinase, which inactivates both Mei2 and Ste11, thereby preventing meiotic entry during the mitotic cell cycle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Watanabe1">[67]</xref>. Together, Pat1 and Mei2 constitute the core mitosis-meiosis switch in fission yeast. Under physiological conditions, complete inactivation of Pat1 and meiotic induction strictly requires the stoichiometric inhibitor Mei3, which is only expressed in heterozygous diploids formed after successful conjugation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-Li2">[69]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001597-VanHeeckeren1">[71]</xref>. Working in concert, these key cellular factors integrate environmental cues and control cellular entry into meiosis. For simplification, many factors and interactions are omitted in this representation. Meiotic activators and repressors are in green and red, respectively. Dashed lines represent proposed mechanism of Erf2–Erf4 in this study. Erf2 and Erf4 expression is significantly upregulated in meiotic cells compared to vegetative cells, and elevated Erf2–Erf4 levels promote the meiotic state by activating Mei2 and/or inactivating Pat1. Dotted lines represent either direct or indirect interactions.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s010" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold><italic>S. pombe</italic></bold><bold> strains used in this study.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s011" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s011" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Candidate Erf2 substrates that are selectively palmitoylated during meiosis.</bold> Proteins were sorted in by their net spectral counts over the DMSO samples in meiotic homozygous diploid <italic>erf2<sup>+</sup>/erf2<sup>+</sup> pat1-114/pat1-114</italic> cells. Based on molecular weight and enrichment over the DMSO control, Isp3 and Rho3 were chosen and biochemically validated in this study.</p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pbio.1001597.s012" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001597.s012" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Oligonucleotide primers used in quantitative RT-PCR.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Fukata1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Protein palmitoylation in neuronal development and synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Resh1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Resh</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Trafficking and signaling by fatty-acylated and prenylated proteins</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>584</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Linder1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deschenes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Palmitoylation: policing protein stability and traffic</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Martin1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adibekian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cravatt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Global profiling of dynamic protein palmitoylation</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Salaun1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salaun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The intracellular dynamic of protein palmitoylation</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Noritake1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noritake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosomi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mobile DHHC palmitoylating enzyme mediates activity-sensitive synaptic targeting of PSD-95</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>186</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-ElHusseiniAel1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Husseini Ael</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dakoji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Synaptic strength regulated by palmitate cycling on PSD-95</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>863</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Zhang1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Tandem fluorescence imaging of dynamic S-acylation and protein turnover</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>8627</fpage>–<lpage>8632</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Wedegaertner1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedegaertner</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Activation and depalmitoylation of Gs alpha</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>–<lpage>1070</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Degtyarev1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Degtyarev</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Increased palmitoylation of the Gs protein alpha subunit after activation by the beta-adrenergic receptor or cholera toxin</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>23769</fpage>–<lpage>23772</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mouillac1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouillac</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Agonist-modulated palmitoylation of beta 2-adrenergic receptor in Sf9 cells</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>21733</fpage>–<lpage>21737</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mundy1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Mitosis and inhibition of intracellular transport stimulate palmitoylation of a 62-kD protein</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Kang1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arstikaitis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Neural palmitoyl-proteomics reveals dynamic synaptic palmitoylation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>456</volume>: <fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>909</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Ahearn1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahearn</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Court</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>FKBP12 binds to acylated h-ras and promotes depalmitoylation</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Roth1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The yeast DHHC cysteine-rich domain protein Akr1p is a palmitoyl transferase</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Bartels1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deschenes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Erf2, a novel gene product that affects the localization and palmitoylation of Ras2 in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>6775</fpage>–<lpage>6787</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Lobo1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greentree</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deschenes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Identification of a Ras palmitoyltransferase in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>41268</fpage>–<lpage>41273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mitchell1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamel</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishizuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Erf4 subunit of the yeast Ras palmitoyl acyl transferase is required for stability of the acyl-Erf2 intermediate and palmitoyl transfer to a Ras2 substrate</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>287</volume> <issue>(41)</issue> <fpage>34337</fpage>–<lpage>34348</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Zhao1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ault</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deschenes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Erf4p and Erf2p form an endoplasmic reticulum-associated complex involved in the plasma membrane localization of yeast Ras proteins</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>49352</fpage>–<lpage>49359</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Roth2"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuchar</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Global analysis of protein palmitoylation in yeast</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>1003</fpage>–<lpage>1013</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Fukata2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adesnik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoll</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bredt</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of PSD-95 palmitoylating enzymes</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>996</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Huang1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singaraja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orban</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cijsouw</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Neuronal palmitoyl acyl transferases exhibit distinct substrate specificity</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2605</fpage>–<lpage>2615</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Bannan1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bannan</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Etten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsoi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Drosophila protein palmitoylome: characterizing palmitoyl-thioesterases and DHHC palmitoyl-transferases</article-title>. <source>Fly (Austin)</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Ohno1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Intracellular localization and tissue-specific distribution of human and yeast DHHC cysteine-rich domain-containing proteins</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1761</volume>: <fpage>474</fpage>–<lpage>483</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Saleem1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mice with alopecia, osteoporosis, and systemic amyloidosis due to mutation in Zdhhc13, a gene coding for palmitoyl acyltransferase</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1000985</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000985" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000985</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mill1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Palmitoylation regulates epidermal homeostasis and hair follicle differentiation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000748</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000748" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000748</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Singaraja1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singaraja</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hadano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Givan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wellington</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>HIP14, a novel ankyrin domain-containing protein, links huntingtin to intracellular trafficking and endocytosis</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>2815</fpage>–<lpage>2828</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mukai1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhilla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Palmitoylation-dependent neurodevelopmental deficits in a mouse model of 22q11 microdeletion</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1302</fpage>–<lpage>1310</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Draper1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>DHHC20: a human palmitoyl acyltransferase that causes cellular transformation</article-title>. <source>Mol Membr Biol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Ducker1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducker</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stettler</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>French</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Upson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Huntingtin interacting protein 14 is an oncogenic human protein: palmitoyl acyltransferase</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>9230</fpage>–<lpage>9237</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Iino1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Negative control for the initiation of meiosis in Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>2447</fpage>–<lpage>2451</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Beach1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>ran1+ controls the transition from mitotic division to meiosis in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Nurse1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Mutants of the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe which alter the shift between cell proliferation and sporulation</article-title>. <source>Mol &amp; Gen Genet</source> <volume>198</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>502</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Charron1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yount</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Robust fluorescent detection of protein fatty-acylation with chemical reporters</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>4967</fpage>–<lpage>4975</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Martin2"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cravatt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Large-scale profiling of protein palmitoylation in mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Wilhelm1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marguerat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dynamic repertoire of a eukaryotic transcriptome surveyed at single-nucleotide resolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>453</volume>: <fpage>1239</fpage>–<lpage>1243</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mata1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The transcriptional program of meiosis and sporulation in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Onken1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onken</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiener</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Philips</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Compartmentalized signaling of Ras in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>9045</fpage>–<lpage>9050</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mitchell2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budde</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deschenes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mutational analysis of Saccharomyces cerevisiae Erf2 reveals a two-step reaction mechanism for protein palmitoylation by DHHC enzymes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>38104</fpage>–<lpage>38114</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Dudler1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gelb</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Palmitoylation of Ha-Ras facilitates membrane binding, activation of downstream effectors, and meiotic maturation in Xenopus oocytes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>11541</fpage>–<lpage>11547</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Yang1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grammel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Comparative analysis of cleavable azobenzene-based affinity tags for bioorthogonal chemical proteomics</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1212</fpage>–<lpage>1222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Shimoda1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Existence of a mojor spore wall protein (23K) in the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe: a possible sporulation-specific protein</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Sato1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Widyastuti</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of genes induced during sexual differentiation in Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Nakano1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The small GTPase Rho3 and the diaphanous/formin For3 function in polarized cell growth in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>4629</fpage>–<lpage>4639</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Wang1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Rho3p regulates cell separation by modulating exocyst function in Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>1331</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Horie1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiwaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The Schizosaccharomyces pombe mei4+ gene encodes a meiosis-specific transcription factor containing a forkhead DNA-binding domain</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2118</fpage>–<lpage>2129</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Davey1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Mutations in cyr1 and pat1 reveal pheromone-induced G1 arrest in the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Harigaya1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harigaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms underlying the mitosis-meiosis decision</article-title>. <source>Chromosome Res</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mata2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilbrey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional regulatory network for sexual differentiation in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>R217</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Winter1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Sum1/Ndt80 transcriptional switch and commitment to meiosis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Kita1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Role of the small GTPase Rho3 in Golgi/Endosome trafficking through functional interaction with adaptin in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e16842</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0016842" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0016842</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Anastasia1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anastasia</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meloy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonough</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A link between mitotic entry and membrane growth suggests a novel model for cell size control</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>197</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Swarthout1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swarthout</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Croke</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greentree</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>DHHC9 and GCP16 constitute a human protein fatty acyltransferase with specificity for H- and N-Ras</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>31141</fpage>–<lpage>31148</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Heasman1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heasman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mammalian Rho GTPases: new insights into their functions from in vivo studies</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>690</fpage>–<lpage>701</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Nadolski1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadolski</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Molecular recognition of the palmitoylation substrate Vac8 by its palmitoyltransferase Pfa3</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>17720</fpage>–<lpage>17730</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Ho1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selvakumar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hester</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>S-nitrosylation and S-palmitoylation reciprocally regulate synaptic targeting of PSD-95</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Dekker1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocks</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vartak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menninger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Small-molecule inhibition of APT1 affects Ras localization and signaling</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Siegel1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obernosterer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oehmen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bicker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A functional screen implicates microRNA-138-dependent regulation of the depalmitoylation enzyme APT1 in dendritic spine morphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>–<lpage>716</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Wilson1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Proteomic analysis of fatty-acylated proteins in mammalian cells with chemical reporters reveals S-acylation of histone H3 variants</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>M110 001198</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Yount1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yount</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moltedo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Palmitoylome profiling reveals S-palmitoylation-dependent antiviral activity of IFITM3</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>610</fpage>–<lpage>614</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Li1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cravatt</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>DHHC5 palmitoylates flotillin-2 and is rapidly degraded on induction of neuronal differentiation in cultured cells</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>287</volume> <issue>(1)</issue> <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Mansilla1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birkenkamp-Demtroder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kruhoffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of DHHC9 in microsatellite stable and instable human colorectal cancer subgroups</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>1896</fpage>–<lpage>1903</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Yamamoto1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chochi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawauchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Gain of 5p15.33 is associated with progression of bladder cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncology</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Hayles1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Genetics of the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genet</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Moreno1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Molecular genetic analysis of fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source> <volume>194</volume>: <fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>823</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Bahler1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longtine</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>A</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Heterologous modules for efficient and versatile PCR-based gene targeting in Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Yeast</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>943</fpage>–<lpage>951</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Watanabe1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki-Yabana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chikashige</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Phosphorylation of RNA-binding protein controls cell cycle switch from mitotic to meiotic in fission yeast</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>386</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Wood1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gwilliam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajandream</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The genome sequence of Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>415</volume>: <fpage>871</fpage>–<lpage>880</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-Li2"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Molecular mimicry in development: identification of ste11+ as a substrate and mei3+ as a pseudosubstrate inhibitor of ran1+ kinase</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>880</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-McLeod1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>A specific inhibitor of the ran1+ protein kinase regulates entry into meiosis in Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>332</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pbio.1001597-VanHeeckeren1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Heeckeren</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dorris</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The mating-type proteins of fission yeast induce meiosis by directly activating mei3 transcription</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>7317</fpage>–<lpage>7326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item>
<term>DHHC</term>
<def>
<p>Asp-His-His-Cys motif</p>
</def>
</def-item></def-list></glossary></back>
</article>