<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLCB-RA-1929R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subject>Computational Biology/Signaling Networks</subject><subject>Computational Biology/Systems Biology</subject><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Modeling Chemotaxis Reveals the Role of Reversed Phosphotransfer and a Bi-Functional Kinase-Phosphatase</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Modeling Bacterial Chemotaxis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tindall</surname><given-names>Marcus J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>Steven L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>Philip K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>Judith P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Centre for Mathematical Biology, Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Institute of Cardiovascular and Metabolic Research, School of Biological Sciences, University of Reading, Reading, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Mathematics, University of Reading, Reading, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Oxford Centre for Integrative Systems Biology, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>School of Biosciences, University of Exeter, Exeter, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>Christopher V.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">m.tindall@reading.ac.uk</email> (MJT); <email xlink:type="simple">s.porter@exeter.ac.uk</email> (SLP)</corresp>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MJT SLP PKM JPA. Performed the experiments: SLP. Analyzed the data: MJT SLP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MJT SLP. Wrote the paper: MJT SLP PKM JPA.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e1000896</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2010</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></date>
</history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tindall et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
<p>Understanding how multiple signals are integrated in living cells to produce a balanced response is a major challenge in biology. Two-component signal transduction pathways, such as bacterial chemotaxis, comprise histidine protein kinases (HPKs) and response regulators (RRs). These are used to sense and respond to changes in the environment. <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> has a complex chemosensory network with two signaling clusters, each containing a HPK, CheA. Here we demonstrate, using a mathematical model, how the outputs of the two signaling clusters may be integrated. We use our mathematical model supported by experimental data to predict that: (1) the main RR controlling flagellar rotation, CheY<sub>6</sub>, aided by its specific phosphatase, the bifunctional kinase CheA<sub>3</sub>, acts as a phosphate sink for the other RRs; and (2) a phosphorelay pathway involving CheB<sub>2</sub> connects the cytoplasmic cluster kinase CheA<sub>3</sub> with the polar localised kinase CheA<sub>2</sub>, and allows CheA<sub>3</sub>-P to phosphorylate non-cognate chemotaxis RRs. These two mechanisms enable the bifunctional kinase/phosphatase activity of CheA<sub>3</sub> to integrate and tune the sensory output of each signaling cluster to produce a balanced response. The signal integration mechanisms identified here may be widely used by other bacteria, since like <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic>, over 50% of chemotactic bacteria have multiple <italic>cheA</italic> homologues and need to integrate signals from different sources.</p>
</abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Chemotactic bacteria sense nutrient gradients and swim towards better environments for growth. A cluster of receptors in the cell membrane detects nutrient levels and signals via a cytoplasmic signaling pathway to the flagellum. The complexity of this signaling pathway varies across different bacterial species. The relatively simple pathway used by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> is well understood; however, many bacteria, for example <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>, have more sophisticated pathways that, as well as being able to detect nutrients, are also able to assess the metabolic state of the cell. The receptors that detect metabolic state are located within an additional cluster that is physically distinct from the one that senses nutrients. In this work, we use a combination of experimentation and mathematical modeling to gain insight into the complex decision-making mechanisms that enable bacteria to weigh-up different stimuli and decide upon an appropriate response. We find novel communication mechanisms between the two signaling clusters that allow the outputs of the signaling pathways to be balanced and tuned according to the prevailing environmental conditions. The signaling principles identified here are likely to be used in other complex sensory networks.</p>
</abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>MJT and SLP were supported by research grant BB/C513350/1 from the Biological and Biotechnology Sciences Research Council (BBSRC). SLP was also supported by the Oxford Centre for Integrative Systems Biology (OCISB). PKM was partially supported by a Royal Society-Wolfson Research Merit award. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Two-component signaling pathways are the major mechanism by which bacterial cells sense and respond to changes in their environment. They regulate processes as diverse as virulence, gene expression, development and motility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Stock1">[1]</xref>. Bacteria can have over 100 different two-component pathways per cell, one form of which controls swimming behavior. This chemosensory pathway has been extensively studied as an example of a two-component signaling pathway as it provides a model of signaling, signal termination and receptor adaptation. Mathematical modeling has proved particularly useful in helping to understand the complexity of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> chemotaxis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Bray1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Alon1">[10]</xref>.</p>
<p>Most chemotactic bacteria sense changes in their extracellular environment using transmembrane chemoreceptors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Hazelbauer1">[11]</xref>. These chemoreceptors signal via an intracellular signaling cascade to the flagellar motor. In the case of <italic>E. coli</italic>, the signaling cascade is well understood <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Szurmant1">[13]</xref>. The chemoreceptors form a quaternary complex at the cell poles with the scaffold protein CheW and the histidine protein kinase, CheA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Maddock1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Briegel1">[16]</xref>. The chemoreceptors detect changes in the periplasmic chemoeffector concentration and control the rate at which CheA autophosphorylates on a conserved histidine residue. In response to decreased attractant concentration, the chemoreceptors signal to increase the rate of CheA autophosphorylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Borkovich1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Boldog1">[19]</xref>. Following autophosphorylation, the phosphoryl group is transferred from the histidine residue of CheA to an aspartate residue in one of the two response regulators (RRs), CheY or CheB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Hess1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Bourret1">[22]</xref>. CheY-P is released from the chemotaxis cluster and diffuses through the cell to the flagellar motor. CheY-P binds the FliM component of the flagellar motors, causing the direction of flagellar rotation to switch from counter-clockwise to clockwise resulting in tumbling of the bacterium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Welch1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Dyer1">[24]</xref>. CheA-P also phosphorylates the methylesterase CheB, which facilitates adaptation of the chemoreceptor cluster <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Lupas1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Sourjik1">[26]</xref>. CheY-P and CheB-P both naturally autodephosphorylate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Thomas1">[27]</xref>, although the rate of CheY-P dephosphorylation is enhanced by CheZ to allow signal termination within the time required for effective gradient sensing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Hess2">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Silversmith1">[29]</xref>.</p>
<p>In contrast to <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> has a more complex signaling pathway with multiple copies of the signaling proteins encoded by three major chemosensory operons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter1">[30]</xref>. Many other bacterial species appear to have multiple chemosensory operons as analysis of sequenced genomes suggests that ∼50% of species with any <italic>che</italic> genes have at least two <italic>cheA</italic>s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter1">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wuichet1">[32]</xref>. This raises the question of how behavior is controlled by two or more homologous pathways and how sensory data from each of the pathways are integrated to produce a balanced response. Under laboratory conditions, <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> swims using a single sub-polar unidirectional flagellum (Fla1), which is controlled by the protein products of <italic>che</italic>Op<sub>2</sub> and <italic>che</italic>Op<sub>3</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Armitage1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-delCampo1">[38]</xref>. The intracellular signaling cascade controlling the Fla1 flagellum comprises three CheA kinase proteins (denoted CheA<sub>2</sub>, CheA<sub>3</sub>, CheA<sub>4</sub>), three CheY proteins (CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheY<sub>6</sub>) and two CheBs (CheB<sub>1</sub>, CheB<sub>2</sub>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter2">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Martin1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter3">[39]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Shah2">[42]</xref>. CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheA<sub>4</sub> are unusual CheAs in that they lack some of the domains found in <italic>E. coli</italic> CheA and neither protein is capable of autophosphorylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref>. However, together CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheA<sub>4</sub> have all of the activities of a functional CheA with CheA<sub>4</sub> forming a homodimer that binds ATP and phosphorylates the Hpt domain of CheA<sub>3</sub>.</p>
<p>The signal transduction proteins are organized and localised into two distinct sensory clusters and the signaling output of both clusters is required for chemotaxis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams2">[44]</xref>. CheA<sub>2</sub> is located in a chemotaxis cluster at the cell poles, which comprises transmembrane chemoreceptors and the signal transduction proteins encoded by <italic>che</italic>Op<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams2">[44]</xref>. This cluster detects changes in the periplasmic concentration of chemoeffectors. Previous data show that CheA<sub>2</sub>-P rapidly phosphorylates CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub>, CheY<sub>6</sub>, CheB<sub>1</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g001">Figure 1</xref>), although the kinetics of phosphotransfer differ in each case <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref>. CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheA<sub>4</sub> localize to a second chemotaxis cluster found in the cytoplasm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams2">[44]</xref>. This cluster contains the signal transduction proteins encoded by <italic>che</italic>Op<sub>3</sub> along with the soluble chemoreceptors and is believed to sense the metabolic state of the cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams2">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams3">[46]</xref>. CheA<sub>3</sub>-P rapidly phosphorylates only the RRs, CheY<sub>6</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Bell1">[47]</xref>. In addition, CheA<sub>3</sub> has an aspartyl-phosphate phosphatase activity that is specific for CheY<sub>6</sub>-P; this activity is required for the rapid signal termination that is necessary for chemotactic responses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>. CheA<sub>3</sub> in conjunction with CheA<sub>4</sub> can therefore be considered to be a bifunctional kinase/phosphatase.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000896-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Diagram showing the RRs phosphorylated by the polar (blue) and cytoplasmic (red) chemotaxis clusters.</title>
<p>The polar chemotaxis cluster contains CheA<sub>2</sub> and responds to the external environment. CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylates and can then serve as a phosphodonor for all of the RRs. The cytoplasmic chemotaxis cluster contains CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheA<sub>4</sub>, and is thought to respond to the metabolic state of the cell. CheA<sub>3</sub> is phosphorylated by CheA<sub>4</sub>. Unlike CheA<sub>2</sub>-P, CheA<sub>3</sub>-P is not able to phosphorylate all of the RRs – it can only phosphorylate CheY<sub>6</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>. All of the RR-Ps spontaneously autodephosphorylate; however, the dephosphorylation of CheY<sub>6</sub>-P is accelerated by the phosphatase activity of CheA<sub>3</sub>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g001" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p><italic>In vitro</italic> studies have shown that all of the <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> CheYs can bind the flagellar switch protein, FliM, and that this binding is strongest when the CheYs are phosphorylated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Ferre1">[49]</xref>, but less is known about the effect of CheY/CheY-P binding to FliM on flagellar rotation. CheY<sub>6</sub> is essential for chemotaxis and CheY<sub>6</sub>-P alone is capable of causing the chemotactic stop that is necessary for changing swimming direction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter3">[39]</xref>. However, CheY<sub>6</sub> alone cannot support chemotaxis; either CheY<sub>3</sub> or CheY<sub>4</sub> are also required. Furthermore, phosphorylation site mutants of CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheY<sub>6</sub> do not support chemotaxis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter3">[39]</xref>, suggesting that phosphorylation of all of these CheYs is necessary for chemotaxis.</p>
<p>Thus there are two complete chemosensory pathways in <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic>, localized to different regions of the cell and with different patterns and kinetics of phosphotransfer to the RRs. However, the outputs of these two signaling pathways must be integrated to control the behavior of a single flagellar motor. <italic>In vitro</italic> biochemistry identified which RRs are phosphorylated by each CheA and the kinetics of the interactions, however, assessing the relative contribution made to RR-P levels by each of these CheAs <italic>in vivo</italic> is more complex, since all of the RR-Ps will be competing with one another for phosphorylation by the CheAs. We used mathematical modeling to predict the possible signaling pathways within this complex system and tested these predictions experimentally.</p>
<p>The aim of this study was therefore to combine our knowledge of the kinetic preferences of the signaling reactions gained from <italic>in vitro</italic> biochemistry with the <italic>in vivo</italic> data on protein copy number within a mathematical model that can predict the changes in RR-P levels resulting from changes in CheA activity at either cluster. This model was then used to analyze the contribution made by each cluster in controlling RR-P levels and the dynamics of the signaling reactions. Using the model, we identified unexpected key roles for reversed phosphotransfer between RR-P and CheA in the network, which would enable communication between the two sensory clusters and thus regulate the output signals. In addition, we demonstrated that the principal RR, CheY<sub>6</sub>, with the aid of its specific phosphatase, the bifunctional CheA<sub>3</sub>/CheA<sub>4</sub> kinase, could act as a phosphate sink for the other RR-Ps. Regulation of the output of sensory networks by the activity of key kinase/phosphatase proteins is likely to be a common mechanism, but this is one of the first to be identified that balances the outputs of two interconnected pathways.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Construction of the mathematical model</title>
<p>Within an <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> cell, CheA<sub>2</sub> has been shown to localize to the polar chemotaxis cluster, while CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheA<sub>4</sub> localize to the cytoplasmic cluster <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams2">[44]</xref>. All the <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> CheYs are free to diffuse throughout the cytoplasm of the cell enabling communication between the receptor clusters and flagellar motor. Unlike <italic>E. coli</italic>, the CheBs are also diffuse in the cytoplasm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter3">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams2">[44]</xref>. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g001">Figure 1</xref>, CheA<sub>2</sub>-P can phosphorylate all of the RRs, whilst CheA<sub>3</sub>-P is only able to phosphorylate CheY<sub>6</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>. What is the reason for this discrimination and how does it contribute towards the chemotactic response of the cell? To understand the role of each signaling cluster we constructed an ordinary differential equation (ODE) model of an <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> cell as detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000896.s004">Text S1</xref>. The model integrates <italic>in vivo</italic> protein expression levels with <italic>in vitro</italic> data on the kinetic preference of the CheAs for each of the RRs to predict RR-P levels throughout a simulated chemotactic response. The model includes the phosphorylation reactions shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t001">Table 1</xref> and was parameterized with published reaction rate constants and protein expression levels (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1000896-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>The phosphorylation reactions included in the model of the <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> chemotaxis signalling pathway.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000896-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reaction number</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reaction</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(1)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autophosphorylation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(2)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphorylation by CheA<sub>4</sub></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(3)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphotransfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(4)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphotransfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(5)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphotransfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(6)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphotransfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(7)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphotransfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(8)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphotransfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(9)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphotransfer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(10)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autodephosphorylation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(11)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autodephosphorylation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(12)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autodephosphorylation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(13)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autodephosphorylation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(14)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autodephosphorylation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(15a)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphatase assisted dephosphorylation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(15b)</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphatase assisted dephosphorylation</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pcbi-1000896-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Parameter values directly determined from experimental data.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000896-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard error</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Units</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">s<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">s<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>10</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>3P</sub> autodephosphorylation</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.93×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">s<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>11</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>4P</sub> autodephosphorylation</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.82×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">s<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>12</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>6P</sub> autodephosphorylation</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.69×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12×10<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">s<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>13</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheB<sub>1P</sub> autodephosphorylation</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73×10<sup>−4</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06×10<sup>−4</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">s<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>14</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheB<sub>2P</sub> autodephosphorylation</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.12×10<sup>−2</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">s<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>15a</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>6P</sub> dephosphorylation by CheA<sub>3</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.20×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>15b</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>6P</sub> dephosphorylation by CheA<sub>3P</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.20×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>A<sub>2T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total concentration of CheA<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.9</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µM</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Gould1">[69]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>A<sub>3T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total concentration of CheA<sub>3</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.9</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.4</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µM</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Gould1">[69]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Y<sub>3T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total concentration of CheY<sub>3</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µM</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Brown1">[68]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Y<sub>4T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total concentration of CheY<sub>4</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µM</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Brown1">[68]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Y<sub>6T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total concentration of CheY<sub>6</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">225</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µM</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Brown1">[68]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>B<sub>1T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total concentration of CheB<sub>1</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81.2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µM</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Gould1">[69]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>B<sub>2T</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total concentration of CheB<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">µM</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Gould1">[69]</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>The parameters for the phosphotransfer reactions were obtained by parameter fitting the previously published <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> chemotaxis phosphotransfer assay data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>, where CheA-<sup>32</sup>P served as a phosphodonor to the RRs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t003">Table 3</xref>). In the few cases where the assays were not very sensitive to the rate of reversed phosphotransfer from RR-P to CheA, reliable estimates of these rates were obtained using alternative phosphotransfer assays, in which RR-P was mixed with unphosphorylated CheA<sub>2</sub> or CheA<sub>3</sub> (examples shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g002">Figure 2</xref>). In these reactions, RR-P was generated using purified phosphorylated CheA P1 domains (either CheA<sub>2</sub>P1-P or CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-P) as the phosphodonor; control reactions lacking RR showed no phosphotransfer from CheA<sub>2</sub>P1-P or CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-P to either CheA<sub>2</sub> or CheA<sub>3</sub>. These experiments showed that while CheA<sub>2</sub> is phosphorylated by CheB<sub>2</sub>-P (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g002">Figure 2C</xref>) it is not phosphorylated by CheY<sub>6</sub>-P (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). The parameter values obtained from these phosphotransfer reactions were then used in constructing the model.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000896-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Phosphorimages of SDS-PAGE gels measuring phosphotransfer rate from CheY<sub>6</sub>-P and CheB<sub>2</sub>-P to CheA<sub>2</sub>.</title>
<p>30 µM CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-<sup>32</sup>P was incubated with 5 µM CheA<sub>2</sub> for 1 hour prior to the addition of (A) reaction buffer, (B) 10 µM CheY<sub>6</sub> and (C) 10 µM CheB<sub>2</sub>. 10 µl reaction samples were then taken at the time points indicated and quenched in 20 µl of 1.5 X SDS/EDTA loading dye. The quenched samples were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and detected by phosphorimaging.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g002" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1000896-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Parameter values estimated indirectly by fitting to phosphotransfer reaction data.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000896-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rate</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Units</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>3</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheY<sub>3</sub> phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.60×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>−3</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheY<sub>3</sub> reverse phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17×10<sup>4</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>4</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheY<sub>4</sub> phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.85×10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>−4</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheY<sub>4</sub> reverse phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.32×10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>5</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheY<sub>6</sub> phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>−5</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheY<sub>6</sub> reverse phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>6</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheB<sub>1</sub> phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78×10<sup>6</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>−6</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheB<sub>1</sub> reverse phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.85×10<sup>6</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>7</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheB<sub>2</sub> phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.07×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>−7</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>2P</sub> to CheB<sub>2</sub> reverse phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>8</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>3P</sub> to CheY<sub>6</sub> phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.75×10<sup>5</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>−8</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>3P</sub> to CheY<sub>6</sub> reverse phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.83×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>9</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>3P</sub> to CheB<sub>2</sub> phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.15×10<sup>4</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>k<sub>−9</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheA<sub>3P</sub> to CheB<sub>2</sub> reverse phosphotransfer</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.10×10<sup>3</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(Ms)<sup>−1</sup></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Response regulator dephosphorylation rates show CheY<sub>6</sub> acts as a phosphate sink</title>
<p><italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> responds to brief stimuli, returning to prestimulus behavior in less than 1 s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Berry1">[50]</xref>. This requires a rapid rate of signal termination. The measured autodephosphorylation half-times of the chemotaxis RRs, however, vary from ∼4 s for CheY<sub>6</sub>-P to ∼4000 s for CheB<sub>1</sub>-P (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t004">Table 4</xref>). As <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> does not have a CheZ homologue, an alternative dephosphorylation mechanism is required. Recently, CheA<sub>3</sub> was shown to be a specific phosphatase for CheY<sub>6</sub>-P <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>, but no phosphatases have been identified for the remaining chemotaxis RRs.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1000896-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of RR-P autodephosphorylation rates with the RR-P dephosphorylation half-times predicted by the model.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000896-t004-4" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Dephosphorylation half-time predicted by simulation (s)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Autodephosphorylation half-time (s)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wild type cells</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Δ<italic>cheY<sub>3</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Δ<italic>cheY<sub>4</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Δ<italic>cheY<sub>6</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Δ<italic>cheB<sub>1</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Δ<italic>cheB<sub>2</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No phosphatase<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">‡</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>3</sub>-P</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36±3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.7</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">296</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>4</sub>-P</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38±3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">543</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.1</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>6</sub>-P</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1±0.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheB<sub>1</sub>-P</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4046±150</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">309</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheB<sub>2</sub>-P</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52±4</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.9</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">430</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.1</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>*</label><p>These values were calculated from the experimentally determined <italic>in vitro</italic> autodephosphorylation rate constants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>†</label><p>The model was allowed to reach a steady state where CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation (reaction 1) and the phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> (reaction 2) were both active. Then reactions 1 and 2 were turned off. These half-times represent the time taken for levels of each of the RR-Ps to fall to half of their steady state values. Deletion of RRs was simulated by setting their total concentration in the model to zero, e.g. for Δ<italic>cheY<sub>3</sub></italic>, <italic>Y<sub>3T</sub></italic> = 0 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>‡</label><p>Lack of CheA<sub>3</sub> phosphatase activity was simulated by setting <italic>k</italic><sub>15<italic>a</italic></sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub>15<italic>b</italic></sub> = 0 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Phosphate sinks have been shown to be involved in signal termination in several bacterial signaling pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Sourjik2">[51]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Rasmussen2">[54]</xref>. To test whether a similar mechanism operates in <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic>, we used the model to predict the decay timecourse of RR-P levels resulting from simultaneously switching off autophosphorylation of CheA<sub>2</sub> (reaction 1 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t001">Table 1</xref>) and the phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> (reaction 2 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t001">Table 1</xref>). Although, the model incorporates the experimentally determined autodephosphorylation rates (reactions 10–15b of <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t001">Table 1</xref>), interestingly, the model predicts that levels of all of the RR-Ps decay with half-lives shorter than ∼7 s (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t004">Table 4</xref>), which is much faster than their experimentally measured autodephosphorylation rates. Within the model, only CheY<sub>6</sub>-P has a phosphatase. The only route by which the model could predict dephosphorylation rates for the other RR-Ps that are faster than their autodephosphorylation rates is for one or more of the RRs to be acting as “phosphate sinks”, with the dephosphorylation of the target RR-P proceeding via reversed phosphotransfer to a CheA, which in turn transfers the phosphoryl group to the sink RR.</p>
<p>To determine which RRs could act as sinks, we simulated RR-P decay rates in cells deleted for a single RR e.g. for the cell lacking CheY<sub>3</sub> we changed <italic>Y<sub>3T</sub></italic> to zero and measured the simulation half-lives of the remaining RR-Ps. We found that only the removal of CheY<sub>6</sub> greatly increased the simulation half-lives of the remaining RR-Ps (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t004">Table 4</xref>), suggesting that CheY<sub>6</sub> acts as a phosphate sink for all of the other RR-Ps. Without CheY<sub>6</sub>, the simulation half-lives of the remaining RRs were in some cases (CheY<sub>3</sub>-P, CheY<sub>4</sub>-P and CheB<sub>2</sub>-P) increased beyond their autodephosphorylation half-times (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t004">Table 4</xref>). This is the result of significant quantities of CheA<sub>3</sub>-P and CheA<sub>2</sub>-P being present at steady state, and persisting for some time after the autophosphorylation reactions (reactions 1 and 2) were turned off. This allows levels of RR-P to be replenished resulting in a RR-P simulation half-time that is slower than their autodephosphorylation half-times. Interestingly, even in the absence of CheY<sub>6</sub>, the simulated dephosphorylation rate of CheB<sub>1</sub>-P was faster than its autodephosphorylation rate. In the absence of CheY<sub>6</sub>, the other RRs (CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>) may act as phosphate sinks for CheB<sub>1</sub>-P i.e. CheB<sub>1</sub>-P acts as a phosphodonor for CheA<sub>2</sub> which in turn donates the phosphoryl groups to CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>. To test this we set the rate of phosphotransfer from CheB<sub>1</sub>-P to CheA<sub>2</sub> (<italic>k<sub>−6</sub></italic>) to zero and found that the simulated dephosphorylation half-time for CheB<sub>1</sub>-P was increased to 4295 s, which is comparable with its autodephosphorylation half-time indicating that in the absence of CheY<sub>6</sub>, one or more of other RRs therefore act as phosphate sinks for CheB<sub>1</sub>.</p>
<p>To confirm that the ability of CheY<sub>6</sub> to act as a phosphate sink was robust to changes in parameters we performed a sensitivity analysis, where we varied each parameter by factors of 0.1, 0.5, 1.5 and 10, and measured the effect on the simulation half-life of CheB<sub>1</sub>-P (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000896.s001">Table S1</xref>). For the parameters that were determined experimentally, the standard error lies well within the range covered by factors of 0.5 and 1.5. The simulation half-life of CheB<sub>1</sub>-P was robust to large changes in the majority of parameters, and in all cases remained much faster than the CheB<sub>1</sub>-P autodephosphorylation rate, but as would be expected showed some sensitivity towards those parameters directly involved in the operation of the CheY<sub>6</sub> phosphate sink i.e. the rates of phosphotransfer between CheB<sub>1</sub> and CheA<sub>2</sub> and between CheA<sub>2</sub> and CheY<sub>6</sub>. In addition, the system was also sensitive to large changes, well outside the range covered by experimental error in parameter determination, in the total concentrations of CheA<sub>2</sub> and CheY<sub>6</sub>. This sensitivity analysis indicates that the parameter space in which the phosphate sink mechanism will work efficiently is broad and extends well beyond the range of experimental errors in the parameters themselves, suggesting that this pathway is likely to operate <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p>
<p>In summary, these simulated data suggest that not only is CheY<sub>6</sub> a key regulator of flagellar motor rotation in <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic>, but it also acts as a “phosphate sink” ensuring rapid dephosphorylation of the other chemotaxis RRs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). This is very different from the <italic>S. meliloti</italic> sink where the sink CheY does not bind to the flagellar motor.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000896-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Summary of the phosphate-sink and phosphorelay pathways.</title>
<p>(A) The phosphotransfer reactions that allow CheY<sub>6</sub> to work as a phosphate-sink for the other RR-Ps. CheY<sub>3</sub>-P, CheY<sub>4</sub>-P, CheB<sub>1</sub>-P can act as phosphodonors for CheA<sub>2</sub>. Phosphoryl groups can take either of two routes from CheA<sub>2</sub> to the CheY<sub>6</sub>-phosphate-sink. CheA<sub>2</sub>-P can directly phosphorylate CheY<sub>6</sub> (shown in green) or alternatively, can phosphorylate CheB<sub>2</sub>, which can transfer the phosphoryl group to CheA<sub>3</sub> which then phosphorylates CheY<sub>6</sub> (shown in blue). CheY<sub>6</sub>-P is rapidly dephosphorylated due to the specific phosphatase activity of the bifunctional enzyme CheA<sub>3</sub>. For diagrammatic simplicity, reversible reactions are shown as operating in the direction that leads towards the sink. (B) Diagram summarizing the role of CheB<sub>2</sub> and CheA<sub>2</sub> in relaying phosphoryl groups from CheA<sub>3</sub>-P to its non-cognate RRs, CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheB<sub>1</sub>. The reactions necessary for this phosphorelay are highlighted in red. At the cytoplasmic chemotaxis cluster, phosphoryl groups are transferred from CheA<sub>3</sub>-P to CheY<sub>6</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>. CheB<sub>2</sub>-P then diffuses to the polar chemotaxis cluster where it serves as a phosphodonor for CheA<sub>2</sub>. CheA<sub>2</sub>-P subsequently acts as a phosphodonor for CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheB<sub>1</sub>. For diagrammatic simplicity, reactions which are reversible are shown as operating in the direction that leads towards the non-cognate RRs of CheA<sub>3</sub>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g003" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>The phosphatase activity of CheA<sub>3</sub> is required for CheY<sub>6</sub> to work as an efficient phosphate sink</title>
<p>In addition to containing the Hpt domain needed for phosphorylation of CheY<sub>6</sub>, CheA<sub>3</sub> is also a phosphatase specific for CheY<sub>6</sub>-P. This phosphatase activity has previously been shown to be essential for chemotaxis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>. We used the model to determine the effect of phosphatase removal on RR-P levels and signal termination times, by setting the rate constants for the CheA<sub>3</sub> phosphatase reactions (15a) and (15b) in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t002">Table 2</xref> to zero. The model predicted very high steady state concentrations of all of the RR-Ps (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t005">Table 5</xref>), with phosphorylation levels of the total chemotaxis RR pool rising from ∼55% to ∼97%. This was the result of increased levels of CheY<sub>6</sub>-P (due to decreased dephosphorylation) leading to higher CheA<sub>2</sub>-P and CheA<sub>3</sub>-P concentrations and therefore higher levels of the other RR-Ps. The model also predicted that the signal termination times for all of the RR-Ps would be longer without the phosphatase (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t004">Table 4</xref>), as CheY<sub>6</sub> would be less effective as a phosphate sink for the other RR-Ps. The model therefore highlights the importance of the phosphatase activity in CheA<sub>3</sub>, and demonstrates that although it is specific for CheY<sub>6</sub>-P, the phosphatase activity indirectly affects the concentration of the other RR-Ps and their signal termination rates as outlined above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Removal of the phosphatase activity is therefore predicted to cause a general increase in RR-P levels, which could account for the non-chemotactic phenotype of the strains lacking phosphatase activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1000896-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of steady state levels of RR-P with and without CheA<sub>3</sub> phosphatase activity.</title>
</caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000896-t005-5" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.t005" xlink:type="simple"/><table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fraction phosphorylated (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Protein</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wild-type cells</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No phosphatase<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">‡</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>3</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>4</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheY<sub>6</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheB<sub>1</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CheB<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total RR pool</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td>
<td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label>‡</label><p>Lack of CheA<sub>3</sub> phosphatase activity was simulated by setting <italic>k</italic><sub>15<italic>a</italic></sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub>15<italic>b</italic></sub> = 0 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>A phosphorelay pathway connects both chemotaxis clusters</title>
<p>We modeled the consequences of chemoeffector stimulation of either of the two chemotaxis clusters by either (i) turning off CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation (reaction (1) – parameter <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> set to zero) to mimic attractant stimulation of the polar chemotaxis cluster or (ii) turning off the phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> (reaction (2) – parameter <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> set to zero) to mimic attractant stimulation of the cytoplasmic chemotaxis cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g004">Figure 4</xref>). As expected, when CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation was turned off (case (i)) there was a reduction in the phosphorylation levels of each of the RRs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g004">Figure 4</xref>) because CheA<sub>2</sub>-P serves as a phosphodonor for all of the RRs. However, counter-intuitively, significant levels of all RR-Ps remained, including CheY<sub>3</sub>-P, CheY<sub>4</sub>-P and CheB<sub>1</sub>-P, which can only be generated by CheA<sub>2</sub>-P.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1000896-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>The predicted variation in levels of RR-P throughout a simulated chemotaxis response.</title>
<p>Initially, CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation in the polar cluster and the phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> in the cytoplasmic cluster are occurring. To mimic attractant stimulation of the polar cluster, CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation is turned off (<italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> = 0) at the point labelled (A). This causes a drop in RR-P levels and a new steady state is reached. (B) Subsequently, CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation is turned back on and the system returns to its original steady state. At point (C), the phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> is turned off (<italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> = 0) to mimic attractant stimulation of the cytoplasmic cluster. As a result of this, RR-P levels fall and a new steady state is reached. (D) Finally, phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> is turned back on and the system returns to its initial steady state.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.g004" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Analysis of the modeling results from case (i) revealed that even though CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation had been turned off, significant levels of CheA<sub>2</sub>-P were present and were being generated by the reversal of reaction (7) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t001">Table 1</xref>) i.e. CheB<sub>2</sub>-P was acting as a phosphodonor for CheA<sub>2</sub> (as demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). In this case, CheY<sub>6</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub> were phosphorylated by CheA<sub>3</sub>-P; CheB<sub>2</sub>-P then served as a phosphodonor for CheA<sub>2</sub> i.e. CheB<sub>2</sub> transfers phosphoryl groups between CheA<sub>3</sub>-P and CheA<sub>2</sub>. The CheA<sub>2</sub>-P generated in this way could then phosphorylate CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheB<sub>1</sub>. This result suggests that CheA<sub>3</sub>-P is linked to the RRs, CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheB<sub>1</sub>, via a multistep phosphorelay i.e. CheA<sub>3</sub>-P (His) to CheB<sub>2</sub> (Asp) to CheA<sub>2</sub> (His) to CheY<sub>3</sub>/CheY<sub>4</sub>/CheB<sub>1</sub> (Asp).</p>
<p>In case (ii), switching off the phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> caused a reduction not only in the levels of CheY<sub>6</sub>-P and CheB<sub>2</sub>-P, but also in levels of CheY<sub>3</sub>-P, CheY<sub>4</sub>-P and CheB<sub>1</sub>-P. Levels of CheY<sub>3</sub>-P, CheY<sub>4</sub>-P and CheB<sub>1</sub>-P were affected because (a) they were dephosphorylated faster since the reduction in CheY<sub>6</sub>-P levels was accompanied by an increase in the unphosphorylated CheY<sub>6</sub> levels which acts as a phosphate sink and (b) there was no input of phosphoryl groups at the cytoplasmic cluster for CheB<sub>2</sub> to transfer to these RRs via CheA<sub>2</sub>. These results indicate that even when CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation is occurring, the bifunctional kinase/phosphatase in the cytoplasmic chemotaxis cluster makes a significant contribution to the phosphorylation levels of all of the RRs.</p>
<p>We performed a sensitivity analysis to look at the effect of varying each of the model parameters on levels of CheY<sub>4</sub>-P when CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation is turned off; under these conditions CheY<sub>4</sub>-P levels give a measure of the extent to which the phosphorelay is occurring (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000896.s002">Table S2</xref>). The system was robust to changes in many of the parameters although as would be expected was sensitive to changes in parameters that directly affect either i) the rate of entry or exit of phosphoryl groups from the system e.g. rate of phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub>, rate of CheY<sub>6</sub>-P dephosphorylation (autodephosphorylation and phosphatase assisted), and the expression levels of CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheY<sub>6</sub> or ii) the functioning of the phosphorelay e.g. the expression levels of CheA<sub>2</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>, rates of phosphotransfer between CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>, between CheB<sub>2</sub> and CheA<sub>2</sub>, and between CheA<sub>2</sub> and CheY<sub>4</sub>. However, despite this sensitivity in almost all cases at least some phosphorylation of CheY<sub>4</sub> was predicted indicating that the phosphorelay remained operational. In the two remaining extreme cases, where CheY<sub>6</sub> expression levels were ten times higher than usual or where the rate of phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> was ten-fold lower than the measured rate, levels of all RR-Ps, not just CheY<sub>4</sub>-P, were extremely low. These results indicate that the phosphorelay operates over a broad range of parameter space, although the extent to which it operates is sensitive to large changes in some of the parameters.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The experimental work leading up to this study produced an outline architecture of the complex signaling network controlling <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> chemotaxis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter1">[30]</xref>. However, the mechanism of integrating the signals produced by each of the signaling clusters to control the flagellar motor was unclear. Mathematical modeling has provided considerable insight into the probable functioning of simpler chemotaxis pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Bray1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Hansen1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Tindall3">[55]</xref>, and a control engineering approach has recently been used in <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> to discriminate between several possible mechanisms of CheY control of the flagellar motor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Roberts1">[56]</xref>. In this study, a mathematical model of <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> chemotaxis was formulated that integrates <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> biochemical data on the kinetic preferences of the signaling reactions with <italic>in vivo</italic> measurements of protein copy number. Analysis of the model revealed two interesting features of the signaling network, both of which rely on reversed phosphotransfer from RR-Ps to CheA. Firstly, rapid signal termination for all chemotaxis RR-Ps may be achieved by CheY<sub>6</sub> acting as a phosphate sink in addition to being the primary motor control protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Secondly, a novel phosphorelay involving CheB<sub>2</sub> appears to link the cytoplasmic and polar chemotaxis clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Together these two network features provide the bifunctional kinase/phosphatase, CheA<sub>3</sub>, with the means to increase or decrease the concentration of all of the chemotaxis RR-Ps and therefore to regulate the output of the two chemosensory clusters.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>CheY<sub>6</sub> is a phosphate sink for all of the chemotaxis RR-Ps</title>
<p>Phosphate sinks provide an alternative mechanism for dephosphorylating RR-Ps <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Sourjik2">[51]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-JimenezPearson1">[52]</xref>, instead of simply hydrolyzing the phosphoryl group (as in autodephosphorylation or phosphatase-assisted-dephosphorylation), the phosphoryl group is transferred to a HPK, which subsequently transfers it to the “phosphate sink” RR. The phosphoryl group is then hydrolyzed from the “phosphate sink” by either autodephosphorylation or phosphatase-assisted-dephosphorylation. The model presented in this study predicted that signal termination occurs rapidly in <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic>, with all RR-Ps dephosphorylating with half-times of less than ∼7 s (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t004">Table 4</xref>). This is consistent with the observed stimulus response time of 1 s for <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Berry1">[50]</xref>, since with a decay half-time of ∼7 s, CheY-P levels could fall by ∼10% during 1s, which, assuming that the <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> motor is as ultrasensitive to changes in CheY-P levels as the <italic>E. coli</italic> motor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Cluzel1">[57]</xref>, would be sufficient to give a significant change in motor rotation bias.</p>
<p>Prior to this study, it was known that CheY<sub>6</sub>-P with the aid of its specific phosphatase, the bifunctional protein CheA<sub>3</sub>, could dephosphorylate rapidly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>, however, the other RR-Ps were known to autodephosphorylate with half-times in excess of 36 s, with CheB<sub>1</sub>-P taking over 4000 s. By removing each of the RRs in turn from the model, we found that CheY<sub>6</sub> was acting as a “phosphate sink” for the other RR-Ps, since cells lacking CheY<sub>6</sub> showed much slower dephosphorylation rates for the remaining RR-Ps (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t004">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Furthermore, we showed that removal of the phosphatase activity of CheA<sub>3</sub> from the model increased the dephosphorylation half-times of all of the RR-Ps, indicating that the phosphatase activity is required for efficient operation of the CheY<sub>6</sub> phosphate sink and rapid signal termination. This phosphate sink role for CheY<sub>6</sub> is additional to its primary role as a direct regulator of flagellar rotation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter3">[39]</xref>.</p>
<p>CheY<sub>6</sub> differs in several ways from the prototypical phosphate sink, CheY1 from <italic>S. meliloti</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Sourjik2">[51]</xref>. CheY<sub>6</sub> directly controls flagellar motor rotation by binding FliM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter3">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Ferre1">[49]</xref>, and has a dedicated phosphatase, in contrast, <italic>S. meliloti</italic> CheY1 does not bind FliM and appears to function only as a “phosphate sink”. Another fundamental difference is the rate of dephosphorylation; CheY<sub>6</sub>-P dephosphorylates much faster than the autodephosphorylation rates of the RRs for which it acts as a sink whereas <italic>S. meliloti</italic> CheY1-P does not autodephosphorylate any faster than the motor binding RR, CheY2-P, for which it is a sink. The <italic>S. meliloti</italic> sink does not need to dephosphorylate quickly because it does not directly affect flagellar rotation and so phosphoryl groups can be stored on it until autodephosphorylation occurs, in contrast, <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> CheY<sub>6</sub> is a key regulator of flagellar rotation and therefore requires rapid signal termination.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>A CheB<sub>2</sub> mediated phosphorelay connects the polar and cytoplasmic signaling clusters</title>
<p>As part of our interrogation of the model, we simulated attractant stimulation of the polar chemotaxis cluster by turning off autophosphorylation of CheA<sub>2</sub>, while allowing phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> to occur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Interestingly under these conditions, even though CheA<sub>3</sub>-P cannot directly phosphorylate CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub>, and CheB<sub>1</sub>, the model predicted non-zero concentrations of these RR-Ps. This is the result of the action of a phosphorelay where phosphoryl groups from CheA<sub>3</sub>-P (His) are transferred to CheB<sub>2</sub> (Asp) then to CheA<sub>2</sub> (His) and subsequently to either CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> or CheB<sub>1</sub> (Asp) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Direct testing of the <italic>in vivo</italic> importance of this phosphorelay is confounded by the dual role of CheB<sub>2</sub>, firstly as a chemoreceptor methylesterase and secondly as a potential intermediate in the phosphorelay. The methylesterase activity of CheB<sub>2</sub> is required for normal chemotaxis and it is not possible to block the phosphorylation of CheB<sub>2</sub> by mutagenesis without impairing the control of this methylesterase activity. It is therefore not known the extent to which this CheB<sub>2</sub> mediated phosphorelay operates <italic>in vivo</italic>; however, the model does incorporate both <italic>in vitro</italic> kinetic preference data and <italic>in vivo</italic> protein expression levels, and this suggests that the phosphorelay may operate <italic>in vivo</italic>, allowing the cytoplasmic cluster to make a significant contribution to phosphorylation levels of the non-cognate RRs; CheY<sub>3</sub>, CheY<sub>4</sub> and CheB<sub>1</sub>.</p>
<p>The model in this study does not include adaptation as this is a poorly understood process in <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic>, with little experimental data. However, it is possible that the adaptation pathway could act to reduce the elevated RR-P levels caused by a constant influx of phosphoryl groups to the polar cluster from the cytoplasmic cluster by modifying the polar receptors in such a way as to reduce the autophosphorylation rate of the polar kinase, CheA<sub>2</sub> i.e. the cell could adapt to constant signals from the cytoplasmic cluster. Although when cells are performing chemotaxis and swimming through gradients of chemoeffector, signals from the cytoplasmic cluster will vary over time and will make a significant contribution to RR-P levels. The relative contribution of this phosphorelay to levels of CheY<sub>3</sub>-P, CheY<sub>4</sub>-P and CheB<sub>1</sub>-P will be modulated by signals coming through the transmembrane chemoreceptors that directly control the rate of CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation and would be greatest when the autophosphorylation rate of CheA<sub>2</sub> is low and the rate of phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub> is high. These conditions could arise when cells are swimming up a gradient of a specific attractant which is sensed by the transmembrane chemoreceptors, while the metabolic state of the cell is worsening due to, for example, decreasing concentrations of an essential nutrient (for which there may not be a transmembrane chemoreceptor). Under such conditions, the increased rate of phosphorylation of CheA<sub>3</sub> by CheA<sub>4</sub>, coupled with the CheB<sub>2</sub>/CheA<sub>2</sub> mediated phosphorelay, could raise levels CheY<sub>3</sub>-P, CheY<sub>4</sub>-P and CheY<sub>6</sub>-P, allowing cells to override their favourable response to the extracellular attractant and swim away from these unfavourable environments.</p>
<p>Numerous examples of other two-component systems employing phosphorelays have been described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Mitrophanov1">[58]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Appleby1">[61]</xref>; however, to the best of our knowledge this is the first example of a phosphorelay involving two distinct HPKs localized to different regions of the cell, and also, the first phosphorelay to be found in a chemotaxis signaling pathway. Given that over 50% of bacteria with any <italic>che</italic> genes have more than two <italic>cheA</italic>s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Hamer1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Wuichet1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>, it seems likely that phosphorelays allowing communication between different CheA homologues could be involved in chemotactic signaling in a wide range of bacterial species.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Signal integration by the cytoplasmic cluster</title>
<p>The polar cluster senses extracellular signals while the cytoplasmic cluster is believed to sense the metabolic state of the cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter1">[30]</xref>. The concentration of each RR-P depends not only on polar kinase activity but also on the balance of kinase and phosphatase activity in the cytoplasmic cluster. The kinase activity of the cytoplasmic cluster resides in CheA<sub>4</sub> and the phosphatase activity resides in CheA<sub>3</sub>; both proteins have P5 (regulatory) domains and it is therefore likely that both activities will be regulated by environmental stimuli <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Scott1">[62]</xref>. A stimulus that increases phosphatase activity would have the effect of reducing levels of all RR-Ps, since the action of the phosphatase would directly accelerate CheY<sub>6</sub>-P dephosphorylation leaving more unphosphorylated CheY<sub>6</sub> to function as a phosphate sink for the other RR-Ps. Such a mechanism could allow the cytoplasmic cluster to tune or modulate signals coming from the polar cluster since increased phosphatase activity would lead to a general decrease in chemotaxis RR-P levels. In contrast, a stimulus that increased kinase activity at the cytoplasmic cluster would increase levels of all RR-Ps because CheA<sub>3</sub>-P would phosphorylate CheY<sub>6</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub> directly; CheB<sub>2</sub> would then shuttle the phosphoryl groups to CheA<sub>2</sub> and from there onto the other RRs while phosphorylation of CheY<sub>6</sub> would reduce its capacity as a phosphate sink resulting in a general increase in RR-P levels. Therefore the overall sensory output of the pathway depends critically on the relative activity of CheA<sub>3</sub> and CheA<sub>4</sub>, and potentially provides a mechanism for signals about the metabolic state of the cell to modulate signals regarding the extracellular environment.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Mathematical model</title>
<p>Full details on the mathematical model are included in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000896.s004">Text S1</xref>. Briefly, the law of mass action was applied to the reactions detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t001">Table 1</xref> to produce a system of non-linear ordinary differential equations (ODEs), which were solved using Matlab (MathWorks). The model was parameterized with data from the literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter3">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter4">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Slovak1">[63]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Ind1">[65]</xref> and our own experiments as detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t002">Tables 2</xref>&amp;<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t003">3</xref>. A parameter fit of the phosphotransfer rates between each kinase and RR (time course data) with that of a mathematical model describing the <italic>in vitro</italic> reactions was performed. A number of local, global and genetic algorithm optimisation procedures were employed (simulated annealing, Hooke and Jeeves, least squares, Levenberg-Marquardt, Nelder-Mead, steepest descent and the genetic algorithm) to obtain a robust set of parameters (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000896-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Plasmids and strains</title>
<p>The plasmids and strains used are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000896.s003">Table S3</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> strains were grown in LB medium at 37°C. Where required, antibiotics were used at concentrations of 100 µg ml<sup>−1</sup> for ampicillin and 25 µg ml<sup>−1</sup> for kanamycin.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Protein purification</title>
<p>His-tagged and GST-tagged <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> CheA, CheY and CheB proteins were purified as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter7">[66]</xref>. Protein purity and concentration was measured as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter5">[45]</xref>. Purified proteins were stored at −20°C.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Preparation of CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-<sup>32</sup>P</title>
<p>CheA<sub>3</sub>P1 was phosphorylated using [γ-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP and CheA<sub>4</sub>, and purified as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Porter6">[48]</xref>. The final preparation of CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-<sup>32</sup>P was free of ATP and CheA<sub>4</sub>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Detection of phosphotransfer from the response regulators to CheA<sub>2</sub></title>
<p>Assays were performed at 20°C in TGMNKD buffer (50 mM Tris HCl, 10% (v/v) glycerol, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 150 mM NaCl, 50 mM KCl, 1 mM DTT, pH 8.0). CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-<sup>32</sup>P was used to phosphorylate the RRs, CheY<sub>6</sub> and CheB<sub>2</sub>, in these assays because it is a good phosphodonor for these proteins and even after prolonged incubation (&gt;1 hour) CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-<sup>32</sup>P does not act as a direct phosphodonor for CheA<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000896-g003">Figure 3A</xref>); therefore any CheA<sub>2</sub>-P generated in these assays is due to phosphotransfer from RR-P to CheA<sub>2</sub> rather than direct phosphotransfer from CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-P to CheA<sub>2</sub>. 30 µM CheA<sub>3</sub>P1-<sup>32</sup>P was mixed with 5 µM CheA<sub>2</sub> prior to the addition of 10 µM RR. Following the addition of RR, reaction aliquots of 10 µl were taken at the indicated timepoints and quenched immediately in 5 µl of 3 X SDS-PAGE loading dye (7.5% (w/v) SDS, 90 mM EDTA, 37.5 mM Tris HCl, 37.5% glycerol, 3% (v/v) β-mercaptoethanol, pH 6.8). Quenched samples were analyzed using SDS-PAGE and phosphorimaging as described previously.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Protein expression levels</title>
<p>Protein expression levels were measured in wild-type <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic> cells grown under microaerobic growth conditions using quantitative immunoblotting as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Ind1">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-BenAnatPorat1">[67]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1000896-Gould1">[69]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000896.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.s001" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p>The effect of parameter variation on the simulation half-life of CheB<sub>1</sub>-P.</p>
<p>(0.09 MB PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000896.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.s002" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p>The effect of parameter variation on the predicted levels of CheY<sub>4</sub>-P when CheA<sub>2</sub> autophosphorylation is turned off (<italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> = 0).</p>
<p>(0.09 MB PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000896.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.s003" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p>Plasmids and bacterial strains used in this study.</p>
<p>(0.01 MB PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1000896.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000896.s004" xlink:type="simple"><label>Text S1</label><caption>
<p>Mathematical modeling.</p>
<p>(0.02 MB PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Stock1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goudreau</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Two-component signal transduction.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>183</fpage>             <lpage>215</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Bray1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Receptor clustering as a cellular mechanism to control sensitivity.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>393</volume>             <fpage>85</fpage>             <lpage>88</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Tindall1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tindall</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Overview of mathematical approaches used to model bacterial chemotaxis II: bacterial populations.</article-title>             <source>Bull Math Biol</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>1570</fpage>             <lpage>1607</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Tindall2"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tindall</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gaglia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Overview of mathematical approaches used to model bacterial chemotaxis I: the single cell.</article-title>             <source>Bull Math Biol</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>1525</fpage>             <lpage>1569</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Hansen1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Chemotaxis in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: a molecular model for robust precise adaptation.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e1</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Tu1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Modeling the chemotactic response of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to time-varying stimuli.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>105</volume>             <fpage>14855</fpage>             <lpage>14860</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Endres1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oleksiuk</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sourjik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Variable sizes of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> chemoreceptor signaling teams.</article-title>             <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>211</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Goldman1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Signal amplification in a lattice of coupled protein kinases.</article-title>             <source>Mol BioSyst</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>1853</fpage>             <lpage>1859</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Rao1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Design and diversity in bacterial chemotaxis: a comparative study in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e49</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Alon1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alon</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Surette</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barkai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leibler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Robustness in bacterial chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>397</volume>             <fpage>168</fpage>             <lpage>171</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Hazelbauer1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hazelbauer</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Falke</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Bacterial chemoreceptors: high-performance signaling in networked arrays.</article-title>             <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>9</fpage>             <lpage>19</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Making sense of it all: Bacterial chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Bio</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>1024</fpage>             <lpage>1037</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Szurmant1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Szurmant</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ordal</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Diversity in chemotaxis mechanisms among the Bacteria and Archaea.</article-title>             <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>             <volume>68</volume>             <fpage>301</fpage>             <lpage>319</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Maddock1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maddock</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Polar location of the chemoreceptor complex in the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> cell.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>259</volume>             <fpage>1717</fpage>             <lpage>1723</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Greenfield1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McEvoy</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Self-organization of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> chemotaxis network imaged with super-resolution light microscopy.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>e1000137</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Briegel1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Briegel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tocheva</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wuichet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Universal architecture of bacterial chemoreceptor arrays.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>17181</fpage>             <lpage>17186</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Borkovich1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Borkovich</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Transmembrane signal transduction in bacterial chemotaxis involves ligand-dependent activation of phosphate group transfer.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>1208</fpage>             <lpage>1212</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Ninfa1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ninfa</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mowbray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Reconstruction of the bacterial chemotaxis signal transduction system from purified components.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>266</volume>             <fpage>9764</fpage>             <lpage>9770</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Boldog1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boldog</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grimme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sligar</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hazelbauer</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Nanodiscs separate chemoreceptor oligomeric states and reveal their signaling properties.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>11509</fpage>             <lpage>11514</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Hess1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourret</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Histidine phosphorylation and phosphoryl group transfer in bacterial chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>336</volume>             <fpage>139</fpage>             <lpage>143</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Sanders1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gillece-Castro</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burlingame</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koshland</surname><given-names>DE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
</person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Identification of the site of phosphorylation of the chemotaxis response regulator protein, CheY.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>264</volume>             <fpage>21770</fpage>             <lpage>21778</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Bourret1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourret</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>Conserved aspartate residues and phosphorylation in signal transduction by the chemotaxis protein CheY.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>87</volume>             <fpage>41</fpage>             <lpage>45</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Welch1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oosawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>S-I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Phosphorylation-dependent binding of a signal molecule to the flagellar switch of bacteria.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>90</volume>             <fpage>8787</fpage>             <lpage>8791</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Dyer1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vartanian</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlquist</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A Molecular Mechanism of Bacterial Flagellar Motor Switching.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Biol</source>             <volume>388</volume>             <fpage>71</fpage>             <lpage>84</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Lupas1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lupas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Phosphorylation of an N-terminal regulatory domain activates the CheB methylesterase in bacterial chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>264</volume>             <fpage>17337</fpage>             <lpage>17342</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Sourjik1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sourjik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Receptor sensitivity in bacterial chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>123</fpage>             <lpage>127</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Thomas1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brewster</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourret</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Two variable active site residues modulate response regulator phosphoryl group stability.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>453</fpage>             <lpage>465</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Hess2"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oosawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Phosphorylation of three proteins in the signalling pathway of bacterial chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>53</volume>             <fpage>79</fpage>             <lpage>87</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Silversmith1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Silversmith</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourret</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Kinetic characterization of catalysis by the chemotaxis phosphatase CheZ: modulation of activity by the phosphorylated CheY substrate.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>283</volume>             <fpage>756</fpage>             <lpage>765</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Porter1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title><italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>: Complexity in chemotactic signalling.</article-title>             <source>Trends Microbiol</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>251</fpage>             <lpage>260</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Hamer1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P-Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reinert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Deciphering chemotaxis pathways using cross species comparisons.</article-title>             <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>3</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Wuichet1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wuichet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhulin</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Origins and diversification of a complex signal transduction system in prokaryotes.</article-title>             <source>Sci Signal</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>ra50</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Armitage1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Macnab</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Unidirectional intermittent rotation of the flagellum of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>169</volume>             <fpage>514</fpage>             <lpage>518</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Porter2"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>The third chemotaxis locus of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> is essential for chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>1081</fpage>             <lpage>1094</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Martin1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>The roles of the multiple CheW and CheA homologues in chemotaxis and in chemoreceptor localization in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>40</volume>             <fpage>1261</fpage>             <lpage>1272</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Pilizota1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pilizota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Branch</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A molecular brake, not a clutch, stops the <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> flagellar motor.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>11582</fpage>             <lpage>11587</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Poggio1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poggio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>breu-Goodger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fabela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A complete set of flagellar genes acquired by horizontal transfer coexists with the endogenous flagellar system in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>189</volume>             <fpage>3208</fpage>             <lpage>3216</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-delCampo1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>del Campo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ballado</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de la Mora</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Poggio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Camarena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Chemotactic control of the two flagellar systems of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> is mediated by different sets of CheY and FliM proteins.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>189</volume>             <fpage>8397</fpage>             <lpage>8401</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Porter3"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Byles</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The CheYs of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>281</volume>             <fpage>32694</fpage>             <lpage>32704</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Martin2"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>DSH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mantotta</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>CheR- and CheB-dependent chemosensory adaptation system of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>183</volume>             <fpage>7135</fpage>             <lpage>7144</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Shah1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>DSH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamblin</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Fine tuning bacterial chemotaxis: analysis of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> behaviour under aerobic and anaerobic conditions by mutation of the major chemotaxis operons and <italic>cheY</italic> genes.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>4601</fpage>             <lpage>4613</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Shah2"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamblin</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Identification of a fourth <italic>cheY</italic> gene in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> and interspecies interaction within the bacterial chemotaxis signal transduction pathway.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>101</fpage>             <lpage>112</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Porter4"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Chemotaxis in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> requires an atypical histidine protein kinase.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>279</volume>             <fpage>54573</fpage>             <lpage>54580</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams2"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Targeting of two signal transduction pathways to different regions of the bacterial cell.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>50</volume>             <fpage>763</fpage>             <lpage>770</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Porter5"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Phosphotransfer in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>J Mol Biol</source>             <volume>324</volume>             <fpage>35</fpage>             <lpage>45</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Wadhams3"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maddock</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mantotta</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>TlpC, a novel chemotaxis protein in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>, localizes to a discrete region in the cytoplasm.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>1211</fpage>             <lpage>1221</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Bell1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Strawson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Using structural information to change the phosphotransfer specificity of a two-component chemotaxis signalling complex.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>e1000306</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Porter6"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>MAJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A bifunctional kinase-phosphatase in bacterial chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>105</volume>             <fpage>18531</fpage>             <lpage>18536</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Ferre1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ferre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de la Mora</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ballado</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Camarena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Biochemical study of multiple CheY response regulators of the chemotactic pathway of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>186</volume>             <fpage>5172</fpage>             <lpage>5177</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Berry1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Response kinetics of tethered <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> to changes in light intensity.</article-title>             <source>Biophys J</source>             <volume>78</volume>             <fpage>1207</fpage>             <lpage>1215</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Sourjik2"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sourjik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Phosphotransfer between CheA, CheY1, and CheY2 in the chemotaxis signal transduction chain of <italic>Rhizobium meliloti</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Biochemistry</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>2327</fpage>             <lpage>2335</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-JimenezPearson1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez-Pearson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Delany</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scarlato</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Phosphate flow in the chemotactic response system of <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Microbiology</source>             <volume>151</volume>             <fpage>3299</fpage>             <lpage>3311</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Rasmussen1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sogaard-Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Coupling of multicellular morphogenesis and cellular differentiation by an unusual hybrid histidine protein kinase in <italic>Myxococcus xanthus</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>56</volume>             <fpage>1358</fpage>             <lpage>1372</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Rasmussen2"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wegener-Feldbrugge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sogaard-Andersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Four signalling domains in the hybrid histidine protein kinase RodK of <italic>Myxococcus xanthus</italic> are required for activity.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>525</fpage>             <lpage>534</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Tindall3"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tindall</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Spatiotemporal modelling of CheY complexes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> chemotaxis.</article-title>             <source>Prog Biophys Mol Biol</source>             <volume>100</volume>             <fpage>40</fpage>             <lpage>46</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Roberts1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>August</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McSharry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A model invalidation-based approach for elucidating biological signalling pathways, applied to the chemotaxis pathway in <italic>R. sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>105</fpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Cluzel1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cluzel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Surette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leibler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>An ultrasensitive bacterial motor revealed by monitoring signaling proteins in single cells.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>287</volume>             <fpage>1652</fpage>             <lpage>1655</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Mitrophanov1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitrophanov</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Groisman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Signal integration in bacterial two-component regulatory systems.</article-title>             <source>Genes Dev</source>             <volume>22</volume>             <fpage>2601</fpage>             <lpage>2611</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Perego1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perego</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hanstein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Djavakhishvili</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <article-title>Multiple protein-aspartate phosphatases provide a mechanism for the integration of diverse signals in the control of development in <italic>B. subtilis</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>79</volume>             <fpage>1047</fpage>             <lpage>1055</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Ogino1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ogino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>An <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> protein that exhibits phosphohistidine phosphatase activity towards the HPt domain of the ArcB sensor involved in the multistep His-Asp phosphorelay.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>573</fpage>             <lpage>585</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Appleby1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bourret</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Signal transduction via the multi-step phosphorelay: not necessarily a road less traveled.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>845</fpage>             <lpage>848</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Scott1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bagg</surname><given-names>EAL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Specificity of localization and phosphotransfer in the CheA proteins of <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Mol Microbiol</source>             <volume>76</volume>             <fpage>318</fpage>             <lpage>330</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Slovak1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slovak</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Differential localization of Mre proteins with PBP2 in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>188</volume>             <fpage>1691</fpage>             <lpage>1700</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Slovak2"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slovak</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Localization of MreB in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> under conditions causing changes in cell shape and membrane structure.</article-title>             <source>J Bacteriol</source>             <volume>187</volume>             <fpage>54</fpage>             <lpage>64</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Ind1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ind</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Byles</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Beyer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>An inducible expression plasmid for <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> and <italic>Paracoccus denitrificans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>75</volume>             <fpage>6613</fpage>             <lpage>6615</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Porter7"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> analysis of the <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> chemotaxis signaling complexes.</article-title>             <source>Method Enzymol</source>             <volume>423</volume>             <fpage>392</fpage>             <lpage>413</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-BenAnatPorat1"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Anat Porat</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zan-Bar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ravid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Quantitative dot-blot assay for low titer anti-lipopolysaccharide antibodies in human plasma.</article-title>             <source>J Immunol Methods</source>             <volume>180</volume>             <fpage>213</fpage>             <lpage>218</lpage>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Brown1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
</person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Control of the unidirectional motor in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>.</article-title>             <comment>D. Phil. Thesis. University of Oxford</comment>          </element-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1000896-Gould1"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname></name>
</person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Chemotaxis gene expression in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> WS8N.</article-title>             <comment>D. Phil. Thesis. University of Oxford</comment>          </element-citation></ref>
</ref-list>

</back>
</article>