<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Computational Biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-18-01755</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Major histocompatibility complex</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Major histocompatibility complex</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Major histocompatibility complex</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Major histocompatibility complex</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Major histocompatibility complex</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasite evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and laboratory medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and laboratory medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathogenesis</subject><subj-group><subject>Host-pathogen interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary immunology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular motors</subject><subj-group><subject>Motor proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Actin motors</subject><subj-group><subject>Myosins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Motor proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Actin motors</subject><subj-group><subject>Myosins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Contractile proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Myosins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Cytoskeletal proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Myosins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Eukaryota</subject><subj-group><subject>Animals</subject><subj-group><subject>Vertebrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Amniotes</subject><subj-group><subject>Birds</subject><subj-group><subject>Passerines</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Evolution of major histocompatibility complex gene copy number</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Evolution of major histocompatibility complex gene copy number</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1220-1075</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bentkowski</surname>
<given-names>Piotr</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Software</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Visualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – review &amp; editing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8503-5701</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Radwan</surname>
<given-names>Jacek</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Evolutionary Biology Group, Faculty of Biology, Adam Mickiewicz University in Poznań, Poland</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van Boven</surname>
<given-names>Michiel</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, NETHERLANDS</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">jradwan@amu.edu.pl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>16</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>5</month>
<year>2019</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e1007015</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>15</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>9</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2019</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Bentkowski, Radwan</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015"/>
<abstract>
<p>MHC genes, which code for proteins responsible for presenting pathogen-derived antigens to the host immune system, show remarkable copy-number variation both between and within species. However, the evolutionary forces driving this variation are poorly understood. Here, we use computer simulations to investigate whether evolution of the number of MHC variants in the genome can be shaped by the number of pathogen species the host population encounters (pathogen richness). Our model assumed that while increasing a range of pathogens recognised, expressing additional MHC variants also incurs costs such as an increased risk of autoimmunity. We found that pathogen richness selected for high MHC copy number only when the costs were low. Furthermore, the shape of the association was modified by the rate of pathogen evolution, with faster pathogen mutation rates selecting for increased host MHC copy number, but only when pathogen richness was low to moderate. Thus, taking into account factors other than pathogen richness may help explain wide variation between vertebrate species in the number of MHC genes. Within population, variation in the number of unique MHC variants carried by individuals (INV) was observed under most parameter combinations, except at low pathogen richness. This variance gave rise to positive correlations between INV and host immunocompetence (proportion of pathogens recognised). However, within-population variation in host immunocompetence declined with pathogen richness. Thus, counterintuitively, pathogens can contribute more to genetic variance for host fitness in species exposed to fewer pathogen species, with consequences to predictions from “Hamilton-Zuk” theory of sexual selection.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author summary</title>
<p>Highly polymorphic genes of the Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC) code for proteins responsible for presenting antigens to lymphocytes, thus initiating adaptive immune response. The polymorphism is driven by coevolution with parasites which are selected to evade recognition by MHC proteins. Expressing many MHC molecules could ensure that an individual could present antigens of most pathogen species encountered, but this comes at a cost, such as enhanced negative selection on lymphocytes leading to holes in T-cell receptor repertoire. Our simulations showed that evolution of the number of MHC genes in the genome is driven by a complex interaction between three factors we explored: pathogen richness, the intrinsic cost of expressing additional MHC variants, and pathogen mutation rate. In contrast to verbal arguments, our results indicate that pathogen richness does not always selects for MHC gene family expansion. Taking into account factors other than pathogen richness, in particular costs of expressing additional MHC variants which are still poorly understood, may help explain striking interspecific variation in the number of MHC genes. Counterintuitively, our results also demonstrated that opportunity for selection on immunocompetence should decrease with MHC gene family expansion.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This research was supported by Polish National Science Centre NCN grant UMO-2013/08/A/NZ8/00153 to JR. Computations were partly supported by PL-Grid infrastructure and the Poznań Supercomputing and Networking Center (PCSS) as part of the KDM#312 computing grant. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="4"/>
<table-count count="4"/>
<page-count count="15"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>PLOS Publication Stage</meta-name>
<meta-value>vor-update-to-uncorrected-proof</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Publication Update</meta-name>
<meta-value>2019-05-29</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>. The source code and its documentation can be obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/pbentkowski/MHC_Evolution" xlink:type="simple">https://github.com/pbentkowski/MHC_Evolution</ext-link>. Simulation results can be found in Supplementary File.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Major histocompatibility complex (MHC) genes code for proteins that present pathogen-derived oligopeptides (antigens) to T-cells, thus initiating an adaptive immune response. MHC genes are highly polymorphic, with dozens to hundreds of variants typically segregating in natural populations (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref003">3</xref>]). This extreme polymorphism is thought to result from balancing selection imposed by pathogenic organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref005">5</xref>], and broadly-reported associations between MHC variants and susceptibility to infection are consistent with the role of pathogens in driving MHC evolution (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref003">3</xref>]). Correlative and comparative analyses reported positive associations between parasite community richness and the number of MHC alleles within a population and strength of positive selection on MHC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref006">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref009">9</xref>], providing further support for the role of parasites in driving MHC diversity. However, a meta-analysis based on 112 mammalian species showed that the signs, let alone the strength, of such associations may vary between taxa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref010">10</xref>]. Interpretation of these differences is hindered by the scarcity of theoretical work exploring the impact of parasite richness on MHC diversity.</p>
<p>The majority of MHC research has focused on amino acid sequence polymorphism. However, an aspect of MHC diversity that has received less attention is the number of MHC variants carried by individuals (in this article, we use the term “variants” to describe individual MHC diversity, which is the number of distinct MHC molecules carried by an individual; we prefer this to the term “alleles” often used in MHC literature, as the variants are not alleles in a strict sense, being often distributed over several, functionally equivalent MHC loci). This number of variants carried by individuals is typically much lower than the number found in the population. For example, in humans, there are 6–7 classical MHC loci, allowing for up to 12–14 different variants in a fully heterozygous individual, while the number of currently identified MHC alleles summed across those loci in the human population exceeds 17 000 (IPD-IMGT/HLA Database (8), Release 3.30.0). Given that most alleles segregating in a population are thought to be maintained by selection from pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref003">3</xref>], such discrepancy suggests that any individual’s MHC diversity is unlikely to be sufficient to efficiently respond to the whole spectrum of pathogens a host may encounter. This implies there is some intrinsic cost of expressing too high MHC diversity. One possible mechanism constraining evolution of individual MHC diversity is the deletion of self-reacting T-cells, during negative selection in the thymus. This deletion is likely to intensify with an increased number of expressed MHC variants, leading to a sub-optimal T-cell repertoire[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref011">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref012">12</xref>, but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref013">13</xref> for criticism]. Recently, this mechanism has been supported by the study of Migalska et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref014">14</xref>], who reported a negative correlation between the number of expressed MHC class I variants and T-cell receptor repertoire in the bank vole. However, alternative mechanisms [reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref013">13</xref>], such as increased risk of autoimmunity or the necessity to reach a critical concentration of MHC–peptide ligands at the surface of antigen-presenting cells, can also play a role.</p>
<p>However, there are huge differences among species in the number of MHC loci, ranging from a very few e.g. in chicken [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref015">15</xref>] or humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref016">16</xref>] to dozens in some rodents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref017">17</xref>] or passerine birds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref018">18</xref>]. This raises the question: why should stabilizing selection on individual MHC diversity lead to such different numbers of MHC loci in different species? Answering this question may have broad implications beyond immunogenetics and host-parasite coevolution. For example, it has been suggested that the exceptional evolutionary success of passerines, a family comprising ca. 70% of all bird species, has been facilitated by their supreme immunity due to extremely high numbers of MHC genes they harbour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref019">19</xref>]. Furthermore, evolution of individual MHC diversity may have implications for biological conservation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref020">20</xref>] or speciation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref021">21</xref>].</p>
<p>Similarly to population-level polymorphism, interspecific differences in MHC copy number could be due to differences in the richness of parasites the species is exposed to, although studies which have examined this association are rare. O’Connor et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref022">22</xref>] found that among passerines, the number of unique MHC variants carried by an individual (which should correlate with the number expressed MHC loci) is lower in the Palearctic compared to Africa, which they ascribed to higher parasite species richness in the latter region. Similarly, Minias et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref023">23</xref>] showed that passerine MHC expansion is related to migratory behaviour, likely in response to larger diversity of pathogens encountered by migratory species. In a more direct approach, Eizaguirre et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref024">24</xref>] compared two lakes and two river populations of three-spined sticklebacks <italic>Gasterosteus aculeatus</italic> and found that lake populations, which systematically harboured more parasite species, had more MHC variants per individual. Similarly, Radwan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref025">25</xref>] found a positive relationship between a proxy for parasite load and individual number of MHC variants in ornate dragon lizard <italic>Ctenophorus ornatus</italic> populations inhabiting isolated patches of natural habitat. Interestingly, the authors did not find a significant association of parasite load with population-level allelic MHC richness and speculated that evolution of high copy number may weaken the balancing selection that might otherwise maintain high polymorphism. Similarly, Dearborn et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref026">26</xref>] argued that high individual MHC diversity which arose in Leach’s storm-petrels, <italic>Oceanodroma leucorhoa</italic> by duplication followed by diversification of MHC class II genes should weaken advantage of heterozygosity at MHC. However, there is a lack of theoretical work on how parasite richness simultaneously affects MHC allelic richness and the number of MHC loci.</p>
<p>Here, we aim to fill this gap using computer simulations based on a framework that has previously been shown to be effective in recovering some of the most important features of MHC evolution, such as high polymorphism, frequency-dependent selection, heterozygote advantage and positive selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref027">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref>]. The model simulates interactions of MHC molecules and antigens produced by pathogens by matching strings of bits, which can mutate both in hosts and in parasites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref027">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref>]. Here, we introduce a new feature to the framework to allow duplication and deletion of MHC genes. We then investigate how the number of pathogen species infecting a host affects the evolution of MHC allelic richness and the number of MHC loci.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Pathogen richness affected the number of unique MHC variants per individual (individual number of variants, INV henceforth) in a complex way, shaped by significant interactions with pathogen evolution rate and with the intrinsic cost of expressing more MHC variants (described by cost parameter α) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1007015.t001">Table 1</xref>). Parasite species richness clearly increased INV at lower α, but at higher α there was little change in the INV across the levels of pathogen richness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g001">Fig 1</xref>). There was also a significant pathogen richness × pathogen mutation rate interaction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1007015.t001">Table 1</xref>), with the positive effect of higher pathogen mutation rate observed at low pathogen richness, but declining to zero as pathogen richness increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1007015.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Relationship between the number of pathogen species and the average numbers of unique MHC variants present in a genome of a host under two penalty factors (α = 0.02; 0.08 –panels) and two pathogen mutation rates (μ<sub>A</sub> = 10<sup>−5</sup>; 5 ∙ 10<sup>−5</sup> –legends).</title>
<p>The points represent the mean of the averaged values of simulations in a given parameter set with the 95% CI of the mean (bars).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1007015.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Results of a generalized linear model analysing the effect of intrinsic cost α, pathogen mutation rate and pathogen richness on the average number of MHC variants per individual (INV) per simulation run.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1007015.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">Estimate</th>
<th align="left">SE</th>
<th align="left">t-value</th>
<th align="left">P-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">intercept</td>
<td align="left">8.26</td>
<td align="left">0.44</td>
<td align="left">18.59</td>
<td align="left">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α</td>
<td align="left">-3.99</td>
<td align="left">0.63</td>
<td align="left">6.25</td>
<td align="left">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">mutation rate</td>
<td align="left">-5.10</td>
<td align="left">0.62</td>
<td align="left">-8.12</td>
<td align="left">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">pathogen richness</td>
<td align="left">-0.04</td>
<td align="left">0.01</td>
<td align="left">-3.23</td>
<td align="left">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × mutation rate</td>
<td align="left">-0.13</td>
<td align="left">0.90</td>
<td align="left">-0.14</td>
<td align="left">0.884</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × pathogen richness</td>
<td align="left">0.17</td>
<td align="left">0.02</td>
<td align="left">7.51</td>
<td align="left">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">m. rate × p. richness</td>
<td align="left">0.09</td>
<td align="left">0.02</td>
<td align="left">4.49</td>
<td align="left">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × m. rate × p. richness</td>
<td align="left">0.005</td>
<td align="left">0.03</td>
<td align="left">0.17</td>
<td align="left">0.860</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>The selection acting on host MHC genotypes, as measured by coefficient of variation (CV) in host fitness (which in our simulation was determined solely by host immunocompetence, i.e. the proportion of pathogens recognized), was shaped by the significant interaction between pathogen richness and mutation rate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1007015.t002">Table 2</xref>). CV in host fitness was much higher at higher pathogen mutation rate when pathogen species number was low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g002">Fig 2</xref>). However, the differences between mutation rates declined, as did CV itself, with an increase in pathogen richness.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1007015.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Relationship between the number of pathogen species and coefficient of variation (CV) in host fitness under two penalty factors (α = 0.02; 0.08) and two pathogen mutation rates (μ<sub>A</sub> = 10<sup>−5</sup>; 5 ∙ 10<sup>−5</sup>).</title>
<p>The average CV fitness is normalized for the number of pathogen species and the number of pathogen generations per one host generation. The points represent the mean of the averaged values of simulations in a given parameter set with the 95% CI of the mean (bars).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1007015.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Results of a general linear model analysing the effect of intrinsic cost α, pathogen mutation rate and pathogen richness on the average coefficient of variation in host fitness per simulation run.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1007015.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">Estimate</th>
<th align="left">SE</th>
<th align="left">t-value</th>
<th align="left">P-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">intercept</td>
<td align="right">0.0016</td>
<td align="right">0.0003</td>
<td align="right">4.43</td>
<td align="right">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α</td>
<td align="right">-0.0014</td>
<td align="right">0.0061</td>
<td align="right">-1.85</td>
<td align="right">0.064</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">mutation rate</td>
<td align="right">92.68</td>
<td align="right">10.04</td>
<td align="right">9.22</td>
<td align="right">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">pathogen richness</td>
<td align="right">2.38e<sup>-5</sup></td>
<td align="right">1.44e<sup>-5</sup></td>
<td align="right">-1.64</td>
<td align="right">0.100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × mutation rate</td>
<td align="right">-70.49</td>
<td align="right">170</td>
<td align="right">-0.41</td>
<td align="right">0.678</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × pathogen richness</td>
<td align="right">2.63e<sup>-4</sup></td>
<td align="right">2.26e<sup>-4</sup></td>
<td align="right">1.16</td>
<td align="right">0.245</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">m. rate × p. richness</td>
<td align="right">-2.06</td>
<td align="right">0.40</td>
<td align="right">-5.13</td>
<td align="right">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × m. rate × p. richness</td>
<td align="right">5.56</td>
<td align="right">6.29</td>
<td align="right">0.88</td>
<td align="right">0.377</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>We observed considerable within-population variation in the INV under most scenarios, except when the number of pathogens was very low (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007015.s004">S4 Fig</xref>). The slopes of the relationship between the number of pathogens presented to the immune system and INV increased with pathogen richness, but slopes were generally low at higher pathogen mutation rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g003">Fig 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1007015.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Coefficients of regression of INV on pathogen presentation ability for various combinations of parameters.</title>
<p>For each simulation run we calculated the linear regression between the number of unique MHCs in individuals and the number of infections they were able to present to the immune system. Boxplots (median and quartiles) summarize the slopes of regression for each parametrization.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The number of MHC variants segregating in a host population (PNV henceforth) was driven by the significant three-way interaction between α, pathogen richness and mutation rate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1007015.t003">Table 3</xref>). PNV generally increased with pathogen richness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g004">Fig 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1007015.t003">Table 3</xref>), but the increase was lower at α = 0.08. High pathogen mutation rate increased PNV only at the combination of low α and high parasite richness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Interestingly, at low α, PNV largely reflected INV, whereas at high α PNV increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g004">Fig 4</xref>) despite that INV did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g001">Fig 1</xref>; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007015.s005">S5 Fig</xref> for correlation between INV and PNV).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1007015.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Relationship between the number of pathogen species and the average numbers of unique MHC variants present in a population under two penalty factors (α = 0.02; 0.08 –panels) and two pathogen mutation rates (μ<sub>A</sub> = 10<sup>−5</sup>; 5 ∙ 10<sup>−5</sup> –legends).</title>
<p>The points represent the mean of the averaged values of simulations in a given parameter set with the 95% CI of the mean (bars).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1007015.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Results of a generalized linear model analysing the effect of intrinsic cost α, pathogen mutation rate and pathogen richness on the average number of MHC variants in a population (PNV) per simulation run.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1007015.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">Estimate</th>
<th align="left">SE</th>
<th align="left">t-value</th>
<th align="left">P-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">intercept</td>
<td align="left">15.82</td>
<td align="left">1.53</td>
<td align="left">10.30</td>
<td align="left">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α</td>
<td align="left">-3.723</td>
<td align="left">2.20</td>
<td align="left">1.68</td>
<td align="left">0.091</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">mutation rate</td>
<td align="left">-8.21</td>
<td align="left">2.17</td>
<td align="left">-3.78</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">pathogen richness</td>
<td align="left">0.31</td>
<td align="left">0.05</td>
<td align="left">6.25</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × mutation rate</td>
<td align="left">8.60</td>
<td align="left">3.11</td>
<td align="left">2.76</td>
<td align="left">0.006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × pathogen richness</td>
<td align="left">2.26</td>
<td align="left">0.08</td>
<td align="left">27.74</td>
<td align="left">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">m. rate × p. richness</td>
<td align="left">0.13</td>
<td align="left">0.07</td>
<td align="left">1.84</td>
<td align="left">0.066</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">α × m. rate × p. richness</td>
<td align="left">-0.70</td>
<td align="left">0.11</td>
<td align="left">-6.11</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our model showed that under the Red Queen-like dynamics of MHC evolution, evolution of INV is shaped by a complex interaction of several factors, including pathogen richness, pathogen mutation rate, and the intrinsic cost of expressing many MHC molecules. Verbal arguments [e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref022">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref023">23</xref>] assumed that INV should generally increase with the number of pathogen species. In our simulations, this was the case only under some parameter combinations, and the form of the relationship depended both on the intrinsic costs of expressing additional MHC variants and on pathogen mutation rate. INV consistently increased across the investigated range of parasite species when the intrinsic cost of large MHC repertoire was small. However, with higher values for the cost factor (α), we did not observe such an increase. This shows that high pathogen richness will not necessarily lead to the evolutionary expansion of MHC gene family. Little is known about the nature of the intrinsic costs of MHC expansion, and even less on how taxa differ in this respect, and therefore we have not modelled any particular mechanism underlying these costs in our simulations. The prevalent explanation is that high MHC diversity increases negative selection of self-reactive T-cell receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref011">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref012">12</xref>], impairing efficiency of immune response. This scenario has recently been supported in bank voles, where TCR repertoire has been demonstrated to decrease with the number of MHC class II variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref014">14</xref>]. Under such a scenario, intermediate numbers of MHC variants should result in the most efficient clearing of infections, as has been observed in some empirical studies, including bank voles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref029">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref031">31</xref>]. However, several studies utilising extensive variation in INV present in passerine birds have observed either no such a relationship, or negative associations between INV and infection [e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref032">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref033">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref035">35</xref>]. This suggests that the nature of the intrinsic costs of expressing many MHC variants may differ between passerines and mammals. One possibility is that expressing too many MHC variants does not compromise passerine TCR repertoire in a way similar to that observed in bank voles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref014">14</xref>], allowing rapid expansion of MHC gene family (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g001">Fig 1</xref>). The study of TCR repertoires in birds, and the way they are shaped by MHC, emerges as an attractive target for future studies.</p>
<p>More generally, understanding inter-specific difference in INV will require extensive study of intrinsic costs of expressing additional MHC variants across vertebrate taxa. Our model indicates that higher pathogen richness is unlikely to explain a spectacular expansions of MHC gene family, such as those observed among passerines. Ancestrally, birds have been characterised by a small number of MHC genes, which is still observed in non-passerines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref023">23</xref>]. Our results suggest that expansion to dozens of MHC loci observed among some passerine superfamilies (Sylvioidea, Passeroidea and Muscicapoidea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref023">23</xref>]) would require the number of pathogen in these lineages to be manifold higher compared to basal groups (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g001">Fig 1</xref>), which does not appear biologically feasible.</p>
<p>Another factor which influenced the evolution of INV in our simulations was pathogen mutation rate, the effect of which was most pronounced at low pathogen species numbers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g001">Fig 1</xref>). This pattern was mirrored by variance in host fitness (measured as CV), which was the highest for high pathogen mutation rate combined with low pathogen richness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g002">Fig 2</xref>). Host haplotypes with more MHC variants should be more likely to carry a variant conferring resistance to a parasite, but efficient evasion of MHC-recognition by fast-evolving pathogens could weaken association between INV and pathogen recognition, consistent with our results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Still, efficient parasite evasion should favour novel MHC variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref>], and such variants are more likely to arise when the number of copies in the genome is high. When average number of MHC variants is already high, however, possessing an extra MCH copy provides relatively smaller advantage in terms of potential for beneficial mutation. This may explain why the effect of pathogen evolution rate on INV was observed only at low pathogen richness (where INV was relatively low).</p>
<p>Similarly, high CV in host fitness at low numbers of pathogen species likely results from the fact that a haplotype that is resistant to a prevalent pathogen genotype (of any species) will gain considerable advantage, whereas with many pathogen species resistance to any given pathogen contributes relatively less to fitness. This may explain why CV in host fitness declined with pathogen richness, which may have interesting implications for predictions stemming from Hamilton and Zuk’s (1982) theory of sexual selection. This theory poses that costly epigamic traits, such as long feathers or bright colouration, are subject to mating preferences because they reflect the genetic aspect of resistance to pathogens. At the interspecific level, the Hamilton-Zuk hypothesis predicts that higher risk of parasite infection should enhance sexual selection for extreme values of such epigamic traits, because of increasing contribution of pathogens to genetic variance in fitness (Hamilton and Zuk 1982, Berlanger and Zuk 2014). Paradoxically, our results indicate that while host genetic diversity for resistance (measured by the number of MHC variants segregating in populations) increased, the variance in host fitness decreased. Our results thus indicate that if the number of pathogen species attacking the host is used as a measure of selective pressure from pathogens, the predicted relationship with an elaboration of epigamic traits might be counter-intuitive.</p>
<p>INV was positively correlated with pathogen recognition ability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g003">Fig 3</xref>), as assumed by models of copy-number evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref011">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref012">12</xref>]. Nevertheless, our simulations suggest no such association should be expected when the number of MHC variants in the species is low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Indeed, in root voles <italic>Microtus oeconomus</italic> and guppy fish <italic>Poecilia reticulata</italic>, both characterised by a low to a moderate number of MHC loci (1–3), possessing particular variants has been shown to be more important than the number of expressed MHC loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref036">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref037">37</xref>].</p>
<p>More interestingly, INV was not a good predictor of pathogen recognition efficiency when parasites evolved fast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g003">Fig 3</xref>). As discussed above, fast-evolving parasites are more effective in evading recognition by MHC haplotypes prevalent in a population than slow-evolving ones. In consequence, when parasites evolve fast, possessing a rare-but-resistant MHC variant should have more of an effect on resistance than possessing many variants.</p>
<p>Our simulations revealed tight associations between PNV and INV, but the slope of the associations depends on the intrinsic cost of expressing additional variants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007015.s005">S5 Fig</xref>). At high α, where increase in pathogen richness does not result in a consistent increase in INV, PNV nevertheless increases, resulting in slope &gt;1. At low α, at which INV is more free to evolve, PNV largely reflects INV, which implies that when selection from many parasites favours gene duplication, per-locus polymorphism may change very little. Our results may explain the findings of comparative analyses showing that high pathogen richness is sometimes not found to be associated with MHC allelic richness (a per-locus measure of variation), despite its effect on the rate of molecular evolution at MHC antigen binding sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref009">9</xref>]. Two recent comparative studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref022">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref023">23</xref>] demonstrated that among passerines, individual number of MHC variants decreases with such likely correlates of pathogen richness as latitude or migratory behaviour (although we know of no work directly linking INV to parasite richness). It would be interesting to see if INV could explain PNV in this system, as predicted by our model.</p>
<p>Concluding, our study showed that in general, pathogen richness selects for expansion of MHC gene family, but is unlikely to explain striking inter-specific differences in the number of MHC genes. The latter can be can be modulated both by the rate at which parasites evolve and, probably more critically, on the strength of mechanisms selecting against the high number of copies in the genome. These mechanisms are not well understood, but warrant investigation as potential causal factors underlying differences in MHC genes family sizes between species. In species which evolved high INV under selective pressure from many pathogen species, within population variation in INV can nevertheless be maintained. Despite high variation in INV, host variance in immunocompetence should, according to our model results, be lower in species experiencing selection pressure from higher diversity of parasites.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Simulation outline</title>
<p>The model is based on an approach first used by Borghans et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref027">27</xref>], which simulated interactions between the peptide-binding grooves of MHC molecules and antigens derived from pathogens by aligning two strings of zeros and ones (bitstrings). In our model, each MHC molecule was represented as a 16-bit-long string, which can be thought of as a representation of the amino acids that form pockets implicated in the specificity of antigen binding (there are 12–23 polymorphic sites contacting antigens in human MHC molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref038">38</xref>]). A pathogen was represented by a single 6000-bit long antigenic molecule, which was tested for a match with host MHC at all possible 16-bit epitopes which could be produced from the antigenic molecule. Antigen binding occurred when there was a match in all position of the bit strings representing the peptide bindig groove of MHC molecules and an epitope (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007015.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). Utilising 16 bits, we could simulate 65,536 (2<sup>16</sup>) MHC epitopes. The probability of finding a random 16-bit sub-string (epitope) in a random 6000 bit antigen was approximately 0.084, a number corresponding to the empirical estimates of an MHC molecule binding a random epitope produced by viral pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref039">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref040">40</xref>]. The way we simulated antigens differed from that in Borghans et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref027">27</xref>] and earlier adaptations of their approach [e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref041">41</xref>] in which a single parasite was represented by a set of 20 independent, 16-bit-long antigens, and 7 matched bits were used as a threshold for pathogen recognition. The rationale for simulating a long antigenic molecule and a higher threshold number of matching bits was that it reduced the number of recognition motifs shared between pathogen species, and, additionally, it facilitated further diversification of species-specific motifs by conserving some of them in a species-specific manner (see below). Nevertheless, the probability of binding a random antigen produced by a given pathogen remained broadly consistent with those earlier studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref027">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref041">41</xref>].</p>
<p>Hosts co-evolved with a variable number (2–64) of haploid pathogen species, which, to simplify simulations, had population sizes equal to that of their hosts [as in previous studies, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref>]. Instead of simulating larger pathogen populations (as would have been observed in nature), higher probability of a mutation in large populations was emulated by a higher pathogen mutation rate. There were 10 pathogen generations per one host generation to reflect the fact that pathogens typically have faster generation times than hosts.</p>
<p>The fitness of pathogen haplotypes was proportional to the number of hosts a pathogen successfully infected, and host fitness was proportional to the number of pathogens recognized (see below for details). The next generation of both hosts and pathogens was drawn in proportion to their fitness. The algorithm described above effectively simulates a host-parasite co-evolution system with Red Queen dynamics [see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref> for more details].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Hosts</title>
<p>MHC genes (i.e. 16 bit-long strings) were located on one diploid pair of host chromosomes. The size of the host population was fixed at 1000 individuals. These individuals were exposed to one, randomly chosen individual of each pathogen species. If the infection was successful (i.e. the pathogen was not recognized by any of the host’s MHC genes), the parasite clone could evolve in the host for 10 generations, ecologically excluding infections by other clones of the same species. If the infection was unsuccessful, a new, randomly selected individual attempted an infection in the next pathogen generation; if successful, this pathogen would be allowed to reproduce until 10 pathogen generations were completed. After 10 pathogen generation passed, host fitness was determined. The fitness was proportional to the number of pathogens presented by the host, but we additionally introduced a cost of having additional MHC variants (see below). The cost was introduced to reflect various mechanisms thought to counteract unconstrained expansion of MHC region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref011">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref013">13</xref>]. Our preliminary analyses indicated that the number of MHC loci rapidly increased and did not stabilise even after thousands of generations if no cost was introduced. The host fitness function was calculated according to the equation:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1007015.e001">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1007015.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.e001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M1">
<mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>P</italic> is the number of pathogen species a host recognized (thus avoiding infection), <italic>N</italic> is the number of unique MHC variants in the host’s genome and <italic>α</italic> is the cost factor. The cost factor <italic>α</italic> was selected to achieve a realistic number of unique MHC types in an individual (i.e. from a few to few dozens).</p>
<p>After interactions with pathogens (across 10 pathogen generation cycles), hosts reproduced with probability proportional to their fitness. We have not modelled separate sexes (i.e. our hosts were equivalent to out-crossing hermaphrodites). During reproduction, each of the diploid mates provided one chromosome (selected randomly) to the resulting progeny. Each mating resulted in one offspring, but individuals could be selected for mating more than once (which was more likely for high fitness hosts), and random mating pair selection was repeated until the size of the host population <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub> was restored.</p>
<p>Host chromosomes could undergo two types of mutations: micromutations within the 16-bit string, and copy number mutations. Micromutations were represented by a flip of a single bit with a given probability. This can be thought of as a non-synonymous substitution in an antigen binding site of MHC molecule, which could occur as a non-synonymous mutation, or micro-recombination (the latter may be the predominant mode of mutation at human MHC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref042">42</xref>]). For the sake of consistency with previous simulation studies, in which mutation rates were given as the probability of change in MHC molecule as a whole (replacement of old MHC with a new one), we report the mutation rate per MHC molecule (i.e. 16 bit string), which translates into per bit rate according to the equation:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1007015.e002">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1007015.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.e002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M2">
<mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(2)</label>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>μ</italic><sub><italic>MHC</italic></sub> is the mutation rate per MHC peptide, <italic>μ</italic><sub><italic>bit</italic></sub> is the mutation rate per single bit in the MHC PBR (see also S1 Appendix in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref028">28</xref>]. We used a host mutation rate of 10<sup>−4</sup> per MHC molecule (or 6.25 × 10<sup>−6</sup> per PBR), which appears realistic based on published literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref042">42</xref>]. We also simulated “macromutations” in MHC, which could be thought of as recombination or gene conversion of large fragments of an exon coding for peptide binding groove. Following earlier work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref027">27</xref>], we simulated macromutations by producing random strings of bits. However, mutation mode have not qualitatively affect our results (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007015.s006">S6 Fig</xref>), therefore in the main text we only present results for micromuations.</p>
<p>Copy number of MHC genes could change via duplication or deletion. Duplication was modelled by adding a new copy of the original sequence on the same chromosome, and during deletion, a gene disappeared from the chromosome. However, the algorithm did not allow the number of MHC loci to go below 1 per chromosome. Each gene could be duplicated with probability 10<sup>−3</sup> and deleted with probability 10<sup>−3</sup>, which is higher than direct empirical estimates for large structural variant indels in human genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref043">43</xref>], but was the minimum necessary for the number of copies to stabilise within realistic computing time. Neo- or sub- functionalization of duplicated loci could occur by mutations described above.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Pathogens</title>
<p>We simulated a variable number of haploid pathogen species, with the population size of each species equal to that of the host. A species was initiated as a single antigen, and thus individuals were sharing the evolutionary origin and history within species, but separate species were initialized independently. Because the possible number of distinct 6000 bit antigens is very large (~1.5 × 10<sup>1806</sup>), pathogen species showed little overlap in their antigenic profiles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007015.s002">S2 Fig</xref>; the probability that a random 16-bit-long sub-string will be present in both of two random and independent 6000-bit-long strings equals to ~0.084<sup>2</sup>). We trialled a variant of the simulations in which each pathogen species had a randomly-assigned, species-specific 33% of bits conserved, but this did not result in a different interpretation, and we do not report results from this version. Pathogen haplotypes were selected for reproduction with probability proportional to the number of hosts they had infected. During each of 10 pathogen generations, every host was matched with a randomly selected individual of each pathogen species and the outcome of the infection was evaluated according to the bit-matching rules described above. A pathogen species could infect an individual host only once per host generation. The successful pathogens reproduced parthenogenetically by producing 'clonal' progeny. The progeny could mutate by changing a single bit to the opposite before advancing to the next round of infections. To examine the role of pathogen evolution rate on our results, we simulated two pathogen mutation rates: 10<sup>−5</sup> and 5 × 10<sup>−5</sup><sub>.</sub> These values resulted in the host-parasite coevolution we sought to produce in our simulations. Exploratory analysis showed that at lower pathogen mutation rates than reported above, pathogens were unable to adapt to host genotypes fast enough, whereas at higher mutation rate fitness differences between host genotypes were small, precluding effective co-evolution [see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref044">44</xref>]. For comparison, the influenza virus NS gene mutates at a rate of 1.5 × 10<sup>−5</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref045">45</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Implementation</title>
<p>The model’s program was written in C++14 language, which generates a number of text files of simulation results that were then analysed and plotted using Python scripts. The general scheme of the algorithm is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007015.s003">S3 Fig</xref>. The source code and its documentation can be obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/pbentkowski/MHC_Evolution" xlink:type="simple">https://github.com/pbentkowski/MHC_Evolution</ext-link>. Summaries of the model’s parameters and their values are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1007015.t004">Table 4</xref>. Each combination of parameters was run 20 times, except for the most computationally demanding simulations with 64 pathogens, which were run 10 times.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1007015.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Parameters of the model.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1007015.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center">Parameter description</th>
<th align="center">Symbol</th>
<th align="center">Values</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Host population size (number of individuals)</td>
<td align="center"><italic>N</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub></td>
<td align="center">1000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Pathogen population size of a species (number of individuals) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001"><sup>1</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center"><italic>N</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub></td>
<td align="center">1000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Number of pathogen species in the simulation</td>
<td align="center"><italic>S</italic></td>
<td align="center">1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32, 64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Antigen length (number of bits)</td>
<td align="center"><italic>a</italic></td>
<td align="center">6000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">MHC’s protein-binding region length (number of bits)</td>
<td align="center"><italic>m</italic></td>
<td align="center">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Number of pathogen generations per one hosts generation</td>
<td align="center"><italic>K</italic></td>
<td align="center">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Total number of hosts generation (a.k.a. simulation time)</td>
<td align="center"><italic>G</italic></td>
<td align="center">5000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Probability of mutation in antigen (per site) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup>3</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center"><italic>μ</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub></td>
<td align="center">10<sup>−5</sup>, 5 · 10<sup>−5</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Probability of mutation in MHC PBR (per protein) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn004"><sup>4</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center"><italic>μ</italic><sub><italic>MHC</italic></sub></td>
<td align="center">10<sup>−4</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Probability of deletion of MHC gene <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>2</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center"><italic>μ</italic><sub><italic>del</italic></sub></td>
<td align="center">10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Probability of duplication of MHC gene <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002"><sup>2</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center"><italic>μ</italic><sub><italic>dupl</italic></sub></td>
<td align="center">10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Cost factor for the host selection function</td>
<td align="center"><italic>α</italic></td>
<td align="center">0.02, 0.08</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p><sup>1</sup> total number of pathogen individuals was equal to N<sub>p</sub>· S</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p><sup>2</sup> probability per reproduction event</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn003"><p><sup>3</sup> probability per site (flip of a single bit)</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn004"><p><sup>4</sup> probability of change of the whole MHC (change in any given site)</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>For evaluation purposes, we considered the last 1250 host generation when the dynamics of the host-parasite co-evolution stabilised in term of the numbers of MHC variants in both populations and individuals. For that period and for each run, we calculated mean PNV and mean CV in host fitness (pathogen presentation ability) by averaging it over 1250 latest host generations. To calculate mean INV, we first averaged across individuals at a given time step, and then took the averaged simulated values across 1250 latest host generations. Coefficients of regression of INV on pathogen presentation ability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g003">Fig 3</xref>) was based on a population 'snapshot' at host generation #5000 (the last one), when we recorded detailed information on each host (what genes they had, what pathogen species they presented). These data are available in Supplementary File 1. Results were analysed with linear models, with an average INV, PNV or CV in host fitness as a response variable, and α, pathogen mutation rate and pathogen richness, and their interactions, as fixed factors. Statistical analyses were done in R 3.4.2.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1007015.ref046">46</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007015.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>The schema of pathogen presentation by a single MHC protein binding region (PBR).</title>
<p>A bit string representing MHC PBR (16-bits-long) slides along the bit string representing antigen (6000-bits-long) until it will encounter an identical sub-string (epitope) in the antigen what leads to the presentation of the pathogen. If all of the host’s MHCs will reach the end of the antigen without finding a matching sub-string, the host gets infected with this pathogen species.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007015.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>The schema of the simulation flow.</title>
<p>The inner loop represents 10 pathogen generations during one host generation (the outer loop).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007015.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Similarities of antigen bit-strings measured between pathogen species (at the start and the end of simulations–double plot panels) and within three randomly selected species (at the end of the simulations).</title>
<p>Presented are 4 runs with 64 pathogen species under two penalty parameters (α = 0.02; 0.08) and two pathogen mutation rates (μ A = 10<sup>–5</sup>; 5 ∙ 10<sup>–5</sup>). We used Hamming distance, a measure of similarity where two bit-strings of length n will have 1⁄2 n similar bits if they were generated randomly. At initialisation, a species will consist of a single copy of the same antigen, but species differ from each other.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007015.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.s004" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Examples of distribution of numbers of unique MHC alleles in individuals.</title>
<p>In columns are the two penalty parameters α = 0.02; 0.08 and two pathogen mutation rates μA = 10<sup>–5</sup>; 5 ∙ 10<sup>–5</sup> (see descriptions above the figure). Rows contain runs with the same number of pathogen species (bold numbers on the right). Each panel represents one run that had its mean number of unique MHCs most similar to the mean calculated from all simulation of the same parametrization.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007015.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.s005" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S5 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Correlation between the mean INV and mean PNV in each simulation run under two penalty parameters (α = 0.02; 0.08).</title>
<p>Note, the y-axes have different scales. On the legend dots indicate runs with pathogen mutation rates μA = 10<sup>–5</sup>, triangles μA = 5 ∙ 10–5. Colours correspond to the number of pathogen species in the simulation (see the legend beneath the panels).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007015.s006" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.s006" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S6 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Comparison of simulation results with host macromutations (colour lines) to those with micromutations (grey lines, same as on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007015.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</title>
<p>The points represent the mean of all the averaged values of simulations in a given parameter set with the 95% CI of the mean (bars).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1007015.s007" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007015.s007" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Excel sheet containing simulation results.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Karl Phillips and Magda Migalska for their comments on earlier versions of this manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrigan</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedrick</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Perspective: Detecting adaptive molecular polymorphism, lessons from the MHC</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1707</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. WOS:000185599701200. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14503614</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernatchez</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>MHC studies in nonmodel vertebrates: what have we learned about natural selection in 15 years?</article-title> <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. 150. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14635837</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spurgin</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>. <article-title>How pathogens drive genetic diversity: MHC, mechanisms and misunderstandings</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>277</volume>(<issue>1684</issue>):<fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2009.2084" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2009.2084</ext-link></comment> WOS:000274858500001.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodmer</surname> <given-names>W.</given-names></name> <article-title>Evolutionary significance of the HL-A system</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1972</year>;<volume>237</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">4113158</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zinkernagel</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Enhanced immunological surveillance in mice heterozygous at H-2 gene complex</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1975</year>;<volume>256</volume>(<issue>5512</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>. 3. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1079575</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wegner</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reusch</surname> <given-names>TBH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalbe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multiple parasites are driving major histocompatibility complex polymorphism in the wild</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. ISI:000180926300006. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14635861</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simkova</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ottova</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>MHC variability, life-traits and parasite diversity of European cyprinid fish</article-title>. <source>Evolutionary Ecology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10682-006-0014-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10682-006-0014-z</ext-link></comment> WOS:000239165200006.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gouy de Bellocq</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charbonnel</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Coevolutionary relationship between helminth diversity and MHC class II polymorphism in rodents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1144</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>. ISI:000256687100021. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1420-9101.2008.01538.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1420-9101.2008.01538.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18462313</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garamszegi</surname> <given-names>LZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunn</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasite-mediated evolution of the functional part of the MHC in primates</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. WOS:000285418500022. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1420-9101.2010.02156.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1420-9101.2010.02156.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091566</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winternitz</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minchey</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garamszegi</surname> <given-names>LZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altizer</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sexual selection explains more functional variation in the mammalian major histocompatibility complex than parasitism</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>280</volume>(<issue>1769</issue>):<fpage>2013</fpage>.1605. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2013.1605" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2013.1605</ext-link></comment> WOS:000330322000013.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tarczy-Hornoch</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Austyn</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The optimal number of major histocompatibility complex molecules in an individual</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>10896</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.89.22.10896" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.89.22.10896</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1438295</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woelfing</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Traulsen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milinski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boehm</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Does intra-individual major histocompatibility complex diversity keep a golden mean?</article-title> <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>364</volume>(<issue>1513</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. ISI:000261150600010.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borghans</surname> <given-names>JAM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noest</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Boer</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Thymic selection does not limit the individual MHC diversity</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Immunology</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3353</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. ISI:000187363100014. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/eji.200324365" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/eji.200324365</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14635043</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Migalska</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Major histocompatibility complex class I diversity limits the repertoire of T cell receptors</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2019</year>:<fpage>201807864</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1807864116" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1807864116</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Volk</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallny</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Minimal-Essential-Mhc and an Unrecognized-Mhc—2 Extremes in Selection for Polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>143</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>. WOS:A1995QR14900004. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7558083</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trowsdale</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>The human major histocompatibility complex: Lessons from the DNA sequence</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. WOS:000165768900007. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.genom.1.1.117" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.genom.1.1.117</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701627</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Migalska</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konczal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotlik</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>De novo transcriptome assembly facilitates characterisation of fast-evolving gene families, MHC class I in the bank vole (Myodes glareolus)</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>348</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. WOS:000395902100005. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/hdy.2016.105" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/hdy.2016.105</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27782121</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biedrzycka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Migalska</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zajac</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Extreme MHC class I diversity in the sedge warbler (Acrocephalus schoenobaenus); selection patterns and allelic divergence suggest that different genes have different functions</article-title>. <source>Bmc Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12862-017-0997-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s12862-017-0997-9</ext-link></comment> WOS:000404927000001.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eimes</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Townsend</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jablonski</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiumi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Satta</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Early Duplication of a Single MHC IIB Locus Prior to the Passerine Radiations</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>9</issue>). <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0163456" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0163456</ext-link></comment> WOS:000383893200128.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eimes</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bollmer</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whittingham</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Oosterhout</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname> <given-names>PO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rapid loss of MHC class II variation in a bottlenecked population is explained by drift and loss of copy number variation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1847</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>. WOS:000293910500001. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1420-9101.2011.02311.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1420-9101.2011.02311.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21605219</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malmstrom</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matschiner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torresen</surname> <given-names>OK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Star</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snipen</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Evolution of the immune system influences speciation rates in teleost fishes</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1204</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>. WOS:000384391600015. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.3645" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ng.3645</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27548311</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornwallis</surname> <given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasselquist</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westerdahl</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>The evolution of immunity in relation to colonization and migration</article-title>. <source>Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-018-0509-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/s41559-018-0509-3</ext-link></comment> WOS:000431613500020.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pikus</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minias</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname> <given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whittingham</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of Copy Number at the MHC Varies across the Avian Tree of Life</article-title>. <source>Genome Biology and Evolution</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evy253" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/gbe/evy253</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eizaguirre</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenz</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sommerfeld</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrod</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalbe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milinski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasite diversity, patterns of MHC II variation and olfactory based mate choice in diverging three-spined stickleback ecotypes</article-title>. <source>Evolutionary Ecology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10682-010-9424-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10682-010-9424-z</ext-link></comment> WOS:000289257900005.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuduk</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LeBas</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babik</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasite load and MHC diversity in undisturbed and agriculturally modified habitats of the ornate dragon lizard</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>5966</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. WOS:000346771900006. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.12984" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/mec.12984</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25355141</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dearborn</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gager</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McArthur</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmour</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mandzhukova</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mauck</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gene duplication and divergence produce divergent MHC genotypes without disassortative mating</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>4355</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. WOS:000383343800017. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.13747" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/mec.13747</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27376487</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borghans</surname> <given-names>JAM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beltman</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Boer</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>MHC polymorphism under host-pathogen coevolution</article-title>. <source>Immunogenetics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>732</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. ISI:000189202400002. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00251-003-0630-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00251-003-0630-5</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14722687</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ejsmond</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Red Queen processes drive positive selection on Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC) genes</article-title>. <source>PLoS Computational Biology</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e1004627</fpage>–<lpage>e</lpage>. MEDLINE:26599213. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004627" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004627</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26599213</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wegner</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalbe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reusch</surname> <given-names>TBH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milinski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Parasite selection for immunogenetic optimality</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>301</volume>(<issue>5638</issue>):<fpage>1343</fpage>–. WOS:000185116400029. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1088293" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1088293</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12958352</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madsen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ujvari</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>MHC class I variation associates with parasite resistance and longevity in tropical pythons</article-title>. <source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1973</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. ISI:000241243100025. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1420-9101.2006.01158.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1420-9101.2006.01158.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17040395</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloch</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babik</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bajer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siński</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of an MHC-DRB genotype and allele number on the load of gut parasites in the bank vole <italic>Myodes glareolus</italic></article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zagalska-Neubauer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cichon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sendecka</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulma</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafsson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>MHC diversity, malaria and lifetime reproductive success in collared flycatchers</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2469</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. ISI:000303388300014. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05547.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05547.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22512812</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sepil</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moghadam</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huchard</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheldon</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characterization and 454 pyrosequencing of Major Histocompatibility Complex class I genes in the great tit reveal complexity in a passerine system</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-12-68" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2148-12-68</ext-link></comment> WOS:000310328900001.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biedrzycka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bielanski</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cmiel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solarz</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zajac</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Migalska</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Blood parasites shape extreme major histocompatibility complex diversity in a migratory passerine</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2594</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.14592" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/mec.14592</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">29654666</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname> <given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bollmer</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman-Gallant</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whittingham</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mhc Variation Is Related to a Sexually Selected Ornament, Survival, and Parasite Resistance in Common Yellowthroats</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. ISI:000315894800007. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01799.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01799.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23461319</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloch</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baran</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buczek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Konarzewski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>MHC influences infection with parasites and winter survival in the root vole Microtus oeconomus</article-title>. <source>Evolutionary Ecology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10682-012-9611-1" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10682-012-9611-1</ext-link></comment> WOS:000316639100012.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cable</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herdegen-Radwan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raubic</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Przesmycka</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Immunogenetic novelty confers a selective advantage in host–pathogen coevolution</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>115</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1552</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1708597115" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1708597115</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jardetzky</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gorga</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strominger</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Crystal structure of the human class II MHC protein HLA-DR1 complexed with an influenza virus peptide</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>368</volume>(<issue>6468</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/368215a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/368215a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8145819</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kast</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname> <given-names>RMP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidney</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drijfhout</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kubo</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grey</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Role of Hla-a Motifs in Identification of Potential Ctl Epitopes in Human Papillomavirus Type-16 E6 and E7 Proteins</article-title>. <source>Journal of Immunology</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>3904</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. WOS:A1994NF01800022.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiskopf</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Angelo</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidney</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sette</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>HLA Class I Alleles Are Associated with Peptide-Binding Repertoires of Different Size, Affinity, and Immunogenicity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Immunology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>191</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>5831</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1302101" xlink:type="simple">10.4049/jimmunol.1302101</ext-link></comment> WOS:000328483900009.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ejsmond</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babik</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>MHC allele frequency distributions under parasite-driven selection: A simulation model</article-title>. <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>332</fpage>. Artn 332 ISI:000285339400005. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-10-332" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2148-10-332</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979635</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klitz</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedrick</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>New reservoirs of HLA alleles: pools of rare variants enhance immune defense</article-title>. <source>Trends in Genetics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. WOS:000309505200003. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tig.2012.06.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.tig.2012.06.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22867968</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloosterman</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francioli</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hormozdiari</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marschall</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hehir-Kwa</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdellaoui</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Characteristics of de novo structural changes in the human genome</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>792</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>. WOS:000355565900002. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.185041.114" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/gr.185041.114</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25883321</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ejsmond</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>MHC diversity in bottlenecked populations: a simulation model</article-title>. <source>Conservation Genetics</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parvin</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moscona</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leider</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palese</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Measurement of the mutation rates of animal viruses—influenza-A virus and poliovirus type-1</article-title>. <source>Journal of Virology</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. WOS:A1986D228300022. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3016304</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1007015.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Team RDC</collab>. <source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source>. 3.4.1. ed. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>