<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PBIOLOGY-D-11-00487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001035</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Synopsis</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
        
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Finding Balance in Cortical Networks</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Synopsis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Meadows</surname>
            <given-names>Robin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <addr-line>Freelance Science Writer, Fairfield, California, United States of
                    America</addr-line>
            </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">robin@nasw.org</email></corresp>
        <fn>
          <p>Selected PLoS Biology research articles are accompanied by a synopsis written
                        for a general audience to provide non-experts with insight into the
                        significance of the published work.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e1001035</elocation-id><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Robin Meadows</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative.Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="RA1" issue="3" page="e1001032" related-article-type="companion" vol="9" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001032" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:type="simple">
                <article-title>Membrane Potential-Dependent Modulation of Recurrent Inhibition in
                    Rat Neocortex</article-title>
            </related-article><counts>
        <page-count count="1"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title/>
      <fig id="pbio-1001035-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001035.g001</object-id>
        <caption>
          <title>The amount of inhibition (light and dark blue) received by neocortical
                        pyramidal cells is regulated by the membrane potential of nearby pyramidal
                        cells. The background shows a paired recording from pyramidal cells.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001035.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>No matter what you're doing at any given moment, from walking to talking or even
                sleeping, your brain is doing its own thing. Networks of neurons constantly and
                often spontaneously generate rhythmic electrical activity in the cortex, the
                brain's outermost layer and the seat of judgment, decision making, and other
                higher order functions. These cortical networks contain pyramidal cells that can
                excite inhibitory interneurons, which can in turn decrease the activity of pyramidal
                cells. This interplay of excitation and inhibition generates specific activity
                patterns that are critical to various cortical functions, like working memory and
                attention. However, it is not clear what cellular mechanisms maintain the proper
                balance between these two opposing inputs.</p>
      <p>Now, in this issue of <italic>PLoS Biology</italic>, Yousheng Shu and colleagues
                report that small changes in the electrical properties of pyramidal cells help
                maintain the excitation–inhibition balance that keeps these cortical networks
                humming along. In addition to exciting other neurons via “all or none”
                events (also known as digital mode) called action potentials, pyramidal cells may
                also have another way of communicating within a network. The researchers had
                previously found that pyramidal cells can use a “graded” method (analog
                mode) of exciting their targets via small changes in their membrane potential.
                Because pyramidal cells activate inhibitory interneurons and thus generate recurrent
                inhibition, the researchers asked whether this analog control of membrane potential
                could fine-tune the balance between excitation and inhibition in the cortex.</p>
      <p>The researchers began investigating recurrent network activity by recording activity
                between pairs of nearby pyramidal cells that presumably had an inhibitory
                interneuron between them. They first established that electrically stimulating one
                pyramidal cell in this microcircuit resulted in a late-onset, “slow”
                recurrent inhibition in the second pyramidal cell. They next made a positive
                (depolarizing) shift of the membrane potential by injecting current into the first
                pyramidal cell, and found that this increased the slow recurrent inhibition in the
                second cell. This modulation was sensitive to membrane potential shifts as small as
                5 to 10 mV, considerably less than the shifts required to generate an all-or-none
                action potential.</p>
      <p>What about the other connections in this microcircuit? Knowing that low-threshold
                spiking (LTS) interneurons can mediate slow recurrent inhibition, the authors next
                asked whether modulation of pyramidal cells can directly influence these inhibitory
                cells. Indeed, they found that small membrane potential shifts in pyramidal cells
                can modulate LTS interneuron activity. Importantly, they also observed these analog
                effects for fast spiking interneurons, which mediate “fast” recurrent
                inhibition. Taken together, these findings demonstrate that the membrane potential
                of pyramidal cells modulates recurrent inhibition, which helps balance the
                excitation and inhibition that lend stability to cortical network rhythms.</p>
      <p>Finally, the researchers examined the possible mechanisms of this membrane potential
                effect, and found a role for a type of potassium current called the D-current that
                helps control the duration of axonal action potentials. Blocking the D-current with
                drugs increased the inhibitory effect between pairs of pyramidal cells as well as
                the excitatory effect of pyramidal cells on LTS interneurons. Based on these
                findings, the researchers proposed the following model: depolarization in the first
                pyramidal cell inactivates D-current and so prolongs axonal action potentials,
                thereby enhancing synaptic transmission to the interneuron that then causes more
                inhibition to the second pyramidal cell.</p>
      <p>By showing that membrane potential helps balance excitation and inhibition in
                microcircuits, this work suggests a key role of analog communication in the rhythmic
                activity of cortical networks. Notably, recent work has implicated disruptions in
                the balance of excitation–inhibition in neurological disorders such as
                epilepsy and schizophrenia. Whether analog modulation may prove relevant to such
                diseases, however, is unknown. Many questions must be investigated before such
                possibilities can be addressed, including whether analog modulation applies to all
                cortical circuits, and whether it occurs during behaviorally relevant processes.</p>
      <p>
                <bold>Zhu J, Jiang M, Yang M, Hou H, Shu Y (2011) Membrane Potential-Dependent
                    Modulation of Recurrent Inhibition in Rat Neocortex.
                    doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1001032</bold>
            </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    
  </back>
</article>