<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">pbio.2002439</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Embryology</subject><subj-group><subject>Embryos</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Experimental organism systems</subject><subj-group><subject>Model organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Drosophila melanogaster</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Model organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Drosophila melanogaster</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Experimental organism systems</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal models</subject><subj-group><subject>Drosophila melanogaster</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Eukaryota</subject><subj-group><subject>Animals</subject><subj-group><subject>Invertebrates</subject><subj-group><subject>Arthropoda</subject><subj-group><subject>Insects</subject><subj-group><subject>Drosophila</subject><subj-group><subject>Drosophila melanogaster</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Morphogenesis</subject><subj-group><subject>Morphogenic segmentation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene identification and analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Computer and information sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Network analysis</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic networks</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene expression</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene regulation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Simulation and modeling</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Cytogenetic techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Fluorescent in situ hybridization</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular probe techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Probe hybridization</subject><subj-group><subject>Fluorescent in situ hybridization</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular biology techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular probe techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Probe hybridization</subject><subj-group><subject>Fluorescent in situ hybridization</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dynamic patterning by the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network reconciles long-germ and short-germ segmentation</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Dynamic patterning by the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5588-796X</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>Erik</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Laboratory for Development and Evolution, Department of Zoology, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Desplan</surname>
<given-names>Claude</given-names>
</name>
<role>Academic Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>New York University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">ec491@cam.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>27</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e2002439</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>13</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>7</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Erik Clark</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439"/>
<abstract>
<p><italic>Drosophila</italic> segmentation is a well-established paradigm for developmental pattern formation. However, the later stages of segment patterning, regulated by the “pair-rule” genes, are still not well understood at the system level. Building on established genetic interactions, I construct a logical model of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule system that takes into account the demonstrated stage-specific architecture of the pair-rule gene network. Simulation of this model can accurately recapitulate the observed spatiotemporal expression of the pair-rule genes, but only when the system is provided with dynamic “gap” inputs. This result suggests that dynamic shifts of pair-rule stripes are essential for segment patterning in the trunk and provides a functional role for observed posterior-to-anterior gap domain shifts that occur during cellularisation. The model also suggests revised patterning mechanisms for the parasegment boundaries and explains the aetiology of the <italic>even-skipped</italic> null mutant phenotype. Strikingly, a slightly modified version of the model is able to pattern segments in either simultaneous or sequential modes, depending only on initial conditions. This suggests that fundamentally similar mechanisms may underlie segmentation in short-germ and long-germ arthropods.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author summary</title>
<p>Segmentation in insects involves the division of the body into several repetitive units. In <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos, all segments are patterned rapidly and simultaneously during early development, in a process known as “long-germ” embryogenesis. In contrast, many insect embryos retain an ancestral or “short-germ” mode of development, in which segments are patterned sequentially, from head to tail, over a period of time. In both types of embryo, the patterning of segment boundaries is regulated by a network of so-called “pair-rule” genes. These networks are thought to be quite divergent due to the different expression patterns observed for the pair-rule genes in each case: regularly spaced arrays of transient stripes in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, and dynamic expression within a posterior “segment addition zone” in short-germ insects. However, even in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, a clear understanding of pair-rule patterning has been lacking. Here, I make a computational model of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network and use simulations to explore how segmentation works. Surprisingly, I find that <italic>Drosophila</italic> segment patterning relies on pair-rule gene expression moving across cells over time. This conclusion differs from older models of pair-rule patterning but is consistent with the subtly dynamic nature of pair-rule stripes in real embryos, previously described in quantitative studies. I conclude that long-germ and short-germ segmentation involve similar expression dynamics at the level of individual cells, even though they look very different at the level of whole tissues. This suggests that the gene networks involved may be much more conserved than previously thought.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>Isaac Newton Trust <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.newtontrust.cam.ac.uk" xlink:type="simple">www.newtontrust.cam.ac.uk</ext-link>. Research grant. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bbsrc.ac.uk" xlink:type="simple">www.bbsrc.ac.uk</ext-link>. Genes to Organisms PhD studentship. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="8"/>
<table-count count="0"/>
<page-count count="38"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>PLOS Publication Stage</meta-name>
<meta-value>vor-update-to-uncorrected-proof</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Publication Update</meta-name>
<meta-value>2017-10-09</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. Additional expression data from wild-type embryos are held in the Dryad Digital Repository (DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cg35k" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cg35k</ext-link>).</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Like other arthropods, the fruit fly <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> has a segmented body plan. This segmental pattern is laid down in the embryo during the first 3 hours of development. During this time, the anteroposterior (AP) axis of the blastoderm is progressively patterned down to cellular-level resolution by an elaborate, multi-tiered network of genes and their encoded transcription factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref002">2</xref>]. These genes were first identified in a landmark genetic screen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref003">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref004">4</xref>], and their regulatory interactions have subsequently been dissected by 3 decades of genetic experiments. Along the way, this body of research has revealed many fundamental principles of transcriptional regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref005">5</xref>], and <italic>Drosophila</italic> segmentation remains a central model for developmental systems biology today.</p>
<p>Much of the “heavy lifting” of segment patterning is carried out by the so-called “pair-rule” genes, which make up the penultimate tier of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> segmentation cascade. The pair-rule genes are the first genes to be expressed in spatially periodic patterns in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryo and are collectively responsible for patterning the expression of the “segment-polarity” genes, which organise and maintain segmentally reiterated compartment boundaries termed “parasegment boundaries”. Notably, this involves transducing a double segment pattern of early pair-rule gene expression, in which each set of stripes is offset slightly from the others, into a single-segment pattern of segment-polarity gene expression, in which most genes are expressed in discrete, non-overlapping domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref006">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>].</p>
<p>There are 7 canonical pair-rule genes: <italic>hairy</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref009">9</xref>], <italic>even-skipped</italic> (<italic>eve</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref010">10</xref>], <italic>runt</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref011">11</xref>], <italic>fushi tarazu</italic> (<italic>ftz</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref012">12</xref>], <italic>odd-skipped</italic> (<italic>odd</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref013">13</xref>], <italic>paired</italic> (<italic>prd</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref014">14</xref>], and <italic>sloppy-paired</italic> (<italic>slp</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref015">15</xref>]. 5 of these genes (<italic>hairy</italic>, <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic>) are known as the “primary” pair-rule genes because they are expressed earlier than the 2 “secondary” pair-rule genes, <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref016">16</xref>]. (Note that these terms have a somewhat tortuous history, and older literature will classify the genes differently.)</p>
<p>Each of the primary pair-rule genes is initially patterned by spatial inputs from the upstream tier of transcription factors, encoded by the “gap” genes, which are expressed in broad, overlapping AP domains during cellularisation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref017">17</xref>]. This patterning occurs in an ad hoc manner, with specific combinations of gap factors regulating the expression of particular pair-rule stripes through discrete “stripe-specific” enhancer elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref018">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref021">21</xref>], which act additively with one another. For certain pair-rule genes, such as <italic>eve</italic>, this regulation is sufficient to generate an overall pattern of 7 equally spaced stripes along the future trunk of the embryo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref022">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref024">24</xref>]. For other pair-rule genes, such as <italic>odd</italic>, the gap-driven pattern is irregular and may have missing stripes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref016">16</xref>]. In these cases, the initial patterns are regularised by cross-regulatory “zebra” enhancer elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref025">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref027">27</xref>], which take periodic inputs from other pair-rule factors and yield periodic outputs. Similar zebra elements are responsible for driving the periodic expression of the secondary pair-rule genes, which turn on after the primary pair-rule patterns have refined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref028">28</xref>].</p>
<p>At gastrulation, the segment-polarity genes turn on, activated by a broadly expressed transcription factor, Odd-paired (Opa) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref029">29</xref>], and spatially regulated by the pair-rule genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref031">31</xref>]. Opa activity also “rewires” the regulatory interactions between the pair-rule genes, causing several of their expression patterns to transition dynamically from double- to single-segment periodicity (i.e., from 7 stripes to 14 stripes) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>]. These pair-rule factors (and/or their paralogs) then play roles in the segment-polarity network, which also contains several components of the Wingless (Wg) and Hedgehog signalling pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref033">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref037">37</xref>].</p>
<p>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> gap gene network has been used frequently in recent years as a case study for the application of dynamical systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref038">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref040">40</xref>] and information theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref041">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref043">43</xref>] approaches to developmental patterning, but the pair-rule network has received little system-level attention. Indeed, the most recent models of pair-rule patterning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref044">44</xref>] date from more than 10 years ago. Since these were published, 3 important discoveries have been made about segment patterning, all of which challenge established assumptions about the <italic>Drosophila</italic> segmentation cascade and all of which concern the pair-rule genes in some way. So long as the pair-rule network remains poorly understood, key questions raised by these findings will go unanswered.</p>
<p>The first discovery is from comparative studies in other arthropod embryos. <italic>Drosophila</italic> is a “long-germ” embryo, patterning almost all of its segments simultaneously in the blastoderm prior to germ-band extension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref045">45</xref>]. However, the ancestral mode of arthropod development is “short-germ” embryogenesis, in which segmentation is sequential and coordinated with germ-band elongation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref046">46</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref048">48</xref>]. Orthologs of the pair-rule genes play a key role in segment patterning in all arthropods studied thus far (for example, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref049">49</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref052">52</xref>]), but in short-germ embryos, their expression has been shown to oscillate in a posterior “segment addition zone” throughout germ-band extension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref053">53</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref055">55</xref>]. This periodic dynamic expression indicates that in these organisms, they are either components of or entrained by a segmentation “clock” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref056">56</xref>]. How the expression of the pair-rule genes in long-germ embryos such as <italic>Drosophila</italic> relates to their expression in short-germ embryos (for example, the model beetle, <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic>) is unclear. It is thus not understood how long-germ segmentation was derived from short-germ segmentation, an important evolutionary transition that has occurred multiple times independently within the higher insects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref057">57</xref>].</p>
<p>The second discovery stems from quantitative studies of <italic>Drosophila</italic> segmentation gene dynamics. These studies have revealed that the domains of gap gene expression in the trunk of the embryo shift anteriorly across the blastoderm over the course of nuclear division cycle 14 (cellularisation) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref058">58</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref060">60</xref>]. The shifts are mirrored downstream in similarly shifting expression of the pair-rule stripes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref059">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref061">61</xref>], a finding that is at odds with existing models of segment patterning, which assume these stripes to be static domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref044">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref062">62</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref064">64</xref>]. While we know that these subtle shifts are ultimately driven by feedback interactions within the gap gene network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref038">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref039">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref065">65</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref067">67</xref>], their functional role (if any) remains unclear.</p>
<p>The final key finding relates to the structure of the pair-rule network itself. In a recent paper on the pair-rule network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>], Michael Akam and I showed that many of the regulatory interactions between the pair-rule genes are temporally regulated (by Opa, as described above). We argued that the pair-rule network is best viewed as 2 distinct networks, 1 operating during cellularisation and 1 during gastrulation, each with a specific topology and resultant dynamics. Analysing the “early” (cellularisation-stage) and “late” (gastrulation-stage) pair-rule networks separately should lead to a better understanding of pair-rule patterning and might also reveal why the network shows this bipartite organisation in the first place.</p>
<p>In this paper, I present a new model of the pair-rule system, which incorporates the stage-specific architecture of the pair-rule network. I take the set of identified genetic interactions between the pair-rule genes as a starting assumption, formalise them in a Boolean logical model, and use dynamical simulations to analyse how they collectively lead to complex pattern formation. I find that gap-mediated kinematic shifts are required for correctly phasing the pair-rule stripes, something that proves crucial for downstream segment patterning. I also find that graded Eve activity is not strictly necessary for pair-rule patterning, and I explain the aetiology of the surprisingly severe <italic>eve</italic> null mutant phenotype. Finally, I show that a slightly modified version of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network gains the capacity to pattern in both simultaneous and sequential modes, conceptually reconciling long- and short-germ segmentation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Topology of the pair-rule network</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref> summarises the inferred regulatory interactions between the pair-rule genes. Following Clark and Akam (2016) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>], individual interactions are assigned to distinct “early” and “late” networks, which operate during mid-cellularisation or late cellularisation/gastrulation, respectively. Note that a few regulatory interactions (e.g., repression of <italic>ftz</italic> by Eve) are common to both networks, but the majority are restricted to a single phase of patterning.</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Structure and patterning function of the pair-rule gene regulatory network.</title>
<p>(A) Cross-regulatory interactions between pair-rule genes during cellularisation (left) and gastrulation (right). Hammerhead arrows represent repression; pointed arrows represent activation. The zebra elements of <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>runt</italic> (yellow box) turn on earlier than those of <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> (blue box). <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>runt</italic> are also regulated by gap inputs through their stripe-specific elements (noted by grey dotted lines), but pair-rule inputs are the dominant influence on their patterns by mid-cellularisation (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s008">S1 Text</xref>). The repression of En by Runt in the late network is dotted because, while the odd-numbered <italic>en</italic> stripes are sensitive to Runt, the even-numbered stripes are regulated differently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref068">68</xref>]. Note that the regulation of <italic>runt</italic> in the late network reflects the regulatory logic of the “7-stripe” element rather than that of the “6-stripe” element [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref069">69</xref>]. (B) The template for polarised parasegment boundaries is formed by a repeating pattern of En, Odd, and Slp stripes. Top: whole mount double FISH images (anterior left, dorsal top) showing that <italic>en</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic> are expressed in abutting, mutually exclusive domains. Middle: enlarged views of the stripes. Bottom: schematic of the overall pattern (anterior left). The grey vertical lines indicate the span of an initial pair-rule repeat relative to the final output pattern. Parasegment boundaries (dotted red lines) will form at the interface between En and Slp domains. Scale bars = 100μm. (C) Schematics indicating the number of distinct states that can be specified by static domains of Hairy and Eve expression. Top: Hairy and Eve are both Boolean variables. There are only 4 possible expression states (1: Hairy on, Eve off; 2: Hairy on, Eve on; 3: Hairy off, Eve on; 4: Hairy off, Eve off). Bottom: Hairy is still Boolean, but Eve is now a multilevel variable. Different shades of red represent different levels of Eve activity: low (lightest), medium, or high (darkest). There are now 8 different possible combined expression states of Hairy and Eve. Grey vertical lines are as in (B). (D) Rich positional information can be conveyed by a dynamic signal. Top: Boolean Eve stripes are depicted travelling from posterior to anterior over time (darker red represents a more recent time point). Middle: The Eve profile over time is recorded in binary digits. Bottom: The Eve signal can be decoded into 6 distinct expression domains, aligned with those in (B). Grey lines are as in (B). <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: <italic>en</italic>, <italic>engrailed</italic>; FISH, fluorescent in situ hybridization; <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>fushi tarazu</italic>; <italic>odd</italic>, <italic>odd-skipped</italic>; <italic>prd</italic>, <italic>paired</italic>; <italic>slp</italic>, <italic>sloppy-paired</italic>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Gene regulatory network models represent “intellectual syntheses” of diverse experimental data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref070">70</xref>]. I arrived at the topologies in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref> by carefully analysing relative expression data in tightly staged wild-type embryos and cross-referencing these observations with the large number of mutant and misexpression experiments recorded in the genetic literature (for example, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref064">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref071">71</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref078">78</xref>]). In places where the data were particularly ambiguous, I also re-characterised pair-rule gene expression in select pair-rule mutants in order to pick apart direct versus indirect regulatory interactions. In almost all cases, the interactions in the network diagrams have been previously inferred by multiple sets of researchers; my contribution has been (1) to bring this body of work together into something consistent and relatively complete and (2) to recognise the distinction between the early and late phases of regulation, rather than pooling all interactions into a single network. Most of the evidence and reasoning behind the inferred interactions (and interactions inferred to be absent) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref> are described in Appendix 1 of Clark and Akam (2016) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>]. Additional evidence in favour of the “early” cross-regulatory interactions between the primary pair-rule genes (boxed yellow area in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>, left) is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s008">S1 Text</xref>, based on patterns of pair-rule gene expression in <italic>hairy</italic>, <italic>eve</italic>, and <italic>runt</italic> mutants.</p>
<p>Two things are immediately clear from the network diagrams. First, the direct regulatory interactions between the pair-rule genes are overwhelmingly repressive. This is consistent with a mode of patterning consisting of spatially ubiquitous activation (by maternally provided factors, for example) combined with precisely positioned repression from other segmentation genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref076">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref079">79</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref081">81</xref>]. While certain of the pair-rule factors (e.g., Ftz and Prd) have been shown to quantitatively up-regulate the expression of other pair-rule genes and thus contribute to this background activation in a spatially modulated way [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref082">82</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref084">84</xref>], these effects do not, for the most part, seem to be important for qualitatively determining the spatial pattern of pair-rule gene expression and so have been omitted from the diagram. Most described incidences of one pair-rule gene genetically activating another pair-rule gene are instead indirect (i.e., mediated by the direct repression of another repressor).</p>
<p>Second, the 2 networks have very different structures, presumably reflecting the different patterning function each must perform. During mid-cellularisation, pair-rule gene cross-regulation is responsible for refining many of the pair-rule stripes and standardising their phasing relative to other pair-rule stripes, resulting in a regular repeating pattern of double-segment periodicity. This is carried out by the early network, which is sparse, composed of unidirectional regulatory interactions, and has no feedback loops. Two of the pair-rule genes, <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>hairy</italic>, are patterned by gap factors rather than other pair-rule factors and so represent “input-only” factors to the network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref016">16</xref>]. The remaining primary pair-rule genes (<italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic>) do receive extensive gap inputs at early stages of cellularisation, but, by mid-cellularisation, their patterns are largely specified by other pair-rule genes (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s008">S1 Text</xref>). (Note, however, that some aspects of the <italic>ftz</italic> pattern cannot be explained by pair-rule inputs alone, see Appendix 2 of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>].) The secondary pair-rule genes turn on later (<italic>prd</italic> at mid-cellularisation and <italic>slp</italic> towards the end of cellularisation) and are patterned by primary pair-rule genes. Overall, the early network has a hierarchical structure, in which Eve and Hairy convey positional information derived from the gap factors to the remaining primary pair-rule genes and eventually to the secondary pair-rule genes.</p>
<p>The late network, on the other hand, is extremely dense and consists largely of mutually repressive pairs of interactions. It is responsible for converting a double-segmental pattern of overlapping stripes into a segmental pattern of discrete segment-polarity fates. This is the final step in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> “segmentation cascade” and completes the transition from the analog (graded) positional information carried by the maternal and gap gene products to the essentially digital positional information carried by the segment-polarity genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref064">64</xref>]. The numerous positive (i.e., double-negative) feedback loops within the late network are consistent with it acting like a multi-stable switch, individual segment-polarity fates representing attractor states towards which the system will rapidly converge.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Pair-rule patterning and positional information</title>
<p>As described above, gap inputs and the early pair-rule network combine to establish a repeating double-segmental pattern of pair-rule gene expression. The positional information within this pattern is then converted into a stable output pattern of segment-polarity states by the late network. Each initial double-segment repeat is about 7–8 nuclei wide, and each specified segment will consist of at least 3 distinct states characterised by the expression of <italic>engrailed</italic> (<italic>en</italic>), <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1B</xref>). The <italic>en</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> stripes are about 1 nucleus wide, while the <italic>slp</italic> stripes are about 1–2 nuclei wide. Parasegment boundaries form wherever En and Slp domains abut, while Odd provides a buffer zone that preserves the AP polarity of each segment. (This tripartite segment pattern conforms to prescient theoretical predictions made by Hans Meinhardt in the early 1980s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref062">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref085">85</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref086">86</xref>].) It is crucial that all 3 domains are specified within each segment—and that they are in the correct order—because patterning defects such as boundary losses, ectopic boundaries, and/or polarity reversals arise when the pattern is perturbed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref076">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>].</p>
<p>The extremely high resolution of the final segmental output pattern implies that the initial double segment pattern established by the early pair-rule network must contain sufficient positional information to allow almost every nucleus to be distinguished from its immediate neighbours. We are thus left with 2 questions. First, how does the early network establish a situation in which the different nuclei within a double-segment repeat each expresses a unique combination of pair-rule factors? Second, how exactly is this code “read” by the late network? (Or, in other words, which sets of initial conditions will result in a cell following an expression trajectory that ends at, for example, stable <italic>en</italic> expression, rather than stable <italic>odd</italic> or stable <italic>slp</italic>?)</p>
<p>In later sections, I address these questions by simulating and analysing the networks shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>. However, before getting into specifics of how particular genes are regulated and expressed, it is worth considering a more fundamental question: where is the positional information coming from in the first place? The topology of the early network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>, left) implies that, to a first approximation, all the positional information in the final pattern must trace back to the expression patterns of just 2 factors, Eve and Hairy. Boolean (ON/OFF) combinations of Eve and Hairy would only be sufficient to specify 4 different domains within each double-segment repeat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1C</xref>, top), whereas the real output pattern consists of at least 6 distinct domains (i.e., En, Odd, Slp, En, Odd, Slp). How is it possible that just 2 independent spatial signals are able to give rise to such a high-resolution final output?</p>
<p>One potential answer is that stripes of Eve and/or Hairy might carry quantitative information that permits them to convey more than 2 “states” within the positional code. Since the early 1990s, this idea has been applied to the graded margins of the early Eve stripes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref075">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref088">88</xref>]. These stripes have been proposed to act as local morphogen gradients, repressing different target genes at different concentration thresholds and thus differentially positioning their respective expression boundaries. Current models of pair-rule patterning rely on the assumption that there are 4 functionally distinct levels of Eve activity across an Eve stripe (from the centre to the edge: HIGH, MEDIUM, LOW, and OFF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref044">44</xref>]. These different levels would provide cellular-level resolution within each double-segment repeat and, combined with information from the Hairy stripe, allow each nucleus to be uniquely specified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1C</xref>, bottom).</p>
<p>While a given concentration of Eve protein may well repress its various targets with different efficacies, it is unlikely that segment patterning relies significantly upon this mechanism, for 3 main reasons. First, for the model to be viable, the Eve stripes would need to provide an accurate and precise set of positional signals within each double-parasegment repeat, i.e., the Eve stripes would have to be extremely regular and all share the same shape and amplitude. However, more posterior Eve stripes show significantly lower expression levels than more anterior Eve stripes throughout most of cellularisation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref059">59</xref>]. Furthermore, pair-rule transcripts are apically localised, and therefore pair-rule gene expression becomes effectively cell autonomous soon after membrane invagination begins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref089">89</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref090">90</xref>]. This means that, unlike for the gap genes (whose transcripts remain free to diffuse between neighbouring nuclei), for <italic>eve</italic>, there is little or no spatial averaging to buffer the high intrinsic noise of transcription [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref091">91</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref092">92</xref>]. This reduces the precision of the Eve signal and thus its capacity to reliably convey analog information.</p>
<p>Second, the morphogen model also requires the readout of the Eve signal to be very sensitive; i.e., <italic>eve</italic> target genes would have to reliably discriminate between different Eve expression levels and pattern their expression boundaries accordingly. However, it is not clear that this actually occurs within the embryo—for example, the model proposes that graded Eve stripes result in offset boundaries of the Eve targets <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic>, but recent observations indicate that these offsets are in fact produced by other mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>].</p>
<p>Third, the morphogen model does not explain the full severity of the <italic>eve</italic> null mutant phenotype, in which aberrant expression patterns are seen even in regions that would be outside the Eve stripes in wild-type embryos. Neither does the morphogen model explain the patterning robustness of <italic>eve</italic> heterozygotes, in which halving Eve expression levels fails to perturb the overall pattern of segment-polarity domains.</p>
<p>How, then, might the spatial resolution of the segment pattern be explained if not by an Eve morphogen gradient? Traditional models of <italic>Drosophila</italic> segmentation are essentially static: each tier of segmentation gene expression provides a single set of spatial signals, which is transduced into a new set of spatial signals by the tier below. This simplifies the real situation in the embryo, in which both gap and pair-rule expression domains shift subtly from posterior to anterior over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref059">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref093">93</xref>]. Explicitly considering these temporal aspects of segmentation gene expression suggests an alternative segment patterning mechanism: using the temporal dynamics of a relatively coarse pair-rule signal to provide high-resolution spatial information across each pattern repeat.</p>
<p>A signal that varies over time can be used to convey an arbitrary quantity of information, even if each reading of that signal provides very little (think of Morse code or binary storage). The <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>hairy</italic> stripes continue to be regulated by gap inputs throughout most of cellularisation and therefore shift across nuclei in concert with the gap domains. This means that, rather than each nucleus having to deduce its position from a single level of, e.g., Eve protein (as in the morphogen model), the nucleus actually experiences a temporal sequence of Eve protein levels. Strikingly, an overall shift of just 2 nuclei would be theoretically sufficient for a Boolean Eve stripe to, on its own, specify the positions of all 6 segment-polarity domains within a double-segment repeat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1D</xref>).</p>
<p>This kind of mechanism would, however, rely on the downstream targets of Eve and Hairy being able to decode a temporal sequence of Eve/Hairy expression and convert it into an appropriate segment-polarity fate. In the following sections, I carry out simulations and analysis of the network shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref> and, based on the results, argue that the cross-regulatory interactions between the pair-rule genes function to achieve exactly this task.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>A simple model of the pair-rule system</title>
<p>In order to investigate how pair-rule patterning works, I used the networks shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref> to create a toy model of the pair-rule system and then simulated pair-rule gene expression across an idealised 1-dimensional tissue. In this section, I briefly describe the structure and assumptions of the modelling approach; a full description of the model plus details of all simulations are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s009">S2 Text</xref>. (Source code for running the simulations is available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s010">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s011">S2</xref> Files, while pair-rule networks in SBML-qual format are available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s012">S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s013">S4</xref> Files).</p>
<p>The genes whose regulation I model explicitly are the 7 pair-rule genes, plus <italic>en</italic>, whose product plays a key role in regulating late pair-rule gene expression. I have also included 4 inputs that are extrinsic to the system: 2 temporal signals, Caudal (Cad) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref094">94</xref>] and Opa, and 2 signals to represent the positional information provided by the gap system, “G1” and “G2”. Cad represses the secondary pair-rule genes during early stages of patterning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>], while Opa turns on midway through patterning and triggers the switch from the early network to the late network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>]. G1 is responsible for patterning the <italic>hairy</italic> pair-rule stripes while G2 is responsible for patterning the <italic>eve</italic> pair-rule stripes. G1 and G2 do not represent specific gap factors but are instead an abstraction of the spatial inputs (i.e., stripe boundary locations) provided by the gap system as a whole.</p>
<p>Each gene in the system is represented by a Boolean variable, and its control logic is formalised using logical rules (essentially equivalent to the “logical equations” used in Sanchez and Thieffry [2003] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref044">44</xref>] or the “vector equations” used in Peter et al. [2012] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref070">70</xref>]). For example, if Opa is OFF (early network), <italic>odd</italic> is expressed only if both Hairy and Eve are also OFF, while if Opa is ON (late network), <italic>odd</italic> expression relies on all of Runt, En, and Slp being OFF (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>). In most cases (apart from, e.g., activation of <italic>en</italic> by Ftz or Prd), gene activation is assumed to be driven by some ubiquitous background factor(s) and is not explicitly included in the model.</p>
<p>The network simulation proceeds by discrete time steps, with expression output at time point <italic>t</italic> + 1 calculated from the state of the system at time point <italic>t</italic>. Because of the speed and dynamicity of segment patterning, time delays associated with protein synthesis and protein decay imply that protein and transcript expression domains for a given gene will often be non-congruent within the <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryo. This is likely to be significant for patterning, and I therefore approximate this effect by adding simple time delay rules into the simulation. Each gene has associated “synthesis delay” and “decay delay” parameter values <italic>s</italic> and <italic>d</italic>, both of which are integers representing a certain number of time steps. (Once a gene turns on, transcript will be present immediately, but protein will only appear <italic>s</italic> time steps later. Similarly, once a gene turns off, transcript will disappear immediately, but protein will only disappear after another <italic>d</italic> timesteps have elapsed.) For parsimony (and consistent with real expression kinetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref082">82</xref>]) all pair-rule genes and <italic>en</italic> are assigned the same delay value, which applies to both <italic>s</italic> and <italic>d</italic>. The specific value of this delay is fairly arbitrary, because the ratio between different delays is what affects how the system behaves, but I have chosen this value to be 6. Given that the half-life of <italic>ftz</italic> RNA during cellularisation is 7 minutes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref079">79</xref>], this means that each time step in the simulation can be thought of as representing on the order of 1 minute of real developmental time. The time delays of the other components in the network (Cad, Opa, G1, and G2) are assigned appropriate values relative to this timescale, so that their simulated behaviour roughly approximates their spatiotemporal expression in a real embryo.</p>
<p>The simulation is set up to occur across a row of 20 “cells”, an idealised representation of the AP axis. This row of cells is not meant to correspond to a specific region of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryo but rather to be generally representative of patterning within the main trunk (i.e., pair-rule stripes 3–6), in which pair-rule genes are not additionally affected by cephalic or terminal factors. Each cell within this “tissue” is simulated independently, starting from a specific set of initial conditions. (As mentioned above, pair-rule transcripts are apically localised, and therefore the cross-regulation between the pair-rule genes is likely to be effectively cell autonomous from roughly mid-cellularisation onwards.)</p>
<p>The starting conditions for each cell usually involve specifying the appropriate expression of G1 and G2, setting Cad to ON, and setting all other genes to OFF. G1 and G2 are initialised with patterns that are offset by 2 cells and repeat every 8 cells, meaning that the <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>eve</italic> stripes specified by these inputs will partially overlap and exhibit a double-segment periodicity, as in real embryos. Gap inputs into <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic> are omitted, meaning that their early expression is organised entirely by the spatial inputs from Hairy and Eve. As the simulation proceeds, Cad protein will disappear, allowing <italic>prd</italic> to turn on [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>], followed by <italic>slp</italic>. (Note that we do not currently know how exactly the timing of <italic>slp</italic> expression is controlled, so in order to reproduce the timing observed in the embryo, <italic>slp</italic> expression in the simulation requires Prd expression to already be present.) Shortly afterwards, Opa protein will turn on, switching the control logic of pair-rule gene expression to the late network and causing pair-rule gene expression to eventually reach a final, stable state. After the switch to the late network, the gap factors and Hairy cease to regulate the pair-rule genes and then fade away, as in real embryos.</p>
<p>Note that the model just described, which is Boolean, deterministic, and uses discrete time steps, is not designed to capture the full complexity of the embryo (in which gene expression is, of course, quantitative, stochastic, and continuous). Rather, it represents a tool to expose the key mechanisms of patterning—and to delineate how much of what is observed in the embryo follows simply from the qualitative structure of the regulatory network. It also provides an important sanity check of the inferences that led to that structure being proposed in the first place.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Posterior-to-anterior expression shifts are crucial for pair-rule patterning</title>
<p>Using the model described above, I first simulated a scenario in which gap gene inputs and hence the pair-rule stripes of Hairy and Eve are completely static. The results are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s022">S9 Movie</xref> and are summarised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2A</xref>. Under these conditions, the positional information provided by Hairy and Eve is essentially equivalent to the situation diagrammed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1C</xref> (bottom) and thus has no possibility of generating the correct segmental output. Unsurprisingly, the simulation does a bad job of recapitulating the patterns of pair-rule gene expression seen in real embryos (see below). In particular, at the end of the simulation, there is no <italic>en</italic> expression anywhere at all, and neither <italic>odd</italic> nor <italic>slp</italic> is expressed in a segmental pattern.</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation output from a Boolean model of the pair-rule network.</title>
<p>Pair-rule gene expression patterns generated by simulating a Boolean model of the pair-rule network, assuming static “gap” inputs (A), dynamic “gap” inputs (B), or dynamic “gap” inputs and no Eve expression (C). Original simulations are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s022">S9</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s024">S11</xref> Movies. In each panel, the horizontal axis represents the anteroposterior (AP) axis (anterior left), while the vertical axis represents the different gene products that might be expressed in a given “cell” (column). Pale colours represent active transcription; dark colours represent active protein (see colour key at top right). Grey vertical lines indicate the span of an idealised double-segment repeat of 8 “cells”. The same 7 time points (T20–T56) are shown for each simulation. Cad turns off between the first (T20) and second (T26) panels (dashed lines), derepressing <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic>. Opa turns on between the third (T32) and fourth (T38) panels (dashed lines), causing a switch from the early to the late network logic. Parasegment boundaries (black vertical lines at T56, located between abutting domains of Slp and En) are only produced by the simulation with dynamic gap inputs (B). <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: Cad, Caudal; Opa, Odd-paired; <italic>prd</italic>, <italic>paired</italic>; <italic>slp</italic>, <italic>sloppy-paired</italic>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>I then simulated a scenario in which the gap gene inputs and hence the Hairy and Eve stripes shift anteriorly over time. Given that the shift rate in real embryos is of the same order as the synthesis and decay rates of the segmentation gene products, I set the rate of these shifts to be such that the time taken for an expression domain to shift anteriorly by 1 cell is equal to the synthesis/decay delay parameter value of the pair-rule genes, i.e., 6 time steps (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s009">S2 Text</xref>).</p>
<p>The simulation output for this scenario is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s023">S10 Movie</xref> and summarised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref>. Even though the pair-rule network is unchanged and the Hairy and Eve stripes retain the same pattern and relative phasing as for the static simulation, the model now performs completely differently. Qualitative aspects of actual pair-rule gene expression (i.e., whether the expression domains of each pair of genes are congruent, overlapping, abutting, or separate, and the way this changes over time) are recapitulated remarkably well. For all pair-rule genes except <italic>prd</italic>, the match between the model output and the real spatiotemporal dynamics of gene expression is about as close as could be achieved by a simple, Boolean model—a few examples are highlighted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g003">Fig 3</xref>, and the full set of comparisons is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s001">S1 Fig</xref>. For <italic>prd</italic>, the real spatiotemporal expression profile is only partially recovered: the early pair-rule stripes are positioned correctly but do not refine correctly at later stages—they narrow rather than split, meaning that alternate segmental stripes are missing from the final pattern (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s003">S3 Fig</xref>). However, the <italic>prd</italic> domains missing from the simulation are not actually required for segment boundary patterning in real embryos (they are not reflected in the larval cuticles of <italic>prd</italic> mutants, although they do have minor effects on <italic>wg</italic> expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref095">95</xref>]). Accordingly, the simulation still generates the correct final segmental output: a repeating pattern of En, Odd, Slp x2, En, Odd, Slp x2.</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>The “dynamic” simulation accurately recapitulates the spatiotemporal expression of the pair-rule genes.</title>
<p>Left: false-coloured double FISH images for selected combinations of pair-rule gene transcripts at 4 different stages. Each panel shows a lateral view of stripes 2–6 (anterior left, dorsal top). Scale bars = 50 μm (rightmost panels use a slightly lower magnification due to tissue rearrangements). Additional expression combinations are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s001">S1 Fig</xref>, while uncropped views of the embryos are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s002">S2 Fig</xref>. Right: simulated transcriptional output for these pairs of genes at 4 different time points (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref>). The earliest time point of the simulated expression (T20) is representative of the leftmost panels of real expression (mid-cellularisation), and so on. The simulation output is generally very similar to the real expression patterns, with 2 main differences related to the discrete nature of the simulations. (1) Real gene expression domains fade over time rather than turning off instantaneously (e.g., compare <italic>hairy</italic> in A′–A″ to the simulated <italic>hairy</italic> expression at T32/T44/T56). (2) Qualitative expression pattern changes may occur gradually between late cellularisation and early gastrulation (e.g., <italic>eve</italic> expression in B–B″/C–C″ or <italic>odd</italic> expression in C–C″/E–E″) rather than instantaneously, as between T32 and T44. (A) <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>eve</italic> pair-rule stripes partially overlap during cellularisation. At gastrulation, <italic>hairy</italic> expression fades away, while the <italic>eve</italic> stripes narrow from the posterior and then also fade. (B) <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> pair-rule stripes are at first expressed in complementary patterns. Starting from late cellularisation, they both narrow from the posterior (<italic>eve</italic> more than <italic>ftz</italic>). <italic>eve</italic> expression later fades away, while <italic>ftz</italic> persists. (C) <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> pair-rule stripes are at first expressed in complementary patterns before both narrowing. <italic>odd</italic> secondary stripes emerge at the posterior of the narrowing <italic>eve</italic> domains, which then fade away, leaving segmental stripes of <italic>odd</italic>. (D) <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> pair-rule stripes partially overlap throughout cellularisation. At gastrulation, <italic>runt</italic> secondary stripes emerge to the posterior of the narrowing <italic>ftz</italic> stripes. Later, the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes refine from the posterior, and the overlaps with <italic>ftz</italic> are lost. (E) The <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> stripes are fairly congruent during cellularisation. At gastrulation, both narrow from the posterior, and the <italic>odd</italic> secondary stripes intercalate between them. Over the course of patterning, their anterior boundaries also become offset from one another. (F) The <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes emerge later than the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes and are offset slightly from their posterior boundaries. (The simulated <italic>slp</italic> domains are wider than the real <italic>slp</italic> domains.) At gastrulation, secondary stripes of both genes emerge between the primary stripes (the widths of the simulated <italic>slp</italic> stripes are now appropriate). The expression patterns become largely congruent, except at the posteriors of the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes. These differences resolve later, when the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes narrow. (G) The <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes emerge later than the <italic>ftz</italic> primary stripes and partially overlap with them. At gastrulation, the secondary <italic>slp</italic> stripes emerge just anterior to the <italic>ftz</italic> domains, which narrow from the posterior, losing the overlaps with the <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes. (H) As for (G), the <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes partially overlap the <italic>odd</italic> primary stripes, and these overlaps are later lost by the <italic>odd</italic> stripes narrowing from the posterior. The secondary stripes of <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> intercalate between the primary stripes and abut one another. <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>even-skipped</italic>; FISH, fluorescent in situ hybridization; <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>fushi tarazu</italic>; <italic>odd</italic>, <italic>odd-skipped</italic>; <italic>slp</italic>, <italic>sloppy-paired</italic>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>These results tell us a number of things. First, it is not strictly necessary to invoke morphogen gradients in order to account for <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule patterning. Second, posterior-to-anterior shifts of the Hairy and/or Eve stripes appear to be crucial for properly patterning the other pair-rule genes, and analysing the different behaviour of the static and shifting simulations should reveal exactly why. Third, the model as formulated is too simple to explain important aspects of the <italic>prd</italic> expression profile. Additional complexities that influence <italic>prd</italic> expression in real embryos could include (1) additional spatial or temporal regulatory inputs missing from the model, (2) quantitative information from existing spatial or temporal inputs that is not captured by the use of Boolean variables, or (3) differential synthesis/degradation rates of particular segmentation gene products not accounted for by the equal time delays assumed by the model. At least the first option seems to apply, as I have recently discovered that the Sox transcription factor Dichaete [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref096">96</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref097">97</xref>] also affects <italic>prd</italic> regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>How and why do the shifts affect patterning?</title>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Dynamic patterning of the early pair-rule stripes</title>
<p>First, let us consider the earliest phase of the simulations (time points 0–24, corresponding to mid-cellularisation in a real embryo), in which double-segmental stripes of the primary pair-rule genes <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic> are patterned by the early pair-rule network. Each of these genes is repressed by 2 other pair-rule factors: <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> by Hairy and Eve, and <italic>runt</italic> by Hairy and Odd (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>, left). In the static simulation, this system rapidly reaches steady state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4A</xref>): <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> are expressed in cells that express neither Eve nor Hairy, while <italic>runt</italic> is restricted to cells that don’t express Hairy but do express Eve (and hence don’t express Odd). This scenario is significantly different from the expression patterns of these genes in a real embryo, in which there are more overlaps between the various stripes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4C</xref>). For example, <italic>runt</italic> expression overlaps with <italic>ftz</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4Cg</xref>) and <italic>odd</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4Cc</xref>) as well as <italic>eve</italic>, while <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> overlap slightly with <italic>hairy</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4Cd and 4Ce</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Dynamic patterning of the primary pair-rule genes.</title>
<p>(A) Regulatory schematic showing the predicted phasing of the primary pair-rule stripes during cellularisation, assuming static, partially overlapping domains of Hairy and Eve. Pale colours represent transcript domains; intense colours represent protein domains; hammerhead arrows represent repressive interactions; grey vertical lines indicate the span of a double-segment pattern repeat. Cross-regulatory interactions are from the early network (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>, left). For simulation output, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s014">S1 Movie</xref>. (B) Regulatory schematic showing the predicted phasing of the pair-rule stripes during cellularisation, assuming dynamic, partially overlapping domains of Hairy and Eve. <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>eve</italic> domains shift anteriorly over time, resulting in offsets between transcript and protein domains. Colours, etc., as for (A). For simulation output, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s015">S2 Movie</xref>. (C) Comparisons between real and predicted phasings of the primary pair-rule stripes. Double FISH images show lateral views of stripes 2–6 (anterior left, dorsal top) in mid-cellularisation stage embryos. In the bottom half of each image, the 2 channels have been thresholded, making regions of overlap easier to see. Scale = 50 μm. Diagrams to the right of each image show the stripe phasings predicted by static (top) or shifting (bottom) gap inputs, respectively (compare A and B). For panels (A) and (B), the 2 models predict the same relative pattern. In all other panels, the models predict different relative patterns. (D) Simultaneous visualisation of <italic>eve</italic> transcript (magenta) and Eve protein (green) in embryos at 4 different stages. Rightmost panels show a ventrolateral view; all other panels show lateral views. Upper panels show whole embryo views; lower panels show enlarged views of stripes 2–6. In stripes 3 onwards, the protein domains lag behind the transcript domains until late gastrulation, indicating that the anterior boundaries of the <italic>eve</italic> stripes shift anteriorly until early gastrulation. In stripe 2, the anterior boundary stabilises significantly earlier. Scale = 50 μm. <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>even-skipped</italic>; FISH, fluorescent in situ hybridization.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>These overlaps represent unstable combinations of gene expression (Hairy represses <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> while Odd represses <italic>runt</italic>), but they are nevertheless present throughout the “early” phase of the second simulation, which incorporates stripe shifts. This is because the dynamic inputs from Hairy and Eve mean that primary pair-rule gene expression is not permitted to reach stable state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4B</xref>), and therefore a fraction of cells within the tissue will be in these transient states at any given point in time. Note that although the gene expression within each cell is constantly changing over the course of the simulation, the overall pattern of stripes remains constant once established, moving across the tissue like an elaborate Mexican wave.</p>
<p>Specifically, the additional overlaps seen in the second simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4B</xref>) arise because the combination of shifting dynamics with time delays for protein synthesis/decay means that domains of active transcription do not necessarily reflect domains of protein activity, and vice versa. If a pair-rule stripe is shifting anteriorly, the protein distribution of that stripe should lag behind the transcript distribution, a prediction I have verified by comparing <italic>eve</italic> transcript and Eve protein expression patterns within individual embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4D</xref>). After a gene turns on at the anterior edge of a stripe, there will be a delay before the protein appears and represses its targets, resulting in small transcriptional overlaps between repressors and their targets (i.e., anterior <italic>hairy</italic>/posterior <italic>ftz</italic>, anterior <italic>hairy</italic>/posterior <italic>odd</italic>, and anterior <italic>odd</italic>/posterior <italic>runt</italic>). Similarly, after a gene turns off at the posterior edge of a stripe, there will be a delay before the protein disappears and its targets are derepressed, resulting in small transcriptional gaps between repressors and their targets (i.e., posterior <italic>eve</italic>/anterior <italic>odd</italic>, posterior <italic>hairy</italic>/anterior <italic>runt</italic>, and posterior <italic>eve</italic>/anterior <italic>ftz</italic>). The exact size of the gaps and overlaps depends on the relationship between the speed of the expression shifts and the length of the time delays involved in protein synthesis and decay: faster relative shift rates will result in larger gaps and overlaps, while slower relative shift rates will result in a pattern closer to the static scenario (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s006">S6 Fig</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s014">S1</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s018">S5</xref> Movies).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Dynamic patterning of the odd-numbered parasegment boundaries</title>
<p>The next phase of the simulations (time points 25–36, corresponding to late cellularisation in a real embryo) is when the secondary pair-rule genes turn on in double-segment patterns and prepattern the odd-numbered (Prd-dependent) parasegment boundaries. These boundaries rely on setting up offset posterior boundaries of <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> expression: <italic>en</italic> is activated by Prd but repressed by Slp, thus resulting in narrow stripes of <italic>en</italic> expression posteriorly abutting each of the <italic>slp</italic> pair-rule stripes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s004">S4 Fig</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Dynamic patterning of the odd-numbered parasegment boundaries.</title>
<p>(A) Regulatory schematic of gene expression at the odd-numbered parasegment boundaries. Domains of Slp, Prd, and Eve expression (dark colours) pattern segment-polarity stripes of <italic>wg</italic>, <italic>en</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic> (pale colours). Anterior left. Hammerhead arrows represent repressive interactions; pointed arrows represent activatory interactions; grey vertical line represents a prospective parasegment boundary. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s004">S4 Fig</xref> for relevant in situ data. (B) Static, “morphogen gradient” model for the patterning of the <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> posterior borders by Eve. The anterior margin of the Eve stripe is graded, with higher levels of Eve protein (darker green) present more posteriorly. High Eve (dark green) is required to repress <italic>prd</italic>, but only medium Eve (medium green) is required to repress <italic>slp</italic>. Based on Fujioka et al. (1995) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>]. (C) Dynamic model for the patterning of the <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> posterior borders by Eve. <italic>prd</italic> is activated earlier (T1, mid-cellularisation) than <italic>slp</italic> (T2, late cellularisation). In between these time points, the anterior border of the Eve domain shifts anteriorly. The posterior border of the <italic>prd</italic> domain is patterned by Eve at T1, but the posterior border of the <italic>slp</italic> domain is patterned by Eve at T2, resulting in a more anterior location. <italic>prd</italic> is no longer repressed by Eve at T2, resulting in stable, overlapping expression of Eve and <italic>prd</italic>. (D) Double FISH images showing the relative phasing of <italic>eve</italic> (green), <italic>prd</italic> (blue), and <italic>slp</italic> (red) expression domains at mid-cellularisation and late cellularisation. Enlarged views of stripes 2–6 are shown below the whole embryo lateral views (anterior left, dorsal top). In the bottom half of each image, the 2 channels have been thresholded, making regions of overlap easier to see. At mid-cellularisation, <italic>slp</italic> is not expressed and the posterior borders of the <italic>prd</italic> stripes abut the anterior borders of the <italic>eve</italic> stripes. At late cellularisation, the posterior borders of the <italic>prd</italic> stripes overlap the anterior borders of <italic>eve</italic> stripes (note the regions that appear cyan), the posterior borders of the <italic>slp</italic> stripes sharply abut the anterior borders of the <italic>eve</italic> stripes, and the posterior borders of the <italic>slp</italic> stripes are offset anteriorly from the posterior borders of the <italic>prd</italic> stripes (arrowheads). These expression patterns are more consistent with the dynamic model (C) than the static morphogen model (B). Scale bars = 50 μm. <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: <italic>en</italic>, <italic>engrailed</italic>; <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>even-skipped</italic>; FISH, fluorescent in situ hybridization; <italic>odd</italic>, <italic>odd-skipped</italic>; <italic>prd</italic>, <italic>paired</italic>; <italic>slp</italic>, <italic>sloppy-paired</italic>; wg, wingless.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The posterior boundaries of <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> are patterned by Eve, which represses both genes during cellularisation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>, left). While <italic>slp</italic> continues to be repressed by Eve throughout later development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref088">88</xref>], <italic>prd</italic> becomes insensitive to Eve towards the end of cellularisation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>] for reasons that are not entirely clear but may relate to the loss of Dichaete expression from the blastoderm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>]. The current model for how the offsets are set up is that the anterior edge of each Eve stripe acts as a morphogen gradient, which represses <italic>slp</italic> at a lower Eve concentration than is required to repress <italic>prd</italic>, thus differentially positioning their expression boundaries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5B</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>]. The reason that patterning fails in the first simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2A</xref>) is that the static, Boolean stripes of Eve position the boundaries of both <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> at the same place, resulting in no offsets and hence no <italic>en</italic> expression. In the second simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref>), however, the <italic>prd</italic>/<italic>slp</italic> offsets do emerge, even though Eve expression remains Boolean. This is because <italic>slp</italic> expression turns on significantly later than <italic>prd</italic> expression (about 10 minutes later in real embryos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref059">59</xref>]), by which time, the Eve boundary has shifted to a more anterior position than where it was when it patterned the <italic>prd</italic> stripes. Thus, whereas under the morphogen model, the distance between the <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> boundaries is measured using Eve concentration, an alternative model is that this distance is instead measured using time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5C</xref>).</p>
<p>These 2 mechanisms are not mutually exclusive, and it may be that they both contribute to patterning in the embryo. However, in their basic forms, they make different predictions about the relative expression dynamics of the <italic>prd</italic> and Eve domains. Under the static morphogen model, the 2 sets of domains should show significant overlaps throughout patterning (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5B</xref>). Under the dynamic model, these overlaps should be absent when the <italic>prd</italic> stripes are first patterned and emerge later, once <italic>prd</italic> becomes resistant to Eve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5C</xref>). Real pair-rule gene expression in the embryo is more consistent with the dynamic model: the posterior boundaries of the <italic>prd</italic> stripes abut the anterior boundaries of the <italic>eve</italic> stripes when they first emerge, and it is only later, when <italic>slp</italic> starts to be expressed, that overlaps between <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>eve</italic> become obvious (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5D</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Dynamic patterning of the even-numbered parasegment boundaries</title>
<p>The final phase of the simulations (time points 37–60, corresponding to gastrulation in real embryos) is when the system switches over to the late network, and the even-numbered (Ftz-dependent) parasegment boundaries are patterned. These boundaries are patterned by the pair-rule stripes of Runt, Ftz, and Slp, which together pattern segmental stripes of <italic>en</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g006">Fig 6A and 6B</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>]. Correctly patterning these latter domains therefore relies on the early network being able to set up the correct relative pattern of <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic> expression. Crucially, this pattern includes narrow overlaps between <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> (which will later give rise to <italic>en</italic> expression) and narrow gaps between <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> (which will later allow <italic>odd</italic> expression to be maintained). This means that the 3 relevant sets of expression boundaries (<italic>ftz</italic> anterior boundaries, <italic>runt</italic> posterior boundaries, and <italic>slp</italic> anterior boundaries) each need to fall in different positions.</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Dynamic patterning of the even-numbered parasegment boundaries.</title>
<p>(A) Double FISH images showing the relative expression patterns of <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic> at late cellularisation. Enlarged views of stripes 2–6 are shown below whole embryo lateral views (anterior left, dorsal top). In the bottom half of each enlarged image, the 2 channels have been thresholded, making regions of overlap easier to see. Scale bars = 50 μm. (B) Regulatory schematic showing the patterning of the even-numbered parasegment boundaries. At gastrulation, Runt, Ftz, and Slp are expressed in partially overlapping domains similar to their transcript expression at late cellularisation (see A). These overlapping domains provide a template for the segment-polarity stripes of <italic>en</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic>: the anterior borders of the Ftz stripes define the posterior borders of the <italic>slp</italic> secondary stripes, the posterior borders of the Runt stripes define the anterior borders of the <italic>odd</italic> primary stripes, and the Slp anterior borders define the posterior borders of the <italic>odd</italic> primary stripes. The even-numbered <italic>en</italic> stripes are activated by Ftz but repressed by Odd and Slp and so are restricted to the region of overlap between Runt and Ftz, in which both <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> are repressed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>]. Anterior left. Hammerhead arrows represent repressive interactions; grey vertical line represents a prospective parasegment boundary. (C) Schematic explaining why the even-numbered parasegment boundaries require dynamic gap inputs in order to be patterned. Given static inputs (top panel, compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2A</xref>), the Ftz anterior boundary (1, pink vertical line), the Runt posterior boundary (2, green vertical line), and the Slp anterior boundary (3, blue vertical line) all coincide, resulting only in broad <italic>slp</italic> expression. Given dynamic inputs (bottom panel, compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref>), the 3 boundaries are each located at different anteroposterior (AP) positions (as in B), resulting in the segment-polarity pattern: <italic>slp</italic>, <italic>en</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, <italic>slp</italic>. (D) Schematic explaining the origin of the offset boundaries of <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>runt</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic>. Top: diagram of the relative expression of Eve, <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic> at late cellularisation (compare A, and see T32 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref>). The solid red vertical line indicates the current position of the Eve posterior border, which coincides with the <italic>ftz</italic> anterior border (1). Dotted red vertical lines indicate previous positions of the dynamic Eve posterior border, coinciding with the <italic>runt</italic> posterior border (2) or the <italic>slp</italic> anterior border (3). Bottom: the regulatory chains responsible for patterning each of the 3 expression boundaries are highlighted in red on the early pair-rule network. All 3 boundaries trace back to Eve, but more posterior boundaries correspond to longer regulatory chains and so incur a longer time lag to resolve, given a change in Eve expression. The 3 different genes (<italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>runt</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic>) are effectively patterned by increasingly earlier incarnations of the Eve stripes, and therefore the existence of spatial offsets between boundaries 1, 2, and 3 relies on the Eve posterior border shifting anteriorly over time. <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: <italic>en</italic>, <italic>engrailed</italic>; FISH, fluorescent in situ hybridization; <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>fushi tarazu</italic>; <italic>odd</italic>, <italic>odd-skipped</italic>; <italic>slp</italic>, <italic>sloppy-paired</italic>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The patterning of each of these sets of boundaries eventually traces back to the posteriors of the Eve stripes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4B</xref>). <italic>ftz</italic> expression is directly patterned by Eve; <italic>runt</italic> is patterned by Odd, which is itself patterned by Eve; and <italic>slp</italic> is patterned by Runt, which, as just mentioned, is indirectly downstream of Eve. In the first simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g006">Fig 6C</xref>, top), these Eve boundaries are static, and thus the boundaries of Runt, Ftz, and Slp end up coinciding exactly. This explains why the <italic>en</italic> stripes fail to emerge and <italic>odd</italic> expression is lost: the expression states that give rise to them are missing from the positional code.</p>
<p>However, the correct boundary positions do emerge from the second simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g006">Fig 6C</xref>, bottom), even though the network is unchanged. Again, this result is caused by the dynamic nature of the Eve stripes. Each of the 3 boundaries is patterned by a regulatory chain of a different length (1, 2, or 3 interactions, respectively) and so will take different lengths of time to adjust to a given change in Eve expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g006">Fig 6D</xref>). This means that when the Eve stripes shift anteriorly over time, the 3 sets of boundaries each lag behind the Eve domains by different distances, thereby providing the necessary positional framework for the final segment pattern.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Patterning dynamics explain the severity of the <italic>eve</italic> mutant phenotype</title>
<p>Above, I described how the final segmental output consists of the pattern [En, Odd, Slp, En, Odd, Slp] across each double-parasegment repeat. I then used a dynamical model of the pair-rule system to show how the Eve stripes are directly or indirectly responsible for patterning most of the expression boundaries in this pattern, including both sets of parasegment boundaries. In this section, I use the same model to simulate and dissect the <italic>eve</italic> mutant phenotype, which has proved hard to account for using traditional patterning models.</p>
<p>Although <italic>eve</italic> was originally identified as a pair-rule gene on the basis of a pair-rule cuticle phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref003">3</xref>], it turned out that this particular mutant allele was an <italic>eve</italic> hypomorph, while <italic>eve</italic> null mutants yield an aperiodic denticle lawn phenotype instead [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref098">98</xref>]. Both odd-numbered and even-numbered <italic>en</italic> stripes are absent from <italic>eve</italic> null mutant embryos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref071">71</xref>], indicating severe mispatterning of upstream pair-rule gene expression. To investigate the aetiology of these effects, I characterised pair-rule gene expression patterns in precisely staged <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos using double fluorescent in situ hybridisation (FISH) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7</xref>) and then cross-referenced these observations with the patterning output of an “in silico” <italic>eve</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s024">S11 Movie</xref>), simulated by starting with the dynamic model and then setting <italic>eve</italic> transcription to remain off (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s009">S2 Text</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title>Aetiology of the <italic>eve</italic> mutant phenotype.</title>
<p>(A–C) “Early” effects. (A–C) Double FISH images of pair-rule gene expression in cellularisation stage wild-type and <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos. Enlarged views of stripes 2–6 are shown (anterior left, dorsal top). Scale = 50 μm. For whole embryo views and single channel views, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s005">S5 Fig</xref>. (A′–C′) Predicted transcriptional output of these genes from “wild-type” and “<italic>eve</italic> mutant” simulations (compare T32 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B and 2C</xref>). (A″–C″) Regulatory interactions relevant to the aberrant expression patterns in <italic>eve</italic> mutants are highlighted on the early pair-rule network (bold arrows). Eve and its regulatory effects, which are absent from the mutant embryos, are shown in grey. (A) Eve normally represses <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>prd</italic>. In <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos, all 3 genes are ectopically expressed: the <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> stripes expand anteriorly, and <italic>prd</italic> is expressed ubiquitously rather than in stripes. These expression changes are recapitulated by the simulation. (B) Eve normally indirectly regulates <italic>runt</italic> expression by repressing its repressor, Odd. In <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos, <italic>odd</italic> expression expands anteriorly (see A), resulting in a down-regulation of the <italic>runt</italic> stripes, except at their anterior margins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s005">S5 Fig</xref>). This effect is recapitulated in a discrete manner by the simulation. (C) Eve normally regulates <italic>slp</italic> in 2 ways: (1) by repressing it directly, and (2) by repressing it indirectly via indirectly maintaining the expression of its repressor, Runt (see B), via direct repression of <italic>odd</italic> (see A). In <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos, <italic>slp</italic> is expressed fairly ubiquitously rather than in narrow stripes. This expansion is evident in the simulated expression, but see legend of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s005">S5 Fig</xref> for discussion of differences between the real and simulated patterns. (D–F) “Late” effects. Double FISH images of pair-rule gene expression in wild-type and <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos over the course of gastrulation. For each set of images, each row compares a wild-type and a mutant embryo of roughly equal age (age increases from top to bottom). Both whole embryo views (anterior left, dorsal top) and enlarged views of stripes 2–6 are shown. For single channel views, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s005">S5 Fig</xref>. (D′–F′) Regulatory interactions that explain the observed pattern maturation are highlighted on the late network (bold arrows). (D) Odd represses <italic>prd</italic> in the late network, and so <italic>prd</italic> expression is lost from cells in which <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>prd</italic> expression initially overlap. In wild-type embryos, the <italic>odd</italic> primary stripes overlap the centres of the <italic>prd</italic> pair-rule stripes, which therefore split in two. In <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos, broad <italic>odd</italic> stripes are overlain on initially aperiodic <italic>prd</italic> expression, which therefore resolves into a pair-rule pattern. (E) There is mutual repression between Slp and Ftz/Odd in the late network (E′). (Note that the repression from Slp appears to be stronger than the reciprocal repression from Ftz and Odd.) In wild-type embryos, Slp causes the primary stripes of both <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> to narrow from the posterior (where they overlap the <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes). In <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos, Slp is broadly expressed, causing general repression of <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic>. Note that expression of both <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> persists in stripe 3 (asterisks), in which there is a corresponding gap in the <italic>slp</italic> expression domain. (F) In the late network, <italic>slp</italic> and <italic>runt</italic> are regulated similarly, and Slp represses all of the repressors of <italic>runt</italic> (i.e., <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>en</italic>). Consequently, <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> take on almost identical expression patterns. In wild-type embryos, the 2 genes become expressed in coincident segmental stripes. In <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos, early broad expression of <italic>slp</italic> allows <italic>runt</italic> to also become ubiquitously expressed. Note that the <italic>slp</italic> domain later resolves into a pair-rule pattern (perhaps due to repression from residual Ftz protein). <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: <italic>en</italic>, <italic>engrailed</italic>; <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>even-skipped</italic>; FISH, fluorescent in situ hybridization; <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>fushi tarazu</italic>; <italic>odd</italic>, <italic>odd-skipped</italic>; <italic>prd</italic>, <italic>paired</italic>; <italic>slp</italic>, <italic>sloppy-paired</italic>.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The experimental results are in accordance with earlier, more fragmentary characterisations of <italic>eve</italic> mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref064">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref073">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref074">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref099">99</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref101">101</xref>] and reveal a number of significant changes to pair-rule gene expression patterns. The <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> primary stripes are broader than usual (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7A</xref>), and the early expression of <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> is largely aperiodic rather than pair rule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7A and 7C</xref>). Then, at gastrulation, segmental patterns of pair-rule gene expression fail to emerge; instead, <italic>prd</italic> resolves into broad pair-rule stripes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7D</xref>), <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> become expressed fairly ubiquitously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7F</xref>), and <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> expression largely disappears (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7E</xref>). These changes are also seen in the <italic>eve</italic> mutant simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2C</xref>) and, as described below, follow logically from the structure of the pair-rule network.</p>
<p>Because Eve expression plays a relatively minor role in late patterning, most of the expression changes just described result from the loss of Eve activity during cellularisation (time points 0–36 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s024">S11 Movie</xref>). First, <italic>odd</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>prd</italic>, all of which are direct targets of Eve repression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7A′</xref>), are expressed ectopically: the <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> primary stripes expand anteriorly (judged relative to <italic>hairy</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7A</xref>, top/middle rows), while the <italic>prd</italic> interstripes (i.e., the gaps between the early broad stripes) are derepressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7A</xref>, bottom row). The ectopic Odd expression has a knock-on effect on <italic>runt</italic> expression, which becomes down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7B and 7B′</xref>). (Note that while <italic>runt</italic> expression is almost entirely lost at this stage of the simulation, in real embryos <italic>runt</italic> remains fairly widely expressed, although at significantly lower levels—see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s005">S5 Fig</xref>. This difference may be partially due to expression from the <italic>runt</italic> stripe-specific elements, which are not included in the model.) The loss of Runt activity then contributes to the misexpression of the <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes, which turn on at the end of cellularisation and would normally be patterned by both Eve and Runt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7C′</xref>). Given the absence of Eve activity and the loss/weakening of Runt activity, <italic>slp</italic> becomes expressed almost ubiquitously within the trunk of the mutant embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7C</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, the downstream effects of these aberrant patterns play out over the course of gastrulation, after the switch to the late network (time points 37–60 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2C</xref> / <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s024">S11 Movie</xref>). Odd represses <italic>prd</italic>, causing the aperiodic domain of <italic>prd</italic> to resolve into a pair-rule pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7D and 7D′</xref>). Odd and Ftz also repress <italic>slp</italic>, causing some small gaps to appear in the <italic>slp</italic> pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7E and 7F</xref>). However, <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> are themselves repressed by Slp very strongly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7E′</xref>), and the ectopic Slp expression in the embryo causes their expression to be almost completely lost (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7E</xref>). In, contrast, new <italic>runt</italic> expression emerges throughout most of the trunk, due to the absence of its repressors, Eve and Odd (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7F and 7F′</xref>).</p>
<p>As a consequence of all this mispatterning, <italic>en</italic> expression is completely repressed, and parasegment boundaries never form. The odd-numbered <italic>en</italic> stripes are specifically blocked by the ectopic Slp expression that replaces the Eve stripes. Above, we saw that these <italic>en</italic> domains are specified by the short regulatory chain [Eve––| Slp––| En], thus explaining why they have been observed to reappear in <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>slp</italic> double mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref101">101</xref>]. On the other hand, the even-numbered <italic>en</italic> stripes are redundantly repressed in <italic>eve</italic> mutants, by both ectopic Odd and ectopic Slp, as a result of the regulatory chains [Eve––| Odd––| En] and [Eve––| Odd––| Runt––| Slp––| En], respectively. The model therefore explains why these stripes reappear in <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>odd</italic> double mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref102">102</xref>] but not in <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>slp</italic> double mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network is compatible with both simultaneous and sequential segmentation</title>
<p>By simulating the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network, I have shown that dynamic spatial inputs from just 2 factors, Hairy and Eve, are sufficient to organise the expression of the system as a whole. In the <italic>Drosophila</italic> blastoderm, these inputs are driven by the dynamic output of the posterior gap system. However, the elaborate control of pair-rule gene expression by gap factors appears to be a relatively recent novelty in arthropod segment patterning, originating during the evolutionary transition from short-germ to long-germ embryogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref103">103</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref104">104</xref>]. It is currently not clear how much of the cross-regulation between the pair-rule genes seen in <italic>Drosophila</italic> is a new adaptation to long-germ development and how much is retained from a short-germ ancestral state.</p>
<p>To explore this question, I determined how many changes to the “wild-type” <italic>Drosophila</italic> simulation it would take in order to produce something resembling a sequential, “clock-and-wave-front” mode of segmentation. I managed to achieve this transition by way of a few plausible alterations, leaving the bulk of the network untouched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g008">Fig 8C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pbio.2002439.g008" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g008</object-id>
<label>Fig 8</label>
<caption>
<title>A slightly modified pair-rule network can pattern segments in both simultaneous and sequential modes.</title>
<p>(A,B) Simulation output for the modified network. Each panel shows the system state at a specific time point between T0 and T200 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s025">S12</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s026">S13</xref> Movies for complete output). In each panel, the horizontal axis represents a region of the anteroposterior (AP) axis (anterior left) and the vertical axis represents the different gene products that might be expressed in a given “cell” (individual columns C1 to C20). Pale colours represent active transcription; dark colours represent protein activity (see colour key at top right). Dotted red lines indicate parasegment boundaries. (A) The system is initialised with uniform expression of Cad and a periodic phase gradient of Hairy expression (protein or transcript “age” increases from posterior to anterior, and the pattern repeats every 8 cells—see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s009">S2 Text</xref> for details). Given these starting conditions, the dynamical behaviour of the system is almost identical to the unmodified network (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref> or <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s023">S10 Movie</xref>). Note, however, that <italic>hairy</italic> transcript is always out of phase with Hairy protein. (B) The system is initialised with uniform expression of Hairy but a decay gradient of Cad (protein disappears from anterior to posterior over time). Given these altered starting conditions, the system behaves differently and patterning takes longer, but the same stable segmental pattern eventually emerges. Note that in this simulation, the primary pair-rule genes continuously oscillate within cells that do not express Opa, and segmental stripes emerge progressively from anterior to posterior as Opa turns on along the AP axis. (C) Comparison of the original (left) and modified (right) early networks. For simplicity, the secondary pair-rule genes are not shown. See text for details. (D) Proposed regulatory homology between phases of segmentation gene expression in long-germ embryos (left) and short-germ embryos (right). In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, the quintessential long-germ insect, there are 3 main phases of segment patterning during embryogenesis. During cellularisation (top), most pair-rule genes are regulated via zebra elements and become expressed in periodic patterns throughout the trunk of the embryo (green region). During gastrulation (middle), segmental patterns of pair-rule genes and segment-polarity genes emerge throughout the trunk (blue region) fairly simultaneously. Finally, during germ band extension (bottom), the segment-polarity network maintains the segment pattern via intercellular signalling throughout the trunk (red region). In short-germ embryos, for example, those of the red flour beetle <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic>, segment patterning occurs continuously throughout germ band extension. Three germ bands of increasing age are depicted: the trunk elongates from the posterior as embryogenesis proceeds. Throughout the whole process, primary pair-rule genes exhibit oscillatory expression in the posterior segment addition zone (green regions). Pair-rule stripes then resolve (and may undergo frequency doubling) in the anterior segment addition zone (blue region). Finally, segment-polarity genes are expressed in segmental stripes starting just anterior to the segment addition zone (red regions). This phase of expression is thought to be regulated by a conserved signalling network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref105">105</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref106">106</xref>]. <bold>Abbreviations</bold>: Cad, Caudal; Opa, Odd-paired.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The only explicit regulatory changes that I made to the simulation were to the control logic of <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>hairy</italic>, and <italic>opa</italic>. First, I removed the regulation of <italic>eve</italic> by gap inputs (G2 in the model) and replaced it with early repression from Runt and Odd, both of which repress the <italic>eve</italic> late element in wild-type embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1A</xref>, right). Second, I removed the regulation of <italic>hairy</italic> by gap inputs (G1 in the model) and replaced it with autorepression, which is a common phenomenon for <italic>her</italic>/<italic>hes</italic> family genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref107">107</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref108">108</xref>]. Third, I tied the onset of <italic>opa</italic> expression to the decay of Cad by making Cad repress <italic>opa</italic>. These changes allowed the gap inputs G1 and G2 to be removed from the model and simplified the temporal control of the patterning process, putting everything downstream of Cad and Hairy.</p>
<p>I took this modified version of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> network and explored how it behaved at the tissue level, given various sets of initial conditions. I found that if I set up a repeating initial phase gradient of Hairy expression (i.e., for each cell along a double-segment repeat, Hairy expression begins at a slightly different point in its feedback cycle) and left initial Cad expression unchanged, the simulation output was essentially identical to before (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g008">Fig 8A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s025">S12 Movie</xref>). This is because the waves of oscillating Hairy expression that sweep through the tissue while the early network is active are sufficient to correctly organise the pair-rule stripes of all the remaining primary pair-rule genes (including Eve), and therefore downstream patterning proceeds unperturbed.</p>
<p>However, I also discovered that if I removed all spatial patterning of Hairy from the initial conditions and instead established an anterior-to-posterior decay gradient of Cad (mimicking the retracting Cad domain seen in short-germ insects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref109">109</xref>]), the simulation still produced the correct segmental output except that, now, this pattern emerged sequentially instead of simultaneously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g008">Fig 8B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s026">S13 Movie</xref>). As Cad decays and disappears from progressively more posterior cells over time, Opa turns on in an anterior-to-posterior wave, switching cells from the early network over to the late network. Cells in the posterior portion of the tissue synchronously passage through a repeating sequence of pair-rule gene expression (Hairy → Eve → Runt → Ftz/Odd → Hairy) until this point and subsequently differentiate into particular segment-polarity fates.</p>
<p>The modified network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g008">Fig 8C</xref>, right) is thus compatible both with <italic>Drosophila</italic>-like pair-rule gene expression and with “clock-and-wave-front” pair-rule gene expression similar to that seen in, e.g., <italic>Tribolium</italic>. This finding suggests (1) that many of the regulatory interactions within the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network might be conserved in short-germ arthropod species and (2) that long-germ and short-germ segmentation involve essentially similar patterning mechanisms and dynamics. Specifically, segment-polarity fate appears to be determined in both cases by the intersection of 2 sets of temporal signals, those carried by the pair-rule genes and those carried by broadly expressed extrinsic timing factors. In long-germ embryos, a periodic pattern of segment-polarity fates is achieved by directly imparting spatial information to the pair-rule genes using the gap system and stripe-specific elements. In short-germ embryos, however, retracting wave fronts of the timing factors provide this spatial information, and the gap genes play other roles.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>A revised view of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network reconciles long-germ and short-germ segmentation</title>
<p>In this manuscript, I have analysed the structure and dynamics of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network using a combination of simulated and experimental data to reveal how segment patterning is achieved. I have discovered a functional role for dynamic gap inputs in correctly phasing the pair-rule stripes and propose revised mechanisms for the patterning of the odd-numbered and even-numbered parasegment boundaries. In contrast to previous models based around the principle of static morphogen gradients, these mechanisms involve a coordinated interplay between intrinsic network dynamics and extrinsic spatiotemporal signals and do not necessarily require graded pair-rule activity.</p>
<p>These findings contribute to the evolving view of the role of Even-skipped, perhaps the best known of the pair-rule factors. Eve has long been known to be required for the expression of both sets of <italic>en</italic> stripes and hence both sets of parasegment boundaries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref071">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref098">98</xref>]. Originally, Eve was thought to achieve this directly by activating <italic>en</italic>. Later, it was recognised that Eve does not regulate <italic>en</italic> directly but instead represses several other pair-rule factors that themselves repress <italic>en</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref075">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref076">76</xref>]; however, quantitative information inherent within the Eve stripes was still believed to establish the template for the <italic>en</italic> stripes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref030">30</xref>]. This conclusion is challenged by the new model presented here, which suggests that static domains of Eve expression would cause a similar degree of pattern loss to that seen in <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryos. Instead, I propose that Eve conveys positional information largely via its expression dynamics, which are decoded downstream by the rest of the pair-rule gene network. (Interestingly, while “French flag” type morphogen gradient mechanisms have been proposed to underpin many developmental patterning systems, several modern studies have found that the reality often involves complex dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref058">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref110">110</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref113">113</xref>].)</p>
<p>The findings also clarify the relationship between long-germ and short-germ segmentation. I have shown that pair-rule patterning is fundamentally a temporal process and that it is therefore straightforward to convert the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network into a clock-and-wave-front system. Under this scenario, the dynamic “early” network regulates oscillatory expression in the posterior of the tissue, while the switch-like “late” network stabilises these outputs into segmental patterns in the anterior. Given that long-germ insects such as <italic>Drosophila</italic> are derived from short-germ ancestors, it seems unlikely that this fluidity between simultaneous and sequential patterning modes is a coincidence. I therefore propose that output from the <italic>Drosophila</italic> early pair-rule network is developmentally homologous to the oscillatory pair-rule gene expression seen in the segment addition zone of short-germ insects such as <italic>Tribolium</italic>, while the output from the late pair-rule network is developmentally homologous to the stripe refinement and frequency doubling that occurs just anterior to the segment addition zone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g008">Fig 8D</xref>). This hypothesis is strongly supported by a recent comparative study carried out by Andrew Peel and myself, which found that different phases of pair-rule gene expression in <italic>Tribolium</italic> exhibit the same correlations with <italic>cad</italic> and <italic>opa</italic> expression as seen in <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>]. Strikingly, the hypothesis implies that the “zebra” elements of <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> (which drive pair-rule patterns in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> blastoderm) represent the relictual components of some ancestral segmentation clock that drove oscillations of these genes with double-segment periodicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref050">50</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>How did long-germ segmentation evolve?</title>
<p>The evolutionary transition from short-germ segmentation to long-germ segmentation is thought to have been driven largely by selection for faster development. A segmentation clock can only tick so fast, and therefore represents a tight production bottleneck when generating segments: a longer body requires a longer time (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s007">S7A Fig</xref>). (Selection for quicker development may also underlie the evolutionary success of “pair-rule” patterning, seen in centipedes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref114">114</xref>] as well as insects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref115">115</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref116">116</xref>], which effectively halves the number of clock cycles required to produce a body of a given length.) In contrast, segmentation can be accomplished remarkably quickly when pair-rule gene expression is initialised with a periodic spatial pattern, as in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</p>
<p>Mechanistically, the transition to long-germ segmentation seems to have involved 2 main changes: (1) a heterochronic shift in the deployment of the pair-rule network from posterior segment addition zone to blastoderm and (2) the elaboration of the posterior gap network and associated stripe-specific elements. These latter processes are likely to have occurred progressively along the AP axis, with intermediate forms exhibiting a composite mode of development: simultaneous for more anterior segments, sequential for more posterior segments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref103">103</xref>]. The process also seems to have been facilitated by the re-use of anterior stripe-specific elements to also drive more posterior pair-rule stripes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref117">117</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref118">118</xref>]. However, given the complexity of <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule patterning, it has not been clear how this process could have evolved gradually and seamlessly, all the while maintaining a perfect segmental output pattern.</p>
<p>The findings in this paper significantly mitigate this problem. In my model of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network, 2 of the primary pair-rule genes are patterned by gap inputs while 3 are patterned by cross-regulation. However, the system works equally well if only 1 of these genes is explicitly patterned and the rest are cross-regulated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s025">S12 Movie</xref>) or if all 5 are patterned by gap inputs and there is no cross-regulation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s021">S8 Movie</xref>). Therefore, direct stripe patterning through stripe-specific elements and indirect stripe patterning through zebra elements can stand in for one another without affecting events downstream. (Similar conclusions, including a potential role for stripe shifts, were reached by a recent in silico evolution study focused on the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref119">119</xref>].) Consequently, there is no need for multiple stripe-specific elements to have evolved simultaneously during the transition to long-germ segmentation: new stripe-specific elements could have evolved one by one, each time slotting into or replacing parts of the existing patterning machinery. Retention of an intact segmentation clock could also have buttressed gap-driven segment patterning during the transition, and such a scenario may apply today to insects such as <italic>Nasonia</italic> and <italic>Bombyx</italic>, which exhibit some evidence of both patterning modes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref120">120</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref122">122</xref>]. The corollary of such flexibility between gap-driven and cross-regulated pair-rule gene expression is, however, that the dynamics of the gap network need to be highly constrained and should resemble those of the original segmentation clock. This appears to be the case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref067">67</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>A trade-off between patterning speed and patterning robustness</title>
<p>Above, I stated that stripe-specific elements and cross-regulation are theoretically interchangeable for positioning pair-rule stripes. In the <italic>Drosophila</italic> blastoderm, the regulatory situation appears to be partially redundant: at least 3 of the primary pair-rule genes possess stripe-specific elements in any given pair-rule repeat, but only 2 of these genes lack zebra elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref016">16</xref>]. Why then have multiple pair-rule genes evolved stripe-specific elements, when patterning just a single gene in this way is theoretically sufficient for making segments? Additionally, why do genes such as <italic>runt</italic> retain a zebra element when they already have a full set of stripe-specific elements?</p>
<p>The first question has 2 likely answers. Using gap inputs to directly pattern multiple genes speeds up the first emergence of a correctly phased pair-rule repeat and hence reduces the total time required for segmentation as well as the minimum magnitude of the stripe shifts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s007">S7B Fig</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s019">S6</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s021">S8</xref> Movies). (The extreme scenario is that gap shifts are dispensed with entirely, as seems to have occurred in the anterior of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> trunk, based on comparisons with the scuttle fly <italic>Megaselia abdita</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref123">123</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref124">124</xref>].) The acquisition of extra stripe-specific elements could therefore have been driven by selection for marginal decreases to the length of development. Alternatively, these elements could have been selected for in order to mitigate irregularities in the patterns of upstream pair-rule genes. For example, <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic> all possess a stripe-specific element for stripe 3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref016">16</xref>], corresponding to a region of the blastoderm in which their repressor, Hairy, is inappropriately expressed early on [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref059">59</xref>].</p>
<p>While the stripe-specific elements of <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic> may therefore increase the speed of patterning, their output patterns are not as regular as those of <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>eve</italic>, probably answering the second question. Irregular gap-driven pair-rule stripes, if not later refined by cross-regulation, would result in aberrant segment-polarity patterns. For example, cross-regulation of the <italic>runt</italic> pair-rule stripes appears to be absent in <italic>Dichaete</italic> mutant embryos, and this leads to severe and variable segmentation defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref087">87</xref>].</p>
<p>However, even if these <italic>runt</italic> stripes were as regular as those of <italic>eve</italic>, cross-regulation might still be required. The <italic>eve</italic> stripes are patterned with a precision of about 1% AP length, i.e., differing in position from embryo to embryo by roughly 1 nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref041">41</xref>]. This positional noise is equivalent to the spatial resolution of the final segment-polarity pattern, in which most stripes are only 1 cell wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g001">Fig 1B</xref>). Therefore, if the <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>runt</italic> stripes both showed positional variation of this magnitude, and this noise was uncorrelated, segmentation defects would likely occur. The benefit of the dynamic patterning carried out by the pair-rule network is that the influence of Eve activity on gene expression is not restricted to the cells currently within each Eve stripe but also extends to cells posterior to these stripes, like wakes stretching out behind moving ships. This means that entire pair-rule repeats become coordinated with the Eve stripes, regardless of where exactly these stripes are located in the blastoderm. Thus, spending extra time to cross-regulate is likely to minimise the consequences of noise in the original spatial signals, a trade-off that is characteristic of many developmental patterning systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref125">125</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Assumptions, unexplained phenomena, and model limitations</title>
<p>I have presented theoretical evidence that posterior-to-anterior shifts of pair-rule stripes, driven by dynamic gap inputs, play a functional role in segment patterning. The plausibility of my model therefore rests on these shifts existing and being of an appropriate speed and magnitude. The basic model (only <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>eve</italic> patterned by gap inputs) requires a minimum shift of 3 nuclei, while versions including greater control of pair-rule gene expression by gap inputs reduce this minimum to 1 or 2 nuclei (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s019">S6</xref>–<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s021">S8</xref> Movies). As yet, these shifts have only been measured in real embryos by comparing population estimates of absolute stripe position (in percent egg length) in fixed material of different ages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref059">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref061">61</xref>]. Interpreting these measurements is not straightforward, but adjustments for nuclear migration suggest shifts of at least 2–3 nuclei for <italic>eve</italic> stripes 3–7, consistent with the requirements of the model. Recent developments in live imaging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref126">126</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref128">128</xref>] mean that it should now be possible to test these estimates directly in individual embryos.</p>
<p>While the new model clarifies many aspects of segment patterning, it also highlights certain regulatory phenomena that are currently unexplained and require further study. For example, it is not clear how the timing of <italic>slp</italic> transcription is controlled, how exactly <italic>prd</italic> is spatially regulated, or which factors are responsible for activating the pair-rule genes.</p>
<p>Finally, the model is obviously simplistic and represents only the first step towards a modern, system-level understanding of the pair-rule network. For example, while the model demonstrates that morphogen-like effects are not necessary to account for pair-rule patterning, it does not rule them out. (Indeed, anterior-to-posterior expression shifts might well contribute to concentration-dependent spatial patterning of target genes, by helping shape the contours of the pair-rule stripes at the protein level.) Careful experimental characterisation of the quantitative relationship between the protein concentrations of input factors and the transcription rate of output factors could form the basis for future, more sophisticated models of <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule patterning, which explore the roles of quantitative and stochastic effects. Future models of short-germ segmentation, on the other hand, could account for morphogenetic processes such as cell division and rearrangement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref129">129</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref131">131</xref>] and/or incorporate known intercellular communication processes that occur both upstream (e.g., Notch-Delta signalling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref132">132</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref134">134</xref>]) and downstream (e.g., Toll receptor codes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref135">135</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref136">136</xref>]) of the pair-rule genes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Concluding remarks</title>
<p>In the introduction to this paper, I highlighted 3 recent findings related to pair-rule patterning: (1) that pair-rule orthologs exhibit oscillating expression in the segment addition zones of short-germ arthropods, (2) that pair-rule gene expression in long-germ insects is patterned by dynamic gap gene expression, and (3) that the pair-rule network in <italic>Drosophila</italic> undergoes an extensive topology change at gastrulation. I then presented evidence that dynamic Eve expression is integral to segment patterning and also that the <italic>Drosophila</italic> pair-rule network is broadly compatible with both simultaneous and sequential modes of segmentation.</p>
<p>I therefore propose the following evolutionary hypothesis, which ties together and potentially explains the 3 original findings. (1) Long-germ and short-germ segmentation are not dichotomous modes of patterning but rather alternative behaviours of a largely conserved pair-rule network. (2) In long-germ insects, ad hoc patterning of stripes by gap inputs stands in for the expression of particular pair-rule gene “clock enhancers”, meaning that gap gene networks are under strong selection to preserve dynamic behaviour. (3) In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, the “early” pair-rule network is derived from the “clock” part of an ancestral short-germ segmentation mechanism, while the “late” network is derived from the stabilising genetic interactions that would have originally established parasegment boundaries anterior to the segment addition zone.</p>
<p>These predictions can be tested in the future by comparative studies in emerging arthropod model species.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<p>Wild-type in situ images are from a previously published data set deposited in the Dryad repository: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cg35k" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cg35k</ext-link> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref137">137</xref>]. The <italic>eve</italic> mutation used was <italic>eve</italic><sup><italic>3</italic></sup> (gift of Bénédicte Sanson) and was balanced over <italic>CyO hb</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic> (Boomington stock no. 6650) in order to easily distinguish homozygous mutant embryos. Whole mount double FISH, microscopy, and image analysis were carried out as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref032">32</xref>]. The <italic>eve</italic>/Eve doubles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g004">Fig 4D</xref> were generated by incubating embryos with 1:1,000 rabbit anti-Eve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref138">138</xref>] and 1:500 anti-rabbit 488 following in situ hybridisation to <italic>eve</italic>. Images were analysed using Fiji [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref139">139</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref140">140</xref>]: intensity profiles were produced using the “multi plot” function, while thresholded images were produced using the “make binary” tool. Simulations were coded in Python (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.python.org" xlink:type="simple">www.python.org</ext-link>) using the libraries NumPy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref141">141</xref>] and Matplotlib [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref142">142</xref>]. SBML-qual files were generated using the GINsim software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ginsim.org" xlink:type="simple">http://ginsim.org</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.2002439.ref143">143</xref>]. All models and simulations are described in detail in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s009">S2 Text</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Extended comparison between real and simulated pair-rule gene expression patterns.</title>
<p>Expanded version of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g003">Fig 3</xref> from the main text, showing all pairwise combinations between <italic>hairy</italic>, <italic>eve</italic>, <italic>runt</italic>, <italic>ftz</italic>, <italic>odd</italic>, and <italic>slp</italic>. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>eve</italic> pair-rule stripes partially overlap during cellularisation. At gastrulation, <italic>hairy</italic> expression fades away, while the <italic>eve</italic> stripes narrow from the posterior and then also fade. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>runt</italic> pair-rule stripes partially overlap during cellularisation. The <italic>eve</italic> stripes become increasingly narrow at gastrulation, and the <italic>runt</italic> secondary stripes emerge anterior to the <italic>eve</italic> stripes. By early GBE, <italic>eve</italic> expression has faded away and <italic>runt</italic> expression has resolved into a regular, segmental pattern. The refinement of the <italic>eve</italic> stripes occurs more gradually in real embryos than in the simulation. Arrowheads in B”‘ indicate new <italic>runt</italic> expression related to the developing nervous system. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> pair-rule stripes are at first expressed in complementary patterns. Starting from late cellularisation, they both narrow from the posterior (<italic>eve</italic> more than <italic>ftz</italic>). <italic>eve</italic> expression later fades away, while <italic>ftz</italic> persists. (<bold>D</bold>) <italic>eve</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> pair-rule stripes are at first expressed in complementary patterns, before both narrowing. <italic>odd</italic> secondary stripes emerge at the posterior of the narrowing <italic>eve</italic> domains, which then fade away, leaving segmental stripes of <italic>odd</italic>. (<bold>E</bold>) <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>runt</italic> pair-rule stripes are expressed in complementary patterns during cellularisation. <italic>hairy</italic> expression then fades away, while <italic>runt</italic> transitions to segmental stripes. (<bold>F</bold>) <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> pair-rule stripes slightly overlap during cellularisation. <italic>hairy</italic> expression then fades away, while the <italic>ftz</italic> stripes narrow. (<bold>G</bold>) <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> pair-rule stripes slightly overlap during cellularisation. <italic>hairy</italic> expression then fades away, while <italic>odd</italic> transitions to narrow segmental stripes. (<bold>H</bold>) <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>ftz</italic> pair-rule stripes partially overlap throughout cellularisation. At gastrulation, <italic>runt</italic> secondary stripes emerge to the posterior of the narrowing <italic>ftz</italic> stripes. Later, the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes refine from the posterior, and the overlaps with <italic>ftz</italic> are lost. (<bold>I</bold>) <italic>runt</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> pair-rule stripes slightly overlap during cellularisation. These overlaps resolve at late cellularisation (slightly earlier than in the simulation). At gastrulation, new <italic>odd</italic> expression emerges just anterior to the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes, while new <italic>runt</italic> expression emerges just posterior to the refining <italic>odd</italic> primary stripes. By early GBE there is a regular segmental pattern of abutting <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>runt</italic> stripes, separated by gaps. Arrowheads in I”‘ indicate new <italic>runt</italic> expression related to the developing nervous system. (<bold>J</bold>) The <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> stripes are fairly congruent during cellularisation. At gastrulation, both narrow from the posterior, and the <italic>odd</italic> secondary stripes intercalate between them. Over the course of patterning, their anterior boundaries also become offset from one another. (<bold>K</bold>) The <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes emerge later than the <italic>hairy</italic> stripes, but share an anterior border with them. (The <italic>slp</italic> stripes in the simulation are too broad at this stage—they should be narrower than the <italic>hairy</italic> stripes.) <italic>hairy</italic> expression then fades away, while <italic>slp</italic> transitions to a segmental pattern. (<bold>L</bold>) The <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes emerge later than the <italic>eve</italic> stripes, and abut their anterior borders. (In the simulation, these <italic>slp</italic> stripes extend too far posteriorly, and overlap with <italic>eve</italic>. The reason is that the <italic>eve</italic> anterior borders would have stabilised by this point in real embryos, but they are still shifting in the simulation.) At gastrulation, the <italic>eve</italic> stripes narrow from the posterior and then fade, while slp transitions to segmental stripes. (<bold>M</bold>) The <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes emerge later than the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes, and are offset slightly from their posterior boundaries. (The simulated <italic>slp</italic> domains are wider than the real <italic>slp</italic> domains.) At gastrulation, secondary stripes of both genes emerge between the primary stripes (the widths of the simulated <italic>slp</italic> stripes are now appropriate). The expression patterns become largely congruent, except at the posteriors of the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes. These differences resolve later, when the <italic>runt</italic> primary stripes narrow. (<bold>N</bold>) The <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes emerge later than the <italic>ftz</italic> primary stripes, and partially overlap with them. At gastrulation, the secondary <italic>slp</italic> stripes emerge just anterior to the <italic>ftz</italic> domains, which narrow from the posterior, losing the overlaps with the <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes. (<bold>O</bold>) As for (N), the <italic>slp</italic> primary stripes partially overlap the <italic>odd</italic> primary stripes, and these overlaps are later lost by the <italic>odd</italic> stripes narrowing from the posterior. The secondary stripes of <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> intercalate between the primary stripes, and abut one other.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Uncropped views of the embryos shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s001">S1 Fig</xref>.</title>
<p>Each panel shows an uncropped version of the corresponding double fluorescent in situ image in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s001">S1 Fig</xref>. All panels show a whole embryo lateral view, anterior left, dorsal top. Embryos within each column are of approximately equal age. Scale = 100 μm.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Some aspects of <italic>prd</italic> expression are not recovered by the simulation.</title>
<p>This figure compares double FISH data of pair-rule gene expression with simulated transcript expression, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g003">Fig 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s002">S2 Fig</xref>. (A) <italic>prd</italic> transcripts (magenta) are shown relative to <italic>eve</italic> (green), <italic>odd</italic> (blue) or <italic>slp</italic> (cyan) transcripts, at four different embryo ages (left) or simulation timepoints (right). Note that the figure presents a different set of developmental ages / simulated timepoints from those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g003">Fig 3</xref> and Supplementary Figure 3, in order to show cellularisation in greater temporal detail. At “early cellularisation”, the primary pair-rule genes are expressed but <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic> are not; at “mid cellularisation”, <italic>prd</italic> is expressed but <italic>slp</italic> is not; at “late cellularisation”, <italic>slp</italic> is additionally expressed. While the simulated expression of <italic>prd</italic> is broadly appropriate early on (e.g. compare <italic>prd</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> expression at mid-cellularisation / T26), several aspects of <italic>prd</italic> expression are not recapitulated by the model. First, the changing phasing of <italic>prd</italic> posterior borders and <italic>eve</italic> anterior borders between mid-cellularisation and late cellularisation (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5</xref>). Second, the splitting of the <italic>prd</italic> stripes at late cellularisation, slightly prior to the appearance of the secondary stripes of <italic>odd</italic> and <italic>slp</italic>. Third, the patterning of the <italic>prd</italic> “A” stripes (i.e. the narrow stripes formed from anterior portions of the early broad stripes, asterisks in the in situ images) and the consequent emergence of single-segment periodicity. (B) Uncropped views of the embryos shown in (A). Scale bars 100 μm.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s004" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Gene expression at the odd-numbered parasegment boundaries.</title>
<p>(A) Double FISH images of segmentation gene expression in gastrulation stage embryos (lateral view, anterior left, dorsal top). Each row shows a different pairwise comparison of the transcripts of the genes <italic>eve</italic> (magenta), <italic>prd</italic> (blue), <italic>slp</italic> (green), <italic>en</italic> (red), <italic>odd</italic> (yellow), and <italic>wg</italic> (cyan). From left to right, the panels in each row show: 1) a whole embryo view; 2) an enlarged view of pair-rule repeats 2–6; 3) the individual channel for the first gene listed in the row label; 4) the individual channel for the second gene listed in the row label. Arrowheads mark the locations of prospective odd-numbered parasegment boundaries. Scale bars 100 μm. (B) Summary schematic showing the relative expression of the Eve, Prd, and Slp protein domains, and the <italic>en</italic>, <italic>wg</italic>, and <italic>odd</italic> transcript domains, at the odd-numbered parasegment boundaries. (C) The same schematic as in B, with the addition of the regulatory interactions between Eve, Prd, and Slp and their target genes. Aside from the colours, which are changed to match the in situ images, this schematic is identical to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g005">Fig 5A</xref>.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s005" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S5 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Expanded view of the <italic>eve</italic> mutant phenotype.</title>
<p>This figure is an expansion of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7</xref> in the main text, showing additional whole embryo and single channel views. Enlarged views show stripes 2–6. Asterisks in (E) indicate the stripe 3 region. Scale = 50 μm. Note the quantitative traces below the images in (C). These plots show the AP intensity profiles of <italic>runt</italic> (green) and <italic>slp</italic> (blue) along a narrow ventral strip of the trunk of the two embryos pictured. In the wild-type embryo, the <italic>runt</italic> stripes are all (except stripe 7) roughly symmetrical and strongly expressed. In the <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryo, <italic>runt</italic> stripes 1–6 (which overlap with <italic>odd</italic> expression, see B), have much lower intensity than <italic>runt</italic> stripe 7 (which doesn’t overlap with <italic>odd</italic> expression, see B) and exhibit a sawtooth pattern, in which expression intensity decreases from anterior to posterior. The <italic>slp</italic> expression in the <italic>eve</italic> mutant embryo, while broad, does display a pair-rule modulation, which is in opposite phase to the downregulated <italic>runt</italic> stripes. Therefore, the same two regulatory interactions (repression of <italic>runt</italic> by Odd, and of <italic>slp</italic> by Runt) are evident in both the in situ data and the simulated data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g007">Fig 7A’</xref>), but lead to slightly different expression patterns in each case, one quantitative and one qualitative.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s006" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s006" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S6 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Stripe phasing depends on the speed of the gap shifts.</title>
<p>Simulation output showing the expression patterns generated by the early pair-rule network, assuming various anterior-to-posterior shifts speeds of the gap inputs (shown in black). See supplementary movies for full simulation output (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s014">S1 Movie</xref> = 0x; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s015">S2 Movie</xref> = 1x; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s016">S3 Movie</xref> = 0.5x; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s017">S4 Movie</xref> = 2x; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s018">S5 Movie</xref> = 3x). Gap domain shift speeds are relative to the time delay for pair-rule protein synthesis / decay: a speed of 1x leads to a one nucleus offset between the anterior borders of transcript and protein domains, a speed of 2x leads to a two nucleus offset, and so on. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s009">S2 Text</xref> for further details about the simulations.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s007" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s007" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S7 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Selection for patterning speed could lead to increasingly elaborate regulation of pair-rule genes by the gap system.</title>
<p>(A,B) Minimum duration required for generating a correct segment pattern (En, Odd, Slp repeats), under various simulation scenarios. Minimum simulation duration (Y-axis) is given as a multiple of the synthesis / decay delay parameter value of the pair-rule gene products (corresponding to 6 timesteps for all simulations shown in this manuscript). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s009">S2 Text</xref> for further details on the various simulations. (A) Minimum time required to pattern a given number of segments by either simultaneous or sequential patterning, using the same network model as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s025">S12</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.2002439.s026">S13</xref> Movies. Sequential patterning requires 12x the delay for the initial two segments, plus 8x the delay for every two additional segments. Simultaneous patterning requires a constant minimum time of 10x the delay, no matter the number of segments. (B) Minimum time (in multiples of the synthesis / decay delay parameter value) required for simultaneous patterning, for systems with increasingly elaborate gap patterning. If only <italic>hairy</italic> receives gap inputs (1), a minimum of time 10x the delay is required (network model as in simulation 12). If both <italic>hairy</italic> and <italic>eve</italic> receive gap inputs (2), the minimum is 7x the delay (network model as in simulation 10). If <italic>runt</italic> or <italic>ftz</italic>/<italic>odd</italic> additionally receive gap inputs (3), the minimum is 6x the delay (early network model as in simulations 6 or 7, respectively, plus late network model as for simulation 10). Finally, if all the primary pair-rule genes receive gap inputs (4), the minimum is 5x the delay (early network model as in simulation 8, plus late network model as for simulation 10). Note that the stripes of <italic>ftz</italic> and <italic>odd</italic> are considered a single pattern, because of their identical regulation in the simulations.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s008" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s008" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Text</label>
<caption>
<title>Regulatory interactions between the primary pair-rule genes during cellularisation.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s009" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s009" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Text</label>
<caption>
<title>Details of models and simulations.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s010" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s010" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Functions needed for running network simulations.</title>
<p>(PY)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s011" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s011" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Template script for network simulations.</title>
<p>Corresponds to the network in Simulation 10 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref>.</p>
<p>(PY)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s012" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s012" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Wild-type pair-rule network in SBML-qual format.</title>
<p>Corresponds to the network in Simulation 10 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g002">Fig 2B</xref>.</p>
<p>(SBML)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s013" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s013" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Modified pair-rule network in SBML-qual format.</title>
<p>Corresponds to the network in Simulations 12 and 13, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.2002439.g008">Fig 8</xref>.</p>
<p>(SBML)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s014" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s014" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 1.</title>
<p>Simulated expression of the primary pair-rule genes, assuming static gap inputs.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s015" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s015" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 2.</title>
<p>Simulated expression of the primary pair-rule genes, assuming dynamic gap inputs.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s016" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s016" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 3.</title>
<p>Simulated expression of the primary pair-rule genes, assuming slow gap shifts.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s017" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s017" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 4.</title>
<p>Simulated expression of the primary pair-rule genes, assuming fast gap shifts.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s018" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s018" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S5 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 5.</title>
<p>Simulated expression of the primary pair-rule genes, assuming very fast gap shifts.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s019" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s019" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S6 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 6.</title>
<p>Pattern establishment when <italic>hairy</italic>, <italic>eve</italic>, and <italic>runt</italic> take gap inputs.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s020" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s020" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S7 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 7.</title>
<p>Pattern establishment when <italic>hairy</italic>, <italic>eve</italic>, and <italic>ftz</italic>/<italic>odd</italic> take gap inputs.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s021" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s021" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S8 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 8.</title>
<p>Pattern establishment when all primary pair-rule genes take gap inputs.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s022" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s022" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S9 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 9.</title>
<p>Simulated behaviour of the whole pair-rule system, assuming static gap inputs.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s023" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s023" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S10 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 10.</title>
<p>Simulated behaviour of the whole pair-rule system, assuming dynamic gap inputs.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s024" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s024" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S11 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 11.</title>
<p>Pair-rule gene expression in a simulated <italic>eve</italic> mutant.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s025" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s025" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S12 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 12.</title>
<p>Simultaneous patterning by the modified pair-rule network.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pbio.2002439.s026" mimetype="video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.2002439.s026" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S13 Movie</label>
<caption>
<title>Simulation 13.</title>
<p>Sequential patterning by the modified pair-rule network.</p>
<p>(MP4)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>I am very grateful to Michael Akam, who advised and encouraged me throughout the course of this project and commented on the manuscript, and to Tim Weil, who contributed lab space and taught me to work with flies. Michalis Averof, Matt Benton, Berta Verd, Olivia Tidswell, and Ezzat El-Sherif commented on a draft of the manuscript. I thank Andrew Peel, Andy Oates, Johannes Jaeger, Siegfried Roth, Bénédicte Sanson, James Briscoe, and Alfonso Martinez-Arias for useful discussions.</p>
</ack>
<glossary>
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<def-list>
<def-item><term>AP</term>
<def><p>anteroposterior</p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term>Cad</term>
<def><p>Caudal</p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>en</italic></term>
<def><p><italic>engrailed</italic></p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>eve</italic></term>
<def><p><italic>even-skipped</italic></p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term>FISH</term>
<def><p>fluorescent in situ hybridisation</p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ftz</italic></term>
<def><p><italic>fushi tarazu</italic></p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>odd</italic></term>
<def><p><italic>odd-skipped</italic></p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term>Opa</term>
<def><p>Odd-paired</p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>prd</italic></term>
<def><p><italic>paired</italic></p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term>SBML</term>
<def><p>Systems Biology Markup Language</p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>slp</italic></term>
<def><p><italic>sloppy-paired</italic></p></def>
</def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>wg</italic></term>
<def><p><italic>wingless</italic></p></def>
</def-item>
</def-list>
</glossary>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The molecular basis for metameric pattern in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiadka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Anterior—posterior patterning in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Adv Dev Biol Biochem</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nüsslein-Volhard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieschaus</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mutations affecting segment number and polarity in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>287</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>801</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6776413</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieschaus</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nüsslein-Volhard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Heidelberg Screen for Pattern Mutants of Drosophila : A Personal Account</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-cellbio-113015-023138" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-cellbio-113015-023138</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27501451</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnosti</surname> <given-names>DN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analysis and function of transcriptional regulatory elements: insights from Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.48.091801.112749" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ento.48.091801.112749</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12359740</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiNardo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Farrell</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Establishment and refinement of segmental pattern in the Drosophila embryo: spatial control of engrailed expression by pair-rule genes</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1212</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3123316</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Arias</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of segment polarity genes in the Drosophila blastoderm by fushi tarazu and even skipped</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>331</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/331073a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/331073a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2893285</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaynes</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujioka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Drawing lines in the sand: even skipped et al. and parasegment boundaries</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2004.03.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2004.03.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110723</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ish-Horowicz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transcription pattern of the Drosophila segmentation gene hairy</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>318</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struhl</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Isolation, structure, and expression of even-skipped: a second pair-rule gene of Drosophila containing a homeo box</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2877745</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gergen</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Isolation of the Drosophila segmentation gene runt and analysis of its expression during embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1179</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2847961</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hafen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroiwa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial distribution of transcripts from the segmentation gene fushi tarazu during Drosophila embryonic development</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>833</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6430568</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulter</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swaykus</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beran-Koehn</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieschaus</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular analysis of odd-skipped, a zinc finger encoding segmentation gene with a novel pair-rule expression pattern</article-title>. <source>Embo J</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>3795</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilchherr</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgartner</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bopp</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frei</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noll</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <source>Isolation of the paired gene of Drosophila and its spatial expression during early embryogenesis</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>321</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossniklaus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Drosophila Sloppy Paired Locus Encodes Two Proteins Involved in Segmentation That Show Homology To Mammalian Transcription Factors</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1030</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1317319</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaul</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>How to make stripes: deciphering the transition from non-periodic to periodic patterns in Drosophila segmentation</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>138</volume>:<fpage>3067</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.062141" xlink:type="simple">10.1242/dev.062141</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21693522</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>The gap gene network</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-010-0536-y" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00018-010-0536-y</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20927566</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rushlow</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Region-specific alleles of the Drosophila segmentation gene hairy</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1037</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3169547</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maniatis</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Early and late periodic patterns of even skipped expression are controlled by distinct regulatory elements that respond to different spatial cues</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2720776</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warrior</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Autoregulatory and gap gene response elements of the even-skipped promoter of Drosophila</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1205</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2743979</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pankratz</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jäckle</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Making stripes in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2238086</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kraut</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warrior</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of a pair-rule stripe in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>827</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2026328</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blair</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of two pair-rule stripes by a single enhancer in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>175</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1006/dbio.1996.0117" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/dbio.1996.0117</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8626035</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujioka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emi-Sarker</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yusibova</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaynes</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analysis of an even-skipped rescue transgene reveals both composite and discrete neuronal and early blastoderm enhancers, and multi-stripe positioning by gap gene repressor gradients</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>2527</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10226011</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiromi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroiwa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Control elements of the Drosophila segmentation gene fushi tarazu</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>603</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3935327</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dearolf</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Topol</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transcriptional control of Drosophila fushi tarazu zebra stripe expression</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2498165</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soong</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gergen</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Drosophila segmentation gene runt has an extended cis-regulatory region that is required for vital expression at other stages of development</article-title>. <source>Mech Dev</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1336975</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutjahr</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanario-Alonso</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pick</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noll</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multiple regulatory elements direct the complex expression pattern of the Drosophila segmentation gene paired</article-title>. <source>Mech Dev</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7873402</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedyk</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiNardo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Odd-paired: A zinc finger pair-rule protein required for the timely activation of engrailed and wingless in Drosophila embryos</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8288124</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujioka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaynes</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Early even-skipped stripes act as morphogenetic gradients at the single cell level to establish engrailed expression</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>4371</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8575337</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiNardo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Establishing parasegments in Drosophila embryos: roles of the odd-skipped and naked genes</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>169</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1006/dbio.1995.1145" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/dbio.1995.1145</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7750646</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Odd-paired controls frequency doubling in Drosophila segmentation by altering the pair-rule gene regulatory network</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e18215</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.18215" xlink:type="simple">10.7554/eLife.18215</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27525481</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadigan</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossniklaus</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Localized Expression of Sloppy Paired Protein Maintains the Polarity of Drosophila Parasegments</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>899</fpage>–<lpage>913</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7926775</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noll</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of the gooseberry gene in Drosophila embryos: maintenance of wingless expression by a wingless—gooseberry autoregulatory loop</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>4499</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8223460</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiNardo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heemskerk</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dougan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Farrell</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name>. <article-title>The making of a maggot: patterning the Drosophila embryonic epidermis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7950320</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrimon</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>The genetic basis of patterned baldness in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7907277</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanson</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Generating patterns from fields of cells: Examples from Drosophila segmentation</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1083</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/embo-reports/kve255" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/embo-reports/kve255</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743020</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blagov</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlov</surname> <given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manu</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myasnikova</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Dynamical analysis of regulatory interactions in the gap gene system of Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>1721</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1534/genetics.104.027334" xlink:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.104.027334</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342511</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manu</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surkova</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spirov</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gursky</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>A-R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Canalization of Gene Expression and Domain Shifts in the Drosophila Blastoderm by Dynamical Attractors</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e1000303</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000303" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000303</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19282965</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gursky</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panok</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myasnikova</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manu</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samsonova</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinitz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Mechanisms of gap gene expression canalization in the Drosophila blastoderm</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21794172</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubuis</surname> <given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tkacik</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieschaus</surname> <given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregor</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bialek</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positional information, in bits</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>16301</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1315642110" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1315642110</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24089448</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tkačik</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubuis</surname> <given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petkova</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregor</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Positional information, Positional error, and readout precision in morphogenesis: A mathematical framework</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>199</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1534/genetics.114.171850" xlink:type="simple">10.1534/genetics.114.171850</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25361898</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Petkova MD, Tkačik G, Bialek W, Wieschaus EF, Gregor T. Optimal decoding of information from a genetic network. 2016. Preprint. Available from: arXiv:1612.08084v1.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thieffry</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Segmenting the fly embryo: a logical analysis of the pair-rule cross-regulatory module</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>224</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957124</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campos-Ortega</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartenstein</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>. <source>The Embryonic Development of Drosophila melanogaster</source>. <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>; <year>1985</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Die Eytipen der Insekten</article-title>. <source>Biol Zbl</source>. <year>1939</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>536</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Specification of the Basic Body Pattern in Insect Embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Adv In Insect Phys</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Short, Long, and Beyond: Molecular and Embryological Approaches to Insect Segmentation</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.47.091201.145251" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ento.47.091201.145251</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11729088</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Damen</surname> <given-names>WGM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prpic</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pair rule gene orthologs in spider segmentation</article-title>. <source>Evol Dev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1525-142X.2005.05065.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1525-142X.2005.05065.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16336415</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choe</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A pair-rule gene circuit defines segments sequentially in the short-germ insect Tribolium castaneum</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>6560</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0510440103" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0510440103</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16611732</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prpic</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Damen</surname> <given-names>WG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression of myriapod pair rule gene orthologs</article-title>. <source>Evodevo</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/2041-9139-2-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/2041-9139-2-5</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21352542</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of the pair rule gene network: Insights from a centipede</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>382</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.06.017" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.06.017</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810931</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarrazin</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peel</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Averof</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A segmentation clock with two-segment periodicity in insects</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>336</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1218256" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1218256</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403177</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sherif</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Averof</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A segmentation clock operating in blastoderm and germband stages of Tribolium development</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>4341</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.085126" xlink:type="simple">10.1242/dev.085126</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23095886</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brena</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>An analysis of segmentation dynamics throughout embryogenesis in the centipede Strigamia maritima</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1741-7007-11-112" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1741-7007-11-112</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289308</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooke</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeeman</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name>. <article-title>A clock and wavefront model for control of the number of repeated structures during animal morphogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">940335</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>PZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Short and long germ segmentation: Unanswered questions in the evolution of a developmental mode</article-title>. <source>Evol Dev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1525-142X.2005.05066.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1525-142X.2005.05066.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16336416</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surkova</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blagov</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlov</surname> <given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Dynamic control of positional information in the early Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>430</volume>:<fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature02678" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature02678</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15254541</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Surkova</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlov</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manu</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myasnikova</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samsonova</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Characterization of the Drosophila segment determination morphome</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>313</volume>:<fpage>844</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2007.10.037" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2007.10.037</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18067886</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sherif</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Shadow Enhancers Mediate Dynamic Shifts of Gap Gene Expression in the Drosophila Embryo</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1164</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2016.02.054" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2016.02.054</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27112292</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keränen</surname> <given-names>SVE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fowlkes</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luengo Hendriks</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sudar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knowles</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Three-dimensional morphology and gene expression in the Drosophila blastoderm at cellular resolution II: dynamics</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>R124</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/gb-2006-7-12-r124" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/gb-2006-7-12-r124</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17184547</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinhardt</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hierarchical inductions of cell states: a model for segmentation in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci Suppl</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3462194</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Odell</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubiger</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>A genetic switch, based on negative regulation, sharpens stripes in Drosophila embryos</article-title>. <source>Dev Genet</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/dvg.1020100303" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/dvg.1020100303</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2500279</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumgartner</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noll</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Network of interactions among pair-rule genes regulating paired expression during primordial segmentation of Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Mech Dev</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1982920</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinitz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glass</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reverse engineering the gap gene network of Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e51</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0020051" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0020051</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manu</surname></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Surkova</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spirov</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gursky</surname> <given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>A-R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Canalization of Gene Expression in the Drosophila Blastoderm by Gap Gene Cross Regulation</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e1000049</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000049" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000049</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19750121</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verd</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crombach</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <source>A damped oscillator imposes temporal order on posterior gap gene expression in Drosophila</source>. <year>2017</year>. Preprint. Available from: bioRxiv <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/068072" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/068072</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klingler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gergen</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantitative analysis of gene function in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10628987</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klingler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soong</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gergen</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Disperse versus compact elements for the regulation of runt stripes in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>177</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1006/dbio.1996.0146" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/dbio.1996.0146</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8660878</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peter</surname> <given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faure</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predictive computation of genomic logic processing functions in embryonic development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>16434</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1207852109" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1207852109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22927416</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rushlow</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cross-regulatory interactions among pair-rule genes in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>233</volume>:<fpage>953</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3755551</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <source>Complementary patterns of even-skipped and fushi tarazu expression involve their differential regulation by a common set of segmentation genes in Drosophila</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>981</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gergen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Interactions between the pair-rule genes runt, hairy, even-skipped and fushi tarazu and the establishment of periodic pattern in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vavra</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The zygotic control of Drosophila pair-rule gene expression: II. Spatial repression by gap and pair-rule gene products</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manoukian</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Concentration-dependent activities of the even-skipped protein in Drosophila embryos</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1740</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1355458</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manoukian</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Control of segmental asymetry in Drosophila embryos</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7915670</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saulier-Le Dréan</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiadka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamic changes in the functions of Odd-skipped during early Drosophila embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>4851</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9806933</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swantek</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gergen</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ftz modulates Runt-dependent activation and repression of segment-polarity gene transcription</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>2281</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.01109" xlink:type="simple">10.1242/dev.01109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15102703</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weir</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubiger</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kornberg</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Repression and turnover pattern fushi tarazu RNA in the early Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>747</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3096577</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weir</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kornberg</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubiger</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial regulation of engrailed expression in the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1194</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2461329</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vavra</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The zygotic control of Drosophila pair-rule gene expression: I. A search for new pair-rule regulatory loci</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2612384</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiadka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Kinetic analysis of segmentation gene interactions in Drosophila embryos</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>1515</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10068644</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiromi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation and Function of the Drosophila Segmentation Gene fushi tarazu</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>963</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2887293</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schier</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehring</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Direct homeodomain—DNA interaction in the autoregulation of the fushi tarazu gene</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>356</volume>:<fpage>804</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/356804a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/356804a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1574120</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinhardt</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <source>Models of biological pattern formation</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>1982</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinhardt</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Models for positional signalling, the threefold subdivision of segments and the pigmentation pattern of molluscs</article-title>. <source>J Embryol Exp Morphol</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>83</volume> <issue>Suppl</issue>:<fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peel</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>. <source>Evidence for the temporal regulation of insect segmentation by a conserved set of developmental transcription factors</source>. <year>2017</year>. Preprint. Available from: bioRxiv <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/145151" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/145151</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujioka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yusibova</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaynes</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The repressor activity of Even-skipped is highly conserved, and is sufficient to activate engrailed and to regulate both the spacing and stability of parasegment boundaries</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>4411</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223400</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Odell</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schubiger</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cytoarchitecture and the patterning of fushi tarazu expression in the Drosophila blastoderm</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1226</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3123317</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ish-Horowicz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Apical localization of pair-rule transcripts requires 3’ sequences and limits protein diffusion in the Drosophila blastoderm embryo</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>927</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1959136</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tikhonov</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregor</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Precise developmental gene expression arises from globally stochastic transcriptional activity</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>789</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.07.025" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2013.07.025</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23953111</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref092"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desponds</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraro</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perez Romero</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Precision of readout at the hunchback gene: analyzing short transcription time traces in living fly embryos</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e1005256</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005256" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005256</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27942043</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref093"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinitz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>On the dynamic nature of positional information</article-title>. <source>BioEssays</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1102</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/bies.20494" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/bies.20494</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041900</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref094"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struhl</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>A molecular gradient in early Drosophila embryos and its role in specifying the body pattern</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>324</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/324537a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/324537a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2878369</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref095"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiadka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Patterning of the Drosophila embryo by a homeodomain-deleted Ftz polypeptide</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>379</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/379162a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/379162a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8538765</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref096"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Soriano</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashburner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Dichaete gene of Drosophila melanogaster encodes a SOX-domain protein required for embryonic segmentation</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>3669</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8951082</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref097"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nambu</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nambu</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Drosophila fish-hook gene encodes a HMG domain protein essential for segmentation and CNS development</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>3467</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8951062</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref098"><label>98</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nusslein-Volhard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kluding</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jurgens</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genes affecting the segmental subdivision of the Drosophila embryo</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3868475</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref099"><label>99</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warrior</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tugwood</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular analysis of even-skipped mutants in Drosophila development</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1824</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2907321</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref100"><label>100</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klingler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gergen</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of runt transcription by Drosophila segmentation genes</article-title>. <source>Mech Dev</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8240970</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref101"><label>101</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riechmann</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irion</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grosskortenhaus</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leptin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Control of cell fates and segmentation in the Drosophila mesoderm</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>2915</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9247334</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref102"><label>102</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulter</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieschaus</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gene activities and segmental patterning in Drosophila: analysis of odd-skipped and pair-rule double mutants</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1812</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3240861</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref103"><label>103</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of segmentation: Rolling back the clock</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>708</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref104"><label>104</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peel</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chipman</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Arthropod segmentation: beyond the Drosophila paradigm</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>905</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrg1724" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrg1724</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16341071</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref105"><label>105</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farzana</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <source>Hedgehog signaling pathway function conserved in Tribolium segmentation</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref106"><label>106</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budd</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Deciphering the onychophoran “segmentation gene cascade”: Gene expression reveals limited involvement of pair rule gene orthologs in segmentation, but a highly conserved segment polarity gene network</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>382</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.07.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.07.010</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23880430</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref107"><label>107</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Autoinhibition with Transcriptional Delay</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1398</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12932323</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref108"><label>108</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schröter</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ares</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morelli</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isakova</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hens</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soroldoni</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Topology and dynamics of the zebrafish segmentation clock core circuit</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e1001364</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001364" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001364</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref109"><label>109</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schröder</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hausdorf</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>A caudal homologue in the short germ band beetle Tribolium shows similarities to both, the Drosophila and the vertebrate caudal expression patterns</article-title>. <source>Dev Genes Evol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>208</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9683744</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref110"><label>110</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dessaud</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulloa</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Interpretation of the sonic hedgehog morphogen gradient by a temporal adaptation mechanism</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>450</volume>:<fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature06347" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature06347</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18046410</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref111"><label>111</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>A System of Repressor Gradients Spatially Organizes the Boundaries of Bicoid-Dependent Target Genes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>149</volume>:<fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2012.03.018" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2012.03.018</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22541432</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref112"><label>112</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregor</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamic interpretation of maternal inputs by the Drosophila segmentation gene network</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>6724</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1220912110" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1220912110</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23580621</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref113"><label>113</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandre</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baena-lopez</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Patterning and growth control by membrane-tethered Wingless</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>505</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature12879" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature12879</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24390349</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref114"><label>114</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chipman</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arthur</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A double segment periodicity underlies segment generation in centipede development</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1250</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2004.07.026" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2004.07.026</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15268854</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref115"><label>115</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaramillo</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pax group III genes and the evolution of insect pair-rule patterning</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>3445</fpage>–<lpage>3458</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11566851</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref116"><label>116</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D’Alessio</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pax3/7 genes reveal conservation and divergence in the arthropod segmentation hierarchy</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>285</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2005.06.014" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2005.06.014</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16083872</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref117"><label>117</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clyde</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corado</surname> <given-names>MSG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paré</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papatsenko</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>A self-organizing system of repressor gradients establishes segmental complexity in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>426</volume>:<fpage>849</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature02189" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature02189</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14685241</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref118"><label>118</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goltsev</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiong</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanzaro</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Different combinations of gap repressors for common stripes in Anopheles and Drosophila embryos</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2004.08.021" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2004.08.021</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501229</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref119"><label>119</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsimiklis</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siggia</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>François</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predicting Ancestral Segmentation Phenotypes from Drosophila to Anopheles Using In Silico Evolution</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e1006052</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1006052" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006052</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27227405</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref120"><label>120</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brent</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payre</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desplan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dual mode of embryonic development is highlighted by expression and function of Nasonia pair-rule genes</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e01440</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.01440" xlink:type="simple">10.7554/eLife.01440</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24599282</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref121"><label>121</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analyses of interactions among pair-rule genes and the gap gene Krüppel in Bombyx segmentation</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>405</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2015.06.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2015.06.005</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref122"><label>122</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakao</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hunchback knockdown induces supernumerary segment formation in Bombyx</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>413</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2016.03.024" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ydbio.2016.03.024</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27016505</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref123"><label>123</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wotton</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez-Guri</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crombach</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alcaine-Colet</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemke</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Quantitative system drift compensates for altered maternal inputs to the gap gene network of the scuttle fly megaselia abdita</article-title>. <source>Elife</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e04785</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref124"><label>124</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crombach</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wotton</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiménez-Guri</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeger</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gap Gene Regulatory Dynamics Evolve along a Genotype Network</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1293</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msw013" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msw013</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26796549</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref125"><label>125</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lander</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name>. <article-title>How Cells Know Where They Are</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>339</volume>:<fpage>923</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1224186" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1224186</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23430648</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref126"><label>126</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertrand</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chartrand</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shenoy</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singer</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Localization of ASH1 mRNA Particles in Living Yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9809065</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref127"><label>127</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gavis</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <article-title>Live Imaging of Endogenous RNA Reveals a Diffusion and Entrapment Mechanism for nanos mRNA Localization in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1159</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12867026</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref128"><label>128</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tikhonov</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregor</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quantitative Imaging of Transcription in Living Drosophila Embryos Links Polymerase Activity to Patterning</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>2140</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2013.08.054" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2013.08.054</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24139738</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref129"><label>129</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benton</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlopoulos</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cell and tissue dynamics during Tribolium embryogenesis revealed by versatile fluorescence labeling approaches</article-title>. <source>Development</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>140</volume>:<fpage>3210</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1242/dev.096271" xlink:type="simple">10.1242/dev.096271</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23861059</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref130"><label>130</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamoto</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hester</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Constantinou</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaine</surname> <given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tewksbury</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matei</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Changing cell behaviours during beetle embryogenesis correlates with slowing of segmentation</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>6635</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms7635" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/ncomms7635</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25858515</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref131"><label>131</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Linking gene regulation to cell behaviors in the posterior growth zone of sequentially segmenting arthropods</article-title>. <source>Arthropod Struct Dev</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref132"><label>132</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stollewerk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoppmeier</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Damen</surname> <given-names>WGM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Involvement of Notch and Delta genes in spider segmentation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>423</volume>:<fpage>863</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature01682" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature01682</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815430</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref133"><label>133</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pueyo</surname> <given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanfear</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couso</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ancestral Notch-mediated segmentation revealed in the cockroach Periplaneta americana</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>16614</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0804093105" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0804093105</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18927236</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref134"><label>134</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ungerer</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stollewerk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The function of Notch signalling in segment formation in the crustacean Daphnia magna (Branchiopoda)</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>383</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref135"><label>135</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paré</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vichas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fincher</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirman</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mainieri</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A positional Toll receptor code directs convergent extension in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>515</volume>:<fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature13953" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature13953</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25363762</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref136"><label>136</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benton</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pechmann</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stappert</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conrads</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Y-T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Toll Genes Have an Ancestral Role in Axis Elongation</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>26</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref137"><label>137</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Data from: Odd-paired controls frequency doubling in Drosophila segmentation by altering the pair-rule gene regulatory network</article-title>. <source>Dryad Digital Repository</source>. Openly available via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cg35k" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cg35k</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref138"><label>138</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rushlow</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characterization and localization of the even-skipped protein of Drosophila</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2884106</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref139"><label>139</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schindelin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arganda-Carreras</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frise</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaynig</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longair</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pietzsch</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2019" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nmeth.2019</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref140"><label>140</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rasband</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eliceiri</surname> <given-names>KW</given-names></name>. <article-title>NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930834</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref141"><label>141</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Walt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colbert</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varoquaux</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>The NumPy Array: A Structure for Efficient Numerical Computation</article-title>. <source>Comput Sci Eng</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref142"><label>142</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Matplotlib: A 2D Graphics Environment</article-title>. <source>Comput Sci Eng</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pbio.2002439.ref143"><label>143</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naldi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thieffry</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaouiya</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>GINsim: A software suite for the qualitative modelling, simulation and analysis of regulatory networks</article-title>. <source>BioSystems</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biosystems.2005.10.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.biosystems.2005.10.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16434137</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>