<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030231</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Synopsis</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Plant Biology</subject>
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Plant Biology</subject>
          <subject>Mathematics/Statistics</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy">
          <subject>Arabidopsis (thale cress)</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Patterns of Genetic Variation Reveal Plant's Evolutionary Roots</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Synopsis</alt-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e231</elocation-id><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Public Library of Science</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article page="e196" related-article-type="companion" vol="3" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.0030196" xlink:title="research article" xlink:type="simple">
				<article-title>The Pattern of Polymorphism in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic></article-title>
			</related-article></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title/>
      <p>Biologists have developed ever more sophisticated ways to find molecular traces of natural selection. These traces—which occur as variations in DNA sequence, or polymorphisms, between and within species—are thought to harbor the genetic basis of adaptive events.</p>
      <p>The study of natural selection at the molecular level has long been dominated by Kimura's theory of neutral evolution, which argues that most polymorphisms (in both DNA and protein sequence) have minor or no selective effect, and are governed by random, not selective, processes. The strength of this theory is that it leads to clear predictions that can be tested to identify those polymorphisms that really are subject to selection. Even though there's a large body of literature devoted to the statistical testing of selective neutrality, these tests are generally based on theoretical models, the assumptions of which have largely been untested. Only recently have the necessary quantities of data for testing the merits of these models become available, thanks to high-throughput genotyping and sequencing technologies.</p>
      <p>Working with <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Arabidopsis thaliana</named-content>, the first plant genome sequenced, Magnus Nordborg, Joy Bergelson, and their colleagues investigate a global survey of polymorphism patterns in the genomes of 96 plants. The scale of their study affords robust insights into the genomic pattern of polymorphism of the plant and sheds light on its demographic history. The results also lay the foundation for future work on the genetic basis of <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. thaliana</named-content> variation while challenging the assumptions of standard mathematical models for determining whether a gene is under natural selection in the plant.</p>
      <p>Nordborg and colleagues sequenced 876 short genome fragments of 96 <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. thaliana</named-content> plants from both worldwide natural populations and laboratory stocks. In total, they described 44,000,000 DNA bases of genetic material, which revealed 17,000 polymorphisms, either in the form of single changes in DNA sequence (single nucleotide polymorphisms, or SNPs) or as losses or additions of DNA sequence between individual plants.</p>
      <p>The level of polymorphism in <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. thaliana</named-content> is unexpectedly high for a plant that is highly self-fertilizing. To see if these polymorphisms were uniformly shared across plant populations, or had a distinct structure, Nordborg and colleagues grouped a subset of the <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. thaliana</named-content> plants into populations based on their geographic origin. Although they found that individuals within a population harbor much of the variation that is typical of the species worldwide, it appeared that some of the variation was specific to particular geographic regions. Furthermore, closely related plants were almost always from the same local region. The authors suggest that is what would be expected for a sexually reproducing species found worldwide. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0030231-g001"/></p>
      <fig id="pbio-0030231-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030231.g001</object-id>
        <caption>
          <title>The global geographic structure of variation in <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Arabidopsis</named-content> is shown by the clusters of similar pie charts signifying patterns of isolation (each chart represents an <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Arabidopsis</named-content> accession)</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.0030231.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>With such a large data set, it also becomes possible to see if the underlying assumptions of mathematical models commonly used for determining whether a gene is under selection are appropriate for <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. thaliana</named-content>. Nordborg and colleagues found that the patterns they observe do not fit the standard neutral model of evolution, which is expected to explain most genetic variation. This model is the benchmark against which researchers pinpoint the signature of selection at particular genes. The authors caution that “commonly used ‘tests of selection’ are simply not valid in <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">A. thaliana</named-content>.”</p>
      <p>Nordborg and colleagues have provided a wealth of detail to our understanding of genetic variation in <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Arabidopsis</named-content> on a genome-wide scale. Future research can now begin to use this <named-content content-type="genus-species" xlink:type="simple">Arabidopsis</named-content> genetic footprint to find the exact variations that contribute to useful plant traits—and plumb its genome for evolutionary clues.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
</article>