<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PBIOLOGY-D-11-02322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Proteins</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Protein interactions</subject>
                <subject>Transmembrane proteins</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biomacromolecule-ligand interactions</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Model organisms</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal models</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Zebrafish</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Molecular cell biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cellular types</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Muscle fibers</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Signal transduction</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Membrane receptor signaling</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Molecular Biology</subject>
          <subject>Cell Biology</subject>
          <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Jamb and Jamc Are Essential for Vertebrate Myocyte Fusion</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Jamb-Jamc Are Essential for Myocyte Fusion</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Powell</surname>
            <given-names>Gareth T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wright</surname>
            <given-names>Gavin J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Hinxton, Cambridge, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Currie</surname>
            <given-names>Peter D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Monash University, Australia</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">gw2@sanger.ac.uk</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>The author(s) have made the following declarations about their contributions: Conceived and designed the experiments: GTP GJW. Performed the experiments: GTP GJW. Analyzed the data: GTP GJW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GTP. Wrote the paper: GTP GJW.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e1001216</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Powell, Wright</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="uri" id="RA1" related-article-type="companion" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001217" xlink:type="simple"> <article-title>Jamb and Jamc Muscle in on Myoblast Fusion</article-title></related-article><abstract abstract-type="toc">
        <p>Jamb and Jamc are an essential cell surface receptor pair that interact to drive fusion between muscle precursor cells during zebrafish development.</p>
      </abstract><abstract>
        <p>Cellular fusion is required in the development of several tissues, including skeletal muscle. In vertebrates, this process is poorly understood and lacks an in vivo-validated cell surface heterophilic receptor pair that is necessary for fusion. Identification of essential cell surface interactions between fusing cells is an important step in elucidating the molecular mechanism of cellular fusion. We show here that the zebrafish orthologues of JAM-B and JAM-C receptors are essential for fusion of myocyte precursors to form syncytial muscle fibres. Both <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are dynamically co-expressed in developing muscles and encode receptors that physically interact. Heritable mutations in either gene prevent myocyte fusion in vivo, resulting in an overabundance of mononuclear, but otherwise overtly normal, functional fast-twitch muscle fibres. Transplantation experiments show that the Jamb and Jamc receptors must interact between neighbouring cells (in trans) for fusion to occur. We also show that <italic>jamc</italic> is ectopically expressed in <italic>prdm1a</italic> mutant slow muscle precursors, which inappropriately fuse with other myocytes, suggesting that control of myocyte fusion through regulation of <italic>jamc</italic> expression has important implications for the growth and patterning of muscles. Our discovery of a receptor-ligand pair critical for fusion in vivo has important implications for understanding the molecular mechanisms responsible for myocyte fusion and its regulation in vertebrate myogenesis.</p>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
        <title>Author Summary</title>
        <p>The fusion of precursor cells is a crucial step in many biological processes, one of which is the development of skeletal muscle. The molecular and cell biology of fusion of muscle precursors has been well described in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> larvae, leading to insights into the process in vertebrates. However, the identity and mechanism of action of essential cell surface proteins for fusion between vertebrate muscle precursors has previously been lacking. Here, we describe a vertebrate-specific cell surface receptor pair that is essential for fusion in zebrafish: Jamb and Jamc. Loss of function of either receptor causes a near-complete block in fusion, resulting in an overabundance of mononucleate muscle fibres that are otherwise overtly normal. We demonstrate that Jamb and Jamc physically interact and are co-expressed by muscle precursors. Moreover, we show that the interaction between them is essential for fusion between neighbouring precursors in an embryo. We hypothesise that binding of Jamb to Jamc is a necessary recognition and adhesion step permissive for, but not sufficient to cause, myocyte fusion. Knowledge of these molecular components in vertebrates will lead to better understanding of how fusion is controlled to pattern skeletal muscle tissue.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Generation of the zebrafish knockout alleles was sponsored by a ZF-MODELS Integrated Project (contract number LSHG- CT-2003-503496) funded by the European Commission and by the Wellcome Trust (grant number WT 077047/Z/05/Z). Our work was supported by the Wellcome Trust (grant number 077108/Z/05/Z). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="12"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Cell–cell fusion is crucial for several biological processes, including placental development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Huppertz1">[1]</xref>, bone remodelling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ishii1">[2]</xref>, fertilisation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Sutovsky1">[3]</xref>, and formation of skeletal muscle fibres <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Capers1">[4]</xref>, but surprisingly remains poorly understood. Skeletal muscle forms the bulk of tissue in vertebrates and is composed of bundles of long syncytial fibres formed by the fusion of post-mitotic muscle precursor cells (myocytes). It is a highly regenerative tissue, constantly undergoing repair and growth through the fusion of myocytes to form new fibres or supplement established ones. Impairment of the function of muscle, through age or genetic lesion, results in mild-to-severe pathologies that shorten lifespan, reduce quality of life, and demand a high burden of care. A more complete understanding of the molecular mechanisms of muscle development may lead to better treatment of muscle diseases and greater insights into regenerative medicine.</p>
      <p>Muscle development has been well characterised in the larval body wall musculature of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>, where fusion occurs between two sub-populations of myoblasts, referred to as the fusion-competent myoblasts (FCMs) and founder cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Bate1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Rochlin1">[7]</xref>. The process of fusion has been resolved into a series of intermediate steps through ultrastructural analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Doberstein1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Sens1">[10]</xref> and identification of the molecular components through forward genetics screens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Onel1">[11]</xref>. A critical step in fusion is the initial recognition and adhesion between the two cell types. This is regulated by the mutually exclusive expression of the cell surface receptor proteins Kirre and Sns, which form a heterophilic receptor pair between neighbouring cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Bour1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Galletta1">[17]</xref>. Mutations in genes encoding these cellular recognition receptors (and their partially redundant paralogues Rst and Hbs) result in a severe block in fusion between the muscle precursors. In vertebrates, a functionally equivalent heterophilic receptor pair that is essential for myocyte fusion in vivo has yet to be identified <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Krauss1">[18]</xref>. One approach to isolate the vertebrate receptors has focussed on using sequence orthology to the fruitfly proteins—a rationale which is validated by emerging evidence that the molecular pathways important for myocyte fusion are conserved across these species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Laurin1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Vasyutina1">[23]</xref>. Cell culture experiments have also suggested the involvement of several other cell surface proteins in vertebrate myocyte fusion, for example BOC and CDO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Kang1">[24]</xref>. Loss-of-function studies of these candidates resulted in mild disruption of myocyte fusion in vivo, leading to the view that this process involves several partially redundant proteins in vertebrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Krauss1">[18]</xref>. Only one vertebrate receptor, Kirrel3l (originally named Kirrel), has been identified as essential for myocyte fusion in vivo by using an antisense morpholino to knockdown the protein in zebrafish embryos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Srinivas1">[22]</xref>. There is no known Kirrel3l counter-receptor involved in the process of fusion, suggesting that other important vertebrate receptors remain to be discovered.</p>
      <p>In this study, we identify two vertebrate cell surface receptors that are crucial for myocyte fusion: Jamb and Jamc (official nomenclature: Jam2a and Jam3b, respectively; Entrez gene: 100005261, 569217, respectively). The mammalian orthologues of both genes, commonly referred to as JAM-B and JAM-C (after rationalisation of the gene family nomenclature within the field <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Muller1">[25]</xref>), have well-characterized roles in leukocyte migration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Weber1">[26]</xref>, tight junction formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-AurrandLions1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ebnet1">[29]</xref>, and spermatogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Gliki1">[30]</xref>. Mouse Jam-B (Jam2) and Jam-C (Jam3) are members of a small sub-group of immunoglobulin superfamily cell surface proteins that is restricted to the deuterostome lineage (TreeFam <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ruan1">[31]</xref>). They contain two extracellular immunoglobulin superfamily domains, a single transmembrane domain and a short cytoplasmic domain ending in a type II PDZ domain binding motif <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ebnet2">[32]</xref>. Heterophilic interactions between Jam-B and Jam-C are thought to be important for leukocyte transmigration across vascular endothelia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Weber1">[26]</xref> and the polarisation of spermatids necessary for complete differentiation into functional spermatozoa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Gliki1">[30]</xref>, but to date, there is no reported function for Jam-B and Jam-C in muscle development.</p>
      <p>We have shown here that <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are co-expressed in developing myoblasts and, by using mutant zebrafish, demonstrate that the physical interaction between them is essential for myocyte fusion in vivo. By analysing the mutant phenotypes and showing that <italic>jamc</italic> expression is misregulated in a muscle patterning mutant, we provide new insights into the regulatory mechanisms that govern vertebrate myogenesis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Zebrafish <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> Are Co-Expressed by Fast Muscle Myoblasts</title>
        <p>To identify novel receptor pairs that might be involved in myocyte fusion, we queried our large database of extracellular protein interactions constructed by screening a library of 249 zebrafish receptor proteins using the AVEXIS assay and supported by embryonic expression patterns of the corresponding genes during zebrafish embryonic development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Bushell1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Martin1">[35]</xref>. One pair, Jamb and Jamc, was selected because both genes are expressed by dividing myoblasts during primary myogenesis, but in distinct patterns. <italic>jamb</italic> is expressed by all fast muscle myoblasts shortly after the formation of each somite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). After approximately 10–13 somites have formed, <italic>jamc</italic> is initially highly expressed in a small, medial sub-population of fast muscle myoblasts along the dorsal-ventral axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1B</xref>, 10–13 somites). Over time, the expression domain of <italic>jamc</italic> expands to include all myoblasts in the hypaxial and epaxial regions of the myotome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1B</xref>, 17–18 somites, 21 somites). <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are co-expressed by all myoblasts in the anterior somites by the 17–18 somites stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1</xref>, 17–18 somites) and in posterior somites at later stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1</xref>, 21 somites). Whilst highly expressed in developing muscle, <italic>jamc</italic> also appears to be expressed at a basal level throughout the embryo—an observation that is replicated using a second riboprobe specific to the 3′ UTR of <italic>jamc</italic> (unpublished data). The expression of both genes in the myotome is attenuated in axial musculature by 24 h post-fertilisation (h. p. f.), but subsequently upregulated in later-developing craniofacial, abdominal, and pectoral fin muscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1A,B</xref>). We conclude that both <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are expressed in the somites of the embryo in a wave along the anterior-posterior axis. Within each somite, <italic>jamc</italic> expression begins medially and spreads laterally throughout the domain of <italic>jamb</italic>-expressing fast muscle myoblasts over time, so that both genes are co-expressed by myoblasts during the initial period of fusion between somitic precursors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Moore1">[20]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Snow1">[36]</xref>. Dynamic co-expression of the <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> genes in the developing musculature and later forming muscles suggested a role for the interaction between these two cell surface receptor proteins in myogenesis.</p>
        <fig id="pbio-1001216-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are co-expressed in myoblasts.</title>
            <p>(A–B) Wholemount in situ hybridisation of <italic>jamb</italic> (A) and <italic>jamc</italic> (B) show expression in myoblasts during somitogenesis (10–13 somites, 17–18 somites, and 21 somites). Expression is attenuated in the myotome after the completion of primary myogenesis (24 h. p. f.) and then later upregulated in craniofacial (cf), pectoral fin (arrows), and hypaxial (open arrowheads) muscle mesoderm (48 h. p. f.). Scale bars represent 50 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title><italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> Are Essential for Myocyte Fusion</title>
        <p>To establish whether <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> were important for myocyte fusion in vivo, mutant alleles of both genes were obtained from the Hubrecht Institute (<italic>HU3319</italic>) and Sanger Institute Zebrafish Mutation Resource (<italic>sa0037</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Mutations within selected exons of <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> were identified by amplifying and directly sequencing PCR products from libraries of chemically mutagenised zebrafish. The <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> allele is a nonsense mutation that results in a premature stop codon near the N-terminus of the protein. A truncating mutation was not recovered for the <italic>jamc</italic> gene, but one allele, <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic>, contained a missense point mutation in a cysteine residue (C<sup>136</sup> to Y) that is predicted to form a structurally critical disulphide bond. Both <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> homozygous mutant embryos exhibited the same striking phenotype: regimented lines of centrally positioned nuclei within each myotome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). In wild-type embryos, somitic fast muscle myocytes fuse together to form multinucleate muscle fibres by approximately 24 h. p. f. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Moore1">[20]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Snow1">[36]</xref>. In <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutants, fast muscle myocytes did not fuse, but instead, fully elongated to form mononuclear fibres that spanned each somite by 48 h. p. f. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2B</xref>) and remained mononucleate until at least 5 days post-fertilisation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). We quantified the lack of fusion in subsequent transplant experiments: 95% and 85% of fast fibres remained mononucleate in <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> donor into <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> host and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> donor into <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> host transplants, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). To provide independent evidence that the mutations in both <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> were responsible for the phenotype, we injected translation-blocking morpholino antisense oligonucleotides targeted to both <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> into wild-type embryos. Embryos injected with either morpholino phenocopied the mutants, demonstrating that the phenotype was not due to closely linked mutations in either the <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> or <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutant lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). From these experiments we conclude that zebrafish <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are essential for myocyte fusion.</p>
        <fig id="pbio-1001216-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are essential for myocyte fusion in vivo.</title>
            <p>(A) Schematics of Jamb and Jamc extracellular proteins. Red stars denote sites of mutation in <italic>HU3319</italic> and <italic>sa0037</italic> alleles. (B–C) Confocal microscopy images of fast-twitch muscle in wild-type, <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic>, and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> 48 h. p. f. (B) and 120 h. p. f. (C) Embryos labelled with membrane targeted RFP (mRFP, cyan; B) or phalloidin-Alexa488 (cyan; C) and DAPI (red) show overabundant, mononuclear myofibres in both mutants. (D) Confocal microscopy images of uninjected, <italic>jamb</italic>, and <italic>jamc</italic> translation-blocking morpholino-injected wild-type embryos, stained with DAPI (red) and phalloidin-Alexa488 (cyan) to stain F-actin in fast muscle fibres. The morpholino-injected embryos replicate the <italic>jam</italic> mutants' phenotype. Myotomes 12–13 shown, anterior left. Scale bars represent 50 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="pbio-1001216-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Quantification of fused (multinucleated) and unfused (mononucleated) fluorescently labelled fast muscle fibres in transplanted hosts.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pbio-1001216-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Donor Genotype</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Host Genotype</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Wild-Type</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unfused</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fused</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>n</italic>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unfused</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fused</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>n</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unfused</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fused</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>n</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">wild-type</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">254, 6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">712, 7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">403, 9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">341, 8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.9%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.1%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">526, 6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.4%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.6%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">525, 9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                  <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">630, 10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">582, 7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">218, 9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> MO<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.8%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">738, 16</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">n. d.</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">407, 9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> and <italic>jamb</italic> MO<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76.0%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.0%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">250, 11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.7%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.3%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">153, 6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n. d.</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>“n” denotes number of fibres, number of embryos analysed at 48 h. p. f. for each transplant experiment.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Translation blocking morpholino injected into donor before transplantation. n. d., not determined.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label>c</label>
              <p>Minority fusion events are likely a result of incomplete morpholino knockdown, as seen in control transplants using <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> or <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutant hosts.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Myogenesis Is Overtly Normal in Both <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> Mutants</title>
        <p>In teleost fish, two spatially segregated muscle populations form during primary myogenesis: superficially located slow-twitch muscle and medial fast-twitch muscle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Currie1">[37]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Devoto1">[39]</xref>. Fast muscle fibres are syncytial (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2B</xref>), but slow muscle fibres remain mononucleate during embryonic development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Roy1">[40]</xref>. To determine if the mononuclear muscle fibres in <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutants do correctly differentiate as fast-twitch muscle, we used antibodies that are specific for the slow and fast isoforms of myosin heavy chain (sMyHC and fMyHC). We observed that both mutants had the same number of normal, superficially positioned slow muscle fibres (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g003">Figure 3A</xref>) with no ectopic expression of sMyHC within the deeper fibres. The medially located, and more numerous, mononuclear fibres in both mutants expressed fMyHC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g003">Figure 3B</xref>), suggesting that specification of fast-twitch muscle was unaffected. Finally, we observed no difference in the ability and timing of spontaneous twitching and response to tactile stimuli in either mutant relative to wild-type, suggesting that the muscles were innervated and fully functional (unpublished data). Together, these data suggest that both mutants are able to complete the myogenic programme, except for a specific defect in fusion. These findings also suggest that other aspects of terminal differentiation, such as elongation and sarcomerogenesis, do not depend upon myocyte fusion in vertebrates.</p>
        <fig id="pbio-1001216-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Fast and slow-twitch muscle fibres are correctly specified in <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> embryos.</title>
            <p>(A) Superimposed confocal microscopy images of 24 h. p. f. wild-type, <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic>, and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> embryos stained with monoclonal antibody F59, which detects slow-muscle-specific myosin heavy chain (sMyHC), show normal slow muscle development in both mutants. (B) Single optical sections of 48 h. p. f. wild-type, <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic>, and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> embryos stained with monoclonal antibody EB165, which detects fast-muscle-specific myosin heavy chain (fMyHC), show that the medial mononuclear fibres in both mutants have differentiated as fast-twitch muscle. Myotomes 12–13 shown, anterior left. Scale bars represent 50 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Fast Muscle Fibres Are Supernumerary in <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> Mutants</title>
        <p>We observed an overt overabundance of fast muscle fibres in both mutants relative to wild-type embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). We quantified this increase by counting fibres outlined by a membrane-localised red fluorescent protein (mRFP) in optical cross-sections of wild-type and mutant embryos at 24, 32, and 48 h. p. f. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g004">Figure 4A</xref>), revealing a statistically significant increase (<italic>p</italic>≤0.001) in fast fibre number in mutants by 1.6–1.8-fold, relative to wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g004">Figure 4B</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s005">Table S1</xref>). Interestingly, there was not as great an increase as might have been expected from the average number of nuclei in each wild-type fast muscle fibre (approximately 2.7 and 3.2 at 32 and 48 h. p. f., respectively; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Moore1">[20]</xref>). Staining mutant embryos with acridine orange did not reveal any increase in apoptosis relative to wild-type (unpublished data). In addition, we did not observe any rounded, unelongated, unfused myoblasts expressing fMyHC in either mutant or wild-type embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g003">Figure 3B</xref>), suggesting that all somitic fast muscle myoblasts had undergone differentiation. Between 32 and 48 h. p. f., myotome muscle fibre number increased by a similar proportion in both mutant and wild-type embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). In contrast, the number of nuclei within each mutant myotome was decreased compared to wild-type embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g004">Figure 4C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s006">Table S2</xref>), suggesting that myoblast proliferation is limited in both mutants. In other words, growth of mutant, mononucleate fast muscle myotome requires less myocytes than the equivalent amount of growth of wild-type, syncytial fast muscle myotome. Taken together, these results reveal that the majority of fast muscle myoblasts could elongate and form functional mononuclear muscle fibres, resulting in an overabundance of fast muscle (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s001">Figure S1</xref>). This suggests that axial fast muscle precursors are not divided into distinct subpopulations.</p>
        <fig id="pbio-1001216-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Fast muscle fibres are supernumary in <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> embryos.</title>
            <p>(A) Transverse sections projected from confocal microscopy images of 48 h. p. f. embryos labelled with mRFP. (B–C) Graphs showing a significant overabundance (1.6–1.8-fold) of muscle fibres in mutants compared to wild-type (B) and calculated muscle nuclei number in wild-type and mutant embryos between 24 and 48 h. p. f. (C). Asterisk denotes <italic>p</italic>≤0.001; one-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic> test; error bars represent standard deviation, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s005">Tables S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s006">S2</xref> for number of embryos in each sample.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Jamb and Jamc Physically Interact</title>
        <p>Both <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are expressed in fast muscle myoblasts during primary myogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1</xref>) and loss-of-function of either gene results in a severe block in myocyte fusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2</xref>), without overtly affecting any other aspect of axial muscle differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that Jamb and Jamc are a receptor pair necessary for myocyte fusion.</p>
        <p>The mammalian orthologues of Jamb and Jamc are known to form both homophilic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Cunningham1">[41]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Santoso1">[42]</xref> and heterophilic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Arrate1">[43]</xref> interaction pairs. Our large-scale systematic protein interaction screen identified a heterophilic interaction between zebrafish Jamb and Jamc, but no homophilic binding was observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Bushell1">[33]</xref>. Homophilic interactions are known to be the main class of false negatives in the AVEXIS assay used in these screens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Bushell1">[33]</xref>, so to determine whether zebrafish Jamb and Jamc could interact homophilically and to quantify the relative biophysical binding parameters, we used soluble recombinant proteins and surface plasmon resonance. We found that both Jamb and Jamc were able to bind each other with an equilibrium binding constant typical of extracellular protein interactions between membrane-embedded cell surface receptors (<italic>K</italic><sub>D</sub>≈4.7±0.7 µM, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g005">Figure 5A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Wright1">[44]</xref>). To compare between all three possible interactions of Jamb and Jamc, we used dissociation phase data of binding experiments to calculate dissociation rate constants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). We took this approach because equilibrium measurements can be confounded by unreliable estimates of analyte activities, which are affected by homophilic interactions within the analyte. Dissociation rate constants are independent of analyte activity and can therefore be more appropriately compared. As expected from studies of the mammalian orthologues, both proteins could also self-associate, but with a much weaker interaction strength than that of the heterophilic interaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). All dissociation curves fitted a first-order decay equation well, suggesting a 1-to-1 binding mechanism. These experiments show that while zebrafish Jamb and Jamc are indeed able to form homodimers, the heterophilic interaction between them is significantly stronger.</p>
        <fig id="pbio-1001216-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Jamb and Jamc physically interact.</title>
            <p>(A) Surface plasmon resonance experiments determine the equilibrium binding constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>D</sub>) for the heterophilic interaction between Jamb and Jamc (inset: sensorgrams showing equilibrium has been reached). (B) Dissociation rate constants and half-lives of homophilic and heterophilic interactions between recombinant extracellular domains of Jamb and Jamc. Curves represent a fit to a first-order decay, indicating a 1∶1 stoichiometry of binding. Dissociation data are the mean of three analyte concentrations for each interaction tested; error bars represent standard deviation.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>The Interaction Between Jamb and Jamc Is Essential for Fusion In Vivo</title>
        <p>Having established that both proteins could physically interact (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g005">Figure 5</xref>) and that <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are co-expressed by myoblasts in wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g001">Figure 1</xref>) and mutant embryos (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s002">Figure S2</xref>), we used cellular transplantation experiments to determine the mechanism of binding between Jamb and Jamc for myocyte fusion in vivo.</p>
        <p>Firstly, to demonstrate that <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> mutant myocytes are unable to fuse to each other, as observed in the mutant phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g002">Figure 2</xref>), we transplanted fluorescent dextran-labelled cells from <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> donors into <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> hosts and counted the number of labelled mononucleated or multinucleated fibres at 48 h. p. f. (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). As expected, only 5% of myocytes derived from transplanted donor cells were able to fuse to mutant host myocytes, showing that expression of Jamc is unable to compensate for the loss of Jamb.</p>
        <p>To establish if myocytes lacking <italic>jamb</italic> are nevertheless competent for fusion, we transplanted cells from <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> donors into wild-type hosts, and vice versa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g006">Figure 6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). When transplanted into wild-type hosts, 93% of <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> mutant cells could form multinucleate fibres, suggesting they are able to fuse with wild-type myocytes. Similarly, 95% of wild-type myocytes were able to form multinucleate fibres when transplanted into <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> hosts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). These results demonstrate that Jamb acts non-cell-autonomously, and that Jamb and Jamc need to be expressed by neighbouring cells for fusion to occur.</p>
        <fig id="pbio-1001216-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Interaction between <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> is necessary and required in trans for myocyte fusion.</title>
            <p>(A–D) Fluorescent dextran-labelled cells (magenta) from <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> donors can form multinucleate fibres with wild-type (A, B), <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> (C), or <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> (D) host cells, respectively. (E, F) Transplanted cells from doubly-deficient donors fail to fuse with wild-type host cells, suggesting both proteins are required and interact in trans. Confocal microscopy images from 48 h. p. f. embryos; anterior left. Schematics illustrate potential binding of Jamb and Jamc between donor (magenta) and host (green) cells in each experiment. bMO, cMO indicate <italic>jamb</italic> or <italic>jamc</italic> translation-blocking morpholino-injected donor embryos. Dotted lines indicate the position of myotome boundaries; arrowheads indicate nuclei within labelled fibres. Nuclei stained with DAPI (green). Scale bars represent 20 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To determine if the Jamb and Jamc interaction between cells is necessary for fusion, we tested the prediction that transplanted <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> mutant cells (that could nevertheless express wild-type Jamc) would be able to fuse to <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> hosts (that could express wild-type Jamb). We observed that 96% of <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> mutant donor cells were able to fuse to <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutant host cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g006">Figure 6C</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). The cellular complementation between <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> mutant myocytes demonstrates that Jamb and Jamc must interact as a heterophilic pair on neighbouring cells and do not act as independent homophilic receptors.</p>
        <p>To show that the interaction between Jamb and Jamc proteins was necessary for fusion and did not require any additional factors, donor cells that were deficient in both Jamb and Jamc (<italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> embryos injected with a <italic>jamc</italic>-targeted morpholino) were transplanted into wild-type hosts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g006">Figure 6E</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). Most doubly-deficient donor cells (88%) could not fuse with wild-type host cells, demonstrating that expression of either Jamb or Jamc is essential for a myocyte to be competent for fusion. Doubly-deficient embryos are indistinguishable from <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutant embryos, suggesting no further phenotypic enhancement from combined knockdown of both proteins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p>
        <p>We repeated each of the transplant experiments described above, except we used <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutants as donors to establish if myocytes from both mutants behaved similarly. As with <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> transplants, we observed that <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> donor cells were unable to fuse to <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> host cells (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>), showing that Jamb is unable to rescue the loss of Jamc; Jamb and Jamc are not redundant. Wild-type donor cells were able to fuse to <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> host cells and vice versa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g006">Figure 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>), demonstrating that <italic>jamc</italic> mutant myocytes are competent for fusion and suggesting that Jamb and Jamc need to be expressed by neighbouring cells for fusion to occur between them. In addition, <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> donor cells were able to complement <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> host cells and fuse with wild-type efficiency (95%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g006">Figure 6D</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). This reinforces the conclusion that Jamb and Jamc must interact as a heterophilic pair between adjacent cells for fusion to occur. Finally, doubly deficient cells (<italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> embryos injected with a <italic>jamb</italic>-targeted morpholino; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s003">Figure S3</xref>) were unable to fuse to wild-type host myocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g006">Figure 6F</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>), further demonstrating that no other factor is interacting with either Jamb or Jamc. Interestingly, <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutant cells transplanted into a wild-type host fused less efficiently than into a <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> host, suggesting that homophilic Jamb interactions between donor and host myocytes could inhibit fusion in the absence of Jamc on the donor cell (compare <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> donor, wild-type host and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> donor, <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> host; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g006">Figure 6B and D</xref>). Taken together, these data show that the physical interaction between Jamb-Jamc is required between neighbouring cells for myocyte fusion to occur in vivo.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title><italic>jamc</italic> Is Ectopically Expressed in <italic>prdm1a</italic> Mutant Slow Muscle Cells That Fuse Inappropriately</title>
        <p>The overabundance of fast muscle fibres in the absence of myocyte fusion suggested that the regulation of <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> might play an important role in the control of muscle patterning and development.</p>
        <p>Slow-twitch muscle myocytes do not undergo fusion during primary myogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Roy1">[40]</xref>. However, in zebrafish embryos mutant for the transcriptional repressor <italic>prdm1a</italic>, the premigratory progenitors of slow-twitch muscle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Devoto1">[39]</xref> express fast muscle-specific genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-vonHofsten1">[45]</xref> and inappropriately fuse with the neighbouring fast muscle myocytes, resulting in the absence of slow muscle fibres <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Roy1">[40]</xref>. These observations suggest that <italic>prdm1a</italic> mutant adaxial cells must ectopically express critical cell surface proteins necessary for myocyte fusion.</p>
        <p>To test if either <italic>jamb</italic>, <italic>jamc</italic>, or <italic>kirrel3l</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Srinivas1">[22]</xref> are ectopically expressed by <italic>prdm1a</italic> mutant adaxial cells, we performed wholemount in situ hybridization using riboprobes for each gene. We observed that <italic>jamc</italic> is misexpressed in the adaxial cells of <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> embryos, but that <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>kirrel3l</italic> are not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g007">Figure 7</xref>). All three genes are expressed in fast muscle myoblasts of <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> mutant embryos, as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001216-g007">Figure 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s004">Figure S4</xref>). These results suggest that misregulation of <italic>jamc</italic> permits ectopic fusion of mutant slow muscle precursors with neighbouring <italic>jamb</italic>-expressing fast muscle myocytes; in wild-type embryos, <italic>prdm1a</italic> represses <italic>jamc</italic> in adaxial cells to prevent this occurring. This also implies that a heterophilic interaction of Jamb and Jamc between mutant slow muscle cells and fast muscle myocytes is necessary for ectopic fusion events to occur. Finally, these data also suggest that transcriptional regulation of <italic>jamc</italic> triggers fast muscle myocyte fusion events in vertebrate musculature.</p>
        <fig id="pbio-1001216-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>jamc</italic> expression is regulated by <italic>prdm1a</italic>.</title>
            <p>Wholemount in situ hybridisation against <italic>jamc</italic> (left panels), <italic>jamb</italic> (middle panels), and <italic>kirrel3l</italic> (right panels) shows that <italic>jamc</italic> is ectopically expressed in premigratory slow muscle precursors (adaxial cells) of <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> mutants that later inappropriately fuse to fast muscle myocytes. In contrast, <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>kirrel3l</italic> are expressed in fast muscle myoblasts in both wild-type and <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> mutant embryos. Flatmounted embryos at 10–13 somite stage; anterior top.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To determine if expression of <italic>jamc</italic> alone is sufficient to cause fusion events between slow muscle cells and fast muscle myocytes, we attempted to ectopically express <italic>jamc</italic> in wild-type slow muscle by microinjecting transgenic embryos containing a slow muscle marker, <italic>Tg(smyhc1::egfp)<sup>i104</sup></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Elworthy1">[46]</xref>, with full-length, capped <italic>jamc</italic> mRNA or a plasmid containing full-length <italic>jamc</italic>. We did not observe any ectopic fusion events with slow muscle cells in injected embryos (unpublished data), suggesting that other components, presumably also regulated by <italic>prdm1a</italic>, are necessary for fusion. Furthermore, we tested whether or not interaction between Jamb and Jamc is sufficient to drive fusion in heterologous cells, as described for the fusogen EFF-1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Podbilewicz1">[47]</xref>, by mixing HEK293E cells transfected with plasmids containing either full-length <italic>jamb</italic> or <italic>jamc</italic>. No fusion events were observed in mixed cultures of <italic>jamb</italic>- and <italic>jamc</italic>-transfected cells, or control cultures containing only <italic>jamb</italic>- or <italic>jamc</italic>-transfected cells (unpublished data). These results suggest that the context of Jamb and Jamc binding determines whether or not the interacting cells will fuse.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Using a combination of quantitative biochemistry, mutant zebrafish, and cell transplantation experiments, we have shown that we have identified a heterophilic interaction between a cell surface receptor pair that is essential in vivo for myocyte fusion in a vertebrate. This discovery has important implications for the molecular mechanism, regulation, and evolution of cellular fusion in the context of myogenesis.</p>
      <p>The identification of Kirrel3l as a functional orthologue of Kirre/Rst in zebrafish and of other key intracellular effectors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Laurin1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Vasyutina1">[23]</xref> suggests conservation of the important signalling pathways for the process of myocyte fusion between vertebrates and invertebrates. Our discovery of Jamb and Jamc as a new deuterostome-restricted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ruan1">[31]</xref> receptor pair that is essential for fusion in the zebrafish axial musculature raises the possibility of vertebrate-specific adaptations of the components and the regulation of muscle development in vertebrates. For example, our results suggest that this interaction is independent of Kirrel3l, suggesting that multiple recognition steps between vertebrate myocytes are required for fusion.</p>
      <p>During differentiation, myocytes make a fundamental decision between founding a new muscle fibre or fusing to an existing one. In chicken and mouse embryos this decision seems to be temporally controlled: primary myocytes form an array of elongated mononucleate fibres, to which later differentiating myocytes fuse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Gros1">[48]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Venters1">[49]</xref>. In the larval body wall of <italic>Drosophila</italic>, this decision is controlled by early specification of myoblasts into two distinct subtypes, ultimately defining the number of muscle fibres formed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Rochlin1">[7]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Bour1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Strnkelnberg1">[16]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Rushton1">[50]</xref>. Our results show that in the absence of fusion in the zebrafish axial musculature, the number of fast-twitch muscle fibres almost doubles, suggesting that the fast muscle precursors are not divided into defined subpopulations, but that each myocyte is capable of founding a fibre if it does not fuse to an existing one. The co-expression of these essential receptors in all fast muscle myoblasts adds to the suggestion that the precursors are not restricted to specific fates. In addition, our transplantation experiments did not reveal any functional subdivision of myocytes; approximately 95% of <italic>jamb</italic> or <italic>jamc</italic> mutant donor myocytes were able to undergo fusion with <italic>jamc</italic> or <italic>jamb</italic> host myocytes, respectively. The dynamic nature of <italic>jamc</italic> expression in fast muscle myoblasts and repression in slow muscle precursors suggest that regulation of <italic>jamc</italic> plays a fundamental role in the patterning of muscles through the timing of fusion events, rather than specification. Furthermore, other elements of terminal differentiation, such as elongation and sarcomerogenesis, seem to be independent of the process of fusion.</p>
      <p>Our results suggest that the interaction between Jamb and Jamc expressed by neighbouring cells is essential for fusion. These cell surface receptors likely mediate an initial recognition and adhesion event similar to that of the cell surface receptors Kirre and Sns in <italic>Drosophila</italic>. It is unlikely that the interaction between Jamb and Jamc is sufficient for fusion because both proteins are known to be expressed and interact in other tissues that do not normally undergo fusion, such as the vascular endothelium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-AurrandLions2">[51]</xref>. Jamb and Jamc permit cellular recognition and adhesion, but do not cause fusion when expressed in heterologous cells such as CHO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Otto1">[52]</xref>, MDCK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-AurrandLions2">[51]</xref>, or HEK293E (unpublished data), unlike EFF-1, a known fusogen in <italic>C. elegans</italic> that causes spontaneous fusion between Sf9 insect cells transfected with membrane-bound splice variants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Podbilewicz1">[47]</xref>. In addition, ectopically expressing either Jamb or Jamc in zebrafish slow muscle cells did not result in inappropriate fusion with fast muscle precursors (unpublished data). We hypothesise that the biological context of Jamb and Jamc binding determines the productive output of that interaction; for example, cellular fusion or tight junction formation. Interaction between Kirre and Sns is thought to be the initiation event for the formation of a crucial adhesion and signalling complex between a founder cell and a fusion-competent myoblast, termed FuRMAS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Kesper1">[9]</xref>. Both Kirre and Sns are thought to be involved in localising important signalling components to this complex, such as Rols7 and Mbc, in order to build and maintain a complex branched F-actin structure necessary for fusion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Onel1">[11]</xref>. Similarly, Jam-B and Jam-C are known to be involved in forming tight junctions between cells and localising other proteins such as ZO-1 to those sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-AurrandLions1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ebnet1">[29]</xref>. A specialised fusion structure has not been reported or characterised in vertebrates to date, but Jamb and Jamc may form part of a similar complex that defines the site of fusion between myocytes.</p>
      <p>A conserved role for JAM-B and JAM-C in myocyte fusion in other vertebrate organisms is an important focus for our future research. In support of this hypothesis, both genes have been shown to be expressed in developing skeletal muscle of mouse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Tang1">[53]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Visel1">[54]</xref> and human embryos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Phillips1">[55]</xref>. Knockout mice models have been generated for both genes and studied in the context of fertility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Gliki1">[30]</xref>, immunity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Imhof1">[56]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Praetor1">[57]</xref>, cardiac development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ye1">[58]</xref>, neurobiology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Scheiermann1">[59]</xref>, and stem cell biology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Sakaguchi1">[60]</xref>. Two independent <italic>Jam-C</italic><sup>−/−</sup> models have been reported with high perinatal mortality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Gliki1">[30]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Praetor1">[57]</xref>; approximately two-thirds of mutant pups die within 48 h after birth and are described as cyanotic and gasping <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Praetor1">[57]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ye1">[58]</xref>. The formation, structure, and integrity of the diaphragm has not been studied in these mice. Surviving <italic>Jam-C</italic> mutant mice also exhibit significant growth retardation starting from the second week of perinatal development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Imhof1">[56]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ye1">[58]</xref>, megaeosophagus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Imhof1">[56]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ye1">[58]</xref>, weaker forepaw grip strength <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Scheiermann1">[59]</xref>, and “jitteriness” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ye1">[58]</xref>. These characteristics could conceivably be a result of underlying muscle defects. Mice deficient in <italic>Jam-B</italic> display no overt phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Tang1">[53]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Sakaguchi1">[60]</xref> although skeletal muscle development and growth have not been specifically examined in detail.</p>
      <p>We believe that identification of the critical function of <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> in zebrafish myocyte fusion presents us with an opportunity to better understand myogenesis in higher vertebrates and cellular fusion in other biological contexts. A molecular explanation of the intercellular recognition processes that are necessary for fusion in, for example, placenta formation and sperm-egg interactions remains incomplete. The identification of Jamb and Jamc as an in vivo validated receptor-ligand pair required for cellular fusion in vertebrates may now provide impetus to shed more light on these biological processes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Zebrafish Husbandry, Embryo Culture, and Fixation</title>
        <p>Zebrafish mutants carrying alleles <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> were obtained from the Hubrecht laboratory and Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute Zebrafish Mutant Resource and maintained according to standard fish husbandry conditions and UK Home Office and Institute regulations and guidelines. Both <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> mutant lines were homozygous viable and fertile in our aquarium, but did not thrive. Embryos were fixed in either 4% paraformaldehyde or, for EB165 immunohistochemistry, in methanol.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Nomenclature and Accession Numbers</title>
        <p>We refer to the zebrafish homologues of <italic>JAM-B</italic> and <italic>JAM-C</italic> as <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic>, respectively, for the sake of clarity and consistency with other recent literature concerning the <italic>JAM</italic> family <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Weber1">[26]</xref>. The official symbols and accession/reference numbers are as follows: <italic>jamb</italic> (official symbol <italic>jam2a</italic>) - Entrez gene: 100005261; <italic>jamc</italic> (official symbol <italic>jam3b</italic>) - Entrez Gene: 569217.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Protein Production, Purification, and Surface Plasmon Resonance</title>
        <p>The extracellular domain of Jamb or Jamc were expressed as a soluble fusion protein with rat Cd4 domains 3 and 4 and either a 6-histidine (Cd4d3+4-6H) or an enzymatically biotinylatable peptide (Cd4d3+4-bio) C-terminal tag. These were purified and used in surface plasmon resonance experiments, essentially as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Bushell1">[33]</xref>. The activity of the Jamc analyte used in binding experiments cannot be accurately determined, as Jamc is capable of homophilic association. Dissociation rate constants (<italic>k</italic><sub>d</sub>), which are not confounded by analyte activities (and can therefore be directly compared), were calculated by averaging the dissociation phase of three different concentrations of purified Jamc-Cd4d3+4-6H or Jamb-Cd4d3+4-6H protein and fitting a simple first-order decay curve. Fits to the data were good, suggesting a 1∶1 stoichiometry of binding. Half lives (<italic>t</italic><sub>½</sub>) were calculated by <italic>t<sub>½</sub></italic> = <italic>ln</italic> 2/<italic>k<sub>d</sub></italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Wholemount In Situ Hybridisation and Immunohistochemistry</title>
        <p>Wholemount in situ hybridisations using digoxygenin-labelled riboprobes were performed using standard protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Thisse1">[61]</xref>. Riboprobe templates were generated from plasmids containing the extracellular domain of <italic>jamb</italic>, <italic>jamc</italic>, or <italic>kirrel3l</italic>.</p>
        <p>Wholemount immunohistochemistry was performed according to standard methods, using mouse monoclonal antibodies F59, EB165 (1∶200; Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank) and anti-mouse IgG, Alexa-488- or Alexa-568-conjugated secondary antibodies (1∶5,000; Molecular Probes). Embryos were mounted in Slowfade Gold with DAPI (Molecular Probes) and/or treated with Alexa-488-conjugated phalloidin (1∶40; Cambrex Biosciences).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Labelling Cell Membranes with mRFP</title>
        <p>Capped membrane-targeted red fluorescent protein mRNA was transcribed from a linearised plasmid <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Ciruna1">[62]</xref> using the mMessage mMachine kit (Ambion) and SP6 polymerase. 1–2 cell stage embryos were microinjected with approximately 4 nl of mRNA (∼25 ng/µl) diluted in sterile water, 0.1% phenol red (Sigma-Aldrich), fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde, and observed by confocal microscopy. Optical cross-sections of fixed, 48 h. p. f. mRFP-labelled embryos were computed from z-stacks collected from myotomes 10–15 in each embryo, using Leica Application Suite Advanced Fluorescence software (LAS AF; Leica Microsystems). Fibres were manually counted in each cross-section; superficial slow muscle fibres were excluded from analysis. Estimation of nuclei was determined by <italic>mf<sub>h</sub>n<sub>h</sub></italic>+(<italic>1−m</italic>)<italic>f<sub>h</sub></italic>, where <italic>m</italic> is the fraction of multinucleated fibres (quantified in same donor into same host genotype transplant controls; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s005">Table S1</xref>), <italic>f<sub>h</sub></italic> is the number of fibres, <italic>n<sub>h</sub></italic> is the average number of nuclei per fibre reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Moore1">[20]</xref>, and <italic>h</italic> is the developmental stage in h. p. f.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Morpholino Treatment</title>
        <p>1- and 2-cell stage embryos were injected with approximately 4 nl of translation blocking morpholinos (∼200 µM, 5–7.5 ng per embryo) diluted in sterile water with 0.1% phenol red. Translation blocking morpholino sequences were as follows: <italic>jamb</italic>: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">GCA CAC CAG CAT TTT CTC CAC AGT G</named-content>; <italic>jamc</italic>: <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">TTA ACG CCA TCT TGG AGT CGG TGA A</named-content>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Cell Transplants</title>
        <p>Transplants were performed essentially as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Xu1">[63]</xref>. Briefly, 1–2-cell stage donor embryos were injected with lysine-fixable fluorescein or rhodamine labelled dextran (10,000 kDa, 1% in sterile water; Molecular Probes). Fluorescently labelled donor cells were transplanted into the marginal cells of unlabelled host embryos between high/sphere to ∼30% epiboly stages. Transplanted embryos were maintained in embryo media supplemented with penicillin (50 U/ml) and streptomycin (50 µg/ml), fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde at 48 h. p. f., and analysed by confocal microscopy.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4h">
        <title>Image Acquisition and Processing</title>
        <p>Confocal microscopy images were collected using a Leica SP5/DM6000 confocal microscope and LAS AF software. Wholemount in situ hybridisation images were obtained using a Zeiss Imager M1 microscope, Zeiss AxioCam Hrc camera, and Zeiss AxioVision software. Entire images were adjusted for contrast, brightness, dynamic range, and resampled to a standardised resolution (300 d. p. i.) using Adobe Photoshop CS2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4i">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical significance between wild-type and mutant fibre counts and nuclei estimates were determined by one-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic> test, modified to take unequal sample size and variance into account. The number of embryos is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s005">Table S1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pbio.1001216.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Model of fast muscle development in <italic>jam</italic> mutant and wild-type embryos. Each panel presents a schematic of a single somite (so), notochord (nc), and adaxial cell (ad) or migrating slow muscle fibres (sm) as viewed dorsally, anterior left, at different stages during somitogenesis; latest stage to the right. In wild-type embryos, fast-twitch myoblasts (fMBs) express <italic>jamb</italic> (blue). At approximately 10–13 somites stage, medio-posterior myoblasts begin to express <italic>jamc</italic>, in addition to <italic>jamb</italic> (red), and differentiate (upper left panel). Other myocytes are able to fuse to the <italic>jamb</italic>, <italic>jamc</italic> expressing myocytes once fully elongated (white arrows, upper middle panel) resulting in multinucleated muscle fibres (upper right panel; nuclei in dark red). This process continues medio-laterally, as slow muscle fibres (sm) migrate to a superficial position (yellow arrow), until all primary somitic fast-twitch myoblasts have fused together to form the fast muscle myotome. Future growth of the myotome requires proliferation of the external cell layer (yellow cells)—myoblasts that are initially within the anterior border of the early somite (ABCs, anterior border cells). In <italic>jam</italic> mutant embryos, <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> are expressed normally (lower left panel). In contrast to wild-type, <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> or <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> myocytes are unable to undergo fusion (lower middle panel) and instead differentiate to form mononucleate fibres (lower right panel), nearly doubling the number of fast muscle fibres.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pbio.1001216.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Expression of <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> in <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutant embryos. In situ hybridisation of <italic>jamb</italic> (left two panels) and <italic>jamc</italic> (right two panels) riboprobes to <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> embryos at 17–18 somites stage; anterior top. Both genes are expressed in fast muscle myoblasts in both <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> and <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> mutants as observed in wild-type embryos.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pbio.1001216.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Combined knockdown of <italic>jamb</italic> and <italic>jamc</italic> does not result in a synthetic myogenesis phenotype. (A, B) Antisense morpholino oligonucleotide knockdown of expression of <italic>jamc</italic> in <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> embryos (A, right) or <italic>jamb</italic> in <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> embryos (B, right) does not result in any further disruption of myogenesis than that observed in <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic> (A, left) or <italic>jamc<sup>sa0037</sup></italic> (B, left) at 48 h. p. f., suggesting no synthetic effect of combined knockdown of both genes. Single confocal microscopy images of myotomes 12–13 in 48 h. p. f. embryos, stained for F-actin (cyan) and nuclei (red). Anterior left; scale bars represent 50 µm.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pbio.1001216.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><italic>jamc</italic> expression in fast muscle myoblasts and adaxial cells of <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> mutants. <italic>jamc</italic> is expressed in fast muscle myoblasts (open arrowheads) and ectopically expressed in premigratory slow muscle precursors (adaxial cells; closed arrowheads) of <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> mutant embryos (bottom). Flatmounted wild-type sibling (top) and <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> mutant embryos (bottom) at 18–20 somites stage, hybridised to <italic>jamc</italic>; anterior left.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pbio.1001216.s005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Average number of fast muscle fibres per myotome in wild-type and mutant embryos at different developmental stages. Values presented as mean ± SD; <italic>n</italic>, number of embryos tested; n.a., not applicable as fibres have not elongated. <sup>†</sup>Significantly different from wild-type, <italic>p</italic>≤0.001. <sup>‡</sup>Significantly different from <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic>, <italic>p</italic>≤0.01. One-tailed <italic>t</italic> test, modified to account for unequal sample sizes and sample variance.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pbio.1001216.s006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001216.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Average number of nuclei per myotome, calculated from number of fast muscle fibres per myotome in wild-type and mutant embryos at different developmental stages, taking the fraction of multinucleated fibres into account (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-1001216-t001">Table 1</xref>). Values presented as mean ± SD, number of embryos tested as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001216.s005">Table S1</xref>. *Values from (Moore et al., 2007) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1001216-Moore1">[20]</xref>. <sup>†</sup>Significantly different from wild-type, p≤0.001. <sup>‡</sup>Significantly different from <italic>jamb<sup>HU3319</sup></italic>, p≤0.01. One-tailed <italic>t</italic> test, modified to account for unequal sample sizes and sample variance.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>For providing the zebrafish knockout alleles <italic>HU3319</italic> and <italic>sa0037</italic>, we thank the Hubrecht laboratory and the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute Zebrafish Mutation Resource. We thank Mariella Ferrante for the <italic>mrfp</italic> construct, Stone Elworthy for <italic>prdm1a<sup>tp39</sup></italic> embryos, Sudipto Roy for the <italic>kirrel3l</italic> cDNA, <italic>Simon Hughes for providing Tg(smyhc1:egfp)<sup>i104</sup> embryos, Cécile Crosnier for assistance in generating injection constructs, and members of the laboratory and Michael Bate for critical comments on the manuscript.</italic></p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Huppertz1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huppertz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Placenta trophoblast fusion.</article-title>             <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>             <volume>475</volume>             <fpage>135</fpage>             <lpage>147</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Ishii1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Osteoclast cell fusion: mechanisms and molecules.</article-title>             <source>Mod Rheumatol</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>220</fpage>             <lpage>227</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Sutovsky1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutovsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Sperm-egg adhesion and fusion in mammals.</article-title>             <source>Expert Rev Mol Med</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>e11</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Capers1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capers</surname><given-names>C. R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1960</year>             <article-title>Multinucleation of skeletal muscle in vitro.</article-title>             <source>J Biophys Biochem Cytol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>559</fpage>             <lpage>566</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Bate1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <article-title>The embryonic development of larval muscles in Drosophila.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>110</volume>             <fpage>791</fpage>             <lpage>804</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Haralalka1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haralalka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abmayr</surname><given-names>S. M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Myoblast fusion in Drosophila.</article-title>             <source>Exp Cell Res</source>             <volume>316</volume>             <fpage>3007</fpage>             <lpage>3013</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Rochlin1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rochlin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylies</surname><given-names>M. K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Myoblast fusion: when it takes more to make one.</article-title>             <source>Dev Biol</source>             <volume>341</volume>             <fpage>66</fpage>             <lpage>83</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Doberstein1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doberstein</surname><given-names>S. K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fetter</surname><given-names>R. D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>A. Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>C. S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Genetic analysis of myoblast fusion: blown fuse is required for progression beyond the prefusion complex.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Biol</source>             <volume>136</volume>             <fpage>1249</fpage>             <lpage>1261</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Kesper1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesper</surname><given-names>D. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stute</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buttgereit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreiskother</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vishnu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Myoblast fusion in Drosophila melanogaster is mediated through a fusion-restricted myogenic-adhesive structure (FuRMAS).</article-title>             <source>Dev Dyn</source>             <volume>236</volume>             <fpage>404</fpage>             <lpage>415</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Sens1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sens</surname><given-names>K. L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>An invasive podosome-like structure promotes fusion pore formation during myoblast fusion.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Biol</source>             <volume>191</volume>             <fpage>1013</fpage>             <lpage>1027</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Onel1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onel</surname><given-names>S. F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renkawitz-Pohl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>FuRMAS: triggering myoblast fusion in Drosophila.</article-title>             <source>Dev Dyn</source>             <volume>238</volume>             <fpage>1513</fpage>             <lpage>1525</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Bour1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bour</surname><given-names>B. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>J. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abmayr</surname><given-names>S. M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Drosophila SNS, a member of the immunoglobulin superfamily that is essential for myoblast fusion.</article-title>             <source>Genes Dev</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>1498</fpage>             <lpage>1511</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Artero1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Artero</surname><given-names>R. D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castanon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylies</surname><given-names>M. K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>The immunoglobulin-like protein Hibris functions as a dose-dependent regulator of myoblast fusion and is differentially controlled by Ras and Notch signaling.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>128</volume>             <fpage>4251</fpage>             <lpage>4264</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Shelton1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kocherlakota</surname><given-names>K. S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abmayr</surname><given-names>S. M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The immunoglobulin superfamily member Hbs functions redundantly with Sns in interactions between founder and fusion-competent myoblasts.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>136</volume>             <fpage>1159</fpage>             <lpage>1168</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-RuizGomez1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Gomez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coutts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M. V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Drosophila dumbfounded: a myoblast attractant essential for fusion.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>102</volume>             <fpage>189</fpage>             <lpage>198</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Strnkelnberg1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strünkelnberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonengel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moda</surname><given-names>L. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertenstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Couet</surname><given-names>H. G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>rst and its paralogue kirre act redundantly during embryonic muscle development in Drosophila.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>128</volume>             <fpage>4229</fpage>             <lpage>4239</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Galletta1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galletta</surname><given-names>B. J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abmayr</surname><given-names>S. M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>SNS: adhesive properties, localization requirements and ectodomain dependence in S2 cells and embryonic myoblasts.</article-title>             <source>Mech Dev</source>             <volume>121</volume>             <fpage>1455</fpage>             <lpage>1468</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Krauss1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>R. S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Regulation of promyogenic signal transduction by cell-cell contact and adhesion.</article-title>             <source>Exp Cell Res</source>             <volume>316</volume>             <fpage>3042</fpage>             <lpage>3049</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Laurin1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fradet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blangy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The atypical Rac activator Dock180 (Dock1) regulates myoblast fusion in vivo.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>105</volume>             <fpage>15446</fpage>             <lpage>15451</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Moore1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>C. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>C. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bidet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>P. W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A role for the myoblast city homologues Dock1 and Dock5 and the adaptor proteins Crk and Crk-like in zebrafish myoblast fusion.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>134</volume>             <fpage>3145</fpage>             <lpage>3153</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Sohn1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>R. L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guyon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A role for nephrin, a renal protein, in vertebrate skeletal muscle cell fusion.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>9274</fpage>             <lpage>9279</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Srinivas1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>B. P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>W. Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A conserved molecular pathway mediates myoblast fusion in insects and vertebrates.</article-title>             <source>Nature Genet</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>781</fpage>             <lpage>786</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Vasyutina1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasyutina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martarelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brakebusch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wende</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birchmeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The small G-proteins Rac1 and Cdc42 are essential for myoblast fusion in the mouse.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>8935</fpage>             <lpage>8940</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Kang1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J. S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulieri</surname><given-names>P. J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taliana</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>R. S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>BOC, an Ig superfamily member, associates with CDO to positively regulate myogenic differentiation.</article-title>             <source>EMBO J</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>114</fpage>             <lpage>124</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Muller1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>W. A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Leukocyte-endothelial-cell interactions in leukocyte transmigration and the inflammatory response.</article-title>             <source>Trends Immunol</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>327</fpage>             <lpage>334</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Weber1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraemohs</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dejana</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The role of junctional adhesion molecules in vascular inflammation.</article-title>             <source>Nature Rev Immunol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>467</fpage>             <lpage>477</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-AurrandLions1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aurrand-Lions</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballestrem</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>B. A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>JAM-2, a novel immunoglobulin superfamily molecule, expressed by endothelial and lymphatic cells.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>276</volume>             <fpage>2733</fpage>             <lpage>2741</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Mandicourt1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandicourt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebnet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aurrand-Lions</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>B. A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>JAM-C regulates tight junctions and integrin-mediated cell adhesion and migration.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>282</volume>             <fpage>1830</fpage>             <lpage>1837</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Ebnet1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebnet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aurrand-Lions</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiefer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>The junctional adhesion molecule (JAM) family members JAM-2 and JAM-3 associate with the cell polarity protein PAR-3: a possible role for JAMs in endothelial cell polarity.</article-title>             <source>J Cell Sci</source>             <volume>116</volume>             <fpage>3879</fpage>             <lpage>3891</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Gliki1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gliki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebnet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aurrand-Lions</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>B. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>R. H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Spermatid differentiation requires the assembly of a cell polarity complex downstream of junctional adhesion molecule-C.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>431</volume>             <fpage>320</fpage>             <lpage>324</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Ruan1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coghlan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coin</surname><given-names>L. J. M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>TreeFam: 2008 update.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>36</volume>             <fpage>D735</fpage>             <lpage>D740</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Ebnet2">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebnet</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vestweber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Junctional adhesion molecules (JAMs): more molecules with dual functions?</article-title>             <source>J Cell Sci</source>             <volume>117</volume>             <fpage>19</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Bushell1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bushell</surname><given-names>K. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sollner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster-Boeckler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>G. J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Large-scale screening for novel low-affinity extracellular protein interactions.</article-title>             <source>Genome Res</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>622</fpage>             <lpage>630</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Sllner1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Söllner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A cell surface interaction network of neural leucine-rich repeat receptors.</article-title>             <source>Genome Biol</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>R99</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Martin1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söllner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charoensawan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adryan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thisse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Construction of a large extracellular protein interaction network and its resolution by spatiotemporal expression profiling.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>2654</fpage>             <lpage>2665</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Snow1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>C. J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goody</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>M. W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>E. C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Time-lapse analysis and mathematical characterization elucidate novel mechanisms underlying muscle morphogenesis.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Genet</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e1000219</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1000219" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000219</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Currie1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>P. D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>P. W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The generation and interpretation of positional information within the vertebrate myotome.</article-title>             <source>Mech Dev</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>3</fpage>             <lpage>21</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Ingham1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>P. W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Hedgehog signalling and the specification of muscle cell identity in the zebrafish embryo.</article-title>             <source>Exp Cell Res</source>             <volume>306</volume>             <fpage>336</fpage>             <lpage>342</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Devoto1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devoto</surname><given-names>S. H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melancon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>J. S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westerfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Identification of separate slow and fast muscle precursor cells in vivo, prior to somite formation.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>122</volume>             <fpage>3371</fpage>             <lpage>3380</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Roy1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>P. W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>The u-boot mutation identifies a Hedgehog-regulated myogenic switch for fiber-type diversification in the zebrafish embryo.</article-title>             <source>Genes Dev</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>1563</fpage>             <lpage>1576</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Cunningham1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>S. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arrate</surname><given-names>M. P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjercke</surname><given-names>R. J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderslice</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>A novel protein with homology to the junctional adhesion molecule. Characterization of leukocyte interactions.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>275</volume>             <fpage>34750</fpage>             <lpage>34756</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Santoso1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orlova</surname><given-names>V. V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>U. J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrei-Selmer</surname><given-names>C. L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The homophilic binding of junctional adhesion molecule-C mediates tumor cell-endothelial cell interactions.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>280</volume>             <fpage>36326</fpage>             <lpage>36333</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Arrate1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arrate</surname><given-names>M. P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>T. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>S. A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Cloning of human junctional adhesion molecule 3 (JAM3) and its identification as the JAM2 counter-receptor.</article-title>             <source>J Biol Chem</source>             <volume>276</volume>             <fpage>45826</fpage>             <lpage>45832</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Wright1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>G. J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Signal initiation in biological systems: the properties and detection of transient extracellular protein interactions.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biosyst</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>1405</fpage>             <lpage>1412</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-vonHofsten1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Hofsten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elworthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>M. J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>F. C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Prdm1- and Sox6-mediated transcriptional repression specifies muscle fibre type in the zebrafish embryo.</article-title>             <source>EMBO Rep</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>683</fpage>             <lpage>689</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Elworthy1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elworthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargrave</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mebus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>P. W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Expression of multiple slow myosin heavy chain genes reveals a diversity of zebrafish slow twitch muscle fibres with differing requirements for Hedgehog and Prdm1 activity.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>135</volume>             <fpage>2115</fpage>             <lpage>2126</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Podbilewicz1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Podbilewicz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leikina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sapir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valansi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suissa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The C. elegans developmental fusogen EFF-1 mediates homotypic fusion in heterologous cells and in vivo.</article-title>             <source>Dev Cell</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>471</fpage>             <lpage>481</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Gros1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scaal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcelle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>A two-step mechanism for myotome formation in chick.</article-title>             <source>Dev Cell</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>875</fpage>             <lpage>882</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Venters1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venters</surname><given-names>S. J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorsteinsdottir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duxson</surname><given-names>M. J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Early development of the myotome in the mouse.</article-title>             <source>Dev Dyn</source>             <volume>216</volume>             <fpage>219</fpage>             <lpage>232</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Rushton1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drysdale</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abmayr</surname><given-names>S. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michelson</surname><given-names>A. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Mutations in a novel gene, myoblast city, provide evidence in support of the founder cell hypothesis for Drosophila muscle development.</article-title>             <source>Development</source>             <volume>121</volume>             <fpage>1979</fpage>             <lpage>1988</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-AurrandLions2">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aurrand-Lions</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson-Leger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du Pasquier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>B. A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Heterogeneity of endothelial junctions is reflected by differential expression and specific subcellular localization of the three JAM family members.</article-title>             <source>Blood</source>             <volume>98</volume>             <fpage>3699</fpage>             <lpage>3707</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Otto1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>D. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campanero-Rhodes</surname><given-names>M. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamanska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>A. K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bovin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>An expression system for screening of proteins for glycan and protein interactions.</article-title>             <source>Anal Biochem</source>             <volume>411</volume>             <fpage>261</fpage>             <lpage>270</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Tang1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W. Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>A mouse knockout library for secreted and transmembrane proteins.</article-title>             <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>749</fpage>             <lpage>755</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Visel1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Visel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thaller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>GenePaint.org: an atlas of gene expression patterns in the mouse embryo.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>32</volume>             <fpage>D552</fpage>             <lpage>D556</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Phillips1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>H. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renforth</surname><given-names>G. L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spalluto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hearn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>A. R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Narrowing the critical region within 11q24-qter for hypoplastic left heart and identification of a candidate gene, JAM3, expressed during cardiogenesis.</article-title>             <source>Genomics</source>             <volume>79</volume>             <fpage>475</fpage>             <lpage>478</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Imhof1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>B. A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gliki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducrest-Gay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juillard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Pulmonary dysfunction and impaired granulocyte homeostasis result in poor survival of Jam-C-deficient mice.</article-title>             <source>J Pathol</source>             <volume>212</volume>             <fpage>198</fpage>             <lpage>208</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Praetor1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Praetor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>J. M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rangell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabote</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Genetic deletion of JAM-C reveals a role in myeloid progenitor generation.</article-title>             <source>Blood</source>             <volume>113</volume>             <fpage>1919</fpage>             <lpage>1928</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Ye1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamzeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geddis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perryman</surname><given-names>M. B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Deletion of JAM-C, a candidate gene for heart defects in Jacobsen syndrome, results in a normal cardiac phenotype in mice.</article-title>             <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>             <volume>149A</volume>             <fpage>1438</fpage>             <lpage>1443</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Scheiermann1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheiermann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aurrand-Lions</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yiangou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Expression and function of junctional adhesion molecule-C in myelinated peripheral nerves.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>318</volume>             <fpage>1472</fpage>             <lpage>1475</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Sakaguchi1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Putative “stemness” gene jam-B is not required for maintenance of stem cell state in embryonic, neural, or hematopoietic stem cells.</article-title>             <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>6557</fpage>             <lpage>6570</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Thisse1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thisse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thisse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>High-resolution in situ hybridization to whole-mount zebrafish embryos.</article-title>             <source>Nature Protoc</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>59</fpage>             <lpage>69</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Ciruna1">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciruna</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mlodzik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schier</surname><given-names>A. F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Planar cell polarity signalling couples cell division and morphogenesis during neurulation.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>439</volume>             <fpage>220</fpage>             <lpage>224</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pbio.1001216-Xu1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stemple</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joubin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Microinjection and cell transplantation in zebrafish embryos.</article-title>             <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>             <volume>461</volume>             <fpage>513</fpage>             <lpage>520</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>AVEXIS</term>
          <def>
            <p>avidity based extracellular interaction screen</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CHO</term>
          <def>
            <p>chinese hamster ovary cells</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>FCM</term>
          <def>
            <p>fusion competent myoblast</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>fMyHC</term>
          <def>
            <p>fast isoform myosin heavy chain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>FuRMAS</term>
          <def>
            <p>fusion-restricted myogenic-adhesive structure</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>h. p. f.</term>
          <def>
            <p>hours post-fertilisation</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>HEK293E</term>
          <def>
            <p>human embryonic kidney 293 cells</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MDCK</term>
          <def>
            <p>Madin-Darby canine kidney epithelial cells</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MO</term>
          <def>
            <p>morpholino</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>mRFP</term>
          <def>
            <p>membrane-targeted red fluorescent protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>sMyHC</term>
          <def>
            <p>slow isoform myosin heavy chain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>UTR</term>
          <def>
            <p>untranslated region</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    
  </back>
</article>