<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-11-01844</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ecosystem modeling</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Social Interaction, Noise and Antibiotic-Mediated Switches in the Intestinal Microbiota</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Switches in the Intestinal Microbiota</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bucci</surname>
            <given-names>Vanni</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
        <sup>¶</sup>
    </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bradde</surname>
            <given-names>Serena</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
        <sup>¶</sup>
    </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Biroli</surname>
            <given-names>Giulio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Xavier</surname>
            <given-names>Joao B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Program in Computational Biology, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Institut Physique Théorique (IPhT) CEA Saclay, and CNRS URA, Gif Sur Yvette, France</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>De Boer</surname>
            <given-names>Rob J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Utrecht University, Netherlands</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">bucciv@mskcc.org</email> (VB); <email xlink:type="simple">serena.bradde@pasteur.fr</email> (SB); <email xlink:type="simple">xavierj@mskcc.org</email> (JBX)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: VB SB GB JXB. Performed the experiments: VB SB. Analyzed the data: VB SB JBX. Wrote the paper: VB SB GB JXB.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn1">
          <p>¶ These authors are joint senior authors on this work.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e1002497</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bucci et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>The intestinal microbiota plays important roles in digestion and resistance against entero-pathogens. As with other ecosystems, its species composition is resilient against small disturbances but strong perturbations such as antibiotics can affect the consortium dramatically. Antibiotic cessation does not necessarily restore pre-treatment conditions and disturbed microbiota are often susceptible to pathogen invasion. Here we propose a mathematical model to explain how antibiotic-mediated switches in the microbiota composition can result from simple social interactions between antibiotic-tolerant and antibiotic-sensitive bacterial groups. We build a two-species (e.g. two functional-groups) model and identify regions of domination by antibiotic-sensitive or antibiotic-tolerant bacteria, as well as a region of multistability where domination by either group is possible. Using a new framework that we derived from statistical physics, we calculate the duration of each microbiota composition state. This is shown to depend on the balance between random fluctuations in the bacterial densities and the strength of microbial interactions. The singular value decomposition of recent metagenomic data confirms our assumption of grouping microbes as antibiotic-tolerant or antibiotic-sensitive in response to a single antibiotic. Our methodology can be extended to multiple bacterial groups and thus it provides an ecological formalism to help interpret the present surge in microbiome data.</p>
      </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
        <title>Author Summary</title>
        <p>Recent applications of metagenomics have led to a flood of novel studies and a renewed interest in the role of the gut microbiota in human health. We can now envision a time in the near future where analysis of microbiota composition can be used for diagnostics and the rational design of new therapeutics. However, most studies to date are exploratory and heavily data-driven, and therefore lack mechanistic insights on the ecology governing these complex microbial ecosystems. In this study we propose a new model grounded on ecological and physical principles to explain intestinal microbiota dynamics in response to antibiotic treatment. Our model explains a hysteresis effect that results from the social interaction between two microbial groups, antibiotic-tolerant and antibiotic-sensitive bacteria, as well as the recovery allowed by stochastic fluctuations. We use singular value decomposition for the analysis of temporal metagenomic data, which supports the representation of the microbiota according to two main microbial groups. Our framework explains why microbiota composition can be difficult to recover after antibiotic treatment, thus solving a long-standing puzzle in microbiota biology with profound implications for human health. It therefore forms a conceptual bridge between experiments and theoretical works towards a mechanistic understanding of the gut microbiota.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This project was supported by NIH New Innovator Award (DP2OD008440) and Lucille Castori Center for Microbes Inflammation and Cancer grants to JBX. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Recent advances in metagenomics provide an unprecedented opportunity to investigate the intestinal microbiota and its role in human health and disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Neish1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen1">[2]</xref>. The analysis of microflora composition has a great potential in diagnostics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Jones1">[3]</xref> and may lead to the rational design of new therapeutics that restore healthy microbial balance in patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Khoruts1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Ruder1">[6]</xref>. Before the clinical translation of human microbiome biology is possible, we must seek to thoroughly understand the ecological processes governing microbiota composition dynamics and function.</p>
      <p>The gastro-intestinal microbiota is a highly diverse bacterial community that performs an important digestive function and, at the same time, provides resistance against colonization by entero-pathogenic bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Pultz1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Endt1">[9]</xref>. Commensal bacteria resist pathogens thanks to resources competition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Neish1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Stecher1">[8]</xref>, growth inhibition due to short-chain fatty acid production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Fukuda1">[10]</xref>, killing with bacteriocins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dabard1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Corr1">[12]</xref> and immune responses stimulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Stecher2">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Keeney1">[14]</xref>. However, external challenges such as antibiotic therapies can harm the microbiota stability and make the host susceptible to pathogen colonization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Pamer1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Buffe1">[20]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Despite its importance to human health, the basic ecology of the intestinal microbiota remains unclear. A recent large-scale cross-sectional study proposed that the intestinal microbiota variation in humans is stratified and fits into distinct enterotypes, which may determine how individuals respond to diet or drug intake <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Arumugam1">[21]</xref>. Although there is an ongoing debate over the existence of discrete microbiome enterotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Wu1">[22]</xref>, they could be explained by ecological theory as different states of an ecosystem <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Scheffer1">[23]</xref>. Ecological theory can also explain how external factors, such as antibiotics, may lead to strong shifts in the microbial composition. A recent study that analyzed healthy adults undergoing consecutive administrations of the antibiotic ciprofloxacin, showed that the gut microbiota changes dramatically by losing key species and can take weeks to recover <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>. Longitudinal studies, such as this one, suggest that many microbial groups can have large and seemingly random density variations in the time-scale of weeks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen4">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Caporaso1">[26]</xref>. The observation of multiple microbial states and the high temporal variability highlight the need for ecological frameworks that account for basic microbial interactions, as well as random fluctuations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Ley1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-dosSantos1">[29]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Here we propose a possible model to study how the intestinal microbiota responds to treatment with a single antibiotic. Our model expands on established ecological models and uses a minimal representation with two microbial groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-MaoJones1">[30]</xref> representing the antibiotic-sensitive and antibiotic-tolerant bacteria in the enteric consortium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). We propose a mechanism of direct interaction between the two bacterial groups that explains how domination by antibiotic-tolerants can persist even after antibiotic cessation. We then develop a new efficient framework that deals with non-conservative multi-stable field of forces and describes the role played by the noise in the process of recovery. We finally support our model by analyzing the temporal patterns of metagenomic data from the longitudinal study of Dethlefsen and Relman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>. We show that the dynamics of microbiota can be qualitatively captured by our model and that the two-group representation is suitable for microbiota challenged by a single antibiotic. Our model can be extended to include multiple bacterial groups, which is necessary for a more general description of intestinal microbiota dynamics in response to multiple perturbations.</p>
      <fig id="pcbi-1002497-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The two-group model of the intestinal microbiota with antibiotic-sensitive and antibiotic-tolerant bacteria.</title>
          <p>Antibiotic sensitives can inhibit the growth of tolerants and both groups compete for the same growth substrate. Model parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represent the antibiotic sensitivity of sensitive and tolerant bacteria (where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represent their affinities to substrate and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represents the inhibition of tolerants by sensitives.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Mathematical model</title>
        <p>We model the microbiota as a homogeneous system where we neglect spatial variation of antibiotic-sensitive (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and antibiotic-tolerant (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) bacterial densities. Their evolution is determined by growth on a substrate and death due to natural mortality, antibiotic killing and social pressure. With these assumptions, we introduce, as a mathematical model, two coupled stochastic differential equations for the density of sensitives and tolerants (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) normalized with respect to the maximum achievable microbial density:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e012" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>In the physics literature these types of equations represent stochastic motion in a non-conservative force field <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The first terms in <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> correspond to the saturation growth terms representing the indirect competition for substrate and depend on <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is the ratio of the maximum specific growth rates between the two groups. If <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> tolerants grow better than sensitives on the available substrate and the reverse is true for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. They effectively describe a microbial system with a growth substrate modeled as a Monod kinetic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Monod1">[31]</xref> in the limit of quasi-steady state approximation for substrate and complete consumption from the microbes (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> for details). Both groups die with different susceptibility in response to the antibiotic treatment, which is assumed to be at steady-state. <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> defines the ratio of the combined effect of antibiotic killing and natural mortality rates between the two groups (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> for details). While the system can be studied in its full generality for different choices of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we consider the case of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because it represents the more relevant case where sensitives are more susceptible to die than tolerants in the presence of the antibiotic. A possible <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that mimics the antibiotic treatments is a pulse function. With this, we are able to reproduce realistic patterns of relative raise (fall) and fall (raise) of sensitives (tolerants) due to antibiotic treatment as we show in Fig. S4 in the Supporting Information Text (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>). Additionally, we introduce the social interaction term between the two groups, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, to implement competitive growth inhibition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Stecher2">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Bucci1">[32]</xref>. In particular, we are interested in the case where the sensitives can inhibit the growth of the tolerants (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), which typically occurs through bacteriocin production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Bucci1">[33]</xref>. Finally we add a stochastic term <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that models the effect of random fluctuations (noise), such as random microbial exposure, which we assume to be additive and Gaussian. The analysis can be generalized to other forms of noise such as multiplicative and coloured.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Antibiotic therapy produces multistability and hysteresis</title>
        <p>We first analyzed the model in the limit of zero noise, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In this case, we were interested in studying the steady state solutions that correspond to the fixed-points of equations (1,2) and are obtained imposing <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We found three qualitatively-distinct biologically meaningful states corresponding to sensitive domination, tolerant domination and sensitive-tolerant coexistence (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>). We evaluated the stability of each fixed point (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>) and identified three regions within the parameter space (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). In the first region the effect of antibiotics on sensitive bacteria is very low (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and domination by sensitives is the only stable state (sensitives monostability). In the second region the effect of the antibiotic on sensitives is stronger than their inhibition over tolerants (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the only stable state is domination by tolerants (tolerants monostability). Finally, in the third region (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) both sensitive and tolerant dominations are possible and stable, while the third coexistence fixed point is unstable (bistability) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>). This simple analysis shows that multistability can occur in a gut microbiota challenged by an antibiotic where one group directly inhibits the other (i.e. through the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> term). Furthermore, it suggests that multistability is a general phenomenon since it requires only that antibiotic-sensitive and antibiotic-tolerant bacteria have similar affinities to nutrients. This is a realistic scenario because tolerants, such as vancomycin resistant <italic>Enterococcus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Ubeda1">[18]</xref>, are often closely related to other commensal but antibiotic-sensitive strains and therefore should have similar affinity to nutrients. Finally, the solution of equations (1) and (2) reveals that hysteresis is present for values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> leading to multistability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Similarly to magnetic tapes, such as cassette or video tapes, which remain magnetized even after the external magnetic field is removed (i.e. stopping the recording), a transient dose of antibiotics can cause a microbiota switch that persists for long time even after antibiotic cessation.</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1002497-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Multistability and hysteresis in a simple model of the intestinal microbiota. A: phase diagram showing the three possible stability regions.</title>
            <p>Antibiotic-sensitive bacteria dominate when <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and antibiotic-tolerant bacteria dominate when <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and therefore these are regions of monostability. There is a region of bistability between the two regions where domination by either sensitives or tolerants is possible. B: schematic display of the hysteresis phenomenon explaining cases where antibiotic treatment produces altered microbiota (i.e. tolerants domination) that persists long after antibiotic cessation. C–F: mean density values obtained simulating the Langevin dynamics for a maximum time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> after an instantaneous change of the parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (C and D) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (E and F). These averages are obtained over <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> noise realizations. C, D and E, F show the antibiotic-tolerants or antibiotic-sensitives densities, respectively, as a function of the social interaction parameter (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or the antibiotic killing (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Noise alters stability points</title>
        <p>The previous analysis shows the existence of multistability in the absence of noise. However, the influx of microbes from the environment and/or the intra-population heterogeneity are expected in realistic scenarios and affect the bacterial density evolution in a non-deterministic fashion. This raises the question of how the noise alters the deterministic stable states and their stability criteria. We assume that the noise is a fraction of bacteria <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that can be added (or removed) at each time step, but on average has no effect since <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This assumption is justified by the fact that a persistent net flux of non-culturable bacteria from the environment is unrealizable. We also assume that this random event at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is not correlated to any previous time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which corresponds to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> characterizes the noise amplitude and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the Dirac delta function. We calculated the stationary probability of the microbiota being at a given state by solving the stationary Fokker-Planck Equation (FPE) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Gardiner1">[34]</xref> corresponding to the Langevin equations (1,2):<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e050" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>By numerically solving equation (3) as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Galan1">[35]</xref>, for increasing <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we find that for small values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the most probable states coincide with the deterministic stable states given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). However, by increasing <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the distribution <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> spreads and the locations of the most probable states change and approach each other. As a consequence, the probability of an unstable coexistence, characterized by <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, increases thus avoiding extinction. This intuitively justifies how recovery to a sensitive-dominated state within a finite time after antibiotic cessation becomes possible with the addition of the noise. Without noise, the complete extinction of sensitive bacteria would have prevented any possible recolonization of the intestine. Beyond a critical noise level (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) bistability is entirely lost and the probability distribution becomes single-peaked with both bacterial groups coexisting. The microbiota composition at the coexistence state can be numerically determined from the solution of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g003">Fig. 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s002">Video S1</xref>. Further investigations based on analytical expansion of the Langevin equations (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>) show that for small random fluctuations, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the first noise-induced corrections to the deterministic density are linearly dependent on <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with a proportionality coefficient determined by the nature of the interactions (insets in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). These linear correction terms can be obtained as a function of the model parameters and, after substituting a particular set of values in the bistable region (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), they are <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for sensitives and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for tolerants. These numbers are different from those reported in the insets of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>. However the discrepancy is due to the propagation of the boundary conditions when numerically solving the solution of the FPE using finite elements (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1002497-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Most probable microbiota states change from bistable scenario to mono-stable coexistence with increasing noise.</title>
            <p>A: the bacterial density joint probability distribution determined by solving the Fokker-Planck equation (3) for four different values of the environmental noise. B: the bacterial densities at the peaks of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of the noise parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Red symbols are data from the numeric solution of the Fokker-Planck equation and the black solid lines are the exponential fit. Parameters used: <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The insets detail the linear regime.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>This has important biological implications since it suggests that extinction is prevented and, more importantly, that a minority of environmental microbes can settle in the gut at a rate that depends on the strength of their social interaction with the established microbiota.</p>
        <p>The introduction of random perturbation affects the stability criteria of the stable states. In particular, we observe that the bistability region decreases when the noise amplitude <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g002">Fig. 2C–F</xref>). At the limit, when <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the bistability is entirely lost and the only stable state is the one where both groups coexist. This concept was previously hypothesized but not explicitly demonstrated in a model of microbial symbionts in corals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-MaoJones1">[30]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Noise affects the recovery time</title>
        <p>Our model predicts that in absence of stochastic fluctuations the recovery time is larger than any observational time-scale so that it is impossible to revert to the conditions preceding antibiotic perturbation (see Fig. S4 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>). In reality, data show that this time can be finite and depends on the microbiota composition and the degree of isolation of the individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Ubeda1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Littman1">[36]</xref>. Thus, we aim to quantitatively characterize how the relative contribution of social interaction and noise level affects the computation of the mean residence time.</p>
        <p>In order to determine the relative time spent in each domination state, we compute the probability of residence <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in each stable state <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> using master equations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Gardiner1">[34]</xref>. This method is more efficient than simulating the system time evolution by direct integration of the Langevin equations because it boils down to solving a deterministic second-order differential equation. Furthermore, this approach scales up well when the number of microbial groups increases, in contrast to the numerical solution of the FPE which can become prohibitive when <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In our model, the master equations for the probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of residing in the tolerant <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or sensitive <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> domination state are:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e079" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the transition rate from state <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which can be obtained in terms of the sum over all the state space trajectories connecting <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>By solving this system of equations at steady-state, we obtain the residence probabilities <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. After computing the transition rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of the parameters, as reported in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>, we determine <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is our theoretical prediction for the mean relative residence time <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> spent in the tolerant domination state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). The theoretical predictions are in good agreement with those obtained by simulating the dynamics multiple times and averaging over different realizations of the noise. A first consequence from this analysis is that the time needed to naturally revert from the altered state depends exponentially on the noise amplitude (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). As such, we predict that for the case of an isolated system (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) the switching time is exponentially larger than any other microscopic scale and the return to a previous unperturbed state is very unlikely. On the contrary, as the level of random exposure <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is increased, the time to recover to the pre-treated configuration decreases (see Fig. S4 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>). Additionally, this method can be considered as a way to indirectly determine the strength of the ecological interactions between microbes which can be achieved by measuring the amount of time that the microbial population spends in one of the particular microbiota states. Therefore, it can potentially be applied to validate proposed models of ecological interactions by comparing residence times measured experimentally with theoretical predictions.</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1002497-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Microbiota resident time in antibiotic-tolerant domination as a function of the: A–B) antibiotic action (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and C–D) social interaction (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) parameters.</title>
            <p>Blue circles show the theoretical predictions obtained by determining the probability of the most probable path. Red circles are obtained by simulating the Langevin dynamics over <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> iterations and averaged for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> noise realizations. Higher order-corrections can be included to increase the theoretical estimation accuracy.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Analysis of metagenomic data reveals antibiotic-tolerant and antibiotic-sensitive bacteria</title>
        <p>We now focus on the dynamics of bacteria detected in the human intestine and test the suitability of our two-group representation by re-analyzing the time behaviour in the recently published metagenomic data of Dethlefsen and Relman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>. The data consisted of three individuals monitored over a 10 month period who were subjected to two courses of the antibiotic ciprofloxacin. Since the data are noisy and complex, and the individual subjects' responses to the antibiotic are distinct <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>, identifying a time behaviour by manual screening is not a trivial task. We do it by using singular value decomposition (SVD) to classify each subject <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> phylotype-by-sample data matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> into its principal components. Because of inter-individual variability we obtain, for each subject, the right and left eigenvectors associated to each eigenvalue. By ranking the phylotypes based on their correlation with the first two components we recover characteristic temporal patterns for each volunteer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Alter1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Brauer1">[38]</xref>.</p>
        <p>In all three subjects, we observe that, in spite of the individualized antibiotic effect, the two dominant eigenvalues or principal components together capture about 70% of the variance observed in the data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g005">Fig. 5A–C</xref>). Invariably, the first component shows a decrease in correspondence to antibiotic treatment and reflects the behaviour of antibiotic-sensitive bacteria (green line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g005">Fig. 5D–F</xref>). Conversely, the second component increases with the antibiotic treatment and represents antibiotic-tolerants (red line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g005">Fig. 5D–F</xref>). The observation that each subject's microbiota can be decomposed into two groups of bacteria with opposite responses to antibiotics supports the validity of the two-group approach used in our model. Classification of each individual's phylotypes as sensitive or tolerant can be obtained by determining their correlation with the two principal components (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>) (information in the right-eigenarrays matrix from SVD). Bacteria correlated with component 1 are usually highly abundant before antibiotic treatment and drop strongly during treatment, often below detection. Vice-versa, bacteria correlated with component 2 are typically in low abundance before the antibiotic and increase with antibiotic administration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g005">Fig. 5G–I</xref>). Interestingly, despite significant inter-individual differences in recovery time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g005">Fig. 5G–I</xref>) and individualized response of each subject, the data show that in each individual the majority of bacteria are antibiotic-sensitive and only a small but significant fraction are tolerant to ciprofloxacin (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>). The recognition of these time-patterns could be considered as a possible tool to indirectly determine the susceptibility of non-culturable commensal bacteria to FDA-approved antimicrobial compounds. However, the presence of strains in the same phylotypes that display both behaviors in response to the drug may constitute a significant challenge for the success of this method.</p>
        <fig id="pcbi-1002497-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Analysis of microbiota response to the antibiotic ciprofloxacin from three subjects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref> using singular value decomposition identifies antibiotic-sensitive and antibiotic-tolerant bacteria.</title>
            <p>A–C: fraction of variance explained by the five most dominant components. D–F: plot of each sample component 1 (green) and 2 (red) coordinates versus sample time. G–I: sorting of the phylotypes log2-transformed abundance matrix based on the correlation within the two principal component. Above (below) the green dashed lines, we display the time series of the top 20 phylotypes strongly correlated (anti-correlated) with component 1 and anti-correlated (correlated) with 2 and dropping (increasing) during treatment, which we identify as sensitves (tolerants). Subject 3 (C,F,I) displays absence of sensitive bacteria for a prolonged period of about 50 days after the first antibiotic treatment. This confirms the fact that microbiota response to antibiotic can differ from subject to subject. Additionally, it also supports our model prediction of remaining locked in a tolerant-dominated state after antibiotic treatment cessation.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The time evolution of the phylotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g005">Fig. 5G–I</xref>) qualitatively agrees with our theoretical prediction that after the antibiotic administration the system moves fast, meaning in a time smaller than any other observable time-scale, into a new stable state with less sensitives and more tolerants. Further, the data also suggest that the return to sensitive domination happens after a recovery-time scale that depends on the microbial composition.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We present a model of inter-bacterial interactions that explains the effect of antibiotics and the counter-intuitive observation that an antibiotic-induced shift in microbiota composition can persist even after antibiotic cessation. Our analysis predicts a crucial dependence of the recovery time on the level of noise, as suggested by experiments with mice where the recovery depends on the exposure to mice with untreated microbiota <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Ubeda1">[18]</xref>. The simple model here introduced is inspired by classical ecological modeling such as competitive Lotka-Volterra models <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Sol1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Zhu1">[40]</xref>, but relies on mechanistic rather than phenomenological assumptions, such as the logistic growth. Although more sophisticated multi-species models include explicit spatial structure to describe microbial consortia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Bucci1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Mitri1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-MunozTamayo2">[43]</xref>, our model is a first attempt to quantitatively analyze the interplay between microbial social interactions (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and stochastic fluctuations (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) in the gut microbiota. We find that these two mechanisms are the key ingredients to reproduce the main features of the dynamics in response to antibiotic (sudden shifts and recovery). Our model can be easily generalized to include spatial variability and more complicated types of noise. Therefore we provide a theoretical framework to quantify microbiota resilience against disturbances, which is an importance feature in all ecosystems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Holling1">[44]</xref>. By introducing a new stochastic formulation, we were able to characterize composition switches within the context of state transition theory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Langer1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Langer2">[46]</xref>, an important development over similar ecological models of microbial populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-MaoJones1">[30]</xref>. We present a new method to calculate the rate of switching between states that identifies the most likely trajectory between two stable states and their relative residence time, which can be subjected to experimental validation. Finally, we apply SVD to previously published metagenomic data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>, which allows us to classify the bacteria of each subject in two groups according to their temporal response to a single antibiotic. The SVD method has been used before to find patterns in temporal high-throughput data, including transcription microarrays <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Alter1">[37]</xref> and metabolomics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Yuan1">[47]</xref>. Although our approach seems to capture well the main temporal microbiota patterns, we should note that the use of the Euclidean distance as a metric for microbiome analysis presents limitations and recent studies have proposed alternative choices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Gonzalez1">[48]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Kuczynski1">[50]</xref>. We also opt for an indirect gradient analysis method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-terBraak1">[51]</xref> because we are interested in emergent patterns from the data regardless of the measurements of the external environmental variable (i.e. presence or absence of the antibiotic) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Kuczynski1">[50]</xref>.</p>
      <p>We propose a mechanism of interaction between two bacterial groups to explain the lack of recovery observed in the experiments that can be validated in the near future. Although training the model with the available data sets would be of great interest, this will not be useful in practice because we need more statistical power to be predictive. However, we anticipate that a properly validated mathematical model of the intestinal microbiota will be a valuable tool to assist in the rational design of antibiotic therapies. For example, we predict that the rate of antibiotic dosage will play a crucial role. In order to let the microbiota recover from antibiotic treatment, it is better to gradually decrease antibiotic dosage at the first sign of average microbiota composition change, which has to be larger than the threshold community change represented by the day-to-day variability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Caporaso1">[26]</xref>, rather than waiting for tolerant-domination and then stopping antibiotic treatment.</p>
      <p>We show here the application of our theory to a two-bacterial group scenario because we are interested in the microbiota response when challenged with a single antibiotic. However, in more realistic conditions the microbiota is subjected to different types of perturbations, which may drive it towards more alternative stable states. Our theory of the microbial-states switches characterization can be naturally extended to more than two states and consists of the solution of the linear system of equations <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the array of probability of residing in each stable state and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the matrix of transition rates among the states.</p>
      <p>The ongoing efforts to characterize the microbial consortia of the human microbiome can yield tremendous benefits to human health <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Turnbaugh1">[52]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Lee1">[55]</xref>. Within the next few years, we are certain to witness important breakthroughs, including an increase in the number of microbiomes sequenced as well as in sequencing depth. Yet, without the proper ecological framework these complex ecosystems will remain poorly understood. Our study shows that, as in other complex microbial ecosystems, ecological models can be valuable tools to interpret the dynamics in the intestinal microbiota.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Full model and simplification</title>
        <p>The model introduced in equations 1 and 2 is derived from the more detailed model described below. We model the bacterial competition in a well-mixed system in the presence of antibiotic treatment by means of the following stochastic differential equations:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e107" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>where we account for two bacterial groups; the intestinal resident sensitive flora <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and an antibiotic tolerant one <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Additionally, we also consider the substrate <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the antibiotic <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> densities. The antibiotic time evolution is simply a balance between inflow and outflow (i.e. no decay due to microbial degradation) where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the system's dilution rate, which sets the characteristic microscopic time-scale, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the constant density of the incoming antibiotic, which can be time dependent. Similarly the substrate concentration, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, results from a mass balance from influx and microbial consumption. As for the antibiotic, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the constant density of the incoming nutrient (i.e. the concentration of resources coming from the small-intestine). The second and third terms in the right-hand side of the second equation in (5) describe the amount of substrate consumed by bacterial growth assuming Monod kinetics where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is the maximum growth rate for sensitives (tolerants), <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the half-saturation constant for growth, which parametrizes the bacterial affinity to the nutrient, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is the yield for growth for sensitives (tolerants). The last two equations describe how sensitives and tolerants grow on the substrate available and are diluted with the factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We mimic the effect of the antibiotic on the sensitives adding a term proportional to the sensitive density where the constant of proportionality <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the antibiotic-killing rate. We also introduce a direct inhibition term <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which mimics the inhibition of sensitive bacteria on the tolerants (social interaction). Finally the Gaussian random variables <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the additive random patterns of exposure and represent the random microbial inflows (outflows) from (to) the external environment.</p>
        <p>It is convenient to scale the variables and set the dilution rate to unity (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Therefore, all the rates have to be compared with respect to the system characteristic dilution rate. Introducing <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and dropping the tilde symbols, we obtain the following dimensionless model:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e141" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>If we assume that the antibiotic is a fast variable compared to the microbial densities (<inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) (i.e. the time-scale at which the antibiotic reaches stationary state is smaller than that of the bacteria), we can solve for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and obtain <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. If we also assume that the incoming substrate is all consumed in microbial growth, therefore maintaining the population in a stationary state with respect to the available resources, and that, similarly to the antibiotic, the resources equilibrate much faster than the bacterial densities (quasi-steady state assumption, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), we obtain that:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e146" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>If we now define a new parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> describing the relative ratio of the combination of antibiotic killing and natural mortality (i.e. wash-out) between sensitives and tolerants, the model reduces to the two variables model in <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reported in equations (1–2).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Effective potential and location of long-term states</title>
        <p>The introduction of random noise has the important consequence of changing the composition of the stable states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1002497-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). In order to characterize this phenomenon, we expand the solution of the Langevin equations (1–2) around one of the stable states obtaining the following set of equations for the variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e150" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>where to simplify the notation we drop the explicit time-dependence. We can easily recognize the first derivative of the force on the right-hand side as the Jacobian matrix computed in one of the minima <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This equation can be solved order by order by defining the expansion <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and writing the equations for each order as:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e153" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e154" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Assuming that the initial condition at time zero is <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which can always be neglected for long-term behaviour, the solution of equation (9) is<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e156" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>This means that the average location of the minima at zero order is not modified by the noise since <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. By computing the solution of the equation (10) we similarly find that:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e158" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>The long-time average value of the first order correction now reads:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e159" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(13)</label></disp-formula>The time integral can be easily computed assuming that the eigenvalues of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are negative, or at least their real part is, as it should be for stable fixed points; therefore we obtain that:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e161" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(14)</label></disp-formula>Thus, we find that the effect of random fluctuations is to correct the value of the stable points as if an external field, proportional to strength of the fluctuations, was present. This field is equal to the mean square displacement at large time opportunely weighted by the inverse of the curvature of the bare potential around the stable points, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The correlation can be now computed using equation (11) and reads:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e163" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(15)</label></disp-formula>Since <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the previous equation simplifies to<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e165" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(16)</label></disp-formula>which results in <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Theoretical estimate of the mean residence time</title>
        <p>The mean residence time in each state is proportional to the residence probability <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> defined in equation (4). To obtain it, we need to compute the transition rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of the model parameters as:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e169" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(17)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the initial and final time and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the functional integral over the trajectory <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Each time trajectory <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, solution of equations (1–2), has an associated weight <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, defined as:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e176" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(18)</label></disp-formula>By discretizing the time so that <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e179" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the microscopic time step, we obtain that the Langevin equations can be written using the Ito prescription <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Gardiner2">[56]</xref> as:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e180" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(19)</label></disp-formula>where we use the short notation <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e181" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the initial value is <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The time discretization allows us to interpret the functional integral in equation (18) as:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e183" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(20)</label></disp-formula>Since the noise is Gaussian and white, its distribution now reads:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e184" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(21)</label></disp-formula>This can be justified using the property of the delta-function <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and its discrete time version <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> so that <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> follows and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>Using the properties of the delta function, and integrating out all <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e189" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>s, the continuous limit expression of equation (21) is<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e190" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(22)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has an intuitive interpretation in thermodynamics and it is related to the entropy production rate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Seifert1">[57]</xref>. By using stationary-phase approximation, it turns out that in the computation of the rate defined in (17) only one path matters, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e192" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is the most probable path. Higher order factors are proportional to the term <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e193" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Langer1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Langer2">[46]</xref>, and therefore simplify with the denominator in equation (21). This comes from the fact that several almost optimal paths can be constructed starting from <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In the optimal path, the system stays in a stable state for a very long time, then it rapidly switches to the other stable state where it persists until <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. By shifting the switching time one obtains sub-optimal paths that, at the leading order in <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, give the same contribution of the optimal one and their number is directly proportional to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This leads to<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e198" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(23)</label></disp-formula></p>
        <p>The functional Gaussian integral can be computed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Langer1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Langer2">[46]</xref> and only provides a sub-leading correction to the saddle-point contribution resulting in the transition rate formula <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is reported in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref> section.</p>
        <p>We now need to determine the optimal path and its associated action <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This path is defined as the one where the functional derivative of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e201" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is set to zero such that the initial and final states are fixed. This produces a set of second-order differential equations<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e202" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(24)</label></disp-formula>which can be solved imposing the initial conditions on <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>It is easy to verify that the downhill solution is <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and it is associated with null action. Meanwhile, the ascending trajectory, which is the one leading to a non-zero action and hence gives the transition rate value, is not given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as it would be for conservative field of forces. This means that in presence of a dissipative term the reverse optimal path from the minimum to the maximum is different with respect to the one connecting the maximum from the minimum of the landscape.</p>
        <p>As the last point, we want to show that the action associated to the optimal path can be further simplified by noticing that<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e207" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(25)</label></disp-formula>We can easily prove this condition by showing that the time derivative <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e208" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> vanishes when equation (24) is satisfied and remembering that the optimal path connects two stable states where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e209" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e210" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This property allows us to rewrite the action as:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e211" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(26)</label></disp-formula></p>
        <p>We solved numerically the equation (24) using a trial-and-error approach. We varied the first-derivative at initial time in order to arrive as close as possible to the final point within some numerical precision. In principle the ideal trajectory connecting two stable points should be computed in the limit of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e212" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> but this trajectory will take infinite time. We report three examples of most probable paths connecting the points <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e213" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e214" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and reverse for a chosen set of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e215" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in Fig. S6 of the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Singular value decomposition</title>
        <p>We first rarefy the raw phylotypes counts matrix as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>. We then normalize the logarithm of the counts according to the following procedure: 1) we add one to all the phylotypes counts to take into account also for the non-detected phylotypes in each sample, 2) we log-transform the data and 3) we normalize the resulting matrix with respect to the samples averages. In formulae, the count associated to phylotype <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e216" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in sample <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e217" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for each subject <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e218" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e219" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e220" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the average value of the counts in each sample and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e221" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the total number of phylotypes. Among all possible normalization schemes, we decide to subtract the column averages because we aim at identifying patterns within samples based on their correlation in bacterial composition. Indeed, the covariance matrix of the samples is proportional to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e222" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e223" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the transpose matrix. SVD on the matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e224" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is thus equivalent to the principal component analysis (PCA) performed on the samples covariance matrix.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1002497.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s001">Text S1</xref> reports additional calculations, figures and details on: 1) model and relative stability analysis, 2) effect of random fluctuations and noise-induced dynamics and 3) Singular Value Decomposition.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1002497.s002" mimetype="video/quicktime" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Video S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s002">Video S1</xref> shows the stationary probability distributions <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e225" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of the sensitive and tolerant densities for increasing noise value <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e226" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which ranges from <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e227" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e228" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For visualization purposes, the noise value associated to each movie frame is displayed as an increasing bar in the top panel.</p>
          <p>(MOV)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pcbi.1002497.s003" mimetype="Video/mp4" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Video S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1002497.s003">Video S2</xref> shows the time evolution of the two principal components for the three subjects from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">[24]</xref>. Empty circles represent untreated samples, asterisks represent samples during treatment <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002497.e229" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and filled circles represent represent samples during treatment 2.</p>
          <p>(MP4)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors acknowledge Chris Sander, Kevin Foster, Jonas Schluter, Carlos Carmona-Fontaine, Massimo Vergassola, Stefano Di Talia, Les Dethlefsen and Deb Bemis for their insightful comments and help. S.B. acknowledges the GDRE 224 GREFI-MEFI CNRS-INdAM.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Neish1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neish</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Microbes in gastrointestinal health and disease.</article-title>             <source>Gastroenterology</source>             <volume>136</volume>             <fpage>65</fpage>             <lpage>80</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McFall-Ngai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>An ecological and evolutionary perspective on human microbiome mutualism and disease.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>449</volume>             <fpage>811</fpage>             <lpage>818</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Jones1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Social network wants to sequence your gut.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/news.2011.523" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/news.2011.523</ext-link></comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Khoruts1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoruts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadowsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Therapeutic transplantation of the distal gut microbiota.</article-title>             <source>Mucosal Immunol</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>4</fpage>             <lpage>7</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Borody1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borody</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surace</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Bacteriotherapy using fecal ora: Toying with human motions.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>475</fpage>             <lpage>483</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Ruder1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruder</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Synthetic biology moving into the clinic.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>333</volume>             <fpage>1248</fpage>             <lpage>1252</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Pultz1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pultz</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stiefel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helfand</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donskey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Mechanisms by which anaerobic microbiota inhibit the establishment in mice of intestinal colonization by vancomycin-resistant enterococcus.</article-title>             <source>J Inf Dis</source>             <volume>191</volume>             <fpage>949</fpage>             <lpage>956</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Stecher1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The role of microbiota in infectious disease.</article-title>             <source>Trends Microbiol</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>107</fpage>             <lpage>114</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Endt1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Endt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaffron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tchitchek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The microbiota mediates pathogen clearance from the gut lumen after non-typhoidal salmonella diarrhea.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Pathog</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e1001097</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Fukuda1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oshima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Bifidobacteria can protect from enteropathogenic infection through production of acetate.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>469</volume>             <fpage>543</fpage>             <lpage>547</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Dabard1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bridonneau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillipe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anglade</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Ruminococcin A, a new lantibiotic produced by a Ruminococcus gnavus strain isolated from human feces.</article-title>             <source>Appl Env Microbiol</source>             <volume>67</volume>             <fpage>4111</fpage>             <lpage>4118</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Corr1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corr</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riedel</surname><given-names>CU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Bacteriocin production as a mechanism for the antiinfective activity of lactobacillus salivarius ucc118.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>104</volume>             <fpage>7617</fpage>             <lpage>7621</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Stecher2">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Mechanisms controlling pathogen colonization of the gut.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>82</fpage>             <lpage>91</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Keeney1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeney</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Enteric pathogen exploitation of the microbiota-generated nutrient environment of the gut.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>92</fpage>             <lpage>98</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Pamer1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pamer</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Immune responses to commensal and environmental microbes.</article-title>             <source>Nat Immunol</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>1173</fpage>             <lpage>1178</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen2">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sogin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The pervasive effects of an antibiotic on the human gut microbiota, as revealed by deep 16 s rrna sequencing.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>e280</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Willing1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willing</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Shifting the balance: antibiotic effects on hostmicrobiota mutualism.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Micro</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>233</fpage>             <lpage>243</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Ubeda1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubeda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenq</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Equinda</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Vancomycin-resistant enterococcus domination of intestinal microbiota is enabled by antibiotic treatment in mice and precedes bloodstream invasion in humans.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Invest</source>             <volume>120</volume>             <fpage>4332</fpage>             <lpage>4341</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Bishara1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bishara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peled</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitlik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samra</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Mortality of patients with antibiotic-associated diarrhoea: the impact of clostridium diffcile.</article-title>             <source>J Hosp Infect</source>             <volume>68</volume>             <fpage>308</fpage>             <lpage>314</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Buffe1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buffe</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarchum</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Equinda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipuma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gobourne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2012</year>             <article-title>Profound alterations of intestinal microbiota following a single dose of clindamycin results in sustained susceptibility to c. difficile-induced colitis.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>80</volume>             <fpage>63</fpage>             <lpage>73</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Arumugam1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Paslier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Enterotypes of the human gut microbiome.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>473</volume>             <fpage>174</fpage>             <lpage>180</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Wu1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bittinger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Linking long-term dietary patterns with gut microbial enterotypes.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>334</volume>             <fpage>105</fpage>             <lpage>108</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Scheffer1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Alternative Stable States and Regime Shifts in Ecosystems.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>ALevin</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>2009, The Princeton guide to ecology</source>             <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>359</fpage>             <lpage>406</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen3">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Incomplete recovery and individualized responses of the human distal gut microbiota to repeated antibiotic perturbation.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>4554</fpage>             <lpage>4561</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Dethlefsen4">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckburg</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bik</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Assembly of the human intestinal microbiota.</article-title>             <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>517</fpage>             <lpage>523</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Caporaso1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Moving pictures of the human microbiome.</article-title>             <source>Genome Biol</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>R50</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Ley1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Ecological and evolutionary forces shaping microbial diversity in the human intestine.</article-title>             <source>Cell</source>             <volume>124</volume>             <fpage>837</fpage>             <lpage>848</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Foster1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krone</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forney</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Application of ecological network theory to the human microbiome.</article-title>             <source>Interdiscip Perspect Infect Dis</source>             <volume>2008</volume>             <fpage>839501</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-dosSantos1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vos</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Systems biology of the gut: the interplay of food, microbiota and host at the mucosal interface.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>539</fpage>             <lpage>550</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-MaoJones1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao-Jones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellner</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>How microbial community composition regulates coral disease development.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>e1000345</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Monod1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1949</year>             <article-title>The growth of bacterial cultures.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>371</fpage>             <lpage>394</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Xavier1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Social interaction in synthetic and natural microbial communities.</article-title>             <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>483</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Bucci1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>The evolution of bacteriocin production in bacterial biofilms.</article-title>             <source>Am Nat</source>             <volume>178</volume>             <fpage>E162</fpage>             <lpage>E173</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Gardiner1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <source>Handbook of Stochastic Methods in Physics, Chemistry, and other Natural Sciences</source>             <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">442</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Galan1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ermentrout</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Stochastic dynamics of uncoupled neural oscillators: Fokker-planck studies with the finite element method.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev E</source>             <volume>76</volume>             <fpage>056110</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Littman1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Littman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pamer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Role of the commensal microbiota in normal and pathogenic host immune responses.</article-title>             <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>311</fpage>             <lpage>323</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Alter1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Singular value decomposition for genome-wide expression data processing and modeling.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>97</volume>             <fpage>10101</fpage>             <lpage>10106</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Brauer1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Conservation of the metabolomic response to starvation across two divergent microbes.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>19302</fpage>             <lpage>19307</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Sol1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solé</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <source>Self-organization in complex ecosystems, volume 42</source>             <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Princeton Univ Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">392</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Zhu1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>On competitive lotkavolterra model in random environments.</article-title>             <source>J Math Anal Appl</source>             <volume>357</volume>             <fpage>154</fpage>             <lpage>170</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Mitri1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Social evolution in multispecies biofilms.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>10839</fpage>             <lpage>10846</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-MunozTamayo1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz-Tamayo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>ric</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leclerc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Mathematical modelling of carbohydrate degradation by human colonic microbiota.</article-title>             <source>J Theor Biol</source>             <volume>266</volume>             <fpage>189</fpage>             <lpage>201</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-MunozTamayo2">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz-Tamayo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Kinetic modelling of lactate utilization and butyrate production by key human colonic bacterial species.</article-title>             <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>             <volume>76</volume>             <fpage>615</fpage>             <lpage>624</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Holling1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1973</year>             <article-title>Resilience and stability of ecological systems.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>23</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Langer1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1967</year>             <article-title>Theory of the condensation point.</article-title>             <source>Ann Phys</source>             <volume>41</volume>             <fpage>108</fpage>             <lpage>157</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Langer2">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1968</year>             <article-title>Theory of nucleation rates.</article-title>             <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>973</fpage>             <lpage>976</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Yuan1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doucette</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>WU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Metabolomics-driven quantitative analysis of ammonia assimilation in E. coli.</article-title>             <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>302</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Gonzalez1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Advancing analytical algorithms and pipelines for billions of microbial sequences.</article-title>             <source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>64</fpage>             <lpage>71</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Hamady1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamady</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Fast unifrac: facilitating high-throughput phylogenetic analyses of microbial communities including analysis of pyrosequencing and phylochip data.</article-title>             <source>ISME J</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>17</fpage>             <lpage>27</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Kuczynski1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuczynski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Microbial community resemblance methods differ in their ability to detect biologically relevant patterns.</article-title>             <source>Nat Meth</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>813</fpage>             <lpage>819</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-terBraak1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ter Braak</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>A theory of gradient analysis.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caswell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Advances in Ecological Research: Classic Papers, Vol 34</source>             <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>235</fpage>             <lpage>282</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Turnbaugh1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamady</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yatsunenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantarel</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>A core gut microbiome in obese and lean twins.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>457</volume>             <fpage>480</fpage>             <lpage>484</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Ichinohe1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ichinohe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peaper</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Microbiota regulates immune defense against respiratory tract inuenza a virus infection.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>5354</fpage>             <lpage>5359</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Veiga1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veiga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallini</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis fermented milk product reduces inammation by altering a niche for colitogenic microbes.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>18132</fpage>             <lpage>18137</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Lee1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazmanian</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Has the microbiota played a critical role in the evolution of the adaptive immune system?</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>330</volume>             <fpage>1768</fpage>             <lpage>1773</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Gardiner2">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1983</year>             <article-title>The escape time in nonpotential systems.</article-title>             <source>J Stat Phys</source>             <volume>30</volume>             <fpage>157</fpage>             <lpage>177</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pcbi.1002497-Seifert1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Stochastic thermodynamics: principles and perspectives.</article-title>             <source>Eur Phys J B</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>423</fpage>             <lpage>431</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>