<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Computational Biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-17-02110</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Nucleic acids</subject><subj-group><subject>RNA</subject><subj-group><subject>Messenger RNA</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Nervous system</subject><subj-group><subject>Synapses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Nervous system</subject><subj-group><subject>Synapses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Electrophysiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurophysiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Synapses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Electrophysiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurophysiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Synapses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurophysiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Synapses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocytosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell processes</subject><subj-group><subject>Secretory pathway</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocytosis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymology</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene expression</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein translation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive science</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognition</subject><subj-group><subject>Memory</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Learning and memory</subject><subj-group><subject>Memory</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzymology</subject><subj-group><subject>Enzyme inhibitors</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Chemical synthesis</subject><subj-group><subject>Biosynthetic techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein synthesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein synthesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Coupled feedback loops maintain synaptic long-term potentiation: A computational model of PKMzeta synthesis and AMPA receptor trafficking</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Coupled feedback loops maintain synaptic long-term potentiation</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9978-9491</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Helfer</surname>
<given-names>Peter</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Software</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Visualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Shultz</surname>
<given-names>Thomas R.</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – review &amp; editing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Psychology and Integrated Program in Neuroscience, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Psychology and School of Computer Science, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Jedrzejewski-Szmek</surname>
<given-names>Joanna</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Instytut Biologii Doswiadczalnej im M Nenckiego Polskiej Akademii Nauk, POLAND</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">peter.helfer@mail.mcgill.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>29</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>5</month>
<year>2018</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e1006147</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>19</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>16</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2018</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Helfer, Shultz</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147"/>
<abstract>
<p>In long-term potentiation (LTP), one of the most studied types of neural plasticity, synaptic strength is persistently increased in response to stimulation. Although a number of different proteins have been implicated in the sub-cellular molecular processes underlying induction and maintenance of LTP, the precise mechanisms remain unknown. A particular challenge is to demonstrate that a proposed molecular mechanism can provide the level of stability needed to maintain memories for months or longer, in spite of the fact that many of the participating molecules have much shorter life spans. Here we present a computational model that combines simulations of several biochemical reactions that have been suggested in the LTP literature and show that the resulting system does exhibit the required stability. At the core of the model are two interlinked feedback loops of molecular reactions, one involving the atypical protein kinase PKMζ and its messenger RNA, the other involving PKMζ and GluA2-containing AMPA receptors. We demonstrate that robust bistability–stable equilibria both in the synapse’s potentiated and unpotentiated states–can arise from a set of simple molecular reactions. The model is able to account for a wide range of empirical results, including induction and maintenance of late-phase LTP, cellular memory reconsolidation and the effects of different pharmaceutical interventions.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author summary</title>
<p>The brain stores memories by adjusting the strengths of connections between neurons, a phenomenon known as synaptic plasticity. Different types of plasticity mechanisms have either a strengthening or a weakening effect and produce synaptic modifications that last from milliseconds to months or more. One of the most studied forms of plasticity, long-term potentiation, is a persistent increase of synaptic strength that results from stimulation and is believed to play an important role in both short-term and long-term memory. Researchers have identified many proteins and other molecules involved in long-term potentiation and formulated different hypotheses about the biochemical processes underlying its induction and maintenance. A growing number of studies support an important role for the protein PKMζ (protein kinase M Zeta) in long-term potentiation. To investigate the explanatory power of this hypothesis, we built a computational model of the proposed biochemical reactions that involve this protein and ran simulations of a number of experiments that have been reported in the literature. We find that our model is able to explain a wide range of empirical results and thus provide insights into the molecular mechanisms of memory.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000038</institution-id>
<institution>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>7927-2012-RGPIN</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Shultz</surname>
<given-names>Thomas R.</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by a Discovery Grant to TRS from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (7927-2012-RGPIN). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="16"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<page-count count="31"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>PLOS Publication Stage</meta-name>
<meta-value>vor-update-to-uncorrected-proof</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>Publication Update</meta-name>
<meta-value>2018-06-08</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All computer program files are available from the ModelDB database, accession number 239541 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://modeldb.yale.edu/239541" xlink:type="simple">http://modeldb.yale.edu/239541</ext-link>).</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The brain stores memories by adjusting the strengths of connections between neurons. Such synaptic plasticity comes in different forms that strengthen or weaken synapses and range from very short-lived to long-lasting. One of the most well-studied forms of plasticity is long-term potentiation, LTP, a phenomenon whereby synaptic strength is persistently increased in response to stimulation. Different forms of LTP are known to play important roles in both short-term and long-term memory.</p>
<p>Many different proteins have been identified in the sub-cellular molecular processes that are involved in LTP. An important question is how these proteins, with lifetimes measured in hours or days, can maintain memories for months or years. We present a computational model that demonstrates how this problem can be solved by two interconnected feedback loops of molecular reactions.</p>
<p>We begin with an overview of LTP with emphasis on the empirical findings that our model aims to explain. This is followed by a description of the model, an account of our results, and discussion of their implications.</p>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="intro">
<title>Background</title>
<p>In his address to the Royal Society in 1894, Santiago Ramon y Cajal hypothesized that the brain stores information by adjusting the strengths of associations between neurons, as well as by growing new connections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref001">1</xref>]. In the years since, the existence of both of these mechanisms, now known as synaptic plasticity and synaptogenesis, respectively, has been well established, and there is ample evidence that synaptic plasticity plays an important role in learning and memory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref002">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref004">4</xref>].</p>
<p>Neurons communicate by transmitting signals across chemical synapses, where presynaptic axon terminals connect to postsynaptic neurons, most often on their dendrites. When a nerve impulse (action potential) arrives at the axon terminal, neurotransmitter molecules are released into the synaptic cleft, a narrow gap between the two neurons, where they activate receptors in the membrane of the postsynaptic neuron. This sets in motion a series of biochemical events in the postsynaptic neuron, the details of which depend on the type of receptor, among other factors. Synaptic strength depends both on the amount of transmitter that is released by the arrival of a nerve impulse at the axon terminal and on the number and sensitivity of the receptors. It may thus be regulated on either the pre- or postsynaptic side, and mechanisms of synaptic plasticity have been shown to operate in both compartments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref003">3</xref>]. Plasticity may either strengthen or weaken a synapse, and the effect may be short-lived or long-lasting. Short-term synaptic plasticity, lasting from milliseconds to minutes, is primarily due to presynaptic mechanisms that adjust the amount of transmitter release, whereas postsynaptic modifications that adjust the number and sensitivity of receptors are important for long-term plasticity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref004">4</xref>]. In particular, this is true of long-term potentiation (LTP), a type of persistent strengthening of synapses in response to stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref006">6</xref>], which has been studied extensively in the CA3-CA1 synapses of the rodent hippocampus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref004">4</xref>] and is known to depend on an increase in the number of receptors inserted in the postsynaptic membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref007">7</xref>].</p>
<p>There are at least two forms of LTP: Moderately strong stimulation induces early-phase LTP (E-LTP), which persists for at most a few hours. When the stimulation is stronger, E-LTP may be followed by late-phase LTP (L-LTP), which can last for days, months or longer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref008">8</xref>] and is believed to be an important mechanism for the storage of long-term memories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref010">10</xref>]. The establishment of L-LTP, known as synaptic or cellular memory consolidation, is a process that takes less than an hour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref012">12</xref>] and requires synthesis of new protein. This has been demonstrated by showing that infusion of protein-synthesis-inhibiting drugs such as anisomycin can prevent establishment of L-LTP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref012">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref015">15</xref>]. On the behavioral level, protein synthesis inhibition (PSI) has been shown to impair the formation of long-term memory, consistent with the notion of L-LTP as a memory mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref016">16</xref>].</p>
<p>Once long-term memory is established, it is in general no longer vulnerable to infusion of a protein synthesis inhibitor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref016">16</xref>]. However, memory retrieval can induce a state of transient instability, during which the memory is again susceptible to protein synthesis inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref017">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref019">19</xref>]. This susceptibility of memory to post-retrieval PSI infusion has been shown to correlate with instability of L-LTP at the neural level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref021">21</xref>], providing further evidence of the importance of LTP as a mechanism of long-term memory. The synaptic destabilization that is triggered by memory retrieval is followed by a period of restabilization which has similarities with the initial synaptic consolidation that follows memory acquisition. It has therefore become known as <italic>memory reconsolidation</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref019">19</xref>], more specifically <italic>synaptic</italic> (or <italic>cellular</italic>) <italic>reconsolidation</italic>, to avoid confusion with the related but distinct phenomenon <italic>systems reconsolidation</italic>, a temporary dependence on the hippocampus for restabilization of a memory after reactivation (retrieval). For reviews of reconsolidation research, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref022">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref024">24</xref>]. For a computational model of systems consolidation and reconsolidation, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref025">25</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Glutamatergic synapses</title>
<p>In this report, we focus on L-LTP induction and maintenance at glutamatergic synapses, the most abundant type of synapse in the vertebrate nervous system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref027">27</xref>]. Glutamatergic synapses contain several kinds of receptors that are activated by the neurotransmitter glutamate. Of particular interest for LTP are the α-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid receptor (AMPA receptor or AMPAR), which mediates synaptic transmission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref028">28</xref>], and the N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDA receptor or NMDAR), which is involved with regulatory functions including the regulation of synaptic strength [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref029">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref030">30</xref>].</p>
<p>AMPARs are ion channels that open when activated by the neurotransmitter glutamate. The opening of the channel allows positively charged ions, mainly sodium and potassium, to flow through the cell membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref031">31</xref>]. This causes a partial depolarization of the membrane, which at rest is polarized by a net negative charge inside the cell. The partial depolarization is known as an excitatory postsynaptic potential, or EPSP, and the amplitude of the EPSP produced by a single action potential arriving at a synapse is a measure of synaptic strength. Among other factors, the EPSP amplitude depends on the number of AMPARs inserted in the postsynaptic density (PSD), the area of cell membrane that constitutes the receiving side of the synapse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref031">31</xref>]. Thus mechanisms that control the trafficking of AMPARs into and out of the PSD play an important part in the regulation of synaptic strength.</p>
<p>AMPARs are heterotetramers, i.e. they consist of four non-identical subunits. The subunits are of four different kinds, named GluA1, GluA2, GluA3 and GluA4, and AMPARs can be made up of different combinations of these [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref032">32</xref>]. GluA2 is of particular interest here, because L-LTP is associated with an increase in the number of GluA2-containing AMPARs inserted in the PSD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref034">34</xref>].</p>
<p>AMPA receptors are not permanently inserted in the PSD, but are constantly being recycled. Certain proteins transport AMPARs into the PSD from pools maintained in adjacent areas, while others remove them (a process known as internalization or endocytosis) and either recycle them to stand-by pools or mark them for degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref035">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref036">36</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Protein kinase M zeta (PKMζ)</title>
<p>Many proteins have been implicated in the induction and maintenance of LTP, including CaMKII, PKA, MAPK and several isoforms of PKC (for a review, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref007">7</xref>]). An atypical isoform of PKC, protein kinase Mζ (PKMζ), is believed to play an important role for L-LTP. The level of PKMζ has been shown to increase as the result of NMDA receptor stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref037">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref038">38</xref>], consistent with its proposed role in L-LTP induction. Inhibition of PKMζ activity results in disruption of established L-LTP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref039">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref041">41</xref>], and perfusion of PKMζ into a neuron can induce L-LTP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref039">39</xref>]. PKMζ activity is believed to increase the number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs at the synapse both by facilitating the trafficking of these receptors into the PSD and by inhibiting their removal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>]. GluA2-containing AMPARs are held at extrasynaptic pools by the protein PICK1 which binds to the GluA2 subunit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref034">34</xref>]. PKMζ facilitates interaction between the trafficking protein NSF and the GluA2 subunit, which results in its release from PICK1, freeing the AMPARs to diffuse laterally into the PSD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref034">34</xref>]. Furthermore, once GluA2-containing AMPARs are inserted in the PSD membrane, PKMζ prevents their removal by inhibiting the interaction between the protein BRAG2 and the GluA2 subunit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref043">43</xref>], an interaction that plays a key part in endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref044">44</xref>].</p>
<p>While GluA2-containing AMPARs are important for the stabilization of L-LTP, there is evidence that GluA2-lacking AMPARs play an important role in the induction of early-phase LTP (E-LTP), and also in reconsolidation. Several studies have shown that GluA2-lacking AMPARs are initially inserted at the time of memory acquisition or LTP induction, and then gradually replaced by GluA2-containing AMPARs during consolidation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref045">45</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref047">47</xref>]. Hong et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>] showed that memory reactivation triggers an abrupt replacement of GluA2-containing AMPARs by GluA2-lacking AMPARs. This is followed by a gradual reversal, i.e. the GluA2-containing AMPARs are restored and the number of GluA2-lacking AMPARs declines, as the potentiated state of the synapse is restabilized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>]. Because the temporary removal of GluA2-containing AMPARs is compensated for by an increase in GluA2-lacking AMPARs, the synaptic strength remains more or less constant during the period of instability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>]. Rao-Ruiz et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref021">21</xref>] reported similar results, although they observed a brief period of reduced synaptic strength between the GluA2-containing AMPAR removal and GluA2-lacking AMPAR insertion. Taken together, these results suggest that the stabilization of LTP, both initially during consolidation, and after reactivation-induced destabilization, requires insertion of GluA2-containing AMPARs, and that PKMζ plays an important role in maintaining the GluA2-containing AMPARs at the synapse.</p>
<p>An important question is how L-LTP, which can last for months or longer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref008">8</xref>], can be maintained by a protein like PKMζ, with a half-life that probably does not exceed several hours or at most a few days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref048">48</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref051">51</xref>]. A proposed answer to this question involves local translation of messenger RNA (mRNA) in or near dendritic spines. Most synapses are formed at dendritic spine heads, with one synapse per spine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref052">52</xref>]. It has been shown that PKMζ mRNA is transported from the cell body to dendrites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref053">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref054">54</xref>], but the mRNA in its basal state is translationally repressed by molecules that bind to it, or to the complex of proteins required to initiate translation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref050">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref053">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref055">55</xref>]. There is evidence that PKMζ catalyzes reactions that lift this translational block [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref049">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref056">56</xref>], possibly through inhibition of the PIN1 protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>], resulting in a positive feedback loop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref049">49</xref>]. By promoting its own synthesis in this manner, PKMζ may be able to remain at an increased level, and thus maintain L-LTP, for a long time, perhaps indefinitely.</p>
<p>It has also been suggested that the increased amount of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs at a potentiated synapse captures the PKMζ molecules and keeps them from dissipating away from the synaptic compartment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>]. This hypothesis is supported by several studies that show that blocking endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPARs can prevent depotentiation under protocols that otherwise cause disruption of L-LTP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref021">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>]. Together with PKMζ’s inhibiting effect on AMPAR endocytosis this constitutes a second feedback loop, a reciprocal relationship in which PKMζ and GluA2-containing AMPARs prevent each other’s removal from the synapse. As we shall see, the interaction between these two feedback loops plays a central role in our explanation of synaptic bistability, that is that synapses have two stable equilibrium states, unpotentiated and potentiated. Transient stimuli can cause a synapse to transition between these two states, but in the absence of such signals it tends to remain in one state or the other.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>L-LTP, LTM and pharmacological interventions</title>
<p>The notion that L-LTP is an important neural correlate of long-term memory (LTM) has been supported experimentally by demonstrating that pharmacological interventions that block L-LTP induction also interfere with the establishment of LTM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref058">58</xref>], and that interventions that disrupt established L-LTP also impair consolidated memories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref059">59</xref>]. Here we consider three types of pharmaceuticals that have been shown to produce significant results with respect to both L-LTP induction and maintenance, and to related behavior-level memory phenomena.</p>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Protein synthesis inhibitors</title>
<p>Infusion of protein synthesis inhibitors (PSIs) such as anisomycin into brain tissue can prevent the induction of L-LTP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref058">58</xref>], and also interferes with memory consolidation, the establishment of LTM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref060">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref061">61</xref>]. Once L-LTP is established, it becomes resistant to infusion of anisomycin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref012">12</xref>]. This does not mean that L-LTP can be maintained indefinitely without ongoing protein synthesis, but rather that it can tolerate an interruption of protein synthesis for the amount of time that anisomycin remains active after infusion.</p>
<p>Reactivation of a consolidated memory, e.g. by a reminder, can temporarily return it to a labile state in which it is again vulnerable to PSI infusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref060">60</xref>]. The putative molecular process underlying this phenomenon has been termed <italic>cellular</italic> or <italic>synaptic memory reconsolidation</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref062">62</xref>]. Concordant with the hypothesis that L-LTP is the neural correlate of LTM, the temporary post-reactivation vulnerability of LTM to PSI infusion can be explained as destabilization of L-LTP, followed by a restabilization phase that requires protein synthesis, hence the susceptibility to PSI. The destabilization has been shown to require the activity of NMDA receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref029">29</xref>], and to depend critically on endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref063">63</xref>].</p>
<p>Thus protein synthesis inhibition is known to both prevent establishment of L-LTP and to block reconsolidation, i.e. block restabilization of L-LTP after retrieval-induced destabilization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>ZIP</title>
<p>Much of the work demonstrating the role of PKMζ in L-LTP is based on administration of the synthetic peptide ZIP (zeta-inhibitory peptide), which binds to the catalytic region of the PKMζ molecule, thus blocking its enzymatic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref041">41</xref>]. On the behavioral level, infusion of ZIP into brain tissue has been shown to impair consolidated LTM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref059">59</xref>]. On the neural level, ZIP is known to disrupt established L-LTP when applied during the maintenance phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref039">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref064">64</xref>]. These results are consistent with the notion of a positive feedback loop: Inhibiting PKMζ’s enzymatic activity prevents it from catalyzing its own synthesis; the PKMζ concentration then drops, the AMPAR endocytosis rate increases, and the synapse returns to its basal state. On the other hand, ZIP does not prevent L-LTP induction when applied only during or immediately after stimulation. This was demonstrated by Ren et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref065">65</xref>] in an in-vitro experiment where onset and duration of ZIP application were precisely controlled.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>GluA2<sub>3Y</sub></title>
<p>GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> is a synthetic peptide that blocks regulated endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref066">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref067">67</xref>]. Infusion of GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> has been shown to block both the destabilizing effect of PSI infusion after memory reactivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>] and the depotentiating effect of ZIP during L-LTP maintenance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref033">33</xref>]. The GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> peptide is modeled on a sequence of the GluA2 subunit’s carboxyl tail and its endocytosis-inhibiting effect is believed to be due to competitive disruption of the binding of endocytosis-related proteins to this sequence on GluA2 subunits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref068">68</xref>].</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Computational model</title>
<p>The findings described above suggest a model of L-LTP maintenance with two connected feedback loops: (1) PKMζ maintains its own mRNA in a translatable state and translation of the mRNA in turn replenishes PKMζ. (2) PKMζ maintains GluA2-containing AMPARs at the synapse, and these in turn keep PKMζ molecules from dissipating away from the synaptic compartment. Below we describe a computational model that incorporates these relationships and investigate its ability to account for results reported in the empirical literature.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Deterministic vs. stochastic simulation</title>
<p>Systems of chemical reactions can be modeled either by deterministic methods based on ordinary differential equations (ODEs) or by stochastic simulation. When the numbers of molecules are small, stochastic simulation is the better choice, because random fluctuations then have significant effects that are not captured by deterministic methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref069">69</xref>]. In particular, random fluctuations can cause a small system to spontaneously transition from one steady state to another; the resulting impact on system stability can be studied in a stochastic simulation, but not in a deterministic model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref070">70</xref>], because the latter only accounts for average reaction rates over a large number of molecules.</p>
<p>The molecules of interest for our simulation are present in small numbers in a dendritic spine head, e.g. fewer than a hundred PKMζ molecules (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1006147.s001">S1 Text</xref>) and at most ca 150 AMPARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref071">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref072">72</xref>]. This is well below the size of system that can be realistically simulated by deterministic methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref070">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref073">73</xref>]. We therefore base our simulation on the Gillespie algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref074">74</xref>], a well-established and widely used approach to discrete and stochastic simulation of reaction systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref069">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref070">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref073">73</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Model description</title>
<p>The model consists of four inter-dependent pairs of processes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g001">Fig 1</xref>):</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Process diagram.</title>
<p>a) Activation/deactivation of PKMζ mRNA (blue). Translational repression of mRNA is lifted by catalytic activity of PKMζ, possibly by phosphorylation of mRNA-binding proteins. A phosphatase (pink) dephosphorylates the same proteins, returning mRNA to its repressed state. b) Synthesis and degradation/dissipation of PKMζ (cyan). Synthesis consists in local translation of PKMζ mRNA. Degradation and/or dissipation away from the synaptic compartment is inhibited by inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs. c) Trafficking of GluA2-containing AMPARs (green) into and out of the PSD. Insertion is facilitated by PKMζ, and removal (endocytosis) by the BRAG2 protein. d) Inhibition/disinhibition of BRAG2-GluA2 interaction. Inhibition is modeled as phosphorylation of BRAG2 (orange) catalyzed by PKMζ, and disinhibition as dephosphorylation catalyzed by a phosphatase. E1 and E2 (dark green) are enzymes activated by NMDAR stimulation at L-LTP induction and memory reactivation, respectively. The effects of PSI, ZIP and GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> (red) are modeled by disabling the indicated catalytic reactions. Solid arrows represent chemical reactions and receptor trafficking. Dashed lines with filled circles represent catalytic activity. Dashed lines with crossbars represent inhibition.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Activation/deactivation of PKMζ mRNA</title>
<p>PKMζ lifts the constitutive translational repression of PKMζ mRNA by phosphorylating some substrate, possibly mRNA-binding proteins attached to the mRNA. The mRNA molecule with attached proteins and ribosomes (polysome) is represented as a single molecule in the model, and de-repression is modeled as phosphorylation of (some component of) this molecule by PKMζ. The opposite reaction, dephosphorylation by a phosphatase assumed to be present at fixed concentration, returns the mRNA to its repressed state.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Synthesis and degradation/dissipation of PKMζ</title>
<p>Synthesis consists in local translation of PKMζ mRNA. (This is somewhat speculative: PKMζ mRNA has been shown to be present in dendrites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref053">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref054">54</xref>], but not specifically in dendritic spines.) Inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs inhibit degradation and/or dissipation of PKMζ away from the synaptic compartment by binding PKMζ molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>], probably via a scaffold protein such as PICK1 or KIBRA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref075">75</xref>]. This is modeled as an affinity of PKMζ for inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, with a reduced dissipation/degradation rate while so attached.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>GluA2-containing AMPAR trafficking into and out of the PSD</title>
<p>The model includes a fixed-size population of GluA2-containing AMPARs. At any time, a subset of the AMPARs are inserted in the PSD while the remainder are maintained in extrasynaptic pools. Transport of AMPARs into the PSD is facilitated by PKMζ and removal (endocytosis) is enabled by the protein BRAG2. In addition to these two regulated processes, constitutive processes traffic AMPARs into and out of the synapse at lower rates.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Inhibition and disinhibition of BRAG2-GluA2 interaction</title>
<p>The mechanism by which PKMζ inhibits the interaction between BRAG2 and the GluA2 subunit to block AMPAR removal from the PSD is not known, but presumably involves phosphorylation of some substrate. We model the inhibition as phosphorylation of the BRAG2 molecule itself; other possibilities include phosphorylation of a site on the GluA2 subunit or of another participating protein. The BRAG2-GluA2 interaction is restored through dephosphorylation of the same substrate by a phosphatase, which is assumed to be present in fixed concentration.</p>
<p>Although the increase in PKMζ level that is associated with L-LTP induction is known to depend on NMDAR activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref038">38</xref>], the underlying biochemical pathways are unknown. In the model this mechanism is represented by an unspecified enzyme that we call E1 which, when activated by a reaction cascade triggered by NMDAR activation, has the ability to lift the translational block on PKMζ mRNA, thereby enabling PKMζ synthesis.</p>
<p>Similarly, the destabilizing effect of memory reactivation has been shown to depend on NMDAR activity and on endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref076">76</xref>], but the biochemical cascades that connect these event have not yet been identified. In our model, reactivation is simulated as an increase in the level of a second unspecified enzyme E2 with the ability to catalyze endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR.</p>
<p>In addition to these processes, the model includes simulation of the effects of the three pharmaceuticals described in the introduction. The time intervals that these drugs remain at a high enough concentration to inhibit their targets depend on the doses infused and also on their specific rates of decay or metabolism. The intervals used here are based on activity periods reported in the cited references:</p>
<p><bold>PSI:</bold> Infusion of a protein synthesis inhibitor is simulated by disabling PKMζ synthesis for nine hours, the amount of time that the protein synthesis inhibitor anisomycin remains active after infusion into brain tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref077">77</xref>].</p>
<p><bold>ZIP:</bold> Administration of the ZIP peptide is simulated by disabling PKMζ’s enzymatic activity–catalysis of mRNA activation, facilitation of GluA2-containing AMPAR trafficking into the PSD and inhibition of BRAG2-GluA2 interaction–for twelve hours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref078">78</xref>].</p>
<p><bold>GluA2</bold><sub><bold>3Y</bold></sub>: Perfusion of GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> is simulated by disabling regulated endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR for twelve hours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref076">76</xref>]. (GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> does not affect constitutive endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref067">67</xref>].)</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1006147.t001">Table 1</xref> lists the molecule species included in the model, including complexes formed during enzymatic reactions. All simulations begin in the lower (unpotentiated) steady state with the indicated initial molecule counts.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1006147.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Molecule species.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Symbol</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
<th align="left">Initial count</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">P</td>
<td align="left">Unbound PKMζ</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">R<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">unphosphorylated PKMζ mRNA (inactive)</td>
<td align="left">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">R<sub>A</sub></td>
<td align="left">phosphorylated PKMζ mRNA (active)</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PP</td>
<td align="left">phosphatase</td>
<td align="left">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PP•R<sub>A</sub></td>
<td align="left">PP + R<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">E1<sub>A</sub></td>
<td align="left">E1 enzyme, active</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">E1<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">E1 enzyme, inactive</td>
<td align="left">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">E1<sub>A</sub>•R<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">E1<sub>A</sub> + R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">A<sub>U</sub></td>
<td align="left">Uninserted GluA2-containing AMPAR</td>
<td align="left">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">A<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">Inserted GluA2-containing AMPAR</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">A<sub>I</sub>•P</td>
<td align="left">PKMζ bound to inserted AMPAR</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">P•R<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">P + R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">A<sub>I</sub>•P•R<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">A<sub>I</sub> + P + R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">B<sub>A</sub></td>
<td align="left">Active BRAG2</td>
<td align="left">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">B<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">Inactive BRAG2</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">PP•B<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">PP + B<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">P•B<sub>A</sub></td>
<td align="left">P + B<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">A<sub>I</sub>•P•B<sub>A</sub></td>
<td align="left">A<sub>I</sub> + P + B<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">B<sub>A</sub>•A<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">B<sub>A</sub> + A<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">B<sub>A</sub>•A<sub>I</sub>•P</td>
<td align="left">B<sub>A</sub> + A<sub>I</sub> + P complex</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">E2<sub>A</sub></td>
<td align="left">E2 enzyme, active</td>
<td align="left">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">E2<sub>I</sub></td>
<td align="left">E2 enzyme, inactive</td>
<td align="left">100</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Simulated Reactions</title>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Activation of PKMζ mRNA</title>
<p>PKMζ mRNA is present in dendritic spines, but is translationally repressed in its basal state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref053">53</xref>] due to mRNA-binding proteins that prevent translation from being initiated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref055">55</xref>]. PKMζ is able to lift the repression, possibly by phosphorylating these proteins, thus catalyzing its own synthesis in a positive feedback loop. We model mRNA with its associated proteins as a single molecule, represented by <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub> in its inactive repressed state, and by <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub> when activated. Activation is modeled using Michaelis-Menten kinetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref073">73</xref>], i.e. a PKMζ molecule (<italic>P</italic>) and an inactive mRNA molecule (<italic>R</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub>) form a complex <italic>P</italic>•<italic>R</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub>. The complex may then either dissociate (reaction 2) or the catalytic reaction (3) may take place, producing active mRNA (<italic>R</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub>):
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e001">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M1">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e002">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M2">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(2)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e003">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M3">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(3)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Deactivation of PKMζ mRNA</title>
<p>The PKMζ mRNA returns to its repressed state when the mRNA-binding proteins are dephosphorylated by a phosphatase which we denote by PP. This is also modeled with Michaelis-Menten kinetics (as are all enzymatic reactions in the model):
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e004">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M4">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(4)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e005">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e005g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M5">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(5)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e006">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e006g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e006" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M6">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(6)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>PKMζ synthesis and degradation/dissipation</title>
<p>PKMζ is synthesized by local translation of active mRNA (reaction 7). Over time PKMζ degrades or diffuses away from the synaptic compartment. Reaction 8 represents the combined effect of these two processes. The model is unspecific with respect to their relative importance for PKMζ turnover.</p>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e007">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e007g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e007" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M7">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(7)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e008">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e008g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e008" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M8">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(8)</label>
</disp-formula>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Inhibition/disinhibition of BRAG2</title>
<p>BRAG2 is inhibited by PKMζ and reactivated by phosphatase. Both processes are described by Michaelis-Menten kinetics. <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub> denote active and inhibited BRAG2, respectively:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e009">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e009g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e009" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M9">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(9)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e010">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e010g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e010" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M10">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(10)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e011">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e011g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e011" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M11">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(11)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e012">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e012g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e012" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M12">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(12)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e013">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e013g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e013" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M13">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(13)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e014">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e014g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e014" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M14">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>14</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(14)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022">
<title>AMPA receptor trafficking</title>
<p>Transport of GluA2-containing AMPARs into the PSD has been shown to involve a trafficking process that is facilitated by PKMζ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref034">34</xref>]. Because the details of this process are unknown, including which substrate of PKMζ mediates it, we model it as a simple enzymatic reaction wherein PKMζ catalyzes the conversion of an uninserted GluA2-containing AMPAR, <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>U</italic>,</sub> to an inserted one, <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub>.</p>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e015">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e015g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e015" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M15">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>15</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(15)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e016">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e016g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e016" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M16">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(16)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e017">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e017g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e017" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M17">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>17</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(17)</label>
</disp-formula>
<p>The protein BRAG2 catalyzes endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPARs, removal from the PSD.</p>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e018">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e018g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e018" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M18">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(18)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e019">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e019g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e019" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M19">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>19</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>Ì</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(19)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e020">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e020g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e020" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M20">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(20)</label>
</disp-formula>
<p>A pair of unregulated processes maintain background cycling of GluA2-containing AMPARs into and out of the PSD:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e021">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e021g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e021" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M21">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(21)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e022">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e022g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e022" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M22">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(22)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023">
<title>Sequestering of PKMζ in the synaptic compartment</title>
<p>Our model implements the notion suggested by Sacktor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>] and supported by empirical results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>], that GluA2-containing AMPARs, when inserted in the PSD, prevent diffusion of PKMζ molecules away from the synapse and/or slows down degradation of PKMζ. We model this as a PKMζ molecule binding to an inserted GluA2-containing AMPAR to form a complex <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub>•<italic>P</italic> (reaction 23) and by bound PKMζ having a much lower rate of dissipation/degradation than free PKMζ (<italic>c</italic><sub><italic>24</italic></sub> &lt;&lt; <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>8</italic></sub>):
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e023">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e023g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e023" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M23">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>23</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(23)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e024">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e024g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e024" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M24">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(24)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>The <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub>•<italic>P</italic> complex is dissolved if the GluA2-containing AMPAR is removed from the membrane by BRAG2 or constitutively:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e025">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e025g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e025" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M25">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(25)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e026">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e026g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e026" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M26">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>26</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(26)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e027">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e027g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e027" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M27">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>27</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(27)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e028">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e028g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e028" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M28">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(28)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>PKMζ remains catalytically active while sequestered by GluA2-containing AMPARs, thus the reactions catalyzed by free PKMζ (reactions 1–3 and 9–11) are also catalyzed by PKMζ when it is bound to <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub>:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e029">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e029g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e029" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M29">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>29</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(29)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e030">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e030g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e030" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M30">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(30)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e031">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e031g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e031" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M31">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>31</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(31)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e032">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e032g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e032" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M32">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>32</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(32)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e033">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e033g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e033" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M33">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(33)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e034">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e034g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e034" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M34">
<mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(34)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec024">
<title>NMDAR stimulation</title>
<p>The mechanism by which NMDAR activation causes an increase in PKMζ is unknown. We model the effect of strong NMDAR stimulation as a rapid increase in the number of active molecules of an unspecified enzyme E1 which, like PKMζ, activates PKMζ mRNA. <italic>E1</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub> and <italic>E1</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub> represent the E1 enzyme in its active and inactive states, respectively:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e035">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e035g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e035" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M35">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>35</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(35)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e036">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e036g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e036" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M36">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>36</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(36)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e037">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e037g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e037" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M37">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>37</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(37)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>The E1 enzyme spontaneously deactivates at a rate that is specified by the reaction constant <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>38</italic></sub>:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e038">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e038g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e038" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M38">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>38</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(38)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec025">
<title>Reactivation</title>
<p>Reactivation of a consolidated memory causes it to become destabilized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref079">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref080">80</xref>]. The molecular mechanism underlying this destabilization is not well understood, but has been showed to depend critically on endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref063">63</xref>]. We model the destabilizing effect of reactivation as an increase in the number of molecules of a second unspecified enzyme, E2, which catalyzes AMPAR endocytosis:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e039">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e039g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e039" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M39">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>39</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(39)</label>
</disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e040">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e040g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e040" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M40">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>40</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(40)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>As in the case of BRAG2-catalyzed endocytosis (reaction 27), the AMPAR/PKMζ complex dissolves when the AMPAR is endocytosed (reaction 40).</p>
<p>The <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub> enzyme spontaneously deactivates at a rate that is specified by the reaction constant <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>41</italic></sub>:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e041">
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e041g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e041" xlink:type="simple"/>
<mml:math display="block" id="M41">
<mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>41</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</alternatives>
<label>(41)</label>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec026">
<title>Protein synthesis inhibition</title>
<p>The effect of PSI infusion is simulated by disabling synthesis of PKMζ (reaction 7).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec027">
<title>Inhibition of PKMζ by ZIP</title>
<p>The effect of ZIP infusion is simulated by disabling all PKMζ enzymatic activity (reactions 1, 9, 15, 29 and 32).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec028">
<title>Inhibition of AMPAR endocytosis by GluA2<sub>3Y</sub></title>
<p>The effect of GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> infusion is simulated by disabling regulated AMPAR endocytosis, whether catalyzed by BRAG2 (reactions 18 and 25) or by the E2 enzyme (reactions 39 and 40).</p>
<p>The simulated reactions are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1006147.t002">Table 2</xref>. Reaction rates are controlled by Gillespie reaction constant, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>1</italic></sub>, <italic>c</italic><sub>2</sub>, etc., such that <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> <italic>dt</italic> is the average probability that a particular combination of the reactant molecules of reaction <italic>i</italic> will react during the next infinitesimal time interval <italic>dt</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref074">74</xref>]. The values for the reaction constants have been selected so that the model’s behavior approximates the observed time courses of the simulated experiments; see cited references in the description of each simulation.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1006147.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Simulated reactions.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">Reaction</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
<th align="left">c<sub>i</sub> (s<sup>-1</sup>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">1</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e042"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e042g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e042" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of P•R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">10.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e043"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e043g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e043" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M43"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of P•R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">3</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e044"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e044g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e044" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M44"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Activation of PKMζ mRNA, catalyzed by PKMζ</td>
<td align="left">100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">4</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e045"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e045g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e045" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M45"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of PP•R<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">4.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">5</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e046"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e046g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e046" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M46"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of PP•R<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">6</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e047"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e047g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e047" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M47"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Deactivation of PKMζ mRNA, catalyzed by phosphatase</td>
<td align="left">100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">7</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e048"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e048g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e048" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M48"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Translation of PKMζ mRNA</td>
<td align="left">0.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">8</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e049"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e049g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e049" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M49"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">PKMζ degradation or dissipation</td>
<td align="left">0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">9</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e050"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e050g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e050" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M50"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of P•B<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">10</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e051"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e051g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e051" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M51"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of P•B<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">11</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e052"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e052g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e052" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M52"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Inhibition of BRAG2, catalyzed by PKMζ</td>
<td align="left">20.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">12</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e053"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e053g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e053" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M53"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of PP•B<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">13</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e054"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e054g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e054" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M54"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of PP•B<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">14</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e055"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e055g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e055" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M55"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>14</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Disinhibition of BRAG2, catalyzed by phosphatase</td>
<td align="left">0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">15</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e056"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e056g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e056" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M56"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>15</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of P•A<sub>U</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">16</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e057"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e057g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e057" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M57"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of P•A<sub>U</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">17</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e058"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e058g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e058" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M58"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>17</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">PKMZ-catalyzed trafficking of GluA2-containing AMPAR into the PSD</td>
<td align="left">20.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">18</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e059"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e059g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e059" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M59"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of B<sub>A</sub>•A<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">10.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">19</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e060"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e060g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e060" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>19</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>Ì</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of B<sub>A</sub>•A<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">20</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e061"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e061g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e061" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M61"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">BRAG2-catalyzed endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR</td>
<td align="left">4.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">21</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e062"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e062g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e062" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M62"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Unregulated trafficking of GluA2-containing AMPAR into the PSD</td>
<td align="left">0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">22</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e063"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e063g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e063" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M63"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Unregulated removal GluA2-containing AMPAR from the PSD</td>
<td align="left">0.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">23</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e064"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e064g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e064" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>23</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Inserted GluA2-containing AMPAR binds PKMζ</td>
<td align="left">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">24</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e065"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e065g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e065" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M65"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Degradation of PKMζ bound to inserted AMPAR</td>
<td align="left">0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">25</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e066"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e066g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e066" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M66"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of B<sub>A</sub>•A<sub>I</sub>•P complex</td>
<td align="left">10.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">26</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e067"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e067g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e067" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M67"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>26</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of BA•AI•P complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">27</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e068"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e068g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e068" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M68"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>27</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">BRAG2-catalyzed endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR with bound PKMζ.</td>
<td align="left">4.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">28</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e069"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e069g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e069" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M69"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Unregulated endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR with bound PKMζ.</td>
<td align="left">0.005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">29</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e070"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e070g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e070" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M70"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>29</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of A<sub>I•</sub>P•R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">10.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">30</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e071"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e071g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e071" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M71"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of A<sub>I•</sub>P•R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">31</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e072"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e072g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e072" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M72"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>31</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Activation of PKMζ mRNA, catalyzed by AMPAR-bound PKMζ</td>
<td align="left">100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">32</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e073"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e073g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e073" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M73"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>32</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of A<sub>I•</sub>P•B<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">1.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">33</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e074"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e074g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e074" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M74"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of A<sub>I•</sub>P•B<sub>A</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">34</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e075"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e075g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e075" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M75"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Inhibition of BRAG2, catalyzed by AMPAR-bound PKMζ</td>
<td align="left">20.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">35</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e076"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e076g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e076" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M76"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>35</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Formation of E1<sub>A</sub>•R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">10.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">36</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e077"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e077g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e077" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M77"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>36</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Dissolution of E1<sub>A</sub>•R<sub>I</sub> complex</td>
<td align="left">400.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">37</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e078"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e078g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e078" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M78"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>37</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Activation of PKMζ mRNA, catalyzed by E1 enzyme</td>
<td align="left">100.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">38</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e079"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e079g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e079" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M79"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>38</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Spontaneous deactivation of E1 enzyme</td>
<td align="left">0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">39</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e080"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e080g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e080" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M80"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>39</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR, catalyzed by E2 enzyme</td>
<td align="left">0.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">40</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e081"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e081g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e081" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M81"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>•</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>40</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">E2-catalyzed endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR with bound PKMζ</td>
<td align="left">0.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">41</td>
<td align="left"><inline-formula id="pcbi.1006147.e082"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1006147.e082g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.e082" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M82"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>41</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left">Spontaneous deactivation of E2 enzyme</td>
<td align="left">0.5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec029">
<title>Simulation environment</title>
<p>The model is implemented as a C++ program and all simulations were executed on an Intel i5-2400 computer running the Debian Linux 8.4 operating system.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec030">
<title>Objectives</title>
<p>Our computational model simulates the regulation of PKMζ concentration at the postsynaptic density and its role in the induction and maintenance of L-LTP. The goal for the model is to simulate the empirical results described in the introduction and summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1006147.t003">Table 3</xref> below. Most of the cited results are from studies of Schaffer collateral synapses on CA1 pyramidal neurons in the rat or mouse hippocampus, a few refer to unspecified hippocampal regions or amygdala of rat or mouse.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1006147.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Simulation objectives.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1006147.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">Result</th>
<th align="left">Description</th>
<th align="left">Citations</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>1</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>Induction by NMDAR stimulation</bold></td>
<td align="left">Strong NMDAR stimulation induces L-LTP</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref040">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref081">81</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>2</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>PSI blocks NMDAR-triggered L-LTP induction</bold></td>
<td align="left">Infusion of protein synthesis inhibitors prevents L-LTP induction by NMDAR stimulation</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref082">82</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>3</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>ZIP during stimulation does not prevent L-LTP induction</bold></td>
<td align="left">ZIP treatment during and immediately after stimulation does not prevent establishment of L-LTP</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref065">65</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>4</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>Induction by PKMζ perfusion</bold></td>
<td align="left">Perfusion of PKMζ into a neuron induces L-LTP</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref039">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref083">83</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>5</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>PSI does not disrupt established L-LTP/LTM</bold></td>
<td align="left">Application of a protein synthesis inhibitor during L-LTP maintenance (without preceding reactivation) does not cause disruption of L-LTP</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref079">79</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>6</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>Reactivation does not disrupt LTM</bold></td>
<td align="left">Memory reactivation does not by itself disrupt LTM</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref079">79</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>7</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>Reactivation followed by PSI infusion does disrupt LTM</bold></td>
<td align="left">PSI administered within a time window after reactivation disrupts LTM</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref079">79</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>8</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>GluA2</bold><sub><bold>3Y</bold></sub> <bold>blocks the LTM-disrupting effect of PSI</bold></td>
<td align="left">GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> administered together with PSI after reactivation blocks the LTM-disrupting effect of PSI</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref063">63</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>9</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>ZIP disrupts established L-LTP</bold></td>
<td align="left">Infusion of ZIP during the maintenance phase disrupts L-LTP</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref039">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref041">41</xref>]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>10</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>GluA2</bold><sub><bold>3Y</bold></sub> <bold>blocks the depotentiating effect of ZIP</bold></td>
<td align="left">GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> infused together with ZIP prevents depotentiation of established L-LTP</td>
<td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref033">33</xref>]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec031" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>In the following plots of simulation results, P denotes the total number of PKMζ molecules in the synaptic compartment, whether free or bound to a substrate or to an AMPAR (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1006147.t001">Table 1</xref>), and <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>I</italic></sub> denotes the number of AMPARs inserted in the PSD, with and without bound PKMζ molecules. Reaction numbers refer to the reactions described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1006147.t002">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<sec id="sec032">
<title>NMDAR stimulation induces L-LTP</title>
<p>We model the result of strong NMDAR stimulation as a rapid increase of the population of active E1 enzyme molecules. This causes the translational repression of PKMζ mRNA to be lifted (reactions 35–37) and synthesis of PKMζ to start (reaction 7). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g002">Fig 2</xref> shows a trace of the number of PKMζ molecules, active PKMζ mRNA molecules and GluA2-containing AMPARs inserted in the PSD during a single simulation run.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>L-LTP induction, single simulation trace.</title>
<p>NMDAR stimulation is simulated by instantaneous activation of 100 E1 molecules at “Stim”. E1 lifts the translational inhibition of PKMζ mRNA, synthesis of PKMζ starts, PKMζ drives up the number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, and the synapse switches to its potentiated steady state. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The model has two stable states: an unpotentiated state in which there are very few active mRNA molecules, PKMζ molecules and inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, and a potentiated state with significantly higher levels of each of these molecules. The brief spike of E1 enzyme lifts the translational repression of enough PKMζ mRNA molecules to trigger a transition to the potentiated state. Although the molecule numbers fluctuate in the potentiated state, it is in fact very stable: No spontaneous depotentiation events are observed even when the model is allowed to run for a full year of simulated time. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g003">Fig 3</xref> shows mean molecule counts for 100 simulations of L-LTP induction. It takes the model between 30 and 60 minutes of simulated time to complete the switch to its upper (potentiated) steady state in which there is a high number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs. This is consistent with the observed duration of the cellular consolidation window [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref058">58</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>L-LTP induction.</title>
<p>The same simulation as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g002">Fig 2</xref>, but here solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. NMDA stimulation triggers a brief spike of E1 activity that activates PKMζ mRNA. This is followed by a slight decline in the number of active mRNA molecules, until the growing amount of PKMζ drives it back up and an equilibrium is reached. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec033">
<title>PSI prevents L-LTP induction</title>
<p>Simulated PSI infusion prevents NMDAR stimulation from inducing L-LTP, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g004">Fig 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>PSI prevents NMDAR stimulation from inducing L-LTP.</title>
<p>E1<sub>A</sub> enzyme activates PKMζ mRNA, but PSI prevents PKMζ synthesis and when the E1 enzyme becomes inactivate, phosphatase returns the mRNA to its inhibited state. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Although the spike of activated E1 enzyme releases the translational block of mRNA, resulting in a high level of activated PKMζ mRNA (R<sub>A</sub> in the model), translation is prevented by the protein synthesis inhibitor, and PKMζ synthesis is not initiated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref037">37</xref>]. When the E1 enzyme returns to its inactive form the mRNA becomes repressed again, and the model remains in its unpotentiated state. Like the potentiated state, the unpotentiated state is very stable: No spontaneous potentiation events are observed even when running the model for a year of simulated time.</p>
<p>By introducing a variable delay between stimulation and PSI infusion, we can study the model’s consolidation window, the time interval after induction during which PSI prevents establishment of L-LTP. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g005">Fig 5</xref>, when the delay before PSI infusion is 20 minutes or less, the model consistently settles in the lower (unpotentiated) steady state with zero or very few inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs. When the delay is 50 minutes or more, the model settles in the upper (potentiated) state where the number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs fluctuates between ca 60 and 100 (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g002">Fig 2</xref>). With intermediate delays, the probability of settling in the upper state gradually increases with increasing delay. The model’s consolidation window is thus in the range 30 to 45 minutes, consistent with empirical results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref012">12</xref>]. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g005">Fig 5</xref> illustrates the model's bistable character: It settles either in the unpotentiated or potentiated state, never in the region with intermediate numbers of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g003">Fig 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g004">Fig 4</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Consolidation window.</title>
<p>Results of simulated NMDAR stimulation followed by PSI infusion after a delay varying from 0 to 60 minutes in 5-minute steps. One hundred simulations were run with each value for the delay. The number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs was recorded twenty hours after stimulation. For each value of the delay, the heights of the columns indicate the number of simulations that terminated with the corresponding numbers of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec034">
<title>ZIP during and immediately after stimulation does not prevent L-LTP induction</title>
<p>ZIP application during stimulation and the first 10 minutes thereafter after does not prevent L-LTP induction, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g006">Fig 6</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>ZIP immediately after stimulation does not prevent L-LTP induction.</title>
<p>In this simulation, ZIP inhibits PKMζ activity during the first 10 minutes after stimulation. L-LTP induction is delayed somewhat compared to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g003">Fig 3</xref>, but enough active PKMζ mRNA remains when the ZIP is removed to trigger a transition to the potentiation state. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Presence of ZIP during the first ten minutes after stimulation does not prevent L-LTP induction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref065">65</xref>]. The stimulation lifts the translational block and PKMζ production gets started. Even though PKMζ’s enzymatic activity is inhibited, the mRNA stays activated long enough to ride out the ZIP activity. When the ZIP is washed out, PKMζ becomes active and drives the synapse into its potentiated state.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec035">
<title>PKMζ infusion induces L-LTP</title>
<p>L-LTP can be induced by diffusion of PKMζ into a neuron [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref039">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref041">41</xref>]. We simulate infusion by rapidly increasing the number of PKMζ molecules in the synaptic compartment to 100. This causes the model to settle into its potentiated state, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g007">Fig 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g007" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g007</object-id>
<label>Fig 7</label>
<caption>
<title>PKMζ infusion induces L-LTP.</title>
<p>Infusion is simulated by stepping the PKMζ molecule count to 100 at “Inf”. The PKMζ lifts the translational inhibition of PKMζ mRNA, synthesis starts and the synapse switches to its potentiated state. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec036">
<title>PSI blocks PKMζ-infusion-induced potentiation</title>
<p>The same level of PKMζ infusion that induces L-LTP in the previous experiment (100 molecules) fails to do so in the presence of PSI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g008">Fig 8</xref>). Although the PKMζ infusion initially causes a temporary increase in the number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, the PSI prevents replenishment to compensate for PKMζ degradation and dissipation and the model returns to its unpotentiated state. This result, though plausible, has not been demonstrated in a published experiment. It thus constitutes a prediction of the model.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g008" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g008</object-id>
<label>Fig 8</label>
<caption>
<title>PSI blocks L-LTP induction by PKMζ infusion.</title>
<p>As in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g007">Fig 7</xref>, infusion of PKMζ is simulated at “Inf”. PKMζ triggers activation of PKMζ mRNA as well as an increase of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, but in the absence of PKMζ synthesis (blocked by PSI), the PKMζ level declines and the synapse settles back into its unpotentiated state. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g008" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec037">
<title>PSI does not disrupt established L-LTP</title>
<p>Fonseca et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref012">12</xref>] demonstrated that suppressing protein synthesis for 100 minutes by bath application of anisomycin did not disrupt established L-LTP. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g009">Fig 9</xref> shows the results of simulating this experiment in our model. The interruption of protein synthesis causes the number of PKMζ molecules to drop, which in turn leads to a transient decline in the number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, but the system recovers when the PSI is removed.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g009" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g009</object-id>
<label>Fig 9</label>
<caption>
<title>PSI infusion during the maintenance phase does not disrupt established L-LTP.</title>
<p>L-LTP is induced by NMDAR stimulation at “Stim”. Once L-LTP is established (100 minutes after induction), protein synthesis inhibition is applied for 100 minutes. The interruption of kinase synthesis causes a decline in the levels of PKMζ and inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, but the synapse recovers when the PSI is removed. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. RA: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g009" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>If the model is correct, then the transient decrease in the number of GluA2-containing AMPARs may be detectable as a reduced EPSP current after PSI application. However, it is possible that the temporary removal of GluA2-containing AMPARs is compensated for by insertion of GluA2-lacking AMPARs, similarly to what has been shown to happen during retrieval-induced destabilization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref045">45</xref>], in which case the synaptic strength would be maintained. If this is the case, then it may instead be possible to detect a transient increase in rectification index, because GluA2-lacking AMPARs, but not GluA2-contaning ones, are characterized by a slight inward rectification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref045">45</xref>]. Our model thus predicts that one or the other of these two effects (EPSP reduction or rectification) should be detectable after PSI application during L-LTP maintenance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec038">
<title>Reactivation destabilizes, but does not disrupt, L-LTP</title>
<p>The effect of memory reactivation is simulated as a brief spike in the amount of active E2 enzyme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g010">Fig 10</xref>). This results in rapid endocytosis of the inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref021">21</xref>] and release of the bound PKMζ molecules which then start to dissipate. However, due to continued synthesis, the PKMζ level is kept from dropping below threshold and the model settles back into the potentiated steady state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref079">79</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g010" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g010</object-id>
<label>Fig 10</label>
<caption>
<title>Reactivation.</title>
<p>NMDAR stimulation is simulated by a pulse of active E1 enzyme at “Stim”, and reactivation by a pulse of active E2 enzyme at “React”. E2<sub>A</sub> causes rapid endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPARs, which in turn leads to PKMζ depletion. PKMζ mRNA only declines slowly, however, and the synapse returns to its potentiated state when the E2 enzyme deactivates. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme, E2<sub>A</sub>: activated E2 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g010" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Although the population of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs is almost completely depleted after reactivation, the levels of PKMζ and active PKMζ mRNA stay well above their depotentiation thresholds and the model reliably recovers from post-reactivation instability (reconsolidation), unless challenged by simulated pharmacological interventions (see below). As mentioned earlier, Hong et al. demonstrated this abrupt decrease of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs after memory retrieval, as well as a corresponding transient increase of GluA2-lacking AMPARs, which maintained the synaptic strength during the labile period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref020">20</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec039">
<title>Reactivation followed by PSI disrupts L-LTP</title>
<p>Simulation of PSI infusion simultaneously with reactivation, or shortly thereafter, causes disruption of L-LTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g011">Fig 11</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g011" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g011</object-id>
<label>Fig 11</label>
<caption>
<title>Reactivation with simultaneous PSI infusion.</title>
<p>As in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g010">Fig 10</xref>, reactivation is simulated as a pulse of active E2 enzyme at “React”, but here the presence of PSI prevents recovery and L-LTP is disrupted. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme, E2<sub>A</sub>: activated E2 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g011" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>In the absence of new protein synthesis, the PKMζ level drops below threshold and the model settles into its unpotentiated state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref079">79</xref>]. By varying the delay between reactivation and PSI infusion, we can establish the model’s reconsolidation window, the time interval after reactivation during which L-LTP is vulnerable to PSI. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g012">Fig 12</xref>, if PSI infusion is applied 15 minutes or less after reactivation, then the model reliably switches to its lower (unpotentiated) steady state with few inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, but with a delay of 30 minutes or more, L-LTP disruption does not result: the model remains in its potentiated state where the number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs fluctuates in the 60–100 range. The model’s reconsolidation window is thus in the range 20 to 30 minutes, consistent with empirical results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref084">84</xref>].</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g012" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g012</object-id>
<label>Fig 12</label>
<caption>
<title>Reconsolidation window.</title>
<p>Results of simulated reactivation followed by PSI infusion. The delay between reactivation and PSI infusion is varied from 0 to 60 minutes in 5-minute steps. One hundred simulations were run with each value for the delay. The number of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs was recorded twenty hours after stimulation. For each value of the delay, the heights of the columns indicate the number of simulations that terminated with the corresponding numbers of inserted AMPARs.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g012" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec040">
<title>GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> blocks post-reactivation PSI-infusion from causing depotentiation</title>
<p>When the GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> peptide is infused together with PSI after reactivation, it prevents the disruption of L-LTP that PSI otherwise causes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref063">63</xref>].</p>
<p>As before, reactivation triggers activation of the E2 enzyme, but here the GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> peptide blocks its endocytotic effect. As a result, the GluA2-containing AMPARs remain inserted and although the PSI stops synthesis of new PKMζ, the existing population of PKMζ molecules, bound to the inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, declines at a slow enough rate to maintain the synapse in its potentiated state while the PSI wears off (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g013">Fig 13</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g013" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g013</object-id>
<label>Fig 13</label>
<caption>
<title>Infusion of PSI and GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> immediately after reactivation.</title>
<p>In this simulation the endocytotic effect of the reactivation-triggered pulse of active E2 enzyme is blocked by GLUA2<sub>3Y</sub>. As a result, the GluA2-containing AMPARs remain inserted and continue to sequester PKMζ molecules. The post-reactivation application of PSI still causes a decline in the level of PKMζ, but because of the low dissipation/degradation rate, the PKMζ level remains high enough that the L-LTP survives until the PSI wears off. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme, E2<sub>A</sub>: activated E2 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g013" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec041">
<title>ZIP infusion disrupts established L-LTP</title>
<p>Infusion of ZIP during L-LTP maintenance causes rapid depotentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref039">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref041">41</xref>]. ZIP inhibits PKMζ enzymatic activity, including both the catalysis of its own synthesis and the maintenance of an increased level of inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs in the PSD. The result is rapid removal of GluA2-containing AMPARs and depletion of PKMζ, and the synapse quickly settles into its unpotentiated state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g014">Fig 14</xref>). The minimum duration of ZIP application needed to reliably disrupt L-LTP in the model is around 30 minutes.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g014" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g014</object-id>
<label>Fig 14</label>
<caption>
<title>ZIP infusion during L-LTP maintenance.</title>
<p>Application of ZIP inhibits PKMζ’s enzymatic activity, leading to rapid depotentiation. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g014" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec042">
<title>GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> blocks depotentiation by ZIP infusion</title>
<p>When the GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> peptide is infused together with ZIP during L-LTP maintenance, the disruptive effect of ZIP is blocked [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref033">33</xref>].</p>
<p>As before, ZIP inhibits PKMζ’s catalysis of its own synthesis as well as its facilitation of AMPAR trafficking into the PSD and its blocking effect on BRAG2-induced endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR. But in this case, even though BRAG2 remains active, the presence of GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> prevents it from inducing endocytosis of the inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs. As a result, the GluA2-containing AMPARs remain in the PSD and continue to maintain the PKMζ molecules at the synapse. The number of PKMζ molecules declines only slowly and the potentiation is able to survive through the 12-hour period of ZIP activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g015">Fig 15</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g015" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g015</object-id>
<label>Fig 15</label>
<caption>
<title>Infusion of ZIP and GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> during L-LTP maintenance.</title>
<p>ZIP blocks PKMζ’s enzymatic activity: PKMζ mRNA returns to its untranslatable state, and BRAG2 becomes active. However, GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> prevents BRAG2 from inducing GluA2-containing AMPAR endocytosis, the PKMζ molecules remain attached to the inserted AMPARs, and the catastrophic disruption of L-LTP seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g014">Fig 14</xref> is averted. Solid lines represent mean molecule counts for 100 simulations. Lightly colored bands indicate standard deviation. R<sub>A</sub>: active PKMζ mRNA, P: PKMζ, A<sub>I</sub>: inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, E1<sub>A</sub>: activated E1 enzyme.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g015" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec043" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The model presented here is able to explain a range of results relating to the role of PKMζ in late-phase long-term synaptic potentiation, including L-LTP induction by NMDAR stimulation or by PKMζ infusion and the findings that whereas PSI, but not ZIP, can block induction of L-LTP, the reverse is true for disruption of established L-LTP. In addition, it accounts for cellular reconsolidation, reconsolidation blockade by PSI infusion and prevention of ZIP- or PSI-induced depotentiation by infusion of the GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> peptide. While subsets of these results have been covered by earlier models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref085">85</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref089">89</xref>], ours is the first to account for all of them. A further distinguishing feature of our model is that it demonstrates that a wide range of empirical findings described in the LTP literature can be accounted for by simple molecular reactions whose rates are governed only by the law of mass action, i.e. without postulating cooperative binding or other non-linear dependencies on reactant concentrations.</p>
<p>Our model demonstrates that a bistable mechanism for synaptic potentiation can arise from the interaction of two coupled feedback loops, neither of which needs itself be bistable. One of these, the mutual reinforcement between PKMζ and PKMζ mRNA, has been featured in previously published models of L-LTP maintenance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref085">85</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref088">88</xref>]. The second positive feedback relationship in our model is between PKMζ and inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs, which mutually maintain each other by inhibiting each other’s removal from the synapse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref042">42</xref>]. The ability of inserted AMPARs to sequester PKMζ molecules at the synapse allows the model to account for findings involving the inhibition of regulated endocytosis of GluA2-containing AMPAR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref057">57</xref>].</p>
<p>Our model exhibits robust bistability; when left to run for a full year of simulated time in either the potentiated or depotentiated state, no spontaneous transitions between the steady-states were observed. The source of this bistability can be understood by considering the interaction between the two feedback loops. The PKMζ-mRNA interaction is a positive feedback loop: A greater number of PKMζ molecules will keep more mRNA molecules in an unrepressed state and more unrepressed mRNA results in a higher rate of PKMζ synthesis. This subsystem has two steady states: a lower steady state with zero PKMζ molecules and zero unrepressed mRNA molecules, and a higher state at a level that depends on the reaction rates, in particular PKMζ’s dissipation rate, because at equilibrium the synthesis and dissipation rates are equal. The lower steady state is unstable; the introduction of just a few PKMζ molecules can cause a switch to the upper state. The PKMζ–mRNA feedback loop thus has only a single stable steady state which depends on the PKMζ dissipation rate, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g016">Fig 16</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1006147.g016" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g016</object-id>
<label>Fig 16</label>
<caption>
<title>PKMζ level at steady state as a function of dissipation rate.</title>
<p>The solid line represents a stable steady state, and the dashed line an unstable steady state. The x-axis represents the reaction constant for PKMζ dissipation/degradation. “C<sub>8</sub>” indicates the value used for the reaction constant of reaction 8, dissipation/degradation of unbound PKMζ. “E” indicates the effective dissipation rate in the potentiated state, when a large proportion of the PKMζ molecules are bound to inserted GluA2-containing AMPARs.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.g016" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Bistability arises because of the influence of the second feedback loop, the interaction between PKMζ and GluA2-containing AMPARs. In the unpotentiated state, the PKMζ dissipation/degradation rate is controlled by the reaction constant c<sub>8</sub>, which has a value of 0.5. As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g016">Fig 16</xref>, the steady state at this rate has zero PKMζ molecules. In the potentiated state, an increased number of GluA2-containing AMPARs in the PSD bind PKMζ molecules; this results in a reduction of the effective PKMζ dissipation/degradation rate to a value where the steady state has ca 100 PKMζ molecules (indicated by ‘E’ in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006147.g016">Fig 16</xref>).</p>
<sec id="sec044">
<title>Comparison with previous computational models of PKMζ regulation</title>
<p>Clopath et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref089">89</xref>] describe a mathematical model of synaptic tagging and capture (STC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref090">90</xref>], wherein mechanisms of tag-setting and triggering of protein synthesis interact with a bistable process that maintains potentiation. Although the authors suggest that one of the model’s parameters may represent the level of PKMζ activity, the mechanisms of the process are unspecified, and the model therefore cannot account for the results targeted by our model: the effects of PSI, ZIP and GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> in the contexts of L-LTP induction and maintenance, or of memory reactivation.</p>
<p>A simple model by Ogasawara and Kawato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref086">86</xref>] simulates L-LTP induction and maintenance as well as reconsolidation based on the interactions of only three molecules: PKMζ, PKMζ mRNA and F-Actin. It is, however, not able to account for most of the results addressed in this paper.</p>
<p>A paper by Zhang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref088">88</xref>] features a dual-loop model of LTP that exhibits windows of susceptibility to PSI after induction and reactivation as well as vulnerability to a kinase inhibitor in the maintenance phase. The relationship between the kinase and AMPA receptors is not modeled, and thus the ability of an endocytosis blocker like GluA2<sub>3Y</sub> to rescue L-LTP is not accounted for. Also, the kinase modeled in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref088">88</xref>] is unnamed but characterized by auto-activation rather than persistent activity, and should therefore probably not be interpreted as PKMζ.</p>
<p>Smolen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref087">87</xref>] model synaptic tagging and capture, including “cross-tagging” between LTP and LTD. As in our model, synaptic stability is based on PKMζ’s ability to catalyze its own synthesis. Unlike our model, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref087">87</xref>] does not account for the effects of protein synthesis inhibition, kinase inhibition, reactivation or the ability of endocytosis blocking to rescue L-LTP.</p>
<p>A paper by Jalil et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref085">85</xref>] models PKMζ regulation at the synapse, with a focus on compensatory interactions between PKMζ and a second atypical PKC isoform, PKC<sub>ι/λ</sub>. Bistability is achieved by combining the PKMζ auto-catalytic synthesis feedback loop with auto-phosphorylation. The model predicts the differential effects of ZIP and PSI at L-LTP induction and maintenance, but does not account for L-LTP rescue by AMPAR endocytosis blocking, nor for reconsolidation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec045">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Our model represents a subset of the mechanisms believed to be involved in LTP induction and maintenance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref003">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref091">91</xref>]. Some processes not included in our model are:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>the induction and stabilization of early LTP, which likely involves GluA2-lacking AMPARs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref045">45</xref>], the MAPK/ERK signaling pathway and the proteins PKA, CaMKII [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref091">91</xref>] and PKCλ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref065">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref092">92</xref>]</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>a later phase of L-LTP, sometimes called LTP3, which requires gene transcription as well as mRNA translation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref093">93</xref>] and may involve a “tagging and capture” mechanism for selectively targeting gene products to potentiated synapses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref040">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref090">90</xref>].</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>polymerization/depolymerization of actin and restructuring of the cytoskeleton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref094">94</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1006147.ref095">95</xref>]</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The processes that we have modeled thus form a subset of a more complex machinery. Nevertheless, it is interesting to note that this relatively simple model is able to account for many of the empirical findings regarding the role of PKMζ in L-LTP induction and maintenance, and to exhibit the degree of stability required for a neural mechanism to support long-lasting memories.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec046">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1006147.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006147.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Text</label>
<caption>
<title>Estimating the number of PKMζ molecules in a spine head.</title>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Marcel Montrey for helpful comments and suggestions.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cajal</surname> <given-names>SRY</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Croonian Lecture: La Fine Structure des Centres Nerveux</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc Lond</source>. <year>1894</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rspl.1894.0063" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspl.1894.0063</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frankland</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bontempi</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>The organization of recent and remote memories</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn1607" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrn1607</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15685217</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudai</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayford</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Molecular and Systems Biology of Memory</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>157</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>186</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2014.03.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2014.03.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24679534</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sossin</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Molecular memory traces</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Sossin</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lacaille</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castellucci</surname> <given-names>VF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belleville</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Essence of Memory</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier Science Bv</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bliss</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collingridge</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Synaptic Model of Memory—Long-Term Potentiation in the Hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>361</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/361031a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/361031a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8421494</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bliss</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lomo</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Long-Lasting Potentiation of Synaptic Transmission in Dentate Area of Anesthetized Rabbit Following Stimulation of Perforant Path</article-title>. <source>J Physiol-London</source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>232</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">4727084</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malenka</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bear</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>. <article-title>LTP and LTD: An embarrassment of riches</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2004.09.012" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2004.09.012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15450156</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name>. <article-title>How Long Will Long-Term Potentiation Last?</article-title> <source>Philosophical Transactions: Biological Sciences</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>358</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krug</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reymann</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matthies</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Anisomycin, an inhibitor of protein synthesis, blocks late phases of LTP phenomena in the hippocampal CA1 region in vitro</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>452</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3401749</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Cellular mechanisms of learning and the biological basis of individuality</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jessel</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Principles of neural science</source>. <edition>4th ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>. pp. <fpage>1247</fpage>–<lpage>1279</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourtchouladze</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abel</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berman</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lapidus</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <article-title>Different training procedures recruit either one or two critical periods for contextual memory consolidation, each of which requires protein synthesis and PKA</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10454361</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fonseca</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nägerl</surname> <given-names>UV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Neuronal activity determines the protein synthesis dependence of long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>478</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn1667" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn1667</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16531998</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of Camp Simulate a Late-Stage of Ltp in Hippocampal Ca1 Neurons</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>260</volume>: <fpage>1661</fpage>–<lpage>1664</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.8389057" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.8389057</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8389057</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Camp Contributes to Messy Fiber Ltp by Initiating Both a Covalently Mediated Early Phase and Macromolecular Synthesis-Dependent Late-Phase</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>79</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(94)90401-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90401-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7923379</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname> <given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <article-title>A macromolecular synthesis-dependent late phase of long-term potentiation requiring cAMP in the medial perforant pathway of rat hippocampal slices</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3189</fpage>–<lpage>3198</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8627357</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Squire</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protein-Synthesis and Memory—a Review</article-title>. <source>Psychol Bull</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>518</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.96.3.518" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0033-2909.96.3.518</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6096908</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Misanin</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Retrograde Amnesia Produced by Electroconvulsive Shock after Reactivation of a Consolidated Memory Trace</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1968</year>;<volume>160</volume>: <fpage>554</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.160.3827.554" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.160.3827.554</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">5689415</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schafe</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Doux</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fear memories require protein synthesis in the amygdala for reconsolidation after retrieval</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>406</volume>: <fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>726</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/35021052" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/35021052</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10963596</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Przybyslawski</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sara</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reconsolidation of memory after its reactivation</article-title>. <source>Behav Brain Res</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0166-4328(96)00153-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0166-4328(96)00153-2</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9079788</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname> <given-names>H-G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>AMPA receptor exchange underlies transient memory destabilization on retrieval</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>8218</fpage>–<lpage>8223</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1305235110" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1305235110</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23630279</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao-Ruiz</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rotaru</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Loo</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mansvelder</surname> <given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stiedl</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smit</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Retrieval-specific endocytosis of GluA2-AMPARs underlies adaptive reconsolidation of contextual fear</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1302</fpage>–<lpage>U117</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.2907" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn.2907</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909089</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bucherelli</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain sites involved in fear memory reconsolidation and extinction of rodents</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.04.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.04.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887284</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Besnard</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caboche</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laroche</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reconsolidation of memory: a decade of debate</article-title>. <source>Prog Neurobiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pneurobio.2012.07.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2012.07.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22877586</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Einarsson</surname> <given-names>EO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Memory reconsolidation: an update</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1191</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05443.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05443.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20392274</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Helfer P, Shultz TR. A Computational Model of Systems Memory Reconsolidation and Extinction. Manuscript submitted for publication;</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Structure and function of glutamate receptor ion channels</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Physiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.physiol.66.050802.084104" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.physiol.66.050802.084104</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977400</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meldrum</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Glutamate as a neurotransmitter in the brain: review of physiology and pathology</article-title>. <source>The Journal of nutrition</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>130</volume>: <fpage>1007S</fpage>–<lpage>1015S</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/130.4.1007S" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/jn/130.4.1007S</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10736372</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maren</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tocco</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Standley</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baudry</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Postsynaptic Factors in the Expression of Long-Term Potentiation (ltp)—Increased Glutamate-Receptor Binding Following Ltp Induction in-Vivo</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>90</volume>: <fpage>9654</fpage>–<lpage>9658</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.90.20.9654" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.90.20.9654</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8415757</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Mamou</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gamache</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>NMDA receptors are critical for unleashing consolidated auditory fear memories</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1237</fpage>–<lpage>1239</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn1778" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn1778</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16998481</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of amygdala glutamate receptors in fear learning, fear-potentiated startle, and extinction</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0091-3057(01)00698-0" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0091-3057(01)00698-0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11830172</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>. <article-title>AMPA receptor trafficking and the mechanisms underlying synaptic plasticity and cognitive aging</article-title>. <source>Dialogues Clin Neurosci</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23576886</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaac</surname> <given-names>JTR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashby</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McBain</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Role of the GluR2 Subunit in AMPA Receptor Function and Synaptic Plasticity</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>859</fpage>–<lpage>871</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2007.06.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2007.06.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17582328</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Migues</surname> <given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardt</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gamache</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>PKMzeta maintains memories by regulating GluR2-dependent AMPA receptor trafficking</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>634</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn.2531" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn.2531</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383136</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sajikumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergold</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>PKM zeta maintains late long-term potentiation by N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor/GluR2-dependent trafficking of postsynaptic AMPA receptors</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>7820</fpage>–<lpage>7827</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0223-08.2008" xlink:type="simple">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0223-08.2008</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18667614</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huganir</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoll</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <article-title>AMPARs and Synaptic Plasticity: The Last 25</article-title> <source>Years. Neuron</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>704</fpage>–<lpage>717</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2013.10.025" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2013.10.025</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24183021</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malinow</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malenka</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>. <article-title>AMPA receptor trafficking and synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.neuro.25.112701.142758" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.neuro.25.112701.142758</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052905</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osten</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valsamis</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protein synthesis-dependent formation of protein kinase M zeta in long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2444</fpage>–<lpage>2451</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8786421</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osten</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valsamis</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naik</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sublette</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Persistent activation of the Zeta isoform of protein kinase C in the maintenance of long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>90</volume>: <fpage>8342</fpage>–<lpage>8346</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.90.18.8342" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.90.18.8342</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8378304</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname> <given-names>DSF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benardo</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blace</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crary</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Protein kinase M zeta is necessary and sufficient for LTP maintenance</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn829" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn829</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11914719</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sajikumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Navakkode</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>JU</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synaptic tagging and cross-tagging: The role of protein kinase M xi in maintaining long-term potentiation but not long-term depression</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>5750</fpage>–<lpage>5756</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1104-05.2005" xlink:type="simple">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1104-05.2005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958741</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>YD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Persistent phosphorylation by protein kinase M zeta maintains late-phase long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1979</fpage>–<lpage>1984</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5132-04.2005" xlink:type="simple">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5132-04.2005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728837</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>How does PKMζ maintain long-term memory?</article-title> <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn2949" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrn2949</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21119699</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glebov</surname> <given-names>OO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Routes, destinations and delays: recent advances in AMPA receptor trafficking</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tins.2011.02.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.tins.2011.02.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21420743</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardt</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y-T</given-names></name>. <article-title>GluA2-dependent AMPA receptor endocytosis and the decay of early and late long-term potentiation: possible mechanisms for forgetting of short- and long-term memories</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc B-Biol Sci</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>369</volume>: <fpage>20130141</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2013.0141" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstb.2013.0141</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24298143</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clem</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huganir</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Calcium-Permeable AMPA Receptor Dynamics Mediate Fear Memory Erasure</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>330</volume>: <fpage>1108</fpage>–<lpage>1112</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1195298" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1195298</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21030604</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessels</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malinow</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synaptic AMPA Receptor Plasticity and Behavior</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2009.01.015" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuron.2009.01.015</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19217372</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plant</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pelkey</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolotto</surname> <given-names>ZA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terashima</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McBain</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Transient incorporation of native GluR2-lacking AMPA receptors during hippocampal long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>602</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn1678" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn1678</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16582904</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oxberry</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crary</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirra</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellular and subcellular localization of PKMζ</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>369</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2013.0140" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstb.2013.0140</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24298142</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>PINing for Things Past</article-title>. <source>Sci Signal</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>pe9</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/scisignal.3112pe9" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/scisignal.3112pe9</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20215644</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Westmark</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westmark</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levenson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Riordan</surname> <given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Pin1 and PKM zeta Sequentially Control Dendritic Protein Synthesis</article-title>. <source>Sci Signal</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>ra18</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/scisignal.2000451" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/scisignal.2000451</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20215645</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palida</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butko</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ngo</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackey</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellisman</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>PKMzeta, But Not PKClambda, Is Rapidly Synthesized and Degraded at the Neuronal Synapse</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>7736</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0004-15.2015" xlink:type="simple">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0004-15.2015</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995463</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westbrook</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The cytology of neurons</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Kandel</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jessel</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Principles of neural science</source>. <edition>4th ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>. pp. <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiebler</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mechanisms of dendritic mRNA transport and its role in synaptic tagging</article-title>. <source>Embo J</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>3540</fpage>–<lpage>3552</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/emboj.2011.278" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/emboj.2011.278</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878995</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muslimov</surname> <given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nimmrich</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tcherepanov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiedge</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dendritic transport and localization of protein kinase M zeta mRNA—Implications for molecular memory consolidation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>279</volume>: <fpage>52613</fpage>–<lpage>52622</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M409240200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M409240200</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15371429</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bramham</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dendritic mRNA: transport, translation and function</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>–<lpage>789</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn2150" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrn2150</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17848965</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crary</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Regulation of Protein Kinase M Synthesis by Multiple Kinases in Long-Term Potentiation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neuroscience</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>3439</fpage>–<lpage>3444</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5612-06.2007" xlink:type="simple">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5612-06.2007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392460</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>Y-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>C-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gean</surname> <given-names>P-W</given-names></name>. <article-title>AMPA receptor endocytosis in the amygdala is involved in the disrupted reconsolidation of Methamphetamine-associated contextual memory</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Learn Mem</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nlm.2013.04.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.nlm.2013.04.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23603364</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudai</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>The neurobiology of consolidations, or, how stable is the engram?</article-title> <source>Annu Rev Psychol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.psych.55.090902.142050" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.psych.55.090902.142050</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744210</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastalkova</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinkhasova</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fenton</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Storage of spatial information by the maintenance mechanism of LTP</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>313</volume>: <fpage>1141</fpage>–<lpage>1144</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1128657" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1128657</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16931766</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quartermain</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Characteristics of Retrograde-Amnesia Following Reactivation of Memory</article-title>. <source>Physiol Behav</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9384(82)90034-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0031-9384(82)90034-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7079373</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schafe</surname> <given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LeDoux</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Memory consolidation of auditory pavlovian fear conditioning requires protein synthesis and protein kinase A in the amygdala</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>RC96</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10974093</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sara</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Retrieval and reconsolidation: Toward a neurobiology of remembering</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/lm.7.2.73" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/lm.7.2.73</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10753974</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>Y-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>C-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>C-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gean</surname> <given-names>P-W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Involvement of protein phosphatases in the destabilization of methamphetamine-associated contextual memory</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>486</fpage>–<lpage>493</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/lm.039941.115" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/lm.039941.115</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27531839</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shema</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudai</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Rapid erasure of long-term memory associations in the cortex by an inhibitor of PKM zeta</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>317</volume>: <fpage>951</fpage>–<lpage>953</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1144334" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1144334</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17702943</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>S-Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname> <given-names>J-Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X-Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bu</surname> <given-names>Y-F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname> <given-names>W-W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>PKCλ is critical in AMPA receptor phosphorylation and synaptic incorporation during LTP</article-title>. <source>The EMBO Journal</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1365</fpage>–<lpage>1380</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/emboj.2013.60" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/emboj.2013.60</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23511975</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadian</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wyszynski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunah</surname> <given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation of GluR2 is required for insulin-stimulated AMPA receptor endocytosis and LTD</article-title>. <source>Embo J</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1040</fpage>–<lpage>1050</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.emboj.7600126" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600126</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976558</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brebner</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campsall</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Nucleus accumbens long-term depression and the expression of behavioral sensitization</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>310</volume>: <fpage>1340</fpage>–<lpage>1343</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1116894" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1116894</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311338</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brebner</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>TP</given-names></name>. <source>Interference Peptides: A Novel Therapeutic Approach Targeting Synaptic Plasticity in Drug Addiction. Molecular Mechanisms of Synaptogenesis</source>. <publisher-loc>Springer</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Boston, MA</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>. pp. <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>484</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-32562-0_33" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/978-0-387-32562-0_33</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname> <given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arkin</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stochastic chemical kinetics and the quasi-steady-state assumption: Application to the Gillespie algorithm</article-title>. <source>J Chem Phys</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>118</volume>: <fpage>4999</fpage>–<lpage>5010</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.1545446" xlink:type="simple">10.1063/1.1545446</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samuels</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Discrete Stochastic Simulation Methods for Chemically Reacting Systems</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Methods in Enzymology: Computer Methods</source>, Vol <volume>454</volume>, Pt A. <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier Academic Press Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>. pp. <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzaki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis-Davies</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nemoto</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miyashita</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iino</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasai</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dendritic spine geometry is critical for AMPA receptor expression in hippocampal CA1 pyramidal neurons</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1086</fpage>–<lpage>1092</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nn736" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nn736</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11687814</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takumi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rinvik</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ottersen</surname> <given-names>OP</given-names></name>. <article-title>The arrangement of glutamate receptors in excitatory synapses</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>868</volume>: <fpage>474</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10414324</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonze</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abou-Jaoude</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouattara</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halloy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>How molecular should your molecular model be? On the level of molecular detail required to simulate biological networks in systems and synthetic biology</article-title>. <source>Methods in enzymology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>487</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-381270-4.00007-X" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/B978-0-12-381270-4.00007-X</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21187226</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname> <given-names>DT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exact stochastic simulation of coupled chemical reactions</article-title>. <source>The journal of physical chemistry</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>2340</fpage>–<lpage>2361</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Memory maintenance by PKMζ—an evolutionary perspective</article-title>. <source>Molecular Brain</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1756-6606-5-31" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1756-6606-5-31</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22986281</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Migues</surname> <given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Archbold</surname> <given-names>GEB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Einarsson</surname> <given-names>EO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonasia</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Blocking Synaptic Removal of GluA2-Containing AMPA Receptors Prevents the Natural Forgetting of Long-Term Memories</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>3481</fpage>–<lpage>3494</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3333-15.2016" xlink:type="simple">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3333-15.2016</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013677</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanisch</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wotjak</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Time course and efficiency of protein synthesis inhibition following intracerebral and systemic anisomycin treatment</article-title>. <source>Neurobiology of Learning and Memory</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>90</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>494</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nlm.2008.02.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.nlm.2008.02.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18395476</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwapis</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarome</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmartin</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helmstetter</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intra-amygdala infusion of the protein kinase Mzeta inhibitor ZIP disrupts foreground context fear memory</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Learn Mem</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nlm.2012.05.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.nlm.2012.05.003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22659643</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Debiec</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>LeDoux</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cellular and systems reconsolidation in the hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12408854</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Memory traces unbound</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0166-2236(02)00042-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0166-2236(02)00042-5</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12536129</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganong</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cotman</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Long-Term Potentiation in the Hippocampus Involves Activation of N-Methyl-D-Aspartate Receptors</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>323</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0006-8993(84)90275-0" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0006-8993(84)90275-0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6151863</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krug</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lossner</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Anisomycin Blocks the Late Phase of Long-Term Potentiation in the Dentate Gyrus of Freely Moving Rats</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Bull</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0361-9230(84)90005-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0361-9230(84)90005-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6089972</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname> <given-names>DSF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benardo</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protein kinase M zeta enhances excitatory synaptic transmission by increasing the number of active postsynaptic AMPA receptors</article-title>. <source>Hippocampus</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/hipo.20171" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/hipo.20171</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16463388</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname> <given-names>Y-X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>Y-X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>H-S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname> <given-names>L-F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A memory retrieval-extinction procedure to prevent drug craving and relapse</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>336</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1215070" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1215070</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22499948</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalil</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shouval</surname> <given-names>HZ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Atypical PKCs in memory maintenance: The roles of feedback and redundancy</article-title>. <source>Learning &amp; memory (Cold Spring Harbor, NY)</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/lm.038844.115" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/lm.038844.115</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26077687</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogasawara</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawato</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The protein kinase M zeta network as a bistable switch to store neuronal memory</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1752-0509-4-181" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1752-0509-4-181</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194445</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baxter</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular Constraints on Synaptic Tagging and Maintenance of Long-Term Potentiation: A Predictive Model</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002620</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002620" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002620</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22876169</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smolen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baxter</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <article-title>The sensitivity of memory consolidation and reconsolidation to inhibitors of protein synthesis and kinases: Computational analysis</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/lm.1844010" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/lm.1844010</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20736337</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clopath</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegler</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilaki</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buesing</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerstner</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tag-Trigger-Consolidation: A Model of Early and Late Long-Term-Potentiation and Depression</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000248</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000248" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000248</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19112486</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>RGM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Synaptic tagging and long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>385</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>536</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/385533a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/385533a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9020359</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweatt</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Toward a molecular explanation for long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1101/lm.6.5.399" xlink:type="simple">10.1101/lm.6.5.399</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10541462</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref092"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsokas</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lesburgueres</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname> <given-names>EJC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tcherepanov</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Compensation for PKMzeta in long-term potentiation and spatial long-term memory in mutant mice</article-title>. <source>eLife</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.14846" xlink:type="simple">10.7554/eLife.14846</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27187150</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref093"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raymond</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <article-title>LTP forms 1, 2 and 3: different mechanisms for the “long” in long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tins.2007.01.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.tins.2007.01.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17292975</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref094"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sondhi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sacktor</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Actin polymerization regulates the synthesis of PKM xi in LTP</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuropharm.2006.07.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2006.07.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914172</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1006147.ref095"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudy</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variation in the persistence of memory: An interplay between actin dynamics and AMPA receptors</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>1621</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brainres.2014.12.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.brainres.2014.12.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25511990</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>