<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-12-01957</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Sensory systems</subject><subject>Single neuron function</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Characteristic Effects of Stochastic Oscillatory Forcing on Neural Firing: Analytical Theory and Comparison to Paddlefish Electroreceptor Data</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Effect of Stochastic Oscillations on Neural Firing</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauermeister</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¤</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwalger</surname><given-names>Tilo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>David F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neiman</surname><given-names>Alexander B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Max-Planck-Institute for the Physics of Complex Systems, Dresden, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience and Physics Department of Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences and Neuroscience Program, Ohio University, Athens, Ohio, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Physics and Astronomy and Neuroscience Program, Ohio University, Athens, Ohio, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Latham</surname><given-names>Peter E.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University College London, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">benjamin.lindner@physik.hu-berlin.de</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Wrote the paper: CB TS DFR ABN BL. Conceived and designed research idea: TS ABN BL. Carried out analytical calculations and numerical simulations: CB TS BL. Conducted the statistical analysis of numerical simulations: CB TS. Developed fitting procedures for the experimental data: ABN BL. Conducted data analysis of electroreceptor data: DFR ABN.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤</label><p>Current address: Otto-von-Guericke University, Magdeburg, Germany.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003170</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Bauermeister et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Stochastic signals with pronounced oscillatory components are frequently encountered in neural systems. Input currents to a neuron in the form of stochastic oscillations could be of exogenous origin, e.g. sensory input or synaptic input from a network rhythm. They shape spike firing statistics in a characteristic way, which we explore theoretically in this report. We consider a perfect integrate-and-fire neuron that is stimulated by a constant base current (to drive regular spontaneous firing), along with Gaussian narrow-band noise (a simple example of stochastic oscillations), and a broadband noise. We derive expressions for the <italic>n</italic>th-order interval distribution, its variance, and the serial correlation coefficients of the interspike intervals (ISIs) and confirm these analytical results by computer simulations. The theory is then applied to experimental data from electroreceptors of paddlefish, which have two distinct types of internal noisy oscillators, one forcing the other. The theory provides an analytical description of their afferent spiking statistics during spontaneous firing, and replicates a pronounced dependence of ISI serial correlation coefficients on the relative frequency of the driving oscillations, and furthermore allows extraction of certain parameters of the intrinsic oscillators embedded in these electroreceptors.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>We explore how a neuron responds to a special type of input signal which is oscillatory but noisy (narrow-band noise). These fluctuations could be due to sensory input, due to oscillatory activity of a surrounding network, or due to a natural stimulus. We study theoretically the effects of noisy oscillations on an idealized model neuron, which would otherwise produce as output a series of action potentials at regular intervals. Because our model is comparably simple, we can describe the effects on ISI statistics analytically with formulas that we test against computer simulations of the model. Moreover, we can compare our theoretical predictions to experimental data from electroreceptors of paddlefish - a biological example for spiking neurons that are naturally stimulated by stochastic oscillatory input. In particular, our theory provides a simple explanation of the seemingly complicated patterns of correlations between interspike intervals, that are observed for the electro-afferents in paddlefish; the theory shows also good agreement with respect to other independent spike train statistics. Our findings further the understanding of how nervous activity is shaped by oscillatory noisy signals, which can emerge in the neural networks of the brain, in the sensory periphery, and in the environment.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>DFR was funded by NIH grant R01DC04922. Part of this research (TS and BL) was also funded by the BMBF (FKZ: 01GQ1001A). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Oscillatory activity is common in neural systems. Mechanical oscillations form an important class of sensory stimuli, for instance, in hearing, but may also be generated autonomously by mechanosensory hair cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Martin1">[1]</xref>. In single neurons, periodicities may occur in the form of subthreshold membrane potential oscillations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schmitz1">[2]</xref>. Oscillations at the level of brainstem and spinal cord neural networks generate the coordinated motor patterns for breathing and locomotion. Cortical networks may cause periodicities of local field potentials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Donoghue1">[3]</xref> or electroencephalogram (EEG) or magnetoencephalogram (MEG) activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Buzski1">[4]</xref>.</p>
<p>With few exceptions, e.g. motor rhythms and the precise rhythm of the electric organ discharge in weakly electric fish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Heiligenberg1">[5]</xref>, the oscillations generated by neural systems are not coherent over long time scales, but instead show fluctuations in both phase and amplitude (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, middle panel, for an example). Such periodic signals with limited coherence are termed <italic>stochastic oscillations</italic>, and are characterized by a preferred frequency band of spectral power. An individual neuron's activity may be affected by stochastic oscillations via synaptic input to it, or from its own endogenous fluctuations. Although stochastic oscillations are frequently found in neural systems, there is generally poor understanding of how an input current of this kind affects the firing pattern of a neuron, its ability to transmit information about time-dependent stimuli, and its interaction with other cells in a neural network. This is in marked contrast to the often studied (non-stationary) problem of how a <italic>deterministic</italic> periodic driving affects neural activity (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Knight1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Burkitt1">[13]</xref>). The simplest yet non-trivial problem that comes up with stochastic oscillations is how they shape the <italic>spontaneous</italic> activity of a spiking neuron, our topic here.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Illustration of the neuron model, showing a calculated membrane voltage trace (upper panel) that yields a spike time whenever a threshold level is reached, and sample trajectories of input narrow-band harmonic noise (middle panel) and broadband short-correlated Ornstein-Uhlenbeck (OU) noise (lower panel).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>For the strictly periodic (i.e. a deterministic) driving, different analytical approaches and results exist (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Bulsara1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Fourcaud1">[12]</xref>). Explicit expressions for the spike statistics of neurons driven by stochastic oscillations, however, are still lacking even for simple integrate-and-fire type models (for a notable exception, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Engel1">[14]</xref> for an approach to the count statistics of such models). Formulas, e.g. for the ISI statistics, are desirable for several reasons. First, the analytical approach gives us a more thorough understanding of the spike time statistics, along with opportunities to formulate falsifiable predictions from the model. Secondly, in many neurons, a stochastic oscillatory drive may arise from noisy background processes rather than from specific sensory input. Analytical results may help to understand this more complicated situation of oscillatory noise and sensory stimuli being present at the same time. Put differently, before we can characterize the signal transmission of such a cell, it is in many cases beneficial to first thoroughly understand its spontaneous (i.e. autonomous signal-independent) activity caused by intrinsic noise or massive synaptic background. Thirdly, the temporal structure of single neuronal spike trains is conserved even if many independent spike trains are superposed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner2">[15]</xref> (weak correlations between neurons will additionally shape the power spectrum of the sum). Hence, on the network level, characteristics like the ISI density and ISI correlations of presynaptic cells driven by stochastic oscillations still affect postsynaptic target cells and thus shape network dynamics. Last, by comparing the ISI statistics of real neurons to analytical expectations, it may in certain cases be possible to draw conclusions about intrinsic parameters of the neural dynamics, which may otherwise be inaccessible, as has been carried out recently for sensory neurons with spike-frequency adaptation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Fisch1">[17]</xref>.</p>
<p>Extensive experimental results pertinent to this problem of how stochastic oscillations shape the spontaneous spiking of a sensory neuron exist for the peripheral electroreceptors in paddlefish, which embed two distinct types of stochastic oscillators, one running at approx. 25 Hz, residing in a population of epithelial cells, which drives another in the peripheral terminals of afferents, running at approximately twice higher frequency. It was shown that the forcing from stochastic epithelial oscillations leads to rather complicated firing statistics of afferent firing, with multiple peaks in spike train power spectra, and extended-range correlations in the ISI sequence, continuing for tens of ISIs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman2">[19]</xref>. We made use of a database of digitized recordings of spontaneous firing of electroreceptor afferents, obtained from <italic>in vivo</italic> paddlefish preparations in which external environmental noise due to water motion was minimized.</p>
<p>In this paper, we present novel analytical results for the firing statistics of a perfect integrate-and-fire (PIF) neuron model, which is driven by noisy oscillations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Engel1">[14]</xref>. The PIF model is the canonical model for a supra-threshold, regularly firing neuron, in which the effective mean input current <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is so strong that it overshadows any voltage-dependence of the subthreshold membrane dynamics. The membrane potential <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> obeys the dynamical equation<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e003"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e003" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the temporal derivative of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The model generates spikes whenever <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> hits the threshold at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and is subsequently reset to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The driving consists of a so-called harmonic noise, representing the stochastic oscillation, given by the following Langevin equations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-SchimanskyGeier1">[20]</xref><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e009"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e009" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e010"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e010" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>together with a short-correlated Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Risken1">[21]</xref><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e011"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>which mimics broadband intrinsic fluctuations. The values of the noise are <italic>not</italic> reset after spiking. Important parameters of the model are: (i) the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the damped frequency <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the harmonic noise to the mean firing rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, (ii) the quality factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> which quantifies the bandwidth and coherence of the harmonic noise, (iii) the non-dimensionalized variance of the harmonic noise <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, (iv) the non-dimensionalized variance of an Ornstein-Uhlenbeck (OU) broadband noise process <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and (v) its non-dimensional correlation time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Our model with stochastic oscillations is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. Note that it can be regarded as a generalization of previous models, in which a PIF model was driven by uncorrelated white noise <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Gerstein1">[22]</xref>, exponentially correlated noise <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner3">[23]</xref>, or a white noise and periodic driving <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Bulsara1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Fourcaud1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Gitterman1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Abbott1">[25]</xref>.</p>
<p>For this simple model, we calculate approximations for the ISI density and the ISI serial correlations and compare them to numerical simulations of the model. When discussing our explicit results, we focus on changes of the ISI statistics upon varying the ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the frequency of stochastic oscillations to the neuron's firing rate, a parameter that also shows a remarkable effect for the electroreceptor afferents of paddlefish. In particular, we show that upon variation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the skewness of the ISI density and also the structure of the ISI correlation coefficient as a function of the lag both change drastically, changes that are well-described by our theory.</p>
<p>We then compare our formulas for the ISI statistics to experimental data from electroreceptor afferents of paddlefish, obtained previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>. The analytical results from our simple perfect integrate-and-fire model work reasonably well in predicting (matching) these experimental data, indicating that the limitations of this model are not severe for representing sensory neurons with a high ongoing firing rate. This accords with other reports of remarkably good performance of stochastic perfect integrate-and-fire models for mimicking the ISI statistics of spontaneously active sensory neurons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Fisch1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Gerstein1">[22]</xref> (for the performance of more general IF models in reproducing spike statistics, see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Rauch1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Badel1">[27]</xref>). We conclude with a short discussion of the implications of our results for oscillatory physiological systems in general.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<p>In this work, we aim at (i) the statistics of individual interspike intervals (ISI) by means of their probability density function (pdf), its coefficient of variation (CV), and its skewness, and (ii) the correlations between ISIs as quantified by the serial correlation coefficient (SCC). We study these statistics for the perfect integrate-and-fire (PIF) model and compare the theoretical results to experimental data.</p>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Perfect integrate-and-fire model</title>
<p>Despite the apparent simplicity of the PIF model, the fire-and-reset condition severely complicates the analysis. For the calculation of the ISI density and ISI correlations, one has to solve a first-passage-time problem in the form of a Fokker-Planck equation in a four-dimensional state-space spanned by the voltage and all the noise variables. The fire-and-reset condition imposes a complicated boundary condition on a half-space <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Brunel1">[28]</xref>, which however can be ignored in the case of a weak colored noise where the standard deviation of the total noise is much smaller than the base current <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, or, in terms of a small parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, if<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e023"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e023" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>In this case, based on the methods presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner3">[23]</xref>, the solution with natural boundary conditions can be used to calculate the ISI density. Furthermore, to obtain explicit expressions for the ISI moments and the SCC, a perturbation calculation of the characteristic function, in which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> enters as the small parameter, turns out to be advantageous. These approximations are outlined in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> and lead, for the considered problem, to formulas of reasonable length for the statistics of interest. In the next section, we compare our formulas to results from numerical simulations for small fixed values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In M<sc>ethods</sc>, we also show some of the statistics as functions of our small parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in order to give the reader some intuition about the range of validity of our formulas.</p>
<p>Our results are valid for arbitrary time scales of harmonic noise and OU noise; the general formulas are provided in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section. However, because the effects of an exponentially correlated noise on ISI statistics are well-known <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner3">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Middleton1">[29]</xref>, we focus on variations in the time scales of the harmonic noise, and set the correlation time of the OU noise to a small value if not stated otherwise. In most of the cases discussed, the latter noise thus acts essentially as a white-noise source. Direct inclusion of a white noise is not possible in our perturbation approach.</p>
<sec id="s2a1">
<title>Shape of interspike interval density; skewness and coefficient of variation</title>
<p>For the ISI density with weak total noise, a short-correlated Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and a high quality factor of the harmonic noise <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we obtain (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>):<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e029"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e029" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>with<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e030"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e030" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e031"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e031" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e032"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e032" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e033"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e033" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the mean ISI. A more lengthy expression that holds true for arbitrary correlation time of the OU noise and arbitrary quality factor of the harmonic noise but still requires that the total noise is weak, is given in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e346">Eqs. (43</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e352">46)</xref>.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g002">Fig. 2A</xref> shows how the skewness of ISI distributions changes for different values of the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. These examples suggest that the ISI distribution is positively skewed for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, symmetrical for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and negatively skewed for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> slightly larger than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In fact, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g003">Fig. 3B</xref> reveals an oscillating pattern of the skewness <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of the frequency ratio. For sufficiently weak OU noise, the skewness is negative if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with integer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, whereas the skewness is positive if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with integer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For stronger OU noise, the skewness is increased such that it is positive for all values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g003">Fig. 3B3</xref>), as shown in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref> for the electroreceptor afferents. This is plausible because it is known that with dominating exponentially correlated noise or with uncorrelated noise, the ISI density is positively skewed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger1">[16]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of ISI distributions <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> obtained from numerical simulation or theory <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e029">Eqs.(6</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e032">9)</xref> for A and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e346">Eqs. (43</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e352">46)</xref> for B.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold>: ISI distributions for different frequency ratios: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (top panel), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (middle panel), or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (bottom panel). Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. <bold>B</bold>: Example of a multimodal ISI histogram at high relative driving frequency <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with harmonic noise input that was nearly periodic (large quality factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and, consequently, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pcbi-1003170-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Second and third-order interval statistics as a function of the frequency ratio for different values of the OU broadband input (remaining parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</title>
<p><bold>A</bold>: Coefficient of variation (CV) for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A1), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A2), or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A3). <bold>B</bold>: Skewness <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (B1) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (B2), or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (B3). Theoretical CV and skewness (blue) were computed by numerical integration from the theoretical ISI distribution <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e029">Eq.(6)</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e032">Eq.(9)</xref> ; the simpler expression <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e077">Eq.(11)</xref> is shown in red in <bold>A</bold>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Note that the ISI distribution can also be multimodal, as demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g002">Fig. 2B</xref> (here, the full theory <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e346">Eqs. (43</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e352">46</xref>) had to be used, because <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is not small as assumed for <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e029">Eq.(6)</xref>). Such multimodal histograms have also been obtained for the FitzHugh-Nagumo and leaky integrate-and-fire models driven by white noise and a strictly periodic signal, and have been experimentally observed for auditory neurons (see, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Longtin1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Rose1">[30]</xref>) and electrosensory neurons in weakly electric fish (see, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Chacron1">[31]</xref>).</p>
<p>Besides the skewness of the distribution, its relative width as quantified by the coefficient of variation (CV) is another important statistic, which characterizes the variability of ISIs. For a sufficiently high quality factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the harmonic noise, and a small correlation time of the broadband OU noise, we obtain the following approximation for the squared CV:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e077"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e077" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula>an expression that yields values close to simulation data and to values of the CV obtained by using an integral involving our approximation for the ISI density <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e029">Eq.(6)</xref> (cf. red lines to symbols and blue lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g003">Fig. 3 A</xref>).</p>
<p>We can draw a few conclusions from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e077">Eq.(11)</xref>. Firstly, the OU and harmonic noise processes make independent contributions to the ISI variability, the two terms being proportional to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This is reasonable because it reflects the addition of the noise sources in the input, and the fact that we used a perturbation theory. Secondly, the CV is an oscillatory function of the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We can certainly expect that driving the system with a multiple of its own (firing) frequency allows for more regular spiking of the neuron (corresponding to the minima in the CV at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) than a forcing with a frequency very different from its autonomous rhythm. Thirdly, there is an overall decline of CV with growing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because of the exponential function. This is explained because the noise intensity of the driving stochastic oscillations declines with increasing frequency <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and hence the harmonic noise becomes less efficient in broadening the ISI density. All of these predictions of the formula are quantitatively confirmed for different values of the standard deviations of the OU noise (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). Remarkably, for a perfect integrate-and-fire model, although the mean firing rate does not depend on the noise <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner3">[23]</xref> (see also <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section)and, in particular not on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, higher-order statistics such as the CV and the skewness do.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2a2">
<title>Serial correlation coefficients</title>
<p>The serial correlation coefficient (SCC) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of interspike intervals can be computed from the variances <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the <italic>n</italic>th-order interval distribution (see M<sc>ethods</sc>). For a high quality factor of the harmonic noise and a small correlation time of the OU broadband noise, the formula for the SCC can be considerably simplified to read<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e087"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e087" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>with parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that do not depend on the interval lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e090"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e090" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(13)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e091"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>For the CV in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq. (12)</xref>, the approximate expression in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e077">Eq.(11)</xref> is adequate.</p>
<p>The dependence of the serial correlation coefficient <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq.(12)</xref> on the lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has the form of a damped oscillation, sampled at discrete values of the lag. This simple structure permits a number of conclusions. Firstly, if assumed to have a short correlation time, Ornstein-Uhlenbeck noise affects the SCC mainly via the CV in the prefactor, and thus tends to <italic>reduce</italic> the amplitude of the serial correlations at all lags. In contrast, an increase in the variance of the harmonic noise <italic>amplifies</italic> the serial correlations. Secondly, spike intervals are correlated mainly due to the correlations in the driving stochastic oscillations, and hence the SCC shows an overall decay with the “lag constant” <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, reflecting simply the finite (limited) phase coherence of the harmonic noise input. Thirdly, the SCC oscillates with the lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, but because the argument <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> attains only integer values, rather complex looking patterns can result if the multiplying factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the trigonometric functions is not an integer or a simple ratio such as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Fourthly, for a frequency ratio of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the SCC is close to zero for all lags because in this case the sine term in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq.(12)</xref> drops out, and the prefactor of the cosine term <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is rather small for a high coherence of the harmonic noise. Hence, if the frequencies of the stochastic oscillation and the neuron coincide, the resulting spike train is close to a renewal process. This is similar to findings in a bistable system under dichotomous driving <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner4">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger2">[33]</xref>, for which the linear correlations vanish if the switching rate of the dichotomous driving coincides with the spontaneous hopping rate of the bistable system.</p>
<p>All of these predictions are confirmed in the comparisons to numerical simulations in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g004">Fig. 4 A</xref>. Correlations are very small for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). They look complex for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and are simply sinusoidal for small <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For a value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, close to one half, a kind of beating pattern emerges. Finally, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we observe a clear and long-extended oscillation of the SCC, alternating between positive and negative values, while decaying. In all cases, our formula works very well in predicting these different structures.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Serial correlation coefficients.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold>: SCC value (ranging from −1 to +1) as a function of the lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of interspike intervals, for different values of the frequency ratio: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A1), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A2), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A3), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A4), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A5), or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A6). Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Dots: simulation. Lines: theory. <bold>B</bold>: SCC at lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, for highly coherent harmonic noise, as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Theoretical curves were computed from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e077">Eq.(11)</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq.(12)</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Another validation of our analytical result at very high coherence of the harmonic noise is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g004">Fig. 4 B</xref>, showing the correlation coefficient of adjacent intervals <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of the frequency ratio. Also in this case, a nontrivial dependence is observed, with clear minima of the SCC at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is an integer), and sharp changes around integer values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>The overall length of the ISI correlations can be characterized by the correlation lag, defined as<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e126"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e126" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(14)</label></disp-formula>The correlation lag measures the temporal extent of the SCCs, irrespective of the sign of the coefficients, in units of the mean interspike interval. For the SCCs approximated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq.(12)</xref>, the sum in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e126">Eq.(14)</xref> is calculated exactly as:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e127"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e127" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(15)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e090">Eq.(13)</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g005">Fig. 5</xref> shows the correlation lag versus the frequency ratio, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. It is clearly maximal and even diverges for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. However, there are sharp local maxima around <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. There are also minima close to zero for integer values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because in this latter case the spike train is nearly a renewal process.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Correlation lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, in units of the mean interspike interval, as a function of the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</title>
<p>Dots show results of numerical simulations; blue lines show theory according to analytical evaluation of the sum <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e126">Eq.(14)</xref>. <bold>A</bold>: Correlation lag for different values of the quality factor of harmonic noise input: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A1), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A2), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A3). Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. <bold>B</bold>: Correlation lag at different levels of OU broadband noise: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (B1), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (B2), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (B3). Parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Comparison with experimental data from paddlefish electroreceptors</title>
<p>The theory developed in the previous sections was applied to experimental data obtained from <italic>in vivo</italic> electroreceptors of paddlefish. A single peripheral electroreceptor (ER) in paddlefish embeds two distinct oscillators. One resides in a population of epithelial cells (epithelial oscillator, EO), and can be recorded near an epithelium. This EO is coupled synaptically to another oscillator associated with the terminal of a given primary sensory afferent neuron (afferent oscillator, AO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>. Unidirectional coupling of these self-sustained oscillators, EO→AO, results in spontaneous biperiodic firing patterns of afferents having two fundamental frequencies, including the EO's at about <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and another corresponding to the mean firing rate of an afferent, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, ranging from 30 up to 78 Hz, depending on the particular electroreceptor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>. These two fundamental frequencies are seen as separate peaks centered at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the power spectral density of an afferent's firing. These peaks were used to determine the frequency ratio of the two oscillators as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Only the AO is affected by external electric field stimuli. The EO acts as a stimulus-independent source of narrow-band noise input to the AO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman3">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman4">[35]</xref>. Thus, the paddlefish electroreceptor system is an appropriate source of experimental data for validating the theory developed here.</p>
<p>In the <italic>in vivo</italic> preparation of paddlefish, an extracellular single unit recording offers information about the firing of an ER afferent. However, parameters of the epithelial oscillator, such as its effective quality factor and its variance, are hidden (D<sc>iscussion</sc>). Previous computational studies have shown that a model of two unidirectionally coupled oscillators reproduces well the spontaneous and response dynamics of paddlefish ERs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Engel1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman2">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Fuwape1">[36]</xref>. Here, we use our theory for the PIF model with harmonic noise, and in particular analytical expressions for the SCCs, to extract statistical and dynamical properties of the oscillators embedded in these ERs, and to verify the theoretical predictions of how the statistics of ISIs depend on the parameters of the coupled oscillators.</p>
<p>We analyzed spontaneous spiking activity from a sample of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ER afferents (M<sc>ethods</sc>). External noise was minimized, and a criterion for stationarity of long data segments was imposed. The data were in the form of sequences of spike times <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was of the order of 15000–50000 spikes, corresponding to recording times of 300–900 s. The mean firing rates of these units were in the range of 37.9–77.7 Hz, with mean and SD of 54.3±8.71 Hz. The ratio of the EO to AO frequencies, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, was 0.48 ± 0.06 for the sample (range 0.40–0.61). The CV of the corresponding ISIs of these units was 0.19 ± 0.05 (range 0.11–0.31). Histograms in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g006">Fig. 6</xref> summarizing these statistics illustrate the diversity of firing rates and variability among this sample of ER afferents.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Histograms of firing statistics for a sample of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> paddlefish ER afferents, including distributions of the mean firing rate, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, A, the ratio of EO to AO frequencies, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, B, and the coefficient of variation, CV, C.</title>
<p>These graphs are for different number of afferents than used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g006">Fig. 6</xref> of Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>From a given spike sequence, we estimated the SCCs, the probability density of ISIs, and the power spectral density of the spike train. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7</xref> shows these measures for three representative afferents with distinct values of the EO-to-AO frequency ratio, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e159" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which were below, near, or above <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For all afferents in the sample, the distributions of ISIs were unimodal, and peaked close to the mean ISI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>). They all showed extended decaying series of significantly non-zero serial correlations, arising from the interaction of the EO and AO, with a structure determined by the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman2">[19]</xref>. To assess the variation of SCC values due to unavoidable minor non-stationarity, we split the spike train into 20 segments, each 2000 ISIs long, and estimated the SCCs for each segment, which yielded error bars for the SCC values shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>. The PSD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7C</xref>) showed a characteristic structure of peaks, with a peak at the fundamental frequencies of the EO and AO (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively), sideband peaks at combination frequencies (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and their higher harmonics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman2">[19]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Experimental data from three representative paddlefish electroreceptor afferents (dots in A1–A3, dots and error bars in B1–B3, and gray lines in C1–C3), compared to theory, for the values of the frequency ratio, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, listed at the top.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold>: ISI probability density functions (PDFs). Theoretical PDFs (red, blue, green lines) were calculated using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e029">Eq.(6)</xref> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, 0.2 and 0.5 (legend in A2), and other parameters derived from fitting the SCCs, as explained in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>, final section. <bold>B</bold>: Serial correlation coefficients (SCCs). Theoretical red lines show least square fits using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq.(12)</xref>. <bold>C–D</bold>: Power spectral densities (PSDs). Theoretical lines (magenta) were obtained from numerical simulation of the PIF model using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e003">Eqs.(1</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e011">4</xref>), with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and other parameters the same as for theoretical curves in panels A1–3, derived from the SCC fitting procedure.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To apply our theory to experimental data, we extracted from the serial correlations of an afferent spike train the four parameters needed for the PIF model: the quality factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the EO (a metric of the bandwidth and coherence of harmonic noise), the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the SD of the EO <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (the magnitude of harmonic noise), and the intensity of broadband OU noise, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. These parameters were extracted using a fitting procedure described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> (last section).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7</xref> illustrates the outcome for three representative ER afferents. Our theoretical expression for the serial correlations of ISIs, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq.(12)</xref>, shown by the red lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>, provided excellent fits for experimental data, as fitted values were within the error bars of most experimental SCCs. The extracted parameters of the PIF model for these three afferents are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003170-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1003170-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Fitted values of PIF parameters for the three afferent neurons for which ISI statistics are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7</xref>.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003170-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afferent</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean firing rate (Hz)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>w</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Q</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10×10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.198</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20×10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.591</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10×10<sup>−3</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>To calculate the probability densities of ISIs and the PSDs, we needed to accept a value for the correlation time of OU broadband noise, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (which was <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e176" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in units of the mean ISI interval, i.e. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). This was the only free parameter in our procedure of comparison of experimental data and theory. Probability densities of ISIs calculated according to the theory <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e029">Eq.(6)</xref> (solid lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>), with the parameters from <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003170-t001">Table 1</xref>, showed good correspondence with experimental data, and weak dependence on the correlation time of OU noise. Instead of tuning up <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the correlation time of OU broadband noise was assumed to be fixed at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e179" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for all afferents, which provided good correspondence of experimental and theoretical ISIs distributions for all units, such as those shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7A</xref>.</p>
<p>Finally, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7C,D</xref> compares power spectra of spike trains obtained from numerical simulations of the PIF model <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e003">Eqs.(1</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e011">4</xref>), using parameters from <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003170-t001">Table 1</xref>, to the PSDs of ER spike trains. Although the PSD's from simulations reproduced well the overall shape of experimental PSDs, the agreement between them is incomplete, especially at low frequencies, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e180" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Hz, suggesting that the PIF model is an oversimplification of the stochastic dynamics of these electroreceptors. In particular, ER afferents in another fish species are known to exhibit spike-frequency adaptation resulting in short-term negative correlations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Chacron2">[37]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Benda1">[39]</xref>. These anticorrelations result in reduced power at low frequencies and a sharper peak at the mean firing rate. A previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman2">[19]</xref> showed that introduction of spike-frequency adaptation in a spiking model of paddlefish ERs results in an additional subtraction of low-frequency power similar to that observed in the experimental PSDs shown in double log scale in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7D</xref>. Nevertheless, the overall agreement of our simple and analytically tractable model is clear.</p>
<p>The quality of fit is further illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g008">Fig. 8A</xref> showing measured and calculated correlation lag of the ISI sequence. Furthermore, correspondence of theory and experiment is demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g008">Fig. 8B</xref> for the skewness of the ISI distribution, an independent variability measure derived from ISI distribution. As seen from the figure, theory estimate was biased towards somewhat smaller values of the skewness. The Spearman rank correlation coefficient was <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e181" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the correlation lags and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the skewness (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e183" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for both).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of experimental data with theory for the sample of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e184" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> paddlefish ERs.</title>
<p><bold>A</bold>: ISI correlation lags <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> calculated from the experimental data according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e126">Eq.(14)</xref>, vs. values from theory, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e127">Eq.(15)</xref>, calculated using parameters obtained from fitting experimental SCCs. <bold>B</bold>: Skewness of experimental vs. theoretical ISI distributions. 45° line is shown by dashed strokes on both panels.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The application of the fitting procedure to our sample of ERs provided the following sample-averaged values for the parameters of the PIF model:</p>
<p><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (range 8.570–29.46), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (range 0.129–0.443), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (range 0.084–0.303). It is noteworthy that the SD values of the broadband OU noise, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e189" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, were close to or even larger than SDs of the harmonic noise, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e190" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Nevertheless, the first-order approximation used in our theory was adequate to provide close correspondence with the experimental data, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Figs. 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g008">8</xref>.</p>
<p>Next, we analyzed how the statistical properties of afferent ISIs depend on the parameters of epithelial oscillations. In contrast to analytical or numerical analyses, which allow studying the dependence of a given statistical measure versus a single control parameter, other parameters being fixed, here instead each experimental data point on the scatter plots of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9</xref> carries a set of 4 measurable parameters (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e192" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e193" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with fixed values. Variation of these parameter values between different ERs allows qualitative tendencies to be clearly seen in the sample of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> experimental data points, and these trends can be compared to theoretical predictions. We start with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>, showing a scatter plot of the electroreceptor ISI correlation lag <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (i.e. how slowly the serial correlations of ISIs decayed; <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e126">Eq.(14)</xref>) versus the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values of epithelial oscillations (i.e. their bandwidth and coherence). According to the theory, SCCs will decay more slowly for more coherent epithelial oscillations (i.e. for larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e198" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values), such that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This prediction was supported by a positive correlation between them in the experimental data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>), having a significant Spearman rank correlation coefficient of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e201" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e202" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), despite considerable scatter.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>Statistical properties of afferent ISIs (ordinates) versus parameters of epithelial oscillations (abscissas), estimated from experimental data for the sample of n = 56 paddlefish ERs (filled circles).</title>
<p><bold>A,B</bold>: The ISI correlation lag characteristic, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, versus values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (A), or the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (B), of epithelial oscillations. <bold>C</bold>: Skewness of ISI distributions versus frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Blue lines: Theoretical results from PIF models for parameters extracted from each ER by fitting (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>, final section), while varying <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e207" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e208" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Solid blue lines: Mean curves for the sample. Dashed blue lines: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e209" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> standard deviation.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To quantitatively compare experimental data to expectations from theory, we calculated <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e210" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e211" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the PIF model <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e127">Eq.(15)</xref> for each ER in the sample, with the other three parameters (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e212" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e213" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e214" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) extracted using the SCC fitting procedure (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>, final section), yielding a curve for that electroreceptor over the range of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e215" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values along the abscissa of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>. The family of n = 56 PIF model curves were then averaged to calculate the sample-averaged tendency <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e216" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (solid blue line) and its standard deviation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e217" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (dashed blue lines):<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e218"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e218" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(16)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e219"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e219" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e220" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e221" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e222" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the parameters for the <italic>k</italic>-th afferent. The mean trend from theory formed a straight line with positive slope, correctly predicting that the correlation lag increases for more coherent epithelial oscillations. More than expected of the experimental data points (47/56 = 84%) fell within the predicted ±1 SD (68%) bands.</p>
<p>The ISI variability metric <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e223" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> also depended strongly on the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e224" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9B</xref>), with the largest correlation lag attained for a value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e225" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> close to 0.5, i.e. when there were two afferent spikes per cycle of epithelial oscillations. This is consistent with the PIF theory (solid blue line) showing a local maximum of the correlation lag for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e226" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Furthermore, most experimental points were within theoretical ±1 SD bounds (blue dashed lines, calculated in the same way as for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9A</xref> but by varying <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e227" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> instead of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e228" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The large scatter of data points presumably was due to diversity of afferent variabilities.</p>
<p>Finally, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9C</xref> shows that the skewness of ISI distributions was negatively correlated with the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e229" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, such that the tails of ISI distributions were significantly reduced at higher values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e230" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (Spearman correlation coefficient <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e231" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e232" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). This negative correlation was borne out by analytical calculations from the PIF model (blue lines).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This report analyzed a scenario in which the membrane potential and spiking of a neuron is forced by weak noisy oscillatory input, in a narrow but non-vanishing frequency band. Our goal was to study the effects of narrow-band noise input on the output spiking statistics of a neuron. Our analysis centered around a perfect integrate-and-fire model of a single neuron, stimulated by a mixture of stochastic oscillations and broadband noise. We obtained novel explicit expressions for the probability density and serial correlation coefficients of the model's interspike intervals (ISIs). By a perturbation calculation of the Fokker-Planck equation, we derived a structurally simple form for the serial correlation coefficient. This novel derivation helps to solve the inverse problem: using the spike statistics of a neuron to estimate parameters of the underlying stochastic processes that drive its firing. No other body of theory has rigorously addressed the implications of narrow-band stochastic input for neural firing statistics, despite much acclaim of the widespread roles of oscillators in nervous systems.</p>
<p>Our new analytical formulas compare extremely well with results from our numerical simulations of the spiking neuron model, provided that the variance of the total input noise is weak, such that the coefficient of variation of spiking output remains low, less than approximately 0.3.</p>
<p>We compared the PIF theory to spike time data from a well-defined experimental system, the electroreceptor afferents of paddlefish, which receive stochastic synaptic driving in a narrow frequency band from ongoing oscillations arising in their sensory epithelia. For a given afferent's sequence of ISIs, a fitting procedure was used to extract four parameters needed for the PIF model, and the model's output was computed. The only appreciable discrepancy between model and experiment was observed in the skewness of ISI distributions in which the model showed consistently smaller values and in the low frequency regime of spike train power spectra, in which the model showed excess noise power. This low frequency regime is presumably shaped by spike-frequency adaptation, which we did not incorporate in our model to keep it analytically tractable.</p>
<p>The fitting parameters varied considerably for different units, reflecting natural variability of the electroreceptors. These natural ranges of values permitted us to check whether different functional relationships were correctly predicted by the theory. For example, in both theory and experiment, the temporal extent of the SCCs (i.e., their correlation lag, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e233" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) increases monotonically with the quality factor of epithelial oscillations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9 A</xref>), whereas <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e234" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> depends in a non-monotonic fashion on the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e235" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, attaining a maximum at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e236" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g009">Fig. 9 B</xref>), for both theory and experiment. We note that previous computational work showed that this frequency ratio corresponds to a maximum mutual information rate for electroreceptor afferents stimulated by a time-varying stimulus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Fuwape1">[36]</xref>. Thus, our study provides further arguments in favor of the idea that oscillators embedded in the electroreceptor system are tuned to maximize stimulus encoding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman3">[34]</xref>.</p>
<p>We applied our formulas to the inverse problem of whether the spike statistics of a neuron can be used to estimate parameters of the underlying stochastic processes that drive its firing. Using only our formulas for the firing rate, the CV, and the serial correlation coefficient, we were able to predict the parameters of the epithelial oscillator (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e237" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the variance of the broadband noise, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e238" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Using these predicted parameters, our analytical formulas provided excellent fits to the experimental serial correlation coefficients, and close correspondence between model and experiment in their ISI distributions and power spectra (except at low frequency).</p>
<p>It could be argued that the suggested solution of the inverse problem is too cumbersome in the case of epithelial oscillations of paddlefish ERs. Power spectra of afferent spike trains show a second fundamental peak due to synaptic input at the frequency of epithelial oscillations, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e239" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, so this spectral peak provides direct information. However, the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e240" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> peak is of limited usefulness for measuring parameters of the epithelial oscillation such as their quality factor, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e241" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, because afferent spike train spectra incorporate the effects of nonlinear transformations during synaptic transmission and spike generation, and also because the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e242" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> peak may overlap with other spectral peaks, e.g. a sideband.</p>
<p>In general, the good agreement of the simple PIF model and the experimental data indicates that the detailed voltage dependence of the neural dynamics, more faithfully modeled in a conductance-based Hodgkin-Huxley model, is less important for the spiking statistics than the stochastic oscillatory driving, provided that the mean input to the neuron is appropriate for tonic firing with low ISI variability. The PIF model is able to reproduce several complex features observed experimentally in the afferent spike timing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman2">[19]</xref>, including skewing of ISI probability densities in different ways, oscillations, beating, or seemingly chaotic patterns in the serial correlations of interspike intervals as a function of the lag. The ability of our theory to reproduce complex non-renewal spike timing may encourage experimentalists to look for and analyze seemingly complex looking patterns in ISI correlations.</p>
<p>Examples of narrowband noisy neural oscillations include the gamma band (25–90 Hz) extracellular field potentials prevalent in mammalian cortex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Burns1">[40]</xref>, which have been suggested, along with transient synchronization between brain areas, to mediate or reflect higher cognitive functions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Buzski1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Traub1">[41]</xref>. Such fast gamma oscillations interact with slower rhythms, including the theta rhythm in hippocampus, and slower oscillations in thalamic nuclei. From the point of view of a single cell in a specific brain region engaged in a specific rhythm, input from other brain regions could be regarded as a stochastic oscillation. What matters the most for the ISI statistics of this cell may be not so much the synchrony of the activity but the frequency ratio between the stochastic oscillatory driving and the mean firing rate of the driven cell. Put differently, instead of coherence and synchronization, an important signal for cognition might be the frequency ratio of narrowband stochastic oscillations in related brain areas. Our work provides a rigorous demonstration and model of how the operation and spiking statistics of neurons can change sharply when the frequencies of different stochastic oscillatory components approach or assume an integer ratio (i.e. a rational number). Perhaps integer ratioing could function as a trigger or gate for cognitive, memory, or other information processes, acting like an event detector.</p>
<p>Specifically, our results show how the structure of a neuron's serial ISI correlations depends characteristically on the frequency ratio of weak stochastic oscillatory input, and the intrinsic periodicity of a neuron receiving the input, with extreme SCC behavior occurring at integer multiples. We have delineated other parameters which strongly affect SCCs including the quality factor of stochastic oscillatory drive (i.e. its bandwidth and coherence), the neuron's mean firing rate, and the overall level of spike timing noise (its CV). Our results bear general importance for the effects of weak stochastic oscillations on the spiking statistics of neurons in other systems, and are relevant to the study of neuronal firing in many brain regions. We have defined a basis in theory for using serial correlations to detect and characterize weak interactions of physiological oscillators, which may apply to other organ systems as well <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Bruce1">[42]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Sack1">[44]</xref>. For example, the breathing and heartbeat rhythms can assume integer frequency ratios, and are known to be coupled <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Schfer1">[45]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Statistics of stationary sequences of interspike intervals</title>
<p>We used conventional metrics, summarized here for clarity, to characterize the statistics of a stationary spike train given by the set of spike times <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e243" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The spiking statistics can be derived from its sequence of interspike intervals (ISIs) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e244" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e245" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the <italic>i</italic>-th ISI. Calculations are simplified without loss of generality by restricting the stationary ensemble of spike trains to those realizations having a spike at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e246" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, called the zero-th spike. Under this choice of the origin, the <italic>n</italic>-th order interval, defined as the sum of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e247" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> consecutive ISIs, is equal to the <italic>n</italic>-th spike time:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e248"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e248" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(17)</label></disp-formula>The stationary spiking statistics can be formulated in terms of the statistics of the <italic>n</italic>th-order intervals, for all <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e249" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Knowing the probability density of the <italic>n</italic>-th-order interval<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e250"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e250" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(18)</label></disp-formula>for arbitrary <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e251" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, yields complete information about the spiking statistics.</p>
<p>The <italic>ISI probability density</italic> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e252" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by the first-order interval density: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e253" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Let the mean ISI be denoted by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e254" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is independent of the index <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e255" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> due to stationarity (here and in the following, the notation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e256" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> refers to the ensemble average). Then, the <italic>mean</italic> of the <italic>n</italic>th-order interval is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e257" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and the <italic>variance</italic> is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e258" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The <italic>coefficient of variation</italic> (CV), defined as the ratio between ISI standard deviation and mean is given by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e259"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e259" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(19)</label></disp-formula>The CV is a measure of irregularity of the spike train; it is equal to one for a Poisson process. The statistics of individual ISIs are further characterized by the <italic>skewness</italic> defined by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e260"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e260" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(20)</label></disp-formula>Correlations among the ISIs are characterized by the <italic>serial correlation coefficient</italic> (SCC)<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e261"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e261" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(21)</label></disp-formula>which depends on the order of ISIs. The SCC measures the correlations between two ISIs that are lagged by an integer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e262" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This measure can be related to the <italic>n</italic>th-order variances by the formula <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner3">[23]</xref><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e263"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e263" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(22)</label></disp-formula></p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Relation between noise parameters</title>
<p>In this paper we gave parameters of the model simulation in terms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e264" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e265" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Here we provide the inverse relationship, how to obtain the simulation parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e266" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e267" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e268" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e269" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e270"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e270" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(23)</label></disp-formula>Using these values, one can easily determine the noise intensities:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e271"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e271" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(24)</label></disp-formula></p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Analytical formulas for a PIF model driven by weak stochastic oscillations</title>
<p>The mean ISI in the PIF model is independent of the properties of a noise with zero mean <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Lindner3">[23]</xref> and is given by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e272"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e272" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(25)</label></disp-formula>In fact, for large times <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e273" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the spike count <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e274" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is determined by the free running solution of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e003">Eq. (1)</xref> (i.e. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e275" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> without resetting, cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Middleton1">[29]</xref>): <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e276" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Averaging this expression, the integral term vanishes and we obtain the firing rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e277" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, from which follows <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e272">Eq. (25)</xref>. Furthermore, using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e248">Eq. (17)</xref>, we find that the mean <italic>n</italic>-th-order interval is given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e278" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>To obtain higher moments as well as the probability density of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e279" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, it is important to recognize that the <italic>n</italic>th-order intervals can be interpreted as a first-passage time (FPT). In fact, in the PIF model the statistics of the sum of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e280" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> subsequent ISIs for a firing threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e281" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is equal to the statistics of a single ISI with respect to a firing threshold at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e282" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The statistics of a single ISI is, however, nothing else than the statistics of the FPT with respect to the boundary <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e283" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for a “particle” that starts at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e284" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and is not reset at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e285" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The equivalence between <italic>n</italic>-th spike time and the FPT with respect to the boundary <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e286" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is due to the fact, that the “velocity” <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e287" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the particle is independent of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e288" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e003">Eq.(1)</xref>. Consequently, the time of the <italic>n</italic>th spike depends only on the total distance <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e289" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that a particle has to cover.</p>
<p>The FPT problem can be solved by using the Fokker-Planck equation for the probability density <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e290" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which is associated to our stochastic model (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Gardiner1">[46]</xref>). This equation reads<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e291"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e291" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(26)</label></disp-formula>The probability density has to satisfy certain boundary and initial conditions. Specifically, we demand that particles that have crossed the boundary <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e292" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are not allowed to re-enter the domain <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e293" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Brunel1">[28]</xref> for a discussion on a related problem). This precludes repeated threshold crossings. As a consequence, there is no probability flux <italic>through</italic> the boundary with negative velocity. Mathematically, this entails the boundary condition<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e294"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e294" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(27)</label></disp-formula>because no particles are found just below the boundary <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e295" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e296" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Furthermore, we require that the probability density and the probability current vanish at infinitely distant boundaries (natural boundary conditions). In the following, we assume that the total noise is weak. In particular, we require that the standard deviation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e297" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is much smaller than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e298" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, or<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e299"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e299" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(28)</label></disp-formula>where<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e300"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e300" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(29)</label></disp-formula>are the normalized variances of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e301" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e302" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Under this assumption, it is highly unlikely that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e303" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> becomes negative and hence, the boundary condition <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e294">Eq.(27)</xref> can be safely neglected.</p>
<p>The initial condition is determined by the fact that at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e304" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the neuron has just fired a spike and the membrane potential has just been reset to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e305" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This implies, that the initial probability must satisfy<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e306"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e306" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(30)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e307" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the probability density of the variables <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e308" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e309" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e310" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <italic>upon firing</italic>. How can one obtain this probability density? To this end, let us for the moment reconsider the original setup, where the trajectories are reset if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e311" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Then the dynamics are restricted to the domain <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e312" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the probability density <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e313" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> will in this case converge to some stationary probability density, which will be denoted by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e314" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The density upon firing must be proportional to the fraction of particles that exit the domain through the surface element <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e315" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> per unit time. This fraction is equal to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e316" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e317" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the stationary probability current in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e318" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> direction. Thus,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e319"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e319" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(31)</label></disp-formula>Under the weak noise assumption <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e299">Eq.(28)</xref>, the stationary distribution <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e320" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> does not depend on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e321" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, because for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e322" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> all values <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e323" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> have equal probability due to the voltage-independence of the membrane dynamics and the loss of the memory about the initial condition. We hence find<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e324"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e324" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(32)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e325" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Upon normalization, the initial condition can now be written as<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e326"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e326" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(33)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>The time-dependent solution of the Fokker-Planck <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e291">equation (26)</xref> with the initial condition (33) can be related to the <italic>n</italic>th-order interval density <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e327" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as follows: The probability per unit time to cross the boundary <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e328" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e329" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is equal to the total probability current across the boundary at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e330" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, hence<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e331"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e331" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(34)</label></disp-formula>For the sake of notational convenience, we will henceforth use the dimensionless time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e332" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and membrane potential <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e333" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Furthermore, we introduce the non-dimensionalized variables<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e334"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e334" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(35)</label></disp-formula>and the non-dimensional parameters<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e335"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e335" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(36)</label></disp-formula>In these rescaled variables the Fokker-Planck equation takes the form<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e336"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e336" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(37)</label></disp-formula></p>
<sec id="s4c1">
<title>Probability density of the <italic>n</italic>th-order intervals</title>
<p>The <italic>n</italic>th-order interval density can be derived from the characteristic function<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e337"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e337" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>In fact, comparing with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e331">Eq.(34)</xref> we observe that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e338" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be represented by the formula<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e339"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e339" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(38)</label></disp-formula>Applying the respective Fourier transform to the FPE yields a first-order equation for the characteristic function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e340" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>Applying the respective Fourier transform to the FPE yields a first-order equation for the characteristic function <italic>Φ</italic>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e341"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e341" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(39)</label></disp-formula>The initial condition can be derived from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e326">Eq.(33)</xref> and reads<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e342"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e342" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(40)</label></disp-formula>To solve <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e341">Eq.(39)</xref>, it is useful to make the ansatz<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e343"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e343" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(41)</label></disp-formula>which after insertion into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e341">Eq.(39)</xref> yields<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e344"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e344" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(42)</label></disp-formula>This equation can be solved by the method of characteristics. Using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e339">Eq.(38)</xref>, the final result reads (with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e345" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>)<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e346"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e346" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(43)</label></disp-formula>where the functions <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e347" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e348" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e349" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are given by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e350"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e350" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(44)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e351"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e351" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(45)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e352"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e352" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(46)</label></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e353"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e353" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(47)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>For stochastic oscillations with a high quality factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e354" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, these expressions can be simplified. In this case, the damped and undamped oscillation frequencies are approximately the same, i.e. we can set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e355" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Assuming furthermore, that the correlation time of the OUP is much smaller than the mean ISI, i.e. if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e356" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we can neglect the exponentials <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e357" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, resulting finally in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e029">Eqs. (6</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e032">9</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c2">
<title>Moments of the <italic>n</italic>th-order interval</title>
<p>To compute the <italic>n</italic>th-order variance, we consider the Laplace transform of the <italic>n</italic>th-order interval density<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e358"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e358" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(48)</label></disp-formula>Knowing this function the moments can be generated by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e359"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e359" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(49)</label></disp-formula>The Laplace transform can be derived from the function<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e360"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e360" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(50)</label></disp-formula>In fact, from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e331">Eq.(34)</xref> we find that<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e361"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e361" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(51)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Applying the transformation (50) to the FPE (37) leads to an equation for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e362" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e363"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e363" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(52)</label></disp-formula>Here, the function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e364" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> arises from the initial condition <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e326">Eq.(33)</xref> and is given by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e365"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e365" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(53)</label></disp-formula><xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e363">Eq.(52)</xref> is difficult to solve, because of the mixed derivatives on the right-hand-side. For weak noise, however, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e366" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a small parameter and perturbation theory can be applied. To this end, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e367" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is written as a power series in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e368" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, i.e. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e369" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Substituting this expansion into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e363">Eq.(52)</xref> and solving order by order, yields an approximation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e370" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for weak noise. Using further <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e359">Eq.(49)</xref>, we obtain in the leading order the <italic>n</italic>th-order variance<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e371"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e371" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(54)</label></disp-formula>where<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e372"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e372" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(55)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e373"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e373" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(56)</label></disp-formula>For <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e374" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we find the squared CV in leading order of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e375" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (cf. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e259">Eq.(19)</xref>):<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e376"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e376" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(57)</label></disp-formula>Again, for a high quality factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e377" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, one can set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e378" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which yields<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e379"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e379" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(58)</label></disp-formula>Furthermore, if <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e380" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the term <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e381" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be neglected in the first term of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e379">Eq.(58)</xref> leading to the simplified formula <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e077">Eq.(11)</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c3">
<title>Serial correlation coefficient</title>
<p>Knowing the <italic>n</italic>th-order variance given above, the SCC can be computed using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e263">Eq.(22)</xref><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e382"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e382" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(59)</label></disp-formula>with<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e383"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e383" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(60)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e384"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e384" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(61)</label></disp-formula>and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e385" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e376">Eq.(57)</xref>. For small correlation time of the OUP, the first term can be neglected. Furthermore, if the quality factor of the harmonic noise is high, we can again use the approximation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e386" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Under these assumptions, the SCC is given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e087">Eq.(12)</xref> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Comparison of numerical simulations to theory for higher noise amplitudes</title>
<p>Here we briefly discuss the range of validity for our approximations. In general, we expect our theory to be valid whenever <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e387" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Let us recall that<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e388"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e388" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(62)</label></disp-formula>and, hence, we can increase <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e389" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> by increasing only <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e390" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, only <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e391" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, or both simultaneously. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g010">Fig. 10</xref>, we chose the first option, i.e. we vary only the harmonic noise strength. In the three panels of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g010">Fig. 10</xref>, we show the CV, the skewness, and the serial correlation coefficient at lag one as functions of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e392" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and for three selected values of the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e393" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Varying both <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e394" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e395" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the ratios <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e396" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or 1 yield very similar results (not shown).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003170-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of ISI statistics from numerical simulation and theory versus noise strength <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e397" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for different values of the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e398" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as indicated in the legends: coefficient of variation (A) with a double logarithmic plot of the same data in the inset, skewness of ISI density (B), and serial correlation coefficient at lag one (C).</title>
<p>Remaining parameters: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e399" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e400" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e401" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e402" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The plots illustrate that the theory works well for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e403" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, confirming its general validity. For the statistics of the single ISI (CV, skewness), only minor deviations are found even for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e404" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. This is not so for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e405" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which shows strong deviations for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e406" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and can even reverse its sign for a strong harmonic driving at frequency ratios <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e407" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e408" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. However, deviations of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e409" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between theory and simulations can be neglected for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e410" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e411" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which covers the experimentally relevant ranges of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e412" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e413" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for paddlefish electroreceptor afferents (data for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e414" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e415" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> look very similar but are not shown).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Data analysis for electroreceptor afferents</title>
<p>Data from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e416" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> afferents of 19 animals were from experiments at University of Missouri-St. Louis in 2000–2002, under an IACUC-approved animal use protocol (W01-13) there. The spontaneous discharges of electroreceptor afferents of paddlefish (<italic>Polyodon spathula</italic>) were recorded in <italic>in vivo</italic> preparations with procedures detailed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>. A fish was held at rest in a plastic chamber, maintained by a stream of oxygenated water. The water temperature was maintained at 22°C. No external electric field or any other relevant kinds of stimulation were applied while recording spontaneous afferent firing. Disturbance of spontaneous afferent firing by the turbulence of water flowing into the mouth of a fish was minimized by partitioning the chamber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1">[18]</xref>. Nonstationarity was further minimized by choosing segments of data in which a moving average of the afferent firing rate over a 10 s window fluctuated less than ±2% from the mean firing rate.</p>
<p>Analyses of spike time sequences from paddlefish electroreceptor afferents were performed using MATLAB's Signal Processing and Statistics Toolboxes. A spike train, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e417" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, was represented as a sequence of delta functions centered at spike times of an afferent, with the mean firing rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e418" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> subtracted: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e419" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For the purpose of estimating the power spectral density (PSD), each delta function was approximated by a rectangular pulse of width <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e420" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and height <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e421" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where the sampling interval <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e422" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was set to 1 ms. The PSD, defined as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e423" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e424" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the Fourier transform of the spike train, was estimated using the Welch periodogram method (function <italic>pwelch</italic> of MATLAB's Signal Processing Toolbox).</p>
<p>The following procedure was used to extract 4 parameters of the PIF model (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e425" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e426" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e427" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e428" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) from an experimental sequence of ISIs:</p>
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item>
<p>An original ISI sequence was normalized to have the mean ISI equal to 1, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e429" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e430" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the average of the sequence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e431" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> intervals)</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>The experimental coefficient of variation and SCCs were calculated according to (19) and (21).</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>The experimental SCCs were fitted using MATLAB function <italic>nlinfit</italic> with the formula (12), where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e432" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e433" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e434" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are fitting parameters. For the fitting, an initial value of the frequency ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e435" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was estimated from the experimental power spectrum density as the ratio of the peak frequencies of epithelial to afferent oscillations, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e436" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, see e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003170-g007">Fig. 7(C1)</xref>.</p>
</list-item><list-item>
<p>Finally, the intensity of OU noise, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e437" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, was calculated from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003170.e077">Eq.(11)</xref>, yielding<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003170.e438"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003170.e438" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(63)</label></disp-formula></p>
</list-item></list>
</sec></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Martin1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bozovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudspeth</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Spontaneous oscillation by hair bundles of the bullfrog's sacculus</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>11</issue>) <fpage>4533</fpage>–<lpage>4548</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Schmitz1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gloveli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Behr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dugladze</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinemann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Subthreshold membrane potential oscillations in neurons of deep layers of the entorhinal cortex</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>999</fpage>–<lpage>1004</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Donoghue1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanes</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatsopoulos</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaál</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Neural discharge and local field potential oscillations in primate motor cortex during voluntary movements</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Buzski1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Buzsáki G (2006) Rhythms of the Brain. New York, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Heiligenberg1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Heiligenberg W (1991) Neural Nets in Electric Fish. Cambridge: MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Knight1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of encoding in a population of neurons</article-title>. <source>J Gen Physiol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>734</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Longtin1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longtin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Stochastic resonance in neuron models</article-title>. <source>J Stat Phys</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Bulsara1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bulsara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Cooperative behavior in the periodically modulated Wiener process: Noise-induced complexity in a model neuron</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>4989</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Bulsara2"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bulsara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elston</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doering</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindenberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Cooperative behavior in periodically driven noisy integrate-and-fire models of neuronal dynamics</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>3958</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Plesser1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plesser</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geisel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Markov analysis of stochastic resonance in a periodically driven integrate-and-fire neuron</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>7008</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Lindner1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schimansky-Geier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Transmission of noise coded versus additive signals through a neuronal ensemble</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>2934</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Fourcaud1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fourcaud</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of the firing probability of noisy integrate-and-fire neurons</article-title>. <source>Neural Comp</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2057</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Burkitt1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkitt</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A review of the integrate-and-fire neuron model: II. inhomogeneous synaptic input and network properties</article-title>. <source>Biol Cyber</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Engel1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helbig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schimansky-Geier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neiman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Coherent stochastic oscillations enhance signal detection in spiking neurons</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>021919</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Lindner2"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Superposition of many independent spike trains is generally not a Poisson process</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>022901</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwalger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fisch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>How noisy adaptation of neurons shapes interspike interval histograms and correlations</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comp Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001026</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Fisch1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwalger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Slow adaptation currents contribute to spike-response variability in a sensory neuron</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>17332</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Neiman1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neiman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Two distinct types of noisy oscillators in electroreceptors of paddle fish</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Neiman2"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neiman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Models of stochastic biperiodic oscillations and extended serial correlations in electroreceptors of paddlefish</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>061915</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-SchimanskyGeier1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schimansky-Geier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zülicke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Harmonic noise: Effect on bistable systems</article-title>. <source>Z Phys B</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Risken1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Risken H (1984) The Fokker-Planck Equation. Berlin: Springer.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Gerstein1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mandelbrot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Random walk models for the spike activity of a single neuron</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Lindner3"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Interspike interval statistics of neurons driven by colored noise</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>022901</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Gitterman1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gitterman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Coherent stochastic resonance in the presence of a field</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>5708</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Abbott1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Vreeswijk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Asynchronous states in a network of pulse-coupled oscillators</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1483</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Rauch1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camera</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lüscher</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fusi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Neocortical pyramidal cells respond as integrate-and-fire neurons to in vivo-like input currents</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>1598</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Badel1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lefort</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brette</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CCH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dynamic I-V curves are reliable predictors of naturalistic pyramidal-neuron voltage traces</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>656</fpage>–<lpage>666</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Brunel1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sergi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Firing frequency of leaky integrate-and-fire neurons with synaptic current dynamics</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source> <volume>195</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Middleton1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chacron</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longtin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Firing statistics of a neuron model driven by long-range correlated noise</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>021920</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Rose1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hind</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Phase-locked response to low-frequency tones in single auditory nerve fibres of the squirrel monkey</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Chacron1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chacron</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longtin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Negative interspike interval correlations increase the neuronal capacity for encoding time-dependent stimuli</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>5328</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Lindner4"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwalger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Correlations in the sequence of residence times</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>210603</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Schwalger2"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwalger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Higher-order statistics of a bistable system driven by dichotomous colored noise</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>021121</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Neiman3"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neiman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Sensory coding in oscillatory electroreceptors of paddlefish</article-title>. <source>Chaos</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>047505</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Neiman4"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neiman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Identifying temporal codes in spontaneously active sensory neurons</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e27380</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Fuwape1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuwape</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neiman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Spontaneous firing statistics and information transfer in electroreceptors of paddlefish</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>051922</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Chacron2"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chacron</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longtin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Negative interspike interval correlations increase the neuronal capacity for encoding time-dependent stimuli</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>5328</fpage>–<lpage>5343</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Chacron3"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chacron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Electroreceptor neuron dynamics shape information transmission</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Benda1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longtin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Spike-frequency adaptation separates transient communication signals from background oscillations</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2312</fpage>–<lpage>2321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Burns1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shapley</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Is gamma-band activity in the local field potential of v1 cortex a “clock” or filtered noise?</article-title> <source>J Neurosci</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>9658</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Traub1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Traub RD, Whittington MA (2010) Cortical oscillations in health and disease. Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Bruce1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Temporal variations in the pattern of breathing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Physiology</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1079</fpage>–<lpage>1087</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Wever1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wever</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Properties of human sleep-wake cycles: parameters of internally synchronized free-running rhythms</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Sack1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Auckley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carskadon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>K</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Circadian rhythm sleep disorders: part ii, advanced sleep phase disorder, delayed sleep phase disorder, free-running disorder, and irregular sleep-wake rhythm: an american academy of sleep medicine review</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1484</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Schfer1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurths</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Heartbeat synchronized with ventilation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>392</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003170-Gardiner1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gardiner CW (1985) Handbook of Stochastic Methods. Berlin: Springer-Verlag.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>