<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher>
            <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
         </publisher></journal-meta>
      <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLBI-RA-9020R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619</article-id><article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Research Article</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
               <subject>Microbiology/Immunity to Infections</subject>
               <subject>Microbiology/Innate Immunity</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tsetse Immune System Maturation Requires the Presence of Obligate
               Symbionts in Larvae</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Symbiosis and Immunity in the Tsetse
               Fly</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weiss</surname>
                  <given-names>Brian L.</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                  <sup>*</sup>
               </xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                  <given-names>Jingwen</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                  <given-names>Serap</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
            <addr-line>Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, Division of Epidemiology of
               Microbial Diseases, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut,
               United States of America</addr-line>
         </aff><contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Schneider</surname>
                  <given-names>David S.</given-names>
               </name>
               <role>Academic Editor</role>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Stanford University, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
            <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">brian.weiss@yale.edu</email></corresp>
            <fn fn-type="con">
               <p>The author(s) have made the following declarations about their contributions:
                  Conceived and designed the experiments: BLW SA. Performed the experiments: BLW JW.
                  Analyzed the data: BLW SA. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: BLW SA.
                  Wrote the paper: BLW SA.</p>
            </fn>
         <fn fn-type="conflict">
            <p>Serap Aksoy, coauthor on this manuscript, is also Editor-in-Chief of <italic>PLoS
                  Neglected Tropical Diseases.</italic></p>
         </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e1000619</elocation-id><history>
            <date date-type="received">
               <day>18</day>
               <month>8</month>
               <year>2010</year>
            </date>
            <date date-type="accepted">
               <day>11</day>
               <month>4</month>
               <year>2011</year>
            </date>
         </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Weiss et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
            terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
            distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source
            are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article ext-link-type="uri" id="related1" related-article-type="companion" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001070" xlink:type="simple">
            <article-title>Tsetse Flies Rely on Symbiotic <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> for
               Immune System Development</article-title>
         </related-article><abstract abstract-type="toc">
            <p>Tsetse harbors an obligate symbiont, <italic>Wigglesworthia glossinidia,</italic>
               that must be present during larval maturation for the fly's immune system to
               develop and function properly during adulthood.</p>
         </abstract><abstract>
            <p>Beneficial microbial symbionts serve important functions within their hosts,
               including dietary supplementation and maintenance of immune system homeostasis.
               Little is known about the mechanisms that enable these bacteria to induce specific
               host phenotypes during development and into adulthood. Here we used the tsetse fly,
                  <italic>Glossina morsitans</italic>, and its obligate mutualist,
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia glossinidia</italic>, to investigate the co-evolutionary
               adaptations that influence the development of host physiological processes.
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is maternally transmitted to tsetse's
               intrauterine larvae through milk gland secretions. We can produce flies that lack
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>
                  (<italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>) yet retain their other
               symbiotic microbes. Such offspring give rise to adults that exhibit a largely normal
               phenotype, with the exception being that they are reproductively sterile. Our results
               indicate that when reared under normal environmental conditions
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults are also
               immuno-compromised and highly susceptible to hemocoelic <italic>E. coli</italic>
               infections while age-matched wild-type individuals are refractory. Adults that lack
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> during larval development exhibit exceptionally
               compromised cellular and humoral immune responses following microbial challenge,
               including reduced expression of genes that encode antimicrobial peptides
                  (<italic>cecropin</italic> and <italic>attacin</italic>), hemocyte-mediated
               processes (<italic>thioester-containing proteins 2</italic> and <italic>4</italic>
               and <italic>prophenoloxidase</italic>), and signal-mediating molecules
                  (<italic>inducible nitric oxide synthase</italic>). Furthermore,
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults harbor a reduced
               population of sessile and circulating hemocytes, a phenomenon that likely results
               from a significant decrease in larval expression of <italic>serpent</italic> and
                  <italic>lozenge</italic>, both of which are associated with the process of early
               hemocyte differentiation. Our results demonstrate that
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> must be present during the development of immature
               progeny in order for the immune system to function properly in adult tsetse. This
               phenomenon provides evidence of yet another important physiological adaptation that
               further anchors the obligate symbiosis between tsetse and
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>.</p>
         </abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary">
            <title>Author Summary</title>
            <p>Beneficial bacterial symbionts, which are ubiquitous in nature, are often
               characterized by the extent to which they interact with the host. In the case of
               mutualistic symbioses, both partners benefit so that each one can inhabit diverse
               ecological niches where neither could survive on its own. Unfortunately, little is
               known about the functional mechanisms that underlie mutualistic relationships.
               Insects represent a group of advanced multi-cellular organisms that harbor
               well-documented symbiotic associations. One such insect, the tsetse fly, harbors a
               maternally transmitted bacterial mutualist called <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>
               that provides its host with essential metabolites missing from its vertebrate
               blood-specific diet. In this study, we further examine the relationship between
               tsetse and <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> by investigating the interaction between
               this bacterium and its host's immune system. We have found that when
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is absent from tsetse during the maturation of
               immature larval stages, subsequent adults are characterized by an underdeveloped
               cellular immune system and thus highly susceptible to infection with a normally
               non-pathogenic foreign microbe. These findings represent an additional adaptation
               that further anchors the steadfast relationship shared between tsetse and its
               obligate symbiont.</p>
         </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was generously funded by grants to S.A. from the NIAID AI051584, NIGMS
               069449 and Ambrose Monell Foundation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.monellvetlesen.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.monellvetlesen.org/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study
               design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the
               manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
            <page-count count="12"/>
         </counts></article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s1">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Bacteria comprise the most abundant and diverse life form on earth. The ubiquity of
            bacteria means they have colonized virtually every ecological niche, including
            habitation within more evolutionarily sophisticated multi-cellular animals. Co-evolution
            over millions of years has provided an opportunity for beneficial symbiotic associations
            to develop between phylogenetically distant taxa. Such affiliations are often
            mutualistic, meaning both partners benefit so that each can successfully inhabit diverse
            environments that neither could survive in on its own <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Moran1">[1]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Wernegreen1">[2]</xref>. Deciphering the mutualistic
            relationships between prokaryotic bacteria and multi-cellular eukaryotic animals is a
            rapidly advancing field of research.</p>
         <p>Performing detailed investigations into the relationships between symbiotic bacteria and
            higher eukaryotes often involves costly and complex procedures. However, insects have
            well-documented symbioses that are attractive to study because they have relatively
            short generation times and are easy and less costly to rear. One insect that harbors
            multiple symbionts is the tsetse fly, <italic>Glossina morsitans</italic>. These
            microbes include the commensal <italic>Sodalis</italic>, the parasite
               <italic>Wolbachia</italic>, and the obligate mutualist <italic>Wigglesworthia
               glossinidia</italic>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Aksoy1">[3]</xref>. Molecular
            phylogenetic analysis indicates that tsetse's symbiosis with
               <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is ancient, dating back 50–80 million years
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Chen1">[4]</xref>. The concordant
            nature of tsetse's obligate association with <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> has
            driven the co-evolution of biological adaptations that are beneficial to both partners.
            For example, the localization of <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> cells within host
            bacteriocytes provides a protective and metabolically favorable niche for this bacterium
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Akman1">[5]</xref>. In return
            tsetse derives benefit from <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> in at least two distinct
            ways. First, tsetse feeds exclusively on vertebrate blood, which is deficient in
            vitamins essential for survival. In accordance, a large proportion of
               <italic>Wigglesworthia's</italic> streamlined (700 kB) genome encodes vitamin
            biosynthesis pathways that presumably supplement tsetse's restricted diet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Akman1">[5]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Nogge1">[6]</xref>. Second, more recent studies indicate
            that <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> may serve an immunologic role in tsetse. These
            flies are the sole vector of pathogenic African trypanosomes, the causative agent of
            sleeping sickness in humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Aksoy2">[7]</xref>. In laboratory experiments infection with immunogenic
            trypanosomes results in a decrease in tsetse fecundity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Hu1">[8]</xref>. Furthermore, parasite infection
            prevalence is higher in flies that lack <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> when compared to
            age-matched wild-type (WT) individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Pais1">[9]</xref>. <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is thought to influence
            tsetse's vectorial competence by modulating its host's humoral immune system
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Wang1">[10]</xref>. Thus, by
            preventing energetically costly parasite infections, this obligate symbiont may
            indirectly benefit the reproductive fitness of tsetse.</p>
         <p>Symbiotic bacteria are rapidly gaining recognition for their important contributions to
            host development and immunity. The most well-known example of this type of interaction
            involves the mammalian microbiome, which modulates gut development during early
            postnatal life and subsequently shapes our mucosal and systemic immune systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Hooper1">[11]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Macpherson1">[12]</xref>. Symbionts also
            serve similar functions in invertebrate hosts. For example, light organ morphogenesis in
            juvenile bobtail squid (<italic>Euprymna scolopes</italic>) initiates only after
            symbiotic <italic>Vibrio fischeri</italic> cells have stably colonized this tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Koropatnick1">[13]</xref>. The pea aphid,
               <italic>Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic>, harbors a secondary symbiont,
               <italic>Hamiltonella defensa</italic>, which can be infected with a lysogenic
            bacteriophage (<italic>A. pisum</italic> secondary endosymbiont; APSE). <italic>A.
               pisum</italic> that harbor both <italic>H. defensa</italic> and APSE are protected
            from being consumed by a parasitic wasp larvae through the action of phage-encoded
            toxins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Oliver1">[14]</xref>.</p>
         <p>To the best of our knowledge no evidence exists that demonstrates insect symbionts can
            confer an impending protective phenotype in their adult host by directing immune system
            development during immature stages. In the present study we investigate the mechanism by
            which <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> contributes to the development and function of
            cellular and humoral immune responses in adult tsetse. Our results show that the
            maturation and normal function of adult cellular immune responses in tsetse are severely
            compromised when <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is absent during larval development.
            This study reveals an important new facet that further anchors the obligate relationship
            between tsetse and <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> and may serve as a useful model to
            understand the highly integrated and dynamic relationship between hosts and their
            beneficial bacterial fauna.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2">
         <title>Results</title>
         <sec id="s2a">
            <title>Tsetse's Susceptibility to <italic>E. coli</italic> Infection Is Dependent
               Upon Age and Symbiotic Status</title>
            <p>Insects are normally capable of mounting an immune response that combats infection
               with various groups of bacteria. Interestingly, in comparison to
                  <italic>Drosophila</italic>, tsetse flies are uniquely susceptible to septic
               infection with 10<sup>3</sup> colony-forming units (CFU) of normally non-pathogenic
                  <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<italic>E. coli</italic>) K12 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Weiss1">[15]</xref>. In the present
               study we further investigated tsetse's unique susceptibility to <italic>E.
                  coli</italic> infection by subjecting wild-type
               (<italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>) and adults from two age groups to hemocoelic
               infections with varying quantities of <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. Three-day-old
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> individuals (flies from this age group are
               hereafter referred to as “young”) were highly susceptible to this
               treatment, as 10<sup>3</sup> CFU resulted in the death of all flies by 8 d
               post-infection (dpi; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure
                  1A</xref>, top graph). In contrast, 77% and 55% of 8-d-old WT
               individuals (flies 8 d old and older are hereafter referred to as
               “mature”) survived for 14 dpi with 10<sup>3</sup> and 10<sup>6</sup> CFU
               of <italic>E. coli</italic> K12, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1A</xref>, middle graph).</p>
            <fig id="pbio-1000619-g001" position="float">
               <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g001</object-id>
               <label>Figure 1</label>
               <caption>
                  <title>Host survival correlates with symbiont status following septic infection
                     with <italic>E. coli</italic> K12.</title>
                  <p>(A) The effects of age and symbiont status on the survival of tsetse following
                     systemic infection with <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. Mature adult
                           <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm-</sup></italic> flies were significantly more
                     susceptible to infection with 10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>E. coli</italic>
                     than were their wild-type counterparts (bottom and middle panels;
                        <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001). (B)
                           <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> flies
                     harbored <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> during immature development but lacked
                     the bacteria as mature adults. (C)
                           <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> adults were
                     infected with tetracycline resistant <italic>E. coli</italic> 1 d after their
                     last antibiotic-supplemented blood meal. Unlike their counterparts that lacked
                        <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> throughout immature development,
                        <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> was able to
                     survive infection with <italic>E. coli</italic>. No significant difference in
                     survival was observed between mature adult <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>
                     versus <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> adults
                     infected with 10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1A</xref> middle panel and
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1C</xref>;
                        <italic>p</italic>  = 0.07). (D) Relative
                        <italic>Sodalis</italic> and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> densities in
                     40-d-old <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults
                        (<italic>n</italic>  = 5 of each) were normalized
                     against host <italic>β-tubulin</italic> copy number. (E) Analysis of
                     bacterial 16s rRNA clone libraries indicates that
                        <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> larvae harbored
                        <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>, <italic>Sodalis</italic>, and
                        <italic>Wolbachia</italic>, while their counterparts from ampicillin treated
                     females harbored only <italic>Sodalis</italic> and <italic>Wolbachia</italic>.
                     No other bacteria were identified from either fly line. (F) Average number
                     (±SEM) of rec<italic>E. coli</italic><sub>pIL</sub> per tsetse strain
                     over time (<italic>n</italic>  = 3 individuals per strain
                     per time point) following septic infection with 10<sup>3</sup> CFU of bacteria.
                     Values shown in red represent lethal infections.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>We demonstrated previously that feeding pregnant female tsetse the antibiotic
               ampicillin results in the generation offspring that lack
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>
                  (<italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>) but still harbor
                  <italic>Sodalis</italic>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Pais1">[9]</xref> and presumably
                  <italic>Wolbachia</italic>. In the present study we determined the survival
               outcome of mature <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> inoculated
               with 10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>E. coli</italic> K12 (the dose required to kill
               ∼50% of mature WT flies; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1A</xref>, middle graph). In comparison to age-matched WT tsetse,
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies were highly
               susceptible to this infection. In fact, at 14 dpi, only 1% of these
               individuals remained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1A</xref>,
               bottom graph). We reasoned that the dramatic susceptibility of mature
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies to infection with
                  <italic>E. coli</italic> could result from one of two scenarios. In the first
               scenario <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> may directly contribute to the adult immune
               response to a foreign micro-organism. In the second scenario, the absence of
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> during larvagensis may give rise to
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults with compromised
               immune functions. To determine if the first scenario is correct we treated mature WT
               tsetse with the antibiotic tetracycline to eliminate all of their microbiota,
               including bacteriome-associated <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1B</xref>), and subsequently challenged these adult
               flies (<italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup>) with
                  10<sup>6</sup> CFU of tetracycline resistant <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. We
               found that, similar to their WT counterparts (<italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>;
                  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1A</xref>, middle panel),
               about 70% of <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup>
               individuals survived this infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). Conversely,
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults were highly
               susceptible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1A</xref>, bottom
               graph). This result suggests that when <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is absent from
               tsetse during larval development subsequent adults are severely
               immuno-compromised.</p>
            <p>We demonstrated that when larval tsetse lacks exposure to
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> in utero their immune system is highly compromised
               during adulthood. This finding does not exclude the possibility that treatment of
               female flies with ampicillin to produce
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> offspring induces
               perturbations in other constituents of tsetse's microbiota. Because
               tsetse's other two known endosymbionts, <italic>Sodalis</italic> and
                  <italic>Wolbachia</italic>, are present at similar densities in
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1D</xref>), we looked for the presence of
               uncharacterized endosymbionts or digestive tract-associated microbes that are
               potentially passed on to developing intra-uterine larvae where they subsequently
               impact immunity. We generated a clone library containing 16s rRNA gene sequences PCR
               amplified from 3<sup>rd</sup> instar
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> larvae and then sequenced multiple clones from
               each tsetse line. Our results indicate that the proportion of
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>, <italic>Sodalis</italic>, and
                  <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in 3<sup>rd</sup> instar
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> larvae is 19%, 75%, and 6%,
               respectively. As expected no <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> 16s rRNA sequences were
               present in <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> larvae, and the
               proportion of <italic>Sodalis</italic> and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> sequences
               present was 71% and 29%, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1E</xref>). No uncharacterized endosymbionts or
               gut-associated environmental microbes were present in any sample. Taken together,
               these results suggest that the presence of <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>
               specifically is responsible for enabling immune system maturation in WT tsetse.</p>
            <p>Our host survival curves indicate that mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> can survive
               infection with <italic>E. coli</italic> while young <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>
               and mature <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> perish. To determine
               a cause for the variation in survival we observed between the four groups following
               infection with <italic>E. coli</italic>, we monitored bacterial growth dynamics over
               the course of the experiment in each group. Bacterial number within mature
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                     <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> peaked at
                  3.8×10<sup>4</sup> and 1.9×10<sup>4</sup>
               <italic>E. coli</italic>, respectively, over the 2-wk period, indicating that these
               groups appeared able to control their infections. In contrast, <italic>E.
                  coli</italic> increased exponentially in young <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>
               and mature <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> and reached a maximum
               density at 6 dpi of 4.2×10<sup>6</sup> and 8.8×10<sup>6</sup>,
               respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1F</xref>). These
               results implicate bacterial sepsis as the cause of high mortality observed in young
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and mature
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>. All of the above-mentioned
               results taken together indicate that mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> are
               considerably more resistant to infection with a foreign microbe than are their
               younger counterparts. Furthermore, tsetse's obligate mutualist,
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>, must be present during the development of
               immature stages so that mature adults are able to overcome infection with <italic>E.
                  coli</italic>.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s2b">
            <title>Expression of Immunity-Related Genes in Adult Tsetse Varies Depending on Symbiont
               Status</title>
            <p>To understand the basis of the compromised immunity we observed in mature
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies, we evaluated the
               expression profile of a set of immunity-related genes from age-matched mature adult
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies that were either
               uninfected or 3 dpi with <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. We included the antimicrobial
               peptides (AMPs) <italic>attacin</italic>, <italic>cecropin</italic>, and
                  <italic>defensin</italic>, which distinctly target gram-negative
                  (<italic>attacin</italic> and <italic>cecropin</italic>) and gram-positive
               bacteria (<italic>defensin</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Hoffmann1">[16]</xref>. Our analysis also included
               thioester-containing proteins (<italic>tep</italic>2 and <italic>tep4</italic>),
               prophenoloxidase (<italic>PPO</italic>), and inducible nitric oxide synthase
                  (<italic>iNOS</italic>). In insects TEPs likely function as pathogen-specific
               opsonins that bind to bacteria or parasites and promote their
               phagocytosis/encapsulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Blandin1">[17]</xref>, while PPO initiates a proteolytic cascade that results in
               melanin deposition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Cerenius1">[18]</xref>. iNOS catalyzes synthesis of the signaling molecule nitric
               oxide (NO), which plays a role in humoral and cellular immunity in Anopheline
               mosquitoes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Dimopoulos1">[19]</xref>, reduvid bugs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Whitten1">[20]</xref>, and <italic>Drosophila</italic>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Foley1">[21]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Carton1">[22]</xref> by inducing AMP
               expression and recruiting hemocytes to the site of infection.</p>
            <p>Our expression results indicate that symbiont status plays little or no role in the
               expression of immunity-related genes in uninfected adults. In fact, with the
               exception of the AMP <italic>defensin</italic>, no significant differences in
               immunity-related gene expression between mature uninfected
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). However, we observed a considerably
               different profile of immunity-related gene expression when these different fly
               strains were infected with <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. Under these circumstances,
               all of the genes evaluated (with the exception of defensin) were expressed at
               significantly higher levels in <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> compared to
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Particular striking was
               the fact that the induction of pathways associated with cellular immunity, such as
               pathogen recognition (<italic>tep</italic>2 and <italic>tep</italic>4) and
               melanization (<italic>PPO</italic>), were significantly compromised in mature
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults. The absence of a
               robust cellular immune response is likely the cause of high mortality among these
               individuals following <italic>E. coli</italic> infection. This analysis indicates
               that <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> must be present during the development of
               immature tsetse in order for immune-related genes to subsequently be expressed in
               mature <italic>E. coli</italic>–infected adults.</p>
            <fig id="pbio-1000619-g002" position="float">
               <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g002</object-id>
               <label>Figure 2</label>
               <caption>
                  <title>The effect of symbiont status on the expression of immunity-related genes
                     in adult tsetse.</title>
                  <p>(A) Target gene expression in uninfected <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                           <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults is indicated
                     relative to the constitutively expressed tsetse β-tubulin gene. (B)
                     Fold-change in the expression of immunity-related genes in
                        <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> tsetse 3 dpi with
                        <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. All values for both tsetse strains are
                     represented as a fraction of average normalized gene expression levels in
                     bacteria-infected flies relative to expression levels in PBS-injected controls.
                     In (A) and (B), quantitative measurements were performed on three biological
                     samples in duplicate. Values are represented as means (±SEM). *
                        <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, ** <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.005
                     (Student's <italic>t</italic>-test).</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s2c">
            <title>Hemocytes Play an Integral Role in Controlling <italic>E. coli</italic> Infection
               Outcomes in Tsetse</title>
            <p>Our analysis of immunity-related gene expression in tsetse suggests that cellular
               immune pathway functions in adult tsetse are particularly compromised when
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is absent during immature development. The most
               prominent cellular immune mechanisms include melanization and phagocytosis. These
               processes, which ultimately result in the removal of foreign invaders in
                  <italic>Drosophila</italic>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Matova1">[23]</xref> and <italic>A.
                  aegypti</italic>
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Hillyer1">[24]</xref>, both arise
               from distinct crystal cell and plasmatocyte hemocyte lineages, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Meister1">[25]</xref>.</p>
            <p>We investigated the role hemocytes might play in determining the susceptible
               phenotype we observed in tsetse following infection with <italic>E. coli</italic>. We
               infected mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> individuals with GFP-expressing
                  <italic>E. coli</italic> and were able to observe that hemocytes had engulfed a
               large number of the introduced cells by 12 hpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). We next inhibited phagocytosis by
               introducing blue fluorescent microspheres directly into tsetse's hemocoel and 12
               h later infected the bead-treated individuals with GFP-expressing <italic>E.
                  coli</italic>. Microscopic inspection of hemocytes harvested 12 hpi with
                  <italic>E. coli</italic> revealed the presence of internalized microspheres and
               the absence of engulfed <italic>E. coli</italic>. This observation indicated that we
               were successful in blocking hemocyte phagocytosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). We subsequently maintained our
               microsphere-injected tsetse for 2 wk with the intention of determining the impact of
               impaired phagocytosis on host survival outcome. Mature
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> flies exhibiting impaired phagocytosis were
               highly susceptible to infection with both 1×10<sup>3</sup> and
                  1×10<sup>6</sup>
               <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. In fact, by day 12 post-infection, all of these flies
               had perished regardless of the initial dose used for infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). This observation contrasts starkly with
               infection outcome in mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> that exhibit normally
               functioning hemocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure 1A</xref>,
               middle graph). Our results suggest that defects in phagocytosis severely compromise
               the ability of these tsetse flies to overcome bacterial infection.</p>
            <fig id="pbio-1000619-g003" position="float">
               <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g003</object-id>
               <label>Figure 3</label>
               <caption>
                  <title>Hemocyte-mediated phagocytosis is a critical component of tsetse's
                     immune response.</title>
                  <p>(A) 8-d-old <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> were subjected to septic
                     infection with GFP-expressing <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. Twelve hours
                     post-infection hemolymph was collected, fixed on glass slides using 2%
                     paraformaldehyde, and microscopically examined for the presence of
                     hemocyte-engulfed bacterial cells. Scale bar  = 10
                     µm. (B) The process of hemocyte-mediated phagocytosis in tsetse was
                     blocked by micro-injecting polystyrene beads into the hemocoel of 8-d-old WT
                     individuals. In consecutive 12 h intervals following bead injection, flies were
                     infected with GFP-expressing <italic>E. coli</italic> K12 and then hemolymph
                     was collected and fixed as described above. Hemocytes appear to have engulfed
                     the beads, thus prohibiting the subsequent uptake of bacterial cells. The inset
                     in each panel shows a higher magnification image of one hemocyte, which is
                     identified by a white triangle in the left-most panel. Scale bar
                      = 20 μm. (C) Tsetse flies that harbor hemocytes
                     incapable of engulfing <italic>E. coli</italic> are susceptible to septic
                     infection with this bacterium while their wild-type counterparts are not. The
                     susceptible phenotype is exhibited regardless of whether phagocytosis-inhibited
                     tsetse were inoculated with 10<sup>3</sup> or 10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>E.
                        coli</italic>. Beads alone had no effect on tsetse mortality. No significant
                     difference existed in survival outcome between mature
                        <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> phagocytosis inhibited flies infected with
                        10<sup>3</sup> versus 10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>E. coli</italic>
                        (<italic>p</italic>  = 0.47, log-rank analysis).
                     Furthermore, no significant difference was present between mature
                           <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies with
                     uninhibited hemocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g001">Figure
                        1A</xref>, bottom panel) and mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>
                     phagocytosis inhibited flies (<italic>p</italic>  = 0.11)
                     infected with 10<sup>6</sup> CFU of <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>A notable result of our immunity-related gene expression analysis was a 37-fold
               decrease in <italic>PPO</italic> levels in
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies. This enzyme is an
               essential component of the melanization pathway, and its expression ultimately
               results in host wound healing and the melanization, encapsulation, and subsequent
               removal of foreign microorganisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Galko1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Ayres1">[28]</xref>. In conjunction with the remarkable variation in
                  <italic>PPO</italic> expression observed between <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>
               and <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>, we were also able to
               visually observe the absence of a melanization response to <italic>E. coli</italic>
               infection in flies lacking <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>. In fact, 30 min
               post-injection with <italic>E. coli</italic>, hemolymph was still actively exuding
               from the inoculation wound of <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>
               flies. Conversely, in WT individuals no hemolymph was detectable and melanin was
               deposited at the wound site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g004">Figure
                  4</xref>). These results further suggest that hemocyte-mediated cellular immunity
               provides an imperative defense against the establishment of bacterial infections in
               tsetse's hemocoel. Furthermore, the absence of this response in
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> individuals was likely
               responsible for the compromised host survival phenotype we observed following
               infection with <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p>
            <fig id="pbio-1000619-g004" position="float">
               <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g004</object-id>
               <label>Figure 4</label>
               <caption>
                  <title>The effect of symbiont status on melanization in tsetse.</title>
                  <p>Mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> tsetse
                        (<italic>n</italic>  = 10 of each strain) were
                     intra-thoracically inoculated with 1×10<sup>3</sup>
                     <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. Thirty minutes post-inoculation the wound site on
                     individuals from each strain was inspected microscopically for the presence of
                     hemolymph clotting and melanin deposition. Thirty minutes post-inoculation,
                     neither hemolymph clotting nor melanin were observed at the wound site of
                           <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> individuals
                     (indicated by a red arrow). In contrast, within the same amount of time,
                     hemolymph no longer exuded from the wound of WT flies and melanin was present
                     surrounding the site (indicted by a white arrow).</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s2d">
            <title>Symbiotic Bacteria Impact the Maturation of Tsetse's Cellular Immune
               Response During Development</title>
            <p>We observed that young <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> were markedly more
               susceptible to infection with <italic>E. coli</italic> K12 than were their mature
               counterparts. Furthermore, symbiont status also altered infection outcome, as mature
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> perished following
                  <italic>E. coli</italic> infection while age-matched WT individuals survived.
               These differential infection outcomes appeared to result from disparities in cellular
               immune system function between the different tsetse lines we examined. Based on these
               observations we hypothesized that the obligate mutualist
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> plays a crucial role in regulating the development
               of cellular immunity in tsetse during immature stages. To test this hypothesis we
               quantified the number of circulating and sessile hemocytes present in young and
               mature adult <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and mature adult
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>. Our results indicate that
               a 1.4-fold increase in circulating hemocyte number occurs between day 3 and day 8 in
               WT tsetse, while no significant change in circulating hemocyte number was observed
               between young and mature <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). Interestingly, mature
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults harbored 3.4× more circulating
               hemocytes than did mature <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults
                  (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). We also looked at
               sessile hemocyte abundance as a further indicator of
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia's</italic> impact on the development of cellular
               immunity in tsetse. In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, this hemocyte subtype
               concentrates in large quantities around the anterior end of the fly's dorsal
               vessel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-ElrodErickson1">[29]</xref>.
               Thus, we indirectly quantified sessile hemocyte abundance immediately adjacent to the
               anterior-most chamber of tsetse's dorsal vessel by measuring the fluorescent
               emission of microspheres that were found engulfed in this region. Young
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults engulfed 1.2× more microspheres
               than their mature counterparts and 15.7× more than mature
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults. Furthermore,
               mature WT adults engulfed 13.2× more microspheres than did age-matched
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g005">Figure 5B</xref>).</p>
            <fig id="pbio-1000619-g005" position="float">
               <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g005</object-id>
               <label>Figure 5</label>
               <caption>
                  <title>The effect of age and symbiont status on the development of tsetse's
                     cellular immune response.</title>
                  <p>(A) Number of hemocytes per µl of hemolymph in young (3 d) and mature (8
                     d) <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>-</sup> tsetse (<italic>n</italic>
                      = 5 individuals from each tsetse strain at both time
                     points). (B) Quantitative analysis of sessile hemocyte abundance in young and
                     mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and mature
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>-</sup> tsetse (<italic>n</italic>
                      = 4 individuals from each tsetse strain and age point).
                     All tsetse strains tested were subjected to hemocoelic injection with blue
                     fluorescent microspheres. Twelve hours post-injection, flies were dissected to
                     reveal tsetse's heart. The left-most panel is a Brightfield image of the
                     three chambers that make up the dorsal vessel (DV; scale bar
                      = 350 µm). The anterior-most chamber is indicated
                     within a white circle. The three remaining panels are close-ups of the anterior
                     chamber (scale bar for all 3 panels  = 80 µm),
                     visualized by excitation with UV light (365/415 nm). Relative fluorescence per
                     tsetse group was determined using ImageJ software. (C) The presence of
                        <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> affects the expression of genes involved in
                     hemocyte differentiation in immature larval tsetse. Target gene expression in
                        <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> larval instars
                     1–3 is indicated relative to the constitutively expressed tsetse
                     β-tubulin gene. Quantitative measurements were performed on three
                     biological samples in duplicate. All values in this figure are represented as
                     means (±SEM). * <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05, **
                        <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.005 (Student' <italic>t</italic>-test).</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Our results demonstrate that <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> must be present during
               the development of immature tsetse in order for cellular immunity to develop and
               function properly in adults. Thus, we speculate that the absence of hemocytes in
               adult tsetse should reflect a lack of blood cell differentiation during the
               development of immature stages. In <italic>Drosophila</italic> the process of blood
               cell differentiation, or hematopoiesis, begins in the embryo and proceeds through all
               larval stages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Evans1">[30]</xref>.
               During <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryogenesis early hematopoiesis can be
               distinguished by the expression of the zinc finger transcription factor
               “Serpent.” Subsequently, another transcription factor,
               “Lozenge,” directs the differentiation of
               <italic>serpent</italic>-expressing precursor cells into a specific lineage of
               hemocytes called crystal cells. To address the relationship between the presence of
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> and early hematopoiesis in tsetse, we used qPCR to
               evaluate the relative number of <italic>serpent</italic> and <italic>lozenge</italic>
               transcripts present in 1<sup>st</sup>, 2<sup>nd</sup>, and 3<sup>rd</sup> instar
               larvae dissected from pregnant <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                     <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> females. Larval instars
               L1, L2, and L3 from WT females expressed 1.7, 2.1, and 1.9 times more
                  <italic>serpent</italic> transcripts, and 4, 4.4, and 3.9 times more
                  <italic>lozenge</italic> transcripts, respectively, than did their counterparts
               from females that lacked <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). This observed attenuated expression of
               both <italic>serpent</italic> and <italic>lozenge</italic> may account for the
               depleted hemocyte population, and compromised cellular immune function, we observed
               in adult <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> individuals.</p>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>In the present study we demonstrate that <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is intimately
            involved in regulating the maturation and function of tsetse's cellular immune
            system during immature larval development. We present a model that links the presence of
               <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> in larval progeny with host immune system maturation
            during development and the subsequent ability of adult tsetse to overcome infection with
            foreign microbes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1000619-g006">Figure 6</xref>).
            Obligate symbioses between intracellular bacteria and multi-cellular eukaryotes
            represent millions of years of co-evolution during which time both partners have adapted
            to increase each other's overall fitness. The association between tsetse and
               <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is an example of this reciprocal relationship in that
            neither organism can survive in the absence of the other.</p>
         <fig id="pbio-1000619-g006" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g006</object-id>
            <label>Figure 6</label>
            <caption>
               <title><italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> modulates the development and function of
                  tsetse's immune system.</title>
               <p>Through a currently unknown mechanism, the presence of
                     <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> in <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> larvae
                  stimulates hemocyte differentiation in a specialized organ that is homologous to
                     <italic>Drosophila's</italic> lymph gland. Upon metamorphosis, specialized
                  hemocyte subtypes are released from the lymph gland and carried over in a
                  functional state to the adult. In the absence of <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>,
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> larvae produce
                  significantly less hemocytes than their WT counterparts. Several innate immunity
                  pathways are activated upon inoculation of <italic>E. coli</italic> into the
                  hemocoel of mature adult <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>. Tsetse's
                  preliminary line of defense against <italic>E. coli</italic> infection likely
                  involves melanization at the wound site. This process is initiated by localized
                  crystal cells, which instigate the melanization cascade by secreting
                  prophenoloxidase (PPO) into the hemolymph. Pathogens that circumvent the wound
                  site then encounter phagocyte-mediated cellular and humoral immune responses.
                  Soluble TEPs likely opsonize bacterial cells, thus tagging them for engulfment by
                  phagocytes. Lysis of engulfed bacteria causes the release of bacterial
                  peptidoglycan PGN that subsequently stimulates the production of AMPs by the fat
                  body. AMPs, which are also generated by hemocytes, are then secreted into the
                  hemolymph where they further abrogate microbial proliferation. Hemocytes also
                  produce reactive oxygen intermediates, such as iNOS, that exhibit direct bacterial
                  toxicity and further stimulate humoral immunity. In the case of
                        <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults, incapacitated
                  hematopoiesis during larval stages results in severely compromised immunity that
                  renders these flies highly susceptible as adults to bacterial infection.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
         </fig>
         <p>We present several lines of evidence indicating that tsetse's resistance to
               <italic>E. coli</italic> positively correlates with fly age and symbiont infection
            status during juvenile stages. Specifically, our results signify that mature
               <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults are resistant to <italic>E. coli</italic>
            infection, while young <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults are susceptible. In
            contrast, both young and old adult flies that lack <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>
            throughout all developmental stages are killed by <italic>E. coli</italic> infections.
            Like their WT counterparts, <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> larvae
            acquire both <italic>Sodalis</italic> and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> while in utero
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Attardo1">[31]</xref>. Although the
            intrauterine larval environment is otherwise aseptic, adult
               <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> can be exposed to a wide range
            of environmental microbes during adulthood. However, neither the presence of other
            symbiotic bacteria (<italic>Sodalis</italic> and <italic>Wolbachia</italic>) in larvae,
            nor environmental microbes acquired during adulthood, appear to be sufficient to induce
            immunity in <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults. Additionally,
            we show that mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults treated with antibiotics to
            eliminate <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>
                  (<italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup>) remain resistant
            to <italic>E. coli</italic> infections. The resistant phenotype of
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> further signifies
            that obligate <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> is not directly responsible for the
            ability of mature adult <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> to overcome septic bacterial
            infection. Instead, it appears that <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>'s presence
            during the maturation of larval progeny stimulates the development of host immunity in
            adults.</p>
         <p>Our quantitative analysis of gene expression indicates that
               <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
               <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults exhibit no significant
            difference in the expression of genes that serve as hallmarks of humoral and cellular
            immunity in the absence of microbial challenge. However, following infection with
               <italic>E. coli</italic>, all pathways were significantly compromised in
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> versus
               <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults. The most notable discrepancy observed
            between the two tsetse lines involved the expression of
               <italic>prophenoloxidase</italic>. Following <italic>E. coli</italic> infection, the
            expression of this gene increased 37-fold in WT tsetse but remained virtually unchanged
            in individuals that lacked <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>. In WT insects, PPO, which is
            an inactive zymogen, is proteolytically cleaved to produce phenoloxidase upon mechanical
            injury or the presence of foreign pathogens. Phenoloxidase then facilitates the process
            of melanin deposition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Cerenius1">[18]</xref>. A functional melanotic pathway would likely increase
            tsetse's resistance to <italic>E. coli</italic> infection in several ways. First,
            sequestration of <italic>E. coli</italic> in a melanotic capsule at the site of
            inoculation would likely help prevent their dissemination into adjacent host tissues.
            This phenomenon has been observed in both the hawk moth, <italic>Manduca sexta</italic>,
            and <italic>Drosophila</italic> following infection with pathogenic bacteria
               (<italic>Photorhabdus luminescens</italic>) and parasitic wasp eggs, respectively
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Eleftherianos1">[32]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Rizki1">[33]</xref>. In both cases the
            lack of melanization at the wound site severely compromised the host's ability to
            subsequently overcome the foreign invader. Second, the melanization cascade results in
            the production of reactive oxygen intermediates that are directly toxic to foreign
            pathogens. In the flesh fly <italic>Sarcophaga peregrina</italic> and <italic>M.
               sexta</italic>, melanization intermediates such as DOPA exhibit direct antimicrobial
            activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Leem1">[34]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Zhao1">[35]</xref>. Finally, melanin at
            the site of inoculation expedites wound healing that could prevent the spread of
            secondary infections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Galko1">[26]</xref>.</p>
         <p>The <italic>E. coli</italic>–susceptible phenotype of mature
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults is likely reflective
            of their blood cell (hemocyte) deficit in comparison to <italic>E.
            coli</italic>–resistant WT flies. In <italic>Drosophila</italic>
            90%–95% of the total hemocyte population is composed of sessile and
            circulating plasmatocytes, which are a distinct hemocyte lineage predominantly
            responsible for engulfing and digesting foreign pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Lebestky1">[36]</xref>. The inability of mature
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> tsetse to survive infection
            with <italic>E. coli</italic> may result from their significantly reduced population of
            phagocytic hemocytes available to engulf bacteria injected into the hemocoel. In fact,
            by injecting polystyrene beads as a means of blocking this physiological process, we
            demonstrate that phagocytosis is a critical component of tsetse's ability to manage
            septic infection with <italic>E. coli</italic> in WT flies. Similarly, mutant
               <italic>Drosophila</italic> that contain a depleted plasmatocyte population, or have
            been injected with beads to prohibit phagocytosis, exhibit a remarkable susceptibility
            to a variety of gram positive and negative bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Charroux1">[37]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Pham1">[38]</xref>. Interestingly,
               <italic>Drosophila</italic> that lack functional plasmatocytes also exhibit a reduced
            capacity to activate humoral immune responses, further inhibiting their ability to fight
            bacterial infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-ElrodErickson1">[29]</xref>.</p>
         <p>In <italic>Drosophila</italic> the crystal cell hemocyte lineage controls the humoral
            melanization cascade via the release of PPO stored in large cytoplasmic inclusion bodies
               <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Evans1">[30]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Bidla1">[39]</xref>. In addition to the
            dramatic reduction in <italic>PPO</italic> expression in
               <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> tsetse, two further lines of
            evidence indicate that this fly strain harbors a significantly reduced population of
            hemocytes that function in a homologous manner to <italic>Drosophila</italic> crystal
            cells. First, <italic>lozenge</italic> expression in all three larval instars from
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> females is significantly
            lower than in their <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> counterparts. In
               <italic>Drosophila</italic> larval crystal cells fail to form in the absence of
               <italic>lozenge</italic> expression, yet the differentiation of other hemocyte types
            proceeds normally <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Lanot1">[40]</xref>.
            Second, we observed that hemocyte-deficient
               <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies were unable to produce a
            viable clot at the site of bacterial inoculation. In mutant <italic>Drosophila</italic>
            strains that lack crystal cells, PPO is absent from the hemolymph. Consequently, the
            melanization cascade fails to initiate and hard clots do not form at wound sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Bidla2">[41]</xref>.</p>
         <p>We discovered that young <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults harbor significantly
            less circulating hemocytes than do mature WT adults. This observation implies that
            circulating hemocyte number in adult WT tsetse increases as a function of age, although
            the specific mechanism underlying this process in tsetse is currently unknown. In adult
               <italic>Drosophila</italic> intact lymph glands are absent and no evidence exists for
            the de novo synthesis of hemocytes following metamorphosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Evans1">[30]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Lanot1">[40]</xref>. Interestingly, we did observe more
            subepidermal sessile hemocytes in young compared to mature
               <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults, although the number was not statistically
            significant between the two groups. We speculate that the increased abundance of
            circulating hemocytes we observed in mature compared to young
               <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> may reflect a shift in the proportion of sessile to
            circulating cells instead of de novo production of new hemocytes. A comparable process
            occurs in <italic>Drosophila</italic> larvae and adults, where the proportion of sessile
            to circulating hemocytes changes following immune stimulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Zettervall1">[42]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Brandt1">[43]</xref>. Furthermore, after larval
               <italic>Drosophila</italic> receive an epidermal wound, circulating hemocytes are
            rapidly recruited to the site of injury. These circulating cells are phagocytically
            active and likely function as a front-line surveillance system against tissue damage and
            microbial infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Babcock1">[44]</xref>. In the mosquito malaria vector <italic>Anopheles
               gambiae</italic>, exposure to <italic>Plasmodium</italic> parasites stimulated an
            increase in the number of granulocytes circulating in the hemolymph. These primed
            mosquitoes were subsequently more resistant to infection with pathogenic bacteria than
            their wild-type counterparts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Rodrigues1">[45]</xref>. We propose that young <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>
            adults and mature <italic>Gmm<sup>Wig</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults may be
            susceptible to <italic>E. coli</italic> infection in part because they harbor
            significantly less circulating hemocytes than do older WT individuals that are
            resistant. Our previous studies indicated that
               <italic>Gmm<sup>Wig</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults are highly susceptible to
            trypanosome infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Pais1">[9]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Wang1">[10]</xref> and that this phenotype may be modulated by tsetse's
            humoral immune system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Hao1">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Hu3">[48]</xref>. Studies are ongoing to determine if cellular immunity also
            modulates tsetse's trypanosome vectorial competence.</p>
         <p>Neonatal humans (and presumably other mammals as well) acquire probiotic gut microbes
            through the act of breast feeding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Martin1">[49]</xref>. These bacteria subsequently stably colonize the naïve
            intestine where they promote immune system maturation and enhance defense against
            infection with pathogenic microbes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-LaraVilloslada1">[50]</xref>. Most lower eukaryotes,
            including insects, hatch from an egg deposited into the environment and thus rely mainly
            on environmental microbes to stimulate their innate immune systems during the
            development of immature stages. For example, <italic>Anopheline</italic> mosquitoes and
               <italic>Drosophila</italic> are exposed to environmental microbes throughout all
            stages of their development. Under these natural conditions subsequent adults exhibit
            potent innate immunity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Dong1">[51]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Charroux2">[52]</xref>. However, when these insects are reared under germ-free
            conditions, they exhibit a severely compromised humoral immune response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Dong1">[51]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Ryu1">[53]</xref>. Tsetse flies are unique among other
            insects because they lead a relatively aseptic existence. Not only do they feed
            exclusively on sterile vertebrate blood, but they also exhibit a unique viviparous
            reproductive strategy. During this type of reproduction, all embryonic and larval stages
            develop within the female's uterus. The protected in utero environment in which
            viviparous offspring develop limits their exposure to environmental microbes. However,
            throughout tsetse larvagenesis maternal milk gland secretions provide the developing
            offspring with nourishment as well as <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>,
               <italic>Sodalis</italic>, and <italic>Wolbachia</italic>
            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Attardo1">[31]</xref>. Interestingly,
            recently established <italic>Sodalis</italic> and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> appear
            unable to influence their host's physiology to the same extent as mutualist
               <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> despite their presence throughout larval development.
            Future studies on this system will focus on determining the chemical and/or metabolic
            elements provided by <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> that stimulate the maturation of
            its host's immune system during larval development.</p>
         <p>The results of this study provide evidence of a novel functional role for obligate
            insect symbionts–host immune system activation during immature developmental
            stages to ensure robust function during adulthood. We demonstrate that the obligate
               <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> provides tsetse offspring the stimuli necessary for
            immune system development, a process that exhibits functional parallels with the
            mammalian system following the transfer of beneficial microbes from mothers to their
            neonates during that act of breast feeding. This phenomenon represents an adaptation
            that further anchors the steadfast relationship shared between tsetse and its obligate
            mutualist. The essential nature of tsetse's dependence on
               <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> provides a potentially exploitable niche to
            experimentally modulate host immunity, with the intention of diminishing this
            insect's capacity to vector deadly trypanosomes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
         <title>Materials and Methods</title>
         <sec id="s4a">
            <title>Tsetse and Septic Infections</title>
            <p>Throughout the text, 3-d-old and 8-d-old tsetse are referred to as
               “young” and “mature,” respectively. Wild-type <italic>G. m.
                  morsitans</italic> (<italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>) were maintained in
               Yale's insectary at 24°C with 50%–55% relative humidity.
               These flies received defibrinated bovine blood every 48 h through an artificial
               membrane feeding system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Moloo1">[54]</xref>. Two <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>-free tsetse lines were
               generated for use in our experiments. The first,
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>, was generated by
               supplementing the diet of pregnant females with 25 µg of ampicillin per ml of
               blood. <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> (offspring of
               ampicillin-fed females) adult are devoid of <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>
               throughout all developmental stages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Pais1">[9]</xref>. PCR using <italic>Wigglesworthia thiamine
               C-</italic>specific primers (forward, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-TGAAAACATTTGCAAAATTTG-3′</named-content>; reverse,
                  <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGTGTTACATAGCATAACAT-3′</named-content>) confirmed that this
               tsetse strain lacked <italic>Wigglesworthia.</italic> The second
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>-free tsetse line,
                     <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup>, was generated by
               feeding mature WT adults three blood meals supplemented with 40 µg/ml
               tetracycline. <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup>
               individuals thus harbored <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>, <italic>Sodalis</italic>,
               and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> throughout the development of all immature stages and
               early adulthood, but lacked these symbionts thereafter. The absence of
                  <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> from mature
                     <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> adults was
               confirmed microscopically by comparing the bacteriome
                  (<italic>Wigglesworthia</italic>-harboring organ) contents of mature WT and
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup> adults.</p>
            <p>Septic infection of tsetse was achieved by anesthetizing flies with CO<sub>2</sub>
               and subsequently injecting individuals with live bacterial cells using glass needles
               and a Narashige IM300 micro-injector. The methods used to produce
               luciferase-expressing <italic>E. coli</italic> K12 (rec<italic>E.
                  coli</italic><sub>pIL</sub>), and the assay used to quantify luciferase expression
               in vivo, were described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Weiss1">[15]</xref>. GFP-expressing and tetracycline-resistant <italic>E.
                  coli</italic> K12 were produced via electroporation with pGFP-UV (Clontech,
               Mountain View, CA) and pBR322 (Promega, Madison, WI) plasmid DNA, respectively. All
               flies treated with tetracycline were subsequently infected with tetracycline
               resistant <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. The number of bacterial cells injected and
               control group designations for all infection experiments are indicated in the
               corresponding figures and their legends. For all survival experiments, treatments
               were performed in triplicate, using 25 flies per <italic>E. coli</italic> treatment
               replicate. LB media controls were performed once using 25 flies.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s4b">
            <title>Real-Time Quantitative PCR (qPCR)</title>
            <p>For analysis of immunity-related gene expression, sample preparation and qPCR were
               performed as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Weiss1">[15]</xref>. Quantitative measurements were performed on three
               biological samples in duplicate and results were normalized relative to tsetse's
               constitutively expressed β-tubulin gene (determined from each corresponding
               sample). Fold-change data are represented as a fraction of average normalized gene
               expression levels in bacteria-infected flies relative to expression levels in
               corresponding uninfected controls.</p>
            <p>For symbiont quantification, total RNA was prepared from 40-d-old adult
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> flies. Symbiont genome
               numbers were quantified using single-copy <italic>Sodalis fliC</italic> and
                  <italic>Wolbachia groEL</italic>. Relative symbiont densities were normalized to
               tsetse <italic>β-tubulin</italic>. All qPCR was performed with an icycler iQ real
               time PCR detection system (Bio-Rad). Values are represented as the mean
               (±SEM). qPCR primer sequences are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1000619.s001">Table S1</xref>.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s4c">
            <title>Bacterial 16s rRNA Clone Libraries</title>
            <p>Universal bacterial 16S rRNA gene primers 27F (5′-AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCA
               G-3′) and 1492R (<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-GGTTACCTTGTTACGACTT-3′</named-content>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Dale1">[55]</xref> were used to produce a clone
               library of 16s rRNA gene sequences found in 3<sup>rd</sup> instar
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> larvae. Five individual
               larvae from each tsetse line were dissecting under sterile conditions and washed in
               DNase (Ambion, Austin, TX) to remove any surface contamination prior to DNA
               extraction. Genomic DNA was isolated using Holmes-Bonner buffer (0.1 mol/L Tris-HCl,
               pH 7.5; 0.35 mol/L NaCl; 10 mmol/L EDTA, pH 8.0; 2% SDS; 7
               mol/L Urea), purified via phenol-chloroform extraction and precipitated in
               100% EtOH. PCR was performed under standard reaction conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Weiss1">[15]</xref>, and the resulting
               products were cloned in the pGEM-T vector (Promega, Madison, WI). Twenty clone
               inserts from each larvae (100 in total from each tsetse line) were sequenced using
               the T7 vector specific primer, and homology to previously described 16s rRNAs was
               determined using the blastn database.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s4d">
            <title>Hemolymph Collection and Hemocyte Quantification</title>
            <p>Depending on the subsequent experiment, tsetse hemolymph was collected using one of
               two methods. For hemocyte quantification, undiluted hemolymph was collected by
               removing one front fly leg at the joint nearest the thorax and then applying gentle
               pressure to the distal tip of the abdomen. Hemolymph exuding from the wound was
               collected using a glass micro-pipette and placed into a microfuge tube on ice.
               Hemocytes were quantified microscopically using a Bright-Line hemocytometer, and
               hemocyte numbers are represented as cells per µl of hemolymph.</p>
            <p>When hemocytes were required for microscopic visualization, hemolymph was collected
               by employing a modified version of the high injection/recovery method previously
               developed for use in mosquitoes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pbio.1000619-Castillo1">[56]</xref>. In brief, tsetse flies were sedated on ice and injected
               with 25 µl of chilled anticoagulant buffer [70% MM medium,
               30% anticoagulant citrate buffer (98 mM NaOH, 186 mM NaCl, 1.7 mM EDTA, and 41
               mM citric acid, buffer pH 4.5), vol/vol] between the last two abdominal
               schlerites using a glass needle and a Narashige IM300 micro-injector. Following a 30
               min incubation on ice, a front leg was removed at the joint most proximal to the
               thorax. At this point internal pressure forced hemolymph diluted with anticoagulant
               buffer to be expelled from the wound site (more liquid could be recovered by applying
               gentle pressure to the distal end of the abdomen). Liquid was collected using a
               pipette and either placed into a chilled microfuge tube or directly into a 24-well
               cell culture plate. In the latter case, cells were allowed to adhere to the plate
               bottom, after which anticoagulant buffer was replaced with MM media.</p>
            <p>Sessile hemocytes were observed by intra-thoracically injecting young and mature
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup>, and mature
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup>
               (<italic>n</italic> = 5 of each strain), with 2 µl of blue
               fluorescent (365/415 nm) 0.2 µm carboxylate-modified beads (Invitrogen corp.).
               Prior to use, beads were washed once in PBS and resuspended in 100% of their
               original volume. Flies were dissected 12 h post-injection to reveal their dorsal
               vessel and surrounding tissue, which was gently washed 3 times with PBS to remove any
               potentially contaminating circulating (non-adherent) hemocytes. Engulfed microspheres
               were visualized using a Zeiss steriomicroscope (Discovery v8) equipped with a coaxial
               fluorescence module. Semi-quantitative comparison of sessile hemocyte number between
               young and mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> adults, and mature
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> adults, was performed by
               quantifying fluorescent signal intensity (<italic>n</italic> = 4
               individuals from each group) using ImageJ software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/" xlink:type="simple">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>).</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s4e">
            <title>Phagocytosis and Melanization Assays</title>
            <p>Phagocytosis by circulating tsetse hemocytes was observed by intra-thoracically
               infecting mature <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> flies (<italic>n</italic>
                = 10) with 1×10<sup>6</sup> GFP-expressing <italic>E.
                  coli</italic> K12. Twelve hours post-infection, hemolymph was collected and
               hemocytes monitored to determine if they had engulfed the GFP-expressing bacterial
               cells. Hemolymph samples were fixed on glass microscope slides via a 2 min incubation
               in 2% PFA. Prior to visualization using a Zeiss Axioscope microscope, slides
               were overlayed with VectaShield hard set mounting medium containing DAPI (Vector
               Laboratories, Burlingame, CA).</p>
            <p>Phagocytosis by tsetse hemocytes was inhibited with blue fluorescent (365/415 nm) 0.2
               µm carboxylate-modified beads (Invitrogen Corp.). Prior to use, beads were
               washed once in PBS and resuspended in 100% of their original volume.
               Inhibition assays were performed by inoculating 8-d-old
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> with 2 µl of beads via their thoracic
               compartment. Twelve hours later, these flies were similarly infected with
                  1×10<sup>3</sup> and 1×10<sup>6</sup> GFP-expressing <italic>E.
                  coli</italic> K12 (experiment was performed in triplicate; <italic>n</italic>
                = 25 flies per replicate). Finally, 12 hours post-infection
               with <italic>E. coli</italic>, hemolymph was collected and processed as described
               above (these samples were overlayed with VectaShield hard set mounting medium that
               lacked DAPI).</p>
            <p>Melanization assays were performed by intra-thoracically inoculating mature
                  <italic>Gmm</italic><sup>WT</sup> and
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic><sup>−</sup> (<italic>n</italic>
                = 10 of each strain) with 1×10<sup>3</sup>
               <italic>E. coli</italic> K12. Subsequently, three individuals from each group were
               monitored microscopically every 10 min for the presence of melanin at the wound site.
               The remaining seven flies from each group were maintained for 2 wk in order to
               observe infection outcome.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s4f">
            <title>Statistics</title>
            <p>Statistical significance of survival curves was determined by log-rank analysis using
               JMP (v8.02) software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmp.com" xlink:type="simple">www.jmp.com</ext-link>). Statistical analysis of qPCR data was performed by
               Student's <italic>t</italic> test using JMP (v8.02) software. Statistical
               significance between various treatments, and treatments and controls, is indicated in
               corresponding figure legends.</p>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s5">
         <title>Supporting Information</title>
         <supplementary-material id="pbio.1000619.s001" mimetype="application/x-excel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000619.s001" xlink:type="simple">
            <label>Table S1</label>
            <caption>
               <p>Primers used for quantitative real-time PCR.</p>
               <p>(0.02 MB XLS)</p>
            </caption>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ack>
         <p>We are grateful to Dr. Yineng Wu for assistance with qPCR, Dr. Corey Brelsford for
            assistance with statistical analysis, and Dan Summers for his help processing bacterial
            16s rRNA clone libraries. We also thank members of the Aksoy lab for critical review of
            the manuscript.</p>
      </ack>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Moran1">
            <label>1</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Moran</surname>
                     <given-names>N. A</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2006</year>
               <article-title>Symbiosis.</article-title>
               <source>Curr Biol</source>
               <volume>16</volume>
               <fpage>R866</fpage>
               <lpage>R871</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Wernegreen1">
            <label>2</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wernegreen</surname>
                     <given-names>J. J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2002</year>
               <article-title>Genome evolution in bacterial endosymbionts of
                  insects.</article-title>
               <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
               <volume>3</volume>
               <fpage>850</fpage>
               <lpage>861</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Aksoy1">
            <label>3</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2000</year>
               <article-title>Tsetse – a haven for microorganisms.</article-title>
               <source>Parasitol Today</source>
               <volume>16</volume>
               <fpage>114</fpage>
               <lpage>118</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Chen1">
            <label>4</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Chen</surname>
                     <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Li</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1999</year>
               <article-title>Concordant evolution of a symbiont with its host insect species:
                  molecular phylogeny of genus <italic>Glossina</italic> and its
                  bacteriome-associated endosymbiont, <italic>Wigglesworthia
                  glossinidia</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>J Mol Evol</source>
               <volume>48</volume>
               <fpage>49</fpage>
               <lpage>58</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Akman1">
            <label>5</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Akman</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Yamashita</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Watanabe</surname>
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Oshima</surname>
                     <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Shiba</surname>
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2002</year>
               <article-title>Genome sequence of the endocellular obligate symbiont of tsetse flies,
                     <italic>Wigglseworthia glossinidia.</italic></article-title>
               <source>Nat Genet</source>
               <volume>32</volume>
               <fpage>402</fpage>
               <lpage>407</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Nogge1">
            <label>6</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nogge</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1976</year>
               <article-title>Sterility in tsetse flies (<italic>Glossina morsitans</italic>
                  Westwood) caused by loss of symbionts.</article-title>
               <source>Experientia</source>
               <volume>32</volume>
               <fpage>995</fpage>
               <lpage>996</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Aksoy2">
            <label>7</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Gibson</surname>
                     <given-names>W. C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lehane</surname>
                     <given-names>M. J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2003</year>
               <article-title>Interactions between tsetse and trypanosomes with implications for the
                  control of trypanosomiasis.</article-title>
               <source>Adv Parasitol</source>
               <volume>53</volume>
               <fpage>1</fpage>
               <lpage>83</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Hu1">
            <label>8</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hu</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rio</surname>
                     <given-names>R. V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Medlock</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Haines</surname>
                     <given-names>L. R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nayduch</surname>
                     <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>Infections with immunogenic trypanosomes reduce tsetse reproductive
                  fitness: potential impact of different parasite strains on vector population
                  structure.</article-title>
               <source>PLoS Neg Trop Dis</source>
               <volume>2</volume>
               <fpage>1</fpage>
               <lpage>10</lpage>
               <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000192" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000192</ext-link></comment>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Pais1">
            <label>9</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Pais</surname>
                     <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lohs</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wu</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wang</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>The obligate mutualist <italic>Wigglesworthia glossinidia</italic>
                  influences reproduction, digestion, and immunity processes of its host, the tsetse
                  fly.</article-title>
               <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
               <volume>74</volume>
               <fpage>5965</fpage>
               <lpage>5974</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Wang1">
            <label>10</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wang</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wu</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Yang</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2009</year>
               <article-title>Interactions between mutualist <italic>Wigglesworthia</italic> and
                  tsetse peptidoglycan recognition protein (PGRP-LB) influence trypanosome
                  transmission.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>106</volume>
               <fpage>12133</fpage>
               <lpage>12138</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Hooper1">
            <label>11</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hooper</surname>
                     <given-names>L. V</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2004</year>
               <article-title>Bacterial contributions to mammalian gut development.</article-title>
               <source>Trends Microbiol</source>
               <volume>12</volume>
               <fpage>129</fpage>
               <lpage>134</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Macpherson1">
            <label>12</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Macpherson</surname>
                     <given-names>A. J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Harris</surname>
                     <given-names>N. L</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2004</year>
               <article-title>Interactions between commensal intestinal bacteria and the immune
                  system.</article-title>
               <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
               <volume>4</volume>
               <fpage>478</fpage>
               <lpage>485</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Koropatnick1">
            <label>13</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Koropatnick</surname>
                     <given-names>T. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Engle</surname>
                     <given-names>J. T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Apicella</surname>
                     <given-names>M. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stabb</surname>
                     <given-names>E. V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Goldman</surname>
                     <given-names>W. E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2004</year>
               <article-title>Microbial factor-mediated development in a host-bacterial
                  mutualism.</article-title>
               <source>Science</source>
               <volume>306</volume>
               <fpage>1186</fpage>
               <lpage>1188</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Oliver1">
            <label>14</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Oliver</surname>
                     <given-names>K. M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Degnan</surname>
                     <given-names>P. H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hunter</surname>
                     <given-names>M. S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Moran</surname>
                     <given-names>N. A</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2009</year>
               <article-title>Bacteriophages encode factors required for protection in a symbiotic
                  mutualism.</article-title>
               <source>Science</source>
               <volume>325</volume>
               <fpage>992</fpage>
               <lpage>994</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Weiss1">
            <label>15</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Weiss</surname>
                     <given-names>B. L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wu</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schwank</surname>
                     <given-names>J. J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Tolwinski</surname>
                     <given-names>N. S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>An insect symbiosis is influenced by bacterium-specific polymorphisms
                  in outer membrane protein A. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</article-title>
               <volume>105</volume>
               <fpage>15088</fpage>
               <lpage>15093</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Hoffmann1">
            <label>16</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
                     <given-names>J. A</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2003</year>
               <article-title>The immune response of <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Nature</source>
               <volume>426</volume>
               <fpage>33</fpage>
               <lpage>38</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Blandin1">
            <label>17</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Blandin</surname>
                     <given-names>S. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Levashina</surname>
                     <given-names>E. A</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>Phagocytosis in mosquito immune responses.</article-title>
               <source>Immunol Rev</source>
               <volume>219</volume>
               <fpage>8</fpage>
               <lpage>16</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Cerenius1">
            <label>18</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Cerenius</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Söderhäll</surname>
                     <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2004</year>
               <article-title>The prophenoloxidase-activating system in
                  invertebrates.</article-title>
               <source>Immunol Rev</source>
               <volume>198</volume>
               <fpage>116</fpage>
               <lpage>126</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Dimopoulos1">
            <label>19</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dimopoulos</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Richman</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Muller</surname>
                     <given-names>H. M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kafatos</surname>
                     <given-names>F. C</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1997</year>
               <article-title>Molecular immune responses of the mosquito <italic>Anopheles
                     gambiae</italic> to bacteria and malaria parasites.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>94</volume>
               <fpage>11508</fpage>
               <lpage>11513</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Whitten1">
            <label>20</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Whitten</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sun</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Tew</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schaub</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Soukou</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>Differential modulation of <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic> nitric
                  oxide activities following challenge with <italic>Trypanosoma rangeli</italic>,
                     <italic>T. cruzi</italic> and bacterial cell wall components.</article-title>
               <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>
               <volume>37</volume>
               <fpage>440</fpage>
               <lpage>452</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Foley1">
            <label>21</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Foley</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>O'Farrell</surname>
                     <given-names>P. H</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2003</year>
               <article-title>Nitric oxide contributes to induction of innate immune responses to
                  Gram-negative bacteria in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Genes Dev</source>
               <volume>17</volume>
               <fpage>115</fpage>
               <lpage>125</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Carton1">
            <label>22</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Carton</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Frey</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nappi</surname>
                     <given-names>A. J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2009</year>
               <article-title>Parasite-induced changes in nitric oxide levels in <italic>Drosophila
                     paramelanica</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>J Parasitol</source>
               <volume>95</volume>
               <fpage>1134</fpage>
               <lpage>1141</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Matova1">
            <label>23</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Matova</surname>
                     <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Anderson</surname>
                     <given-names>K. V</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2006</year>
               <article-title>Rel/NF-κB double mutants reveal that cellular immunity is central
                  to <italic>Drosophila</italic> host defense.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>103</volume>
               <fpage>16424</fpage>
               <lpage>16429</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Hillyer1">
            <label>24</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hillyer</surname>
                     <given-names>J. F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                     <given-names>S. L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Christensen</surname>
                     <given-names>B. M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2003</year>
               <article-title>Rapid phagocytosis and melanization of bacteria and
                     <italic>Plasmodium</italic> sporozoites by hemocytes of the mosquito
                     <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>J. Parasitol</source>
               <volume>89</volume>
               <fpage>62</fpage>
               <lpage>69</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Meister1">
            <label>25</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Meister</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lagueux</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2003</year>
               <article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> blood cells.</article-title>
               <source>Cell Microbiol</source>
               <volume>5</volume>
               <fpage>573</fpage>
               <lpage>580</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Galko1">
            <label>26</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Galko</surname>
                     <given-names>M. J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Krasnow</surname>
                     <given-names>M. A</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2004</year>
               <article-title>Cellular and genetic analysis of wound healing in
                     <italic>Drosophila</italic> larvae.</article-title>
               <source>PLoS Biol</source>
               <volume>2</volume>
               <fpage>1114</fpage>
               <lpage>1126</lpage>
               <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0020239" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020239</ext-link></comment>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Christensen1">
            <label>27</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Christensen</surname>
                     <given-names>B. M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Li</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Chen</surname>
                     <given-names>C. C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nappi</surname>
                     <given-names>A. J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2005</year>
               <article-title>Melanization immune responses in mosquito vectors.</article-title>
               <source>Trends Parasitol</source>
               <volume>21</volume>
               <fpage>192</fpage>
               <lpage>199</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Ayres1">
            <label>28</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ayres</surname>
                     <given-names>J. S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schneider</surname>
                     <given-names>D. S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>A signaling protease required for melanization in
                     <italic>Drosophila</italic> affects resistance and tolerance of
                  infections.</article-title>
               <source>PLoS Biol</source>
               <volume>6</volume>
               <fpage>2764</fpage>
               <lpage>2773</lpage>
               <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0060305" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.0060305</ext-link></comment>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-ElrodErickson1">
            <label>29</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Elrod-Erickson</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mishra</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schneider</surname>
                     <given-names>D. S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2000</year>
               <article-title>Interactions between the cellular and humoral immune responses in
                     <italic>Drosophila.</italic></article-title>
               <source>Curr Biol</source>
               <volume>10</volume>
               <fpage>781</fpage>
               <lpage>784</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Evans1">
            <label>30</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Evans</surname>
                     <given-names>C. J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sinenko</surname>
                     <given-names>S. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mandal</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Martinez-Agosto</surname>
                     <given-names>J. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hartenstein</surname>
                     <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>Genetic dissection of hematopoiesis using <italic>Drosophila</italic>
                  as a model system.</article-title>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bodmer</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>R</surname>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <source>Advances in developmental biology, Volume 18</source>
               <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
               <fpage>259</fpage>
               <lpage>298</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Attardo1">
            <label>31</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Attardo</surname>
                     <given-names>G. M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lohs</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Heddi</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Alam</surname>
                     <given-names>U. H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Yildirim</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>Analysis of milk gland structure and function in <italic>Glossina
                     morsitans</italic>: milk protein production, symbiont populations and
                  fecundity.</article-title>
               <source>J Insect Physiol</source>
               <volume>54</volume>
               <fpage>1236</fpage>
               <lpage>1242</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Eleftherianos1">
            <label>32</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Eleftherianos</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Boundy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Joyce</surname>
                     <given-names>S. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aslam</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Marshall</surname>
                     <given-names>J. W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>An antibiotic produced by an insect-pathogenic bacterium suppresses
                  host defenses through phenoloxidase inhibition.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>104</volume>
               <fpage>2419</fpage>
               <lpage>2424</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Rizki1">
            <label>33</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rizki</surname>
                     <given-names>T. M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rizki</surname>
                     <given-names>R. M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1990</year>
               <article-title>Encapsulation of parasitoid eggs in phenoloxidase-deficient mutants of
                     <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>J Insect Physiol</source>
               <volume>36</volume>
               <fpage>523</fpage>
               <lpage>529</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Leem1">
            <label>34</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Leem</surname>
                     <given-names>J. Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nishimura</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kurata</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Shimada</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                     <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>1996</year>
               <article-title>Purification and characterization of
                  N-beta-alanyl-5-S-glutathionyl-3,4-dihydroxyphenylalanine, a novel antibacterial
                  substance of <italic>Sarcophaga peregrina</italic> (flesh fly).</article-title>
               <source>J Biol Chem</source>
               <volume>271</volume>
               <fpage>13573</fpage>
               <lpage>13577</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Zhao1">
            <label>35</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zhao</surname>
                     <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Li</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wang</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jiang</surname>
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>Broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity of the reactive compounds
                  generated <italic>in vitro</italic> by <italic>Manduca sexta</italic>
                  phenoloxidase.</article-title>
               <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>
               <volume>37</volume>
               <fpage>952</fpage>
               <lpage>959</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Lebestky1">
            <label>36</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lebestky</surname>
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Chang</surname>
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hartenstein</surname>
                     <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2000</year>
               <article-title>Specification of <italic>Drosophila</italic> hematopoietic lineage by
                  conserved transcription factors.</article-title>
               <source>Science</source>
               <volume>288</volume>
               <fpage>146</fpage>
               <lpage>149</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Charroux1">
            <label>37</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Charroux</surname>
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Royet</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2009</year>
               <article-title>Elimination of plasmatocytes by targeted apoptosis reveals their role
                  in multiple aspects of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> immune
                  response.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>106</volume>
               <fpage>9797</fpage>
               <lpage>9802</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Pham1">
            <label>38</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Pham</surname>
                     <given-names>L. N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dionne</surname>
                     <given-names>M. S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Shirasu-Hiza</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schneider</surname>
                     <given-names>D. S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>A specific primed immune response in <italic>Drosophila</italic> is
                  dependent on phagocytes.</article-title>
               <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
               <volume>3</volume>
               <fpage>1</fpage>
               <lpage>8</lpage>
               <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.0030026" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030026</ext-link></comment>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Bidla1">
            <label>39</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bidla</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dushay</surname>
                     <given-names>M. S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Theopold</surname>
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>Crystal cell rupture after injury in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
                  requires the JNK pathway, small GTPases and the TNF homolog Eiger.</article-title>
               <source>J Cell Sci</source>
               <volume>120</volume>
               <fpage>1209</fpage>
               <lpage>1215</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Lanot1">
            <label>40</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lanot</surname>
                     <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zachary</surname>
                     <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Holder</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Meister</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2001</year>
               <article-title>Postembryonic hematopoiesis in
                  <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Dev Biol</source>
               <volume>230</volume>
               <fpage>243</fpage>
               <lpage>257</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Bidla2">
            <label>41</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bidla</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lindgren</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Theopold</surname>
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dushay</surname>
                     <given-names>M. S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2005</year>
               <article-title>Hemolymph coagulation and phenoloxidase in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
                  larvae.</article-title>
               <source>Dev Comp Immunol</source>
               <volume>29</volume>
               <fpage>669</fpage>
               <lpage>679</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Zettervall1">
            <label>42</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zettervall</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Anderl</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Williams</surname>
                     <given-names>M. J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Palmer</surname>
                     <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kurucz</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2004</year>
               <article-title>A direct screen for genes involved in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
                  blood cell activation.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>101</volume>
               <fpage>14192</fpage>
               <lpage>14197</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Brandt1">
            <label>43</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Brandt</surname>
                     <given-names>S. M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schneider</surname>
                     <given-names>D. S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>Bacterial infection of fly ovaries reduces egg production and induces
                  local hemocyte activation.</article-title>
               <source>Dev Comp Immunol</source>
               <volume>31</volume>
               <fpage>1121</fpage>
               <lpage>1130</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Babcock1">
            <label>44</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Babcock</surname>
                     <given-names>D. T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Brock</surname>
                     <given-names>A. R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Fish</surname>
                     <given-names>G. S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wang</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Perrin</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>Circulating blood cells function as a surveillance system for damaged
                  tissue in <italic>Drosophila</italic> larvae.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>105</volume>
               <fpage>10017</fpage>
               <lpage>10022</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Rodrigues1">
            <label>45</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Brayner</surname>
                     <given-names>F. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Alves</surname>
                     <given-names>L. C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dixit</surname>
                     <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Barillas-Mury</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2010</year>
               <article-title>Hemocyte differentiation mediates innate immune memory in
                     <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> mosquitoes.</article-title>
               <source>Science</source>
               <volume>329</volume>
               <fpage>1353</fpage>
               <lpage>1355</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Hao1">
            <label>46</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hao</surname>
                     <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kasumba</surname>
                     <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lehane</surname>
                     <given-names>M. J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Gibson</surname>
                     <given-names>W. C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kwon</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2001</year>
               <article-title>Tsetse immune responses and trypanosome transmission: implications for
                  the development of tsetse-based strategies to reduce
                  trypanosomiasis.</article-title>
               <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
               <volume>98</volume>
               <fpage>12648</fpage>
               <lpage>12653</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Hu2">
            <label>47</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hu</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2005</year>
               <article-title>An antimicrobial peptide with trypanocidal activity characterized from
                     <italic>Glossina morsitans morsitans</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>
               <volume>35</volume>
               <fpage>105</fpage>
               <lpage>115</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Hu3">
            <label>48</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Hu</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Aksoy</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2006</year>
               <article-title>Innate immune responses regulate trypanosome parasite infection of the
                  tsetse fly <italic>Glossina morsitans morsitans</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
               <volume>60</volume>
               <fpage>1194</fpage>
               <lpage>1204</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Martin1">
            <label>49</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Martin</surname>
                     <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Langa</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Reviriego</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jimenez</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Marin</surname>
                     <given-names>M. L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2003</year>
               <article-title>Human milk is a source of lactic acid bacteria for the infant
                  gut.</article-title>
               <source>J Pediatr</source>
               <volume>143</volume>
               <fpage>754</fpage>
               <lpage>758</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-LaraVilloslada1">
            <label>50</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lara-Villoslada</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Olivares</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Sierra</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
                     <given-names>J. M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Boza</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2007</year>
               <article-title>Beneficial effects of probiotic bacteria isolated from breast
                  milk.</article-title>
               <source>Br J Nutr</source>
               <volume>98</volume>
               <fpage>S96</fpage>
               <lpage>S100</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Dong1">
            <label>51</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dong</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Manfredini</surname>
                     <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dimopolous</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2009</year>
               <article-title>Implications of the mosquito midgut microbiota in the defense against
                  malaria parasites.</article-title>
               <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
               <volume>5</volume>
               <fpage>1</fpage>
               <lpage>10</lpage>
               <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1000423" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000423</ext-link></comment>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Charroux2">
            <label>52</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Charroux</surname>
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Royet</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2010</year>
               <article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> immune response: from systemic
                  antimicrobial peptide production in fat body cells to local defense in the
                  intestinal tract.</article-title>
               <source>Fly</source>
               <volume>4</volume>
               <fpage>40</fpage>
               <lpage>47</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Ryu1">
            <label>53</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ryu</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Kim</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Lee</surname>
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Bai</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nam</surname>
                     <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
               </person-group>
               <year>2008</year>
               <article-title>Innate immune homeostasis by the homeobox gene caudal and
                  commensal-gut mutualism in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Science</source>
               <volume>319</volume>
               <fpage>777</fpage>
               <lpage>782</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Moloo1">
            <label>54</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Moloo</surname>
                     <given-names>S. K</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1971</year>
               <article-title>An artificial feeding technique for
                  <italic>Glossina</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Parasitol</source>
               <volume>68</volume>
               <fpage>507</fpage>
               <lpage>512</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Dale1">
            <label>55</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Dale</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Beeton</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Harbison</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jones</surname>
                     <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Pontes</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2006</year>
               <article-title>Isolation, pure culture, and characterization of
                     “<italic>Candidatus arsenophonus arthropodicus</italic>,” and
                  intracellular secondary endosymbiont from the hippoboscid louse fly
                     <italic>Pseudolynchia canariensis</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>App Environ Microbiol</source>
               <volume>72</volume>
               <fpage>2997</fpage>
               <lpage>3004</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="pbio.1000619-Castillo1">
            <label>56</label>
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Castillo</surname>
                     <given-names>J. C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Robertson</surname>
                     <given-names>A. E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Strand</surname>
                     <given-names>M. R</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2006</year>
               <article-title>Characterization of hemocytes from the mosquitoes <italic>Anopheles
                     gambiae</italic> and <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>.</article-title>
               <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>
               <volume>36</volume>
               <fpage>891</fpage>
               <lpage>903</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <glossary>
         <title>Abbreviations</title>
         <def-list>
            <def-item>
               <term>AMP</term>
               <def>
                  <p>antimicrobial protein</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>CFU</term>
               <def>
                  <p>colony-forming units</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>dpi</term>
               <def>
                  <p>days post-infection</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>GFP</term>
               <def>
                  <p>green fluorescent protein</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>
                  <italic>Gmm<sup>Wgm</sup></italic>
                  <sup>−</sup>
               </term>
               <def>
                  <p><italic>Wigglesworthi</italic>a-free <italic>Glossina morsitans
                        morsitans</italic></p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>
                  <italic>Gmm</italic>
                  <sup>WT</sup>
               </term>
               <def>
                  <p>wild-type <italic>Glossina morsitans morsitans</italic></p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>
                  <italic>Gmm</italic>
                  <sup>WT/<italic>Wgm</italic>−</sup>
               </term>
               <def>
                  <p>adult wild-type <italic>Glossina morsitans morsitans</italic> treated with
                     tetracycline</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>hpi</term>
               <def>
                  <p>hours post-infection</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>iNOS</term>
               <def>
                  <p>inducible nitric oxide synthase</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>PPO</term>
               <def>
                  <p>prophenoloxidase</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>qPCR</term>
               <def>
                  <p>real-time quantitative PCR</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>rRNA</term>
               <def>
                  <p>ribosomal RNA</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
               <term>TEP</term>
               <def>
                  <p>thioester-containing protein</p>
               </def>
            </def-item>
         </def-list>
      </glossary>
      
   </back>
</article>