<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS Computational Biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-16-01355</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Adults</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Bioenergetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive science</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognition</subject><subj-group><subject>Memory</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Learning and memory</subject><subj-group><subject>Memory</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive science</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognition</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Population biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population metrics</subject><subj-group><subject>Fecundity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Urology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fecundity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Developmental biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Morphogenesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive science</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Learning</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Learning</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Learning</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Learning and memory</subject><subj-group><subject>Learning</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical and statistical techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical models</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A model for brain life history evolution</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A model for brain life history evolution</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1015-3089</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>González-Forero</surname> <given-names>Mauricio</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="currentaff001"><sup>¤</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6892-7406</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Faulwasser</surname> <given-names>Timm</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lehmann</surname> <given-names>Laurent</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Ecology and Evolution, University of Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland</addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Laboratoire d’Automatique, École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland</addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="aff003">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Institute for Applied Computer Science, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Eggenstein-Leopoldshafen, Baden-Württemberg, Germany</addr-line>
</aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Alizon</surname> <given-names>Samuel</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>CNRS, FRANCE</addr-line>
</aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p>
<list list-type="simple">
<list-item>
<p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> MGF LL.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Data curation:</bold> MGF.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> MGF LL.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> LL.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Investigation:</bold> MGF.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Methodology:</bold> MGF LL TF.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Project administration:</bold> MGF LL.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Resources:</bold> TF.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Software:</bold> MGF.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Supervision:</bold> LL.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Visualization:</bold> MGF.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> MGF LL.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> MGF LL TF.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001">
<label>¤</label>
<p>Current Address: School of Biology, University of St Andrews, St Andrews, United Kingdom</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">Mauricio.GonzalezForero@unil.ch</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>9</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>e1005380</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>19</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>25</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>González-Forero et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380"/>
<abstract>
<p>Complex cognition and relatively large brains are distributed across various taxa, and many primarily verbal hypotheses exist to explain such diversity. Yet, mathematical approaches formalizing verbal hypotheses would help deepen the understanding of brain and cognition evolution. With this aim, we combine elements of life history and metabolic theories to formulate a metabolically explicit mathematical model for brain life history evolution. We assume that some of the brain’s energetic expense is due to production (learning) and maintenance (memory) of energy-extraction skills (or cognitive abilities, knowledge, information, etc.). We also assume that individuals use such skills to extract energy from the environment, and can allocate this energy to grow and maintain the body, including brain and reproductive tissues. The model can be used to ask what fraction of growth energy should be allocated at each age, given natural selection, to growing brain and other tissues under various biological settings. We apply the model to find uninvadable allocation strategies under a baseline setting (“me vs nature”), namely when energy-extraction challenges are environmentally determined and are overcome individually but possibly with maternal help, and use modern-human data to estimate model’s parameter values. The resulting uninvadable strategies yield predictions for brain and body mass throughout ontogeny and for the ages at maturity, adulthood, and brain growth arrest. We find that: (1) a me-vs-nature setting is enough to generate adult brain and body mass of ancient human scale and a sequence of childhood, adolescence, and adulthood stages; (2) large brains are favored by intermediately challenging environments, moderately effective skills, and metabolically expensive memory; and (3) adult skill is proportional to brain mass when metabolic costs of memory saturate the brain metabolic rate allocated to skills.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
<title>Author summary</title>
<p>Complex cognition and relatively large brains occur in a diversity of mammal, bird, and fish species among others, and there is a large number of mostly verbal hypotheses to explain what causes their evolution in certain species but not others. However, these hypotheses have scarcely exploited the power of formulating them in mathematical terms, which has been very useful to understand the evolution of other traits. To address this issue, we formulate a mathematical model that allows incorporating many of those hypotheses and that can be used to obtain predictions for how much and how fast the brain should grow depending on the hypothesis assumed. We apply the model to humans in a setting where each individual must extract energy from the environment alone (e.g., by hunting or cooking) but possibly with its mother’s help when young (“me vs nature”). We find that a me-vs-nature setting can be enough to produce a variety of human features, including large brain sizes and an adolescence life stage. Our model can be used to compare hypotheses promoting brain evolution, such as harsh environments or plentiful social interactions.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution>Schweizerischer Nationalfonds zur Förderung der Wissenschaftlichen Forschung (CH)</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>PP00P3-146340</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Lehmann</surname> <given-names>Laurent</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>This work was funded by Swiss NSF grant PP00P3-146340 to LL <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.snf.ch/en/Pages/default.aspx" xlink:type="simple">http://www.snf.ch/en/Pages/default.aspx</ext-link>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="6"/>
<table-count count="1"/>
<page-count count="28"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Complex cognitive abilities and relatively large brains are distributed across a variety of taxa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref001">1</xref>], and there is a large number of primarily verbal hypotheses proposed to explain such diversity. Leading hypotheses suggest that various ecological and social challenges favor enhanced cognition or relatively large brains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref009">9</xref>]. Empirical tests for these hypotheses regularly involve assessment of correlations, for instance, between diet quality or group size with cognitive ability or proxies thereof [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref010">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref017">17</xref>]. A complementary approach has been via functional studies; for example, behavioral experiments in humans find refined cognitive skills for social rather than general function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref018">18</xref>], and brain imaging also in humans has identified various brain regions specialized for social interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref019">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref020">20</xref>]. More recently, studies have addressed more directly the causes of large-brain evolution via phylogenetic analyses, artificial selection experiments, and genomic patterns of selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref021">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref025">25</xref>]. However, as hypotheses have remained mostly verbal, understanding of brain evolution may benefit from mathematical formalization to be used in synergy with empirical research, which can reveal features that are otherwise difficult to identify given biological complexity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref026">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref027">27</xref>]. In addition, mathematical models that can make quantitative rather than essentially qualitative predictions could facilitate obtaining contrasting predictions from the diversity of hypotheses, thereby sharpening their tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref028">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref029">29</xref>]. Thus, here we formulate an evolutionary model that can be used to ask what quantitative and qualitative predictions arise from the various hypotheses for complex-cognition or large-brain evolution once these hypotheses are expressed in mathematical form.</p>
<p>A successful modeling approach in evolutionary research is life history theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref030">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref035">35</xref>]. Life history theory considers decisions regarding resouce allocation that individuals make over their lifespan, taking into account tradeoffs between competing ends (e.g., current vs future reproduction, number vs size of offspring, and growth vs reproduction) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref030">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref033">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref034">34</xref>]. Such tradeoffs are of particular importance in complex-cognition and large-brain evolution because the brain uses copious amounts of energy that could be used for other functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref036">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref039">39</xref>]. While life history theory has been thoroughly used to explain the distribution of a variety of traits (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref040">40</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref044">44</xref>]), it has remained relatively underdeveloped for cognition and brain (but see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref029">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref045">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref046">46</xref>]). A first barrier is that mathematical modeling of brain evolution must describe how the brain impacts fitness without being overwhelmed by brain mechanistic details and at the same time it should consider enough mechanistic details to be able to make testable predictions. Existing models have described brain’s impact on fitness as facilitating energy acquisition from the environment allowing this energy to be used to increase survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref046">46</xref>], as facilitating energy production and/or decreasing the probability of being scrounged by others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref047">47</xref>], as increasing offspring survival via parental care despite increasing mortality at birth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref048">48</xref>], as increasing collaborative efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref049">49</xref>], as increasing mating ability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref050">50</xref>], and as increasing the complexity of decision making regarding cooperation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref051">51</xref>]. While these models have contributed to the understanding of brain evolution, a life history model is still lacking that incorporates real estimates of the metabolic costs of the brain while causally yielding quantitative predictions for brain and body size throughout ontogeny from a given brain-evolution hypothesis.</p>
<p>However, producing quantitative predictions that match empirical data from causal mathematical models is challenging given biological complexity. Despite this difficulty, metabolic theory has been successful at making quantitative predictions about ontogenetic body mass with the added bonus that its focus on metabolism allows using a top-down perspective without the need to describe the inner functioning of the system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref052">52</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref056">56</xref>]. Thus, with the aim of producing quantitative predictions from given brain-evolution hypotheses, we combine elements of life history and metabolic theories to derive a mathematical model to study brain life history evolution. The model can be used to determine an individual’s optimal strategy regarding its energy allocation to the growth of its different tissues at each point in its life, which allows obtaining quantitative predictions for body and brain size under different biological settings.</p>
<p>Our model builds on previous approaches considering brain as embodied capital invested in fitness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref046">46</xref>]. We consider separately the physical and functional embodied capital, the former being brain itself and the latter being skills (or cognitive abilities, knowledge, information, etc.) generated by the brain during ontogeny. Thus, our life-history approach considers skills throughout ontogeny. This implements the notion that information gained and maintained by the brain during growth should be considered when modeling brain evolution because selection for skill learning may delay maturity and thus impose tradeoffs among brain, body, and reproduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref001">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref045">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref046">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref057">57</xref>]. A defining feature of our model is that it assumes that some of the brain’s energetic consumption at each time is due to acquisition and maintenance of skills (or cognitive abilities, knowledge, information, etc.). In turn, we consider skills that allow overcoming energy-extraction challenges that the individual faces at each age, and by doing so the individual obtains some energetic reward. The model allows to study various biological settings depending on what poses the challenge faced at a given age and on who engages in overcoming the challenge: that is, the challenge can be posed by the non-social environment (nature), or it can be posed by social partners (them); also, the individual can engage in overcoming the challenge alone (me) or in concert with social partners (us): me (or us) vs nature (or them) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref045">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref046">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref049">49</xref>]. By applying different settings, our framework allows to investigate different brain-evolution hypotheses.</p>
<p>We apply our model to a baseline setting where individuals face exclusively ecological (non-social) challenges which are overcome by the individual alone (“me vs nature” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref049">49</xref>]). This application captures basic aspects of hypotheses emphasizing ecological challenges as drivers of large-brain and complex-cognition evolution (e.g., that the non-social environment is a primary driver). Then, given that the brain consumes some of its energy to gain and maintain skills and given the various types of challenges that the individual faces at each age, we obtain a model that allows to predict how much an individual should grow its brain to obtain the energetic returns from skills. By feeding the model with parameter values for modern humans, we show how the model can yield predictions for life history stages as well as ontogenetic body and brain mass. We intend our me-vs-nature application to be compared with future applications of the model that include additional aspects of ecological-challenge hypotheses (e.g., variable environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref058">58</xref>]) and aspects of social-challenge hypotheses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Model</title>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Biological scenario</title>
<p>We consider a clonal, well-mixed, female population of large and constant size, where the environment is constant, generations are overlapping, and individuals’ age is measured in continuous time (i.e., standard demographic assumptions of models of life history evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref032">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref035">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref040">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref042">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref059">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref060">60</xref>]). We partition the body of each female into three types of tissues (or cells): reproductive tissue, brain tissue, and the remainder tissue, which we refer to as somatic. To have energy at each age for body growth, body maintenance, and reproduction, each female extracts energy from its environment (e.g., by locating food, or by making resources usable through cracking or cooking), possibly with the help of its mother (maternal care) and/or by interacting with other individuals in the population (e.g., through cooperative hunting or social competition for resources). To extract energy, each individual is assumed to use a number of relevant energy-extraction skills, which are produced and maintained by the brain.</p>
<p>We aim to determine the optimal allocation strategy of an individual’s energy budget to the growth of the different tissues throughout its lifespan, which simultaneously addresses the central life history question that asks what the optimal allocation to reproduction is ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref061">61</xref>] p. 43; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref033">33</xref>] p. 72; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref062">62</xref>] p. 109; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref032">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref035">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref040">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref042">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref059">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref060">60</xref>]). An allocation strategy is here a vector of evolving traits that is a function of the individual’s age, and that determines the individual’s energy allocation to the growth of its different tissues throughout the individual’s lifespan. To analyze how selection affects the evolution of the allocation strategy, we carry out an evolutionary invasion analysis (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref035">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref063">63</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref065">65</xref>]), and thus consider that only two strategies can occur in the population, a mutant <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e001"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M1"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and a resident (wild-type) <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e002"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M2"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> allocation strategies. As is standard in evolutionary invasion analysis, we thus seek to establish which strategy is uninvadable, that is, resistant to invasion by any alternative strategy taken from the set <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e003"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e003" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M3"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">U</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> of feasible allocation strategies, and which thus provides a likely final point of evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref066">66</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref068">68</xref>]. From demographic assumptions we make below, it is well established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref059">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref068">68</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref072">72</xref>] that an uninvadable strategy <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e004"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e004" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M4"><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> satisfies
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e005"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e005g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e005" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup> <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo> <mml:mo form="prefix">arg</mml:mo> <mml:munder><mml:mo form="prefix" movablelimits="true">max</mml:mo> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder> <mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(1)</label></disp-formula>
which implies that <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e006"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e006g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e006" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M6"><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is a best response to itself, where
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e007"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e007g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e007" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn> <mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup> <mml:mi>l</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mi>m</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(2)</label></disp-formula>
is the basic reproductive number (lifetime number of offspring) of a single mutant in an otherwise monomorphic resident population, and <italic>T</italic> is an age after which the individual no longer reproduces or is dead. The basic reproductive number depends on the probability <italic>l</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) that a mutant individual survives from birth until age <italic>t</italic> and on its rate <italic>m</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) of offspring production at age <italic>t</italic> with density dependence (“effective fecundity” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref073">73</xref>], or the expected number of offspring produced at age <italic>t</italic> per unit time with density dependence), where these two vital rates may be functions of mutant and resident traits, <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e008"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e008g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e008" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M8"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e009"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e009g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e009" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M9"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>To determine the lifetime offspring production <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> and how it connects to the state variables (tissues and skill) and to the evolving traits, we relate brain and skill growth to vital rates, which in turn is mediated by the connection between energy extraction, metabolism, and tissue growth. We thus formally derive our model by making these connections.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Tracking resting metabolic rate</title>
<p>Standard life history models refer to complete components of the energy budget (e.g., assimilated energy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref074">74</xref>]). In practice, it is easier to measure heat release (metabolic rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref075">75</xref>]). Hence, to facilitate empirical parameter estimation, we follow the approach of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref054">54</xref>] and formulate our life history model in terms of resting metabolic rate allocation, rather than energy budget allocation. Thus, we track how resting metabolic rate is due to growth and maintenance of different tissues, in particular the brain.</p>
<p>We start from the partition of the individual’s energy budget used by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref055">55</xref>], which divides the energy budget (assimilation rate) into heat released at rest (resting metabolic rate) and the remainder (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g001">Fig 1</xref>; see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref075">75</xref>] for details justifying this partition). The amount of energy used per unit time by an individual is its assimilation rate. Part of this energy per unit time is stored in the body (<italic>S</italic>) and the rest is the total metabolic rate, which is the energy released as heat per unit time after use. Part of the total metabolic rate is the resting metabolic rate <italic>B</italic><sub>rest</sub> and the remainder is the energy released as heat per unit time due to activity <italic>B</italic><sub>act</sub>. In turn, part of the resting metabolic rate is due to maintenance of existing biomass <italic>B</italic><sub>maint</sub>, and the remainder is due to production of new biomass <italic>B</italic><sub>syn</sub>. We refer to <italic>B</italic><sub>syn</sub> as the growth metabolic rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g001">Fig 1</xref>). We formulate our model in terms of allocation of growth metabolic rate <italic>B</italic><sub>syn</sub> to the growth of the different tissues.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1005380.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Partition of energy budget.</title>
<p>Note the relation of resting metabolic rate to assimilation rate. Modified from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref055">55</xref>].</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Energy partitioning</title>
<p>Denote by <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) the number of cells of type <italic>i</italic> of a focal mutant female of age <italic>t</italic>, where <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s} corresponds to brain, reproductive, and the remainder cells which we refer to as somatic, respectively. Assume that an average cell of type <italic>i</italic> in the resting body releases an amount of heat <italic>B</italic><sub>c<italic>i</italic></sub> per unit time. Hence, the total amount of heat released per unit time by existing cells in the resting individual is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e010"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e010g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e010" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>maint</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(3)</label></disp-formula>
which gives the part of resting metabolic rate due to body mass maintenance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref055">55</xref>].</p>
<p>Denote by <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e011"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e011g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> the time derivative of <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>). Assume that producing a new average cell of type <italic>i</italic> releases an amount of heat <italic>E</italic><sub>c<italic>i</italic></sub>. Hence, the total amount of heat released per unit time by the resting individual due to production of new cells is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e012"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e012g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e012" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>syn</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(4)</label></disp-formula>
which gives the rate of heat release in biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref055">55</xref>], and we call it the growth metabolic rate. From <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e012">Eq (4)</xref>, we have that
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e013"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e013g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e013" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>syn</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(5)</label></disp-formula>
for <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s}, where <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) is the fraction of the growth metabolic rate due to production of new type-<italic>i</italic> cells at time <italic>t</italic> (summing over all cell types in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e013">Eq 5</xref> returns <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e012">Eq 4</xref>). The resulting time sequence <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e014"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e014g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e014" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="bold">u</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> <mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup> <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <bold>u</bold>(<italic>t</italic>) = (<italic>u</italic><sub>b</sub>(<italic>t</italic>), <italic>u</italic><sub>r</sub>(<italic>t</italic>), <italic>u</italic><sub>s</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)), of allocations from birth to (reproductive) death is the evolving multidimensional trait in our model and <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e015"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e015g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e015" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M15"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">U</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the set of all feasible allocations strategies.</p>
<p>From our partitioning in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g001">Fig 1</xref>, the total amount of heat released by the resting individual per unit time at age <italic>t</italic> is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e016"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e016g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e016" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>maint</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>syn</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(6)</label></disp-formula>
which is the individual’s resting metabolic rate at age <italic>t</italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Tissue growth rate</title>
<p>Let the mass of an average cell of type <italic>i</italic> be <italic>x</italic><sub>c<italic>i</italic></sub> for <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s}. Then, changing units from cell number to mass, the mass of tissue <italic>i</italic> at age <italic>t</italic> is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e017"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e017g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e017" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(7)</label></disp-formula>
and hence, using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e013">Eq (5)</xref>, we have that the growth rate in mass of tissue <italic>i</italic> is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e018"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e018g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e018" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M18"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd> <mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd> <mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr> <mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd> <mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac> <mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>syn</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(8)</label></disp-formula>
To continue the change of cell-number units to mass, we denote the heat released for producing an average mass unit of tissue <italic>i</italic> as <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> = <italic>E</italic><sub>c<italic>i</italic></sub>/<italic>x</italic><sub>c<italic>i</italic></sub>, which we assume constant with respect to time for simplicity. This gives
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e019"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e019g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e019" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>syn</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(9)</label></disp-formula>
Substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e016">Eq (6)</xref> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e019">Eq (9)</xref>, we obtain the model’s first key equation specifying the growth rate of tissue <italic>i</italic>:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e020"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e020g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e020" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mspace width="1pt"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>maint</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(10)</label></disp-formula>
where from Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e010">3</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e017">7</xref>), we have that
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e021"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e021g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e021" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>maint</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(11)</label></disp-formula>
and the mass-specific cost of tissue maintenance is <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> = <italic>B</italic><sub>c<italic>i</italic></sub>/<italic>x</italic><sub>c<italic>i</italic></sub>, which we also assume constant with respect to time for simplicity. From Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e020">10</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e021">11</xref>), the mass unit in which <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) for <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s} is measured (e.g., gram or kilogram) is determined by the mass unit in <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Skill learning rate</title>
<p>We assume that the individual at age <italic>t</italic> has a skill level <italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) at energy extraction, which is a quantitative variable measuring the individual’s ability to overcome challenges of energy extraction. Skill level <italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) can be measured on a scale that is best suited for each application, for example as the individual’s number of skills at age <italic>t</italic> (e.g., as may be useful in anthropology; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref081">81</xref>]), or as an index of performance at a series of tasks (e.g., as in comparative psychology studies; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref001">1</xref>]). We assume that some of the brain metabolic rate is due to acquiring and maintaining energy-extraction skills [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref076">76</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref080">80</xref>]. Denote by <italic>B</italic><sub>rest,b</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) the brain metabolic rate of the individual at age <italic>t</italic> (i.e., the heat released by the brain per unit time with the individual at rest). From energy conservation, the brain metabolic rate must equal the heat released by the brain per unit time due to brain growth and brain maintenance; that is, from Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e010">3</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e012">4</xref>) in mass units, the brain metabolic rate must satisfy
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e022"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e022g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e022" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(12)</label></disp-formula>
Let <italic>s</italic><sub>k</sub> be the fraction of brain metabolic rate allocated to energy-extraction skills, which we assume constant for simplicity. Suppose that the brain releases on average an amount of heat <italic>E</italic><sub>k</sub> for increasing skill level by one unit (learning cost; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref076">76</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref078">78</xref>]). Similarly, assume that the brain releases on average an amount of heat <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub> per unit time for maintaining a skill unit (memory cost; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref079">79</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref080">80</xref>]). For simplicity, we assume <italic>E</italic><sub>k</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub> to be constant with respect to time. From energy conservation, the rate of heat release by the brain due to skill growth and skill maintenance must equal the brain metabolic rate due to energy-extraction skill:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e023"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e023g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e023" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M23"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(13)</label></disp-formula>
Rearranging, we obtain the model’s second key equation specifying skill learning rate:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e024"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e024g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e024" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(14)</label></disp-formula>
In analogy with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e020">Eq (10)</xref>, the first term in the numerator of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e024">Eq (14)</xref> gives the heat released due to skill learning and memory whereas the second term gives the heat released for memory. [Note that an equation for skill growth rate can be similarly derived, not in terms of allocation to skill growth <italic>and</italic> maintenance <italic>s</italic><sub>k</sub>, but in terms of allocation to skill growth <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> as for <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e020">Eq (10)</xref>.] As with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e020">Eq (10)</xref>, from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e024">Eq (14)</xref> the unit in which <italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) is measured is determined by the skill unit in <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>k</sub>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>How skill affects energy extraction</title>
<p>We now derive an expression that specifies how brain affects energy extraction in the model. We consider that energy extraction depends on the focal female’s skills but possibly also on the skills of other females in the population. To make this dependence explicit, we denote by <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e025"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e025g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e025" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M25"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> the amount of energy extracted by the focal female per unit time at time <italic>t</italic> from the environment. So, using <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g001">Fig 1</xref> the energy-extraction rate is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e026"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e026g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e026" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M26"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>A</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:mtext>surplus</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(15)</label></disp-formula>
<inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e027"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e027g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e027" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M27"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> depends on the mutant’s skill and possibly other features (control or state variables, or body mass) which ultimately depend on the mutant allocation strategy <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e028"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e028g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e028" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M28"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Additionally, the energy-extraction rate <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e029"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e029g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e029" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M29"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> also depends on the skill or other features of the resident population which ultimately depend on the resident allocation strategy <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e030"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e030g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e030" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M30"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Let <italic>E</italic><sub>max</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) be the amount of energy that the individual obtains from the environment per unit time at age <italic>t</italic> if it is maximally successful at energy extraction (which also possibly depends on body mass). We define the energy-extraction efficiency <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e031"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e031g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e031" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M31"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> at age <italic>t</italic> as the normalized energy-extraction rate at age <italic>t</italic>:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e032"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e032g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e032" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M32"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(16)</label></disp-formula>
which is thus a dimensionless energy extraction performance measure.</p>
<p>We also define the ratio of resting metabolic rate to energy-extraction rate as
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e033"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e033g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e033" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M33"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(17)</label></disp-formula>
and, motivated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e033">Eq (17)</xref>, we define
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e034"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e034g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e034" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M34"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>q</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(18a)</label></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e035"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e035g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e035" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M35"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(18b)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>From <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e035">Eq (18b)</xref>, we have that
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e036"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e036g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e036" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M36"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(19)</label></disp-formula>
Consequently, <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e037"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e037g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e037" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M37"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> gives the resting metabolic rate when the individual is maximally successful at energy extraction.</p>
<p>Adult resting metabolic rate typically scales with adult body mass as a power law across all living systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref082">82</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref085">85</xref>], and also ontogenetically in humans to a good approximation (Fig C in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>; but see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref086">86</xref>]). Such scaling is empirically obtained from measurements in mostly well-fed individuals, and thus we assume that the empirically measured power-law scaling applies to the resting metabolic rate when the individual is maximally successful at energy extraction, <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e038"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e038g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e038" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M38"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>; that is, we assume
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e039"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e039g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e039" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M39"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>K</mml:mi> <mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi> <mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(20)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>x</italic><sub>B</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>x</italic><sub>b</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>x</italic><sub>r</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>x</italic><sub>s</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) is body mass at age <italic>t</italic>, <italic>β</italic> is a scaling coefficient, and <italic>K</italic> is a constant independent of body mass (both <italic>β</italic> and <italic>K</italic> may depend on the resident strategy; note that <italic>β</italic> need not be 3/4). We further assume that energy-extraction efficiency <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e040"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e040g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e040" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M40"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is independent of body mass, whereby Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e036">19</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e039">20</xref>) yield the model’s third key equation specifying resting metabolic rate as:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e041"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e041g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e041" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M41"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>K</mml:mi> <mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced> <mml:mspace width="1pt"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi> <mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(21)</label></disp-formula> <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq (21)</xref> has two noteworthy implications. First, energy-extraction efficiency <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e042"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e042g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e042" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> regulates the amount of heat that is released from tissue maintenance and synthesis: e.g., a zero energy-extraction efficiency means no heat is released at rest. Second, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq (21)</xref> implies that an increase in body mass is accompanied by an increase in the rate of heat release <italic>B</italic><sub>rest</sub>(<italic>t</italic>). But from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e026">Eq (15)</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g001">Fig 1</xref> we have that <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>B</italic><sub>rest</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>S</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) + <italic>B</italic><sub>act</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) + surplus, which means that an increase in the rate of heat release <italic>B</italic><sub>rest</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) due to increased body mass must be accompanied by either (1) an increase in the energy-extraction rate <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), (2) a decrease in the rate of energy stored <italic>S</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), (3) a decrease in the rate of heat release due to activity <italic>B</italic><sub>act</sub>(<italic>t</italic>), or (4) a decrease in the surplus:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e043"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e043g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e043" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M43"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:mi>S</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>act</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="0.5pt"/><mml:mtext>surplus</mml:mtext></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(22)</label></disp-formula>
That is, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq (21)</xref> specifies a physical constraint imposed by body size that requires that an increased resting metabolic rate due to a larger body mass is achieved by balancing the energy budget from the mentioned sources so that <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e043">Eq (22)</xref> is satisfied. Given that a power law between resting metabolic rate and body mass is ubiquitously observed across living systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref082">82</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref085">85</xref>], we assume that individuals adjust their energy budget as just described (i.e., satisfy <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e043">Eq 22</xref>) so that the physical constraint implied by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq (21)</xref> is met.</p>
<p>Consequently, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq (21)</xref> implies that increasing a tissue’s mass increases the resting metabolic rate which may increase the growth metabolic rate. To see this, consider the following. From Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e016">6</xref>), (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">21</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e021">11</xref>), the increase in growth metabolic rate with an increase in the mass of tissue <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s} is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e044"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e044g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e044" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M44"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>maint</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>K</mml:mi> <mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mfenced> <mml:mspace width="1pt"/><mml:mi>β</mml:mi> <mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(23)</label></disp-formula>
When <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e044">Eq (23)</xref> is positive, an increase in the mass of tissue <italic>i</italic> increases the growth metabolic rate: resting metabolic rate increases more than maintenance metabolic rate, so there is a remainder due to growth. In addition, this remainder is greatest if <italic>i</italic> is the cheapest tissue to maintain (i.e., if <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the smallest for <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s}). Therefore, if a tissue (e.g., brain) is favored to grow, other particularly cheap-to-maintain tissues (e.g., soma) may be favored to grow if they increase the growth metabolic rate, which reflects an increase in the energy available for growth given that the individual balances its energy budget as indicated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e043">Eq (22)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Closing the model: Assume a hypothesis to obtain a closed model capable of predictions</title>
<p>The expression for the resting metabolic rate (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq 21</xref>) closes the model from a metabolic point of view, since after substituting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq (21)</xref> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e020">Eq (10)</xref> (and using Eqs <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e021">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e022">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e024">14</xref>), the ontogenetic dynamics of the brain, reproductive, and somatic tissue mass, <italic>x</italic><sub>b</sub>(<italic>t</italic>), <italic>x</italic><sub>r</sub>(<italic>t</italic>), and <italic>x</italic><sub>s</sub>(<italic>t</italic>), and of skill level, <italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>), are expressed in terms of such state variables, of empirically estimable parameters, and on the evolving traits (mutant <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e045"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e045g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e045" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M45"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and resident <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e046"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e046g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e046" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M46"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>). That is, the ontogenetic dynamics are given by
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e047"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e047g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e047" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M47"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>​</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext> <mml:mspace width="1pt"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(24a)</label></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e048"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e048g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e048" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M48"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1pt"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>​</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="1pt"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(24b)</label></disp-formula>
The ontogenetic dynamics of the state variables <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) are thus non-linear.</p>
<p>To close the model from an evolutionary perspective and compute an optimal allocation strategy, we need expressions for how the state variables relate to the vital rates [<italic>l</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>m</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)] in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e007">Eq (2)</xref> and expressions for the energy-extraction efficiency [<inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e049"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e049g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e049" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M49"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>]. A large number of settings can be conceived with the model so far, both for the vital rates and energy-extraction efficiency. We focus on an application aiming at modeling human brain evolution from a baseline “me-vs-nature” setting.</p>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Vital rates</title>
<p>For simplicity, we consider that the mortality rate <italic>μ</italic> is independent of age and of the evolving traits, so
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e050"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e050g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e050" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M50"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mo form="prefix">exp</mml:mo> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:mi>μ</mml:mi> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(25)</label></disp-formula>
We also assume that density-dependent regulation acts on fecundity (e.g., through lottery competition) so that the effective fecundity <italic>m</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is proportional to fecundity <italic>f</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), defined as the rate of offspring production at age <italic>t</italic> without density dependence (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref069">69</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref073">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref087">87</xref>]). That is, we let
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e051"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e051g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e051" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M51"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>C</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo> <mml:mi>f</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(26)</label></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e052"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e052g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e052" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M52"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is a proportionality factor that depends on population size which ultimately depends on the resident strategy <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e053"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e053g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e053" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M53"><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>We obtain a measure of fecundity <italic>f</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) with a reasoning analogous to that used for the learning rate of skills. In particular, we assume that some of the metabolic rate of the reproductive tissue is due to offspring production and maintenance. Denote by <italic>B</italic><sub>rest,r</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) the metabolic rate of the reproductive tissue at age <italic>t</italic> (i.e., the heat released by the reproductive tissue per unit time with the individual at rest). From energy conservation and Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e010">3</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e012">4</xref>) in mass units, the reproductive metabolic rate must satisfy
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e054"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e054g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e054" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M54"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(27)</label></disp-formula>
Let <italic>s</italic><sub>o</sub> be the fraction of the reproductive metabolic rate allocated to offspring production and maintenance, which we assume constant for simplicity. Let <italic>x</italic><sub>o</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) be the number of offspring the individual has at age <italic>t</italic>. Suppose that the reproductive tissue releases an amount of heat <italic>E</italic><sub>o</sub> for the production of an average offspring (fecundity cost). Similarly, assume that the reproductive tissue releases an amount of heat <italic>B</italic><sub>o</sub> per unit time for maintaining an average offspring (physiological cost of maternal care; e.g., due to lactation). Hence, from energy conservation, the rate of heat release by the reproductive tissue due to offspring production and maintenance must equal the reproductive metabolic rate allocated to offspring production and maintenance:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e055"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e055g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e055" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M55"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(28)</label></disp-formula>
Rearranging, we obtain the model’s fourth key equation specifying fecundity:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e056"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e056g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e056" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M56"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mtext>rest</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(29)</label></disp-formula>
The first term in the numerator of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e056">Eq (29)</xref> gives the heat released due to reproduction and physiological maternal care whereas the second term gives the heat released for physiological maternal care.</p>
<p>We simplify <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e056">Eq (29)</xref> as follows. If the reproductive tissue is defined narrowly enough (e.g., as preovulatory ovarian follicles) so that it is not involved in offspring maintenance, the physiological costs of maternal care incurred by the reproductive tissue are essentially null (i.e., <italic>B</italic><sub>o</sub> ≈ 0; they are, however, included in the maintenance costs <italic>B</italic><sub>s</sub> of the somatic tissue as we defined it above). If additionally, reproductive tissue maintenance is much more expensive than production (i.e., <italic>B</italic><sub>r</sub> ≫ <italic>E</italic><sub>r</sub>/(time unit), which holds with our estimated parameters for humans; Table B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>), using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e054">Eq (27)</xref> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e056">Eq (29)</xref>, fecundity can be approximated as
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e057"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e057g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e057" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M57"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>≈</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mfrac> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(30)</label></disp-formula>
For the results reported below, the approximation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e057">Eq (30)</xref> is accurate and yields no detectable difference in the predicted adult brain and body mass [section 8.2.1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>].</p>
<p>Using Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e051">26</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e057">30</xref>), effective fecundity becomes
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e058"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e058g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e058" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M58"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>≈</mml:mo> <mml:mi>C</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(31)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>f</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic>s</italic><sub>o</sub><italic>B</italic><sub>r</sub>/<italic>E</italic><sub>o</sub> is the number of offspring produced per unit time per mass unit of reproductive tissue in the absence of density dependence. We assume that non-physiological costs of maternal care are included in <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e059"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e059g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e059" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M59"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Effective fecundity is then proportional to the mass of reproductive tissue, which is consistent with medical approaches that predict women’s fecundity in terms of ovarian follicle count [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref088">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref089">89</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Energy acquisition</title>
<p>We now model energy acquisition by specifying expressions for energy-extraction efficiency <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e060"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e060g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e060" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Considering different expressions for <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e061"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e061g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e061" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M61"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> allows incorporating key aspects of hypotheses for cognition and brain evolution. For instance, hypotheses postulating ecological challenges (e.g., food gathering or food processing) as drivers of cognition and brain evolution can be modeled by letting the energy-extraction efficiency <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e062"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e062g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e062" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M62"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> depend on the individual’s skills and the non-social environment. Alternatively, hypotheses postulating social challenges involving cooperation (e.g., hunting big game) can be modeled by letting <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e063"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e063g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e063" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M63"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> have a positive dependence on the skills of both the individual and those of its social partners. Similarly, hypotheses postulating social challenges involving competition (e.g., outsmarting social partners) can be modeled by letting <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e064"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e064g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e064" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> have a negative dependence on the skills of the social partners. Ideally, expressions for <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e065"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e065g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e065" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M65"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> would be empirically informed. In the cases just mentioned, identifying uninvadable allocation strategies for non-social models involves an optimal control problem, while for the social models it involves a differential game problem. As a first approximation, we address here the non-social situation using plausible expressions for <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e066"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e066g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e066" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M66"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> that are at present not empirically grounded but that are based on expressions previously derived from basic assumptions (axioms) about contests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref090">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref091">91</xref>].</p>
<p>We assume that energy extraction at age <italic>t</italic> is done exclusively by overcoming a challenge posed by the non-social environment (e.g., gathering food or lighting a fire) and that the individual engages alone but possibly with its mother’s help in overcoming such a challenge (“me vs nature”). From our assumption of clonality, the mother of a mutant is equally mutant. Thus, this me-vs-nature setting implies that the energy-extraction efficiency, <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e067"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e067g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e067" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M67"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mspace width="-0.166667em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">v</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is independent of the resident strategy.</p>
<p>We treat the me-vs-nature setting as a contest against the environment. We thus let energy-extraction efficiency <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e068"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e068g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e068" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M68"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> take the form of a contest success function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref090">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref092">92</xref>]:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e069"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e069g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e069" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M69"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo> <mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">u</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>+</mml:mo> <mml:mi>c</mml:mi> <mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(32)</label></disp-formula>
which depends on two terms. First, energy-extraction efficiency depends on the difficulty of the challenge at age <italic>t</italic>, measured by <italic>d</italic>(<italic>t</italic>). The higher <italic>d</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), the more challenging energy extraction is and the higher the energy-extraction skill level must be to obtain resources. We let <italic>d</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>α</italic>[1 − <italic>φ</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)], where <italic>α</italic> is the environmental difficulty and <italic>φ</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is the facilitation of the challenge due to maternal care. For simplicity, we let this facilitation be independent of maternal skill (exogenously determined facilitation; see section 8.2.3 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref> and section “Skill through ontogeny” below for a relaxation of this assumption that makes maternal facilitation <italic>φ</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) endogenous, i.e., depend on maternal skill). Thus, we let maternal facilitation be an exponentially decreasing function of age:
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e070"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e070g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e070" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M70"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub> <mml:mo form="prefix">exp</mml:mo> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(33)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>φ</italic><sub>0</sub> is the maternal facilitation at birth and <italic>φ</italic><sub>r</sub> is its rate of decrease. For simplicity, we ignore the increased resting metabolic rate caused by gestation and lactation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref093">93</xref>].</p>
<p>Second, energy-extraction efficiency depends on the individual’s competence, denoted by <italic>c</italic>(<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)). We consider two cases that are standard in contest models: (1) a power function <italic>c</italic>(<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)) = [<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)]<sup><italic>γ</italic></sup>, so energy-extraction efficiency <italic>e</italic>(<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)) is a contest success function in ratio form (power competence); and (2) an exponential function <italic>c</italic>(<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)) = [exp(<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>))]<sup><italic>γ</italic></sup> so energy-extraction efficiency is in difference form (exponential competence) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref090">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref092">92</xref>]. In both cases, the parameter <italic>γ</italic> describes the effectiveness of skills at energy extraction. Thus, with <italic>γ</italic> = 0, skills are ineffective while with increasing <italic>γ</italic> a lower skill level is sufficient to extract energy. In general, competence <italic>c</italic>(<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)) represents features of the individual (e.g., how increasing skill changes efficiency in information processing by the brain), and of the environment (e.g., how adding the skill of caching nuts to that of cracking nuts changes energy-extraction efficiency). For a given skill effectiveness (<italic>γ</italic>), exponential competence assumes a steeper increase in competence with increasing skill than power competence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Model summary and solution implementation</title>
<p>On substituting Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e050">25</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e058">31</xref>) into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e007">Eq (2)</xref> along with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e069">Eq (32)</xref> into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e047">Eq (24)</xref>, the model is closed and can be used to determine uninvadable allocation strategies and the resulting equilibrium growth patterns. A schematic description of the model is in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g002">Fig 2</xref>. From our simplifying assumptions, determining an uninvadable allocation strategy reduces to an optimal control problem. We obtain locally uninvadable allocation strategies using optimal control methodology (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref094">94</xref>]), both by a “direct simultaneous” approach with the software GPOPS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref095">95</xref>] for numerical approximations and by an “indirect” approach using Pontryagin’s Maximum Principle for analytical results (sections 1–4 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). GPOPS is based on a pseudospectral method which converts the optimal control problem into a nonlinear program that can be addressed using available solvers. This direct solution approach partitions the time interval [0, <italic>T</italic>] into sub intervals and, using an initial guess of the (allocation) solution (control), finds the resulting value of the (lifetime number of offspring) objective. Applying the gradient of the objective with respect to a representation of the control, this approach refines the control until no higher objective is attained. In contrast, the indirect approach uses necessary first-order conditions that the solution must satisfy to construct the solution (see section 7 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref> for additional method details).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1005380.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Schematic description of the model.</title>
<p>The body is partitioned in three tissues. Some of the energetic expense of the reproductive tissue is for producing and maintaining offspring, and some of the energetic expense of the brain is for producing and maintaining energy-extraction skills. These skills allow extracting energy that can be used to produce and maintain the different tissues.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The model depends on 22 parameters which measure (P1) tissue mass in the newborn (<italic>x</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>0</sub> for <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s}), (P2) tissue metabolism (<italic>K</italic>, <italic>β</italic>, <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> for <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s}), (P3) demography (<italic>f</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>μ</italic>, and <italic>T</italic>), (P4) skill of the newborn (<italic>x</italic><sub>k0</sub>), (P5) skill metabolism (<italic>s</italic><sub>k</sub>, <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>k</sub>), (P6) maternal care (<italic>φ</italic><sub>0</sub> and <italic>φ</italic><sub>r</sub>), and (P7) energy extraction (<italic>α</italic> and <italic>γ</italic>). From their definitions, the parameters are measured in units of mass, energy, time, and skill. The parameter <italic>f</italic><sub>0</sub> only displaces the objective vertically and thus has no effect on the uninvadable allocation strategies. The parameter <italic>T</italic> is taken finite for numerical implementation and set as the observed age of menopause.</p>
<p>We use published data for human females to estimate 13 parameters that affect the uninvadable allocation strategies (P1–P3) (section 5,6 and Table B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). These parameters include the mass-specific production and maintenance metabolic costs of the different tissues including the brain (<italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> for <italic>i</italic> ∈ {b, r, s}), and with these parameters and in particular with their relative values fixed, the model can only generate a vastly narrower set of outcomes. These 13 parameters are in units of mass, energy, and time which we measure in kg, MJ (megajoules), and years, respectively. The remaining 8 parameters that affect the uninvadable allocation strategies (P4–P7) measure skill metabolism, skill effectiveness, environmental difficulty, and maternal care, and given that an empirically grounded relationship between skill and energy-extraction efficiency is still unavailable, these parameters are less easily estimated from available data. Their values could be estimated using optimization algorithms that minimize the difference between predicted and observed body and brain mass, but given the complexity of the model, such investigations are beyond the scope of the present paper. As a first approximation, for these parameters we identify by trial and error benchmark values that yield a model output roughly in agreement with observed ontogenetic body and brain mass data for modern human females. Such benchmark parameter values are different with power (Table C in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>) and exponential (Table D in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>) competence. The benchmark parameter values include <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>k</sub> which determine skill level units, and as we do not estimate these parameters from empirical data, we measure skill level in unspecified units denoted as “skill unit”. We first present the numerical results for the two sets of benchmark parameter values and then the results when deviating from them (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref> for analytical results and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s002">S1 Computer Code</xref> for numerical implementation).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Predicted life history stages: Childhood, adolescence, and adulthood</title>
<p>The optimal strategy we obtain divides the individual’s lifespan in three broad stages: (1) a “childhood” stage, defined as the stage lasting from birth to the age at maturity <italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub>, during which allocation to growth of reproductive tissue is zero; (2) an “adolescence” stage, defined as the stage lasting from <italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub> to the age at adulthood <italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub>, during which there is simultaneous allocation to growth of somatic and reproductive tissue; and (3) an “adulthood” stage, defined as the stage lasting from <italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub> to the end of the individual’s reproductive career, during which all growth allocation is to reproductive tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3A</xref>). These life stages are obtained with either power or exponential competence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3A and 3E</xref>). Note that the ages at maturity <italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub> and adulthood <italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub> (switching times) are not parameters but an output of the model.</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1005380.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Locally uninvadable growth strategy (<inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e071"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e071g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e071" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M71"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>) and the resulting growth patterns (<inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e072"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e072g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e072" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M72"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi>i</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>) under a me-vs-nature setting.</title>
<p>Lines are model’s results and circles are observed values in human females. Results with (A-D) power and (E-H) exponential competence. (A,E) Uninvadable growth strategy vs age. (C,G) Resulting growth metabolic rate vs age. (B,F) Resulting body and tissue mass vs age. (D,H) Resulting brain and reproductive mass vs age. Lines and circles with the same color are respectively the model’s prediction and the observed values in modern human females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref096">96</xref>]. Black circles are the observed (B,F) adult female body mass and (D,H) adult sex-averaged brain mass, either for late <italic>H. erectus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref097">97</xref>] or Neanderthals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref098">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref099">99</xref>]. The growth strategy (A,E) has numerical jitter due to negligible numerical error (Fig B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>) and is here filtered for figure clarity (see unfiltered figure in Fig D in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The obtained childhood stage, which is the only stage where there is allocation to brain growth, is further subdivided in three periods: (1a) “ante childhood”, defined here as lasting from birth to the age of brain growth onset <italic>t</italic><sub>b0</sub>, during which there is pure allocation to somatic growth; (1b) “childhood proper”, defined here as lasting from <italic>t</italic><sub>b0</sub> to the age of brain growth arrest <italic>t</italic><sub>b</sub>, during which there is simultaneous allocation to somatic and brain growth; and (1c) “preadolescence”, defined here as lasting from <italic>t</italic><sub>b</sub> to <italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub>, during which there is pure somatic growth. Hence, brain growth occurs exclusively during “childhood proper”. The occurrence of an “ante childhood” without brain growth disagrees with observation in humans. Two possible and particularly relevant reasons for this discrepancy may be either the absence of social interactions in this setting of the model, or the approximation of resting metabolic rate by a power law (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq 21</xref>) which underestimates resting metabolic rate (and thus growth metabolic rate) during ante childhood (Fig C in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>; note that although improving the fit of resting metabolic rate with body mass is straightforward, this introduces additional non-linearities that make the optimal control problem numerically more challenging and this exploration is beyond the scope of the present paper). The switching times <italic>t</italic><sub>b0</sub> and <italic>t</italic><sub>b</sub> are also an output rather than parameters of the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3A</xref>).</p>
<p>With the exception of the age of brain growth onset, the predicted timing of childhood, adolescence, and adulthood closely follows that observed in humans with competence being either a power or an exponential function of skill level, given their respective benchmark parameter values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1005380.t001">Table 1</xref>). Recall that measurement units (i.e., years, kg, and MJ), excepting skill units, are real in that they result from the units of the parameter values estimated from empirical data (Table B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Hence, while using realistic metabolic costs of brain and body, the model can correctly predict major stages of human life history with accurate timing, with the exception of no brain growth allocation during ante childhood (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1005380.t001">Table 1</xref>). Later in the paper we address how these results change with changes in parameter values.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1005380.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Predictions for life history timing and adult brain and body mass with a me-vs-nature setting and the benchmark parameter values.</title>
<p>Switching times and adult values resulting with competence as a power or exponential function (PC and EC) for the results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3</xref>. *Observed values in human females: age at maturity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref100">100</xref>], adulthood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref101">101</xref>], brain growth onset and arrest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref096">96</xref>], adult body mass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref096">96</xref>], and adult brain mass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref096">96</xref>]. †Encephalization quotient, calculated as <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e073"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e073g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e073" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M73"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>EQ</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>/</mml:mo> <mml:mo>[</mml:mo> <mml:mn>11</mml:mn> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo> <mml:mn>22</mml:mn> <mml:mo>×</mml:mo> <mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo> <mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup> <mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup> <mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn> <mml:mo>.</mml:mo> <mml:mn>76</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup> <mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> (mass in kg) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref102">102</xref>].</p>
</caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pcbi.1005380.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table border="0" frame="box" rules="all">
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2"/>
<th align="left" rowspan="2"/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Predicted with</th>
<th align="center">Observed in*</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="right">PC</th>
<th align="right">EC</th>
<th align="right"><italic>H. sapiens</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="4">Age at:</td>
<td align="left">Maturity, <italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub> [y]</td>
<td align="char" char=".">9.94</td>
<td align="char" char=".">9.70</td>
<td align="right">7–13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Adulthood, <italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub> [y]</td>
<td align="char" char=".">23.37</td>
<td align="char" char=".">17.33</td>
<td align="right">≈17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Brain growth onset, <italic>t</italic><sub>b0</sub> [y]</td>
<td align="char" char=".">2.36</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.81</td>
<td align="right">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Brain growth arrest, <italic>t</italic><sub>b</sub> [y]</td>
<td align="char" char=".">7.19</td>
<td align="char" char=".">7.34</td>
<td align="right">≈17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="3"/>
<td align="left">Adult body mass, [kg]</td>
<td align="char" char=".">53.19</td>
<td align="char" char=".">67.79</td>
<td align="right">51.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Adult brain mass, [kg]</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.02</td>
<td align="char" char=".">1.53</td>
<td align="right">1.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">EQ<sup>†</sup>, [ ]</td>
<td align="char" char=".">4.43</td>
<td align="char" char=".">5.52</td>
<td align="right">5.87</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Body and brain mass through ontogeny</title>
<p>The optimal growth strategy generates the following predicted body and brain mass throughout ontogeny. For total body mass, there is fast growth during ante childhood, followed by slow growth during childhood proper, a growth spurt during preadolescence, slow growth during adolescence, and no growth during adulthood, each of which closely follows the observed growth pattern in humans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). Most body growth is due to somatic growth, and this results because if a tissue mass is favored to grow (e.g., brain) the energy required for its production can be made available by increasing the growth metabolic rate by producing the cheapest tissue to maintain which is the soma (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e044">Eq 23</xref>; Table B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>), under our assumption that individuals balance their energy budget as in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e043">Eq (22)</xref>. The slow body growth during childhood proper results from the simultaneous allocation to somatic and brain growth and from the decreasing growth metabolic rate due to the increasing energetic costs of brain maintenance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). The growth spurt during preadolescence arises because (1) all growth metabolic rate is allocated to inexpensive somatic growth, and (2) growth metabolic rate increases due to increased metabolic rate caused by increasing, inexpensive-to-maintain somatic mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). The slow growth during adolescence is due to simultaneous somatic and reproductive growth, and to the elevated costs of reproductive tissue maintenance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). These growth patterns result in two major peaks in growth metabolic rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). While the first peak in growth metabolic rate is made possible by maternal care, the second peak is made possible by the individual’s own skills (Fig G panel D in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). After the onset of adulthood at <italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub>, growth metabolic rate is virtually depleted and allocation to growth has essentially no effect on tissue growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3C</xref>).</p>
<p>Whereas predicted body growth patterns are qualitatively similar with either power or exponential competence, they differ quantitatively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3B and 3F</xref>). With power competence, the predicted body mass is nearly identical to that observed in human females throughout life (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). In contrast, with exponential competence, the predicted body mass is larger throughout life than that of human females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3F</xref>). Our exploration of the parameter space indicates that the larger body mass with exponential competence relative to power competence is robust to parameter change (see section “A large brain is favored…” below and section 8.8 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
<p>Regarding brain mass, the model predicts it to have the following growth pattern. During ante childhood, brain mass remains static, in contrast to the observed pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3D</xref>). During childhood proper, brain mass initially grows quickly, then it slows down slightly, and finally grows quickly again before brain growth arrest at the onset of preadolescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3D</xref>). Predicted brain growth is thus delayed by the obtained ante-childhood period relative to the observed brain growth in humans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3D</xref>). As previously stated, such brain growth delay may be a result of the absence of social interactions in this model setting, or an inaccuracy arising from the underestimation of resting metabolic rate during ante childhood by the power law of body mass.</p>
<p>Predicted brain growth patterns are also qualitatively similar but quantitatively different with power and exponential competence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3D and 3H</xref>). Adult brain mass is predicted to be larger with competence as an exponential rather than as a power function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3D and 3H</xref>). As for body mass, our exploration of the parameter space indicates that the larger brain mass with exponential competence is robust to parameter change (see section “A large brain is favored…” below and section 8.8 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Moreover, the encephalization quotient (EQ, which is the ratio of observed adult brain mass over expected adult brain mass for a given body mass) is also larger with exponential competence for the benchmark parameter values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi.1005380.t001">Table 1</xref>). For illustration, with competence as a power function, the predicted adult body and brain mass approach those observed in late <italic>H. erectus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3B and 3D</xref>). In contrast, with competence as an exponential function, the predicted adult body and brain mass approach those of Neanderthals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3F and 3H</xref>). The larger EQ with exponential competence is also robust to parameter change (see section “Factors favoring a large EQ…” below and 8.8 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Skill through ontogeny</title>
<p>The obtained optimal growth strategy predicts the following patterns for the skill level at energy-extraction throughout ontogeny. Under the same parameter values as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3</xref>, the individual’s skill level increases most during childhood and adolescence, skill level continues to increase after brain growth arrest, and skill level plateaus in adulthood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g004">Fig 4</xref>). That is, skill growth is “determinate”, in agreement with empirical observations for food production skills (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Yet, if memory cost <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub> is substantially lower, skill level can continue to increase throughout life (i.e., skill growth is then “indeterminate”; Fig K panel E in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e024">Eq 14</xref>). Nevertheless, in that case, the agreement between predicted and observed body and brain mass throughout ontogeny is substantially reduced (Fig K panels B,C in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1005380.g004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g004</object-id>
<label>Fig 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Predicted skill level at energy extraction throughout ontogeny plateaus in adulthood.</title>
<p>Lines are the predicted skill level vs age with (A) power and (B) exponential competence for the results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g003">Fig 3</xref>. Circles are the observed cumulative distribution of self-reported acquisition ages of food production skills in female Tsimane horticulturalists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref081">81</xref>] multiplied by our <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e074"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e074g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e074" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M74"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. However, note that the observed skills in Tsimane involve cumulative social learning which we do not model explicitly.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The requirement for skill growth to be determinate is that the brain metabolic rate allocated to skills [<italic>s</italic><sub>k</sub><italic>B</italic><sub>rest,b</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)] becomes saturated with skill maintenance [<italic>x</italic><sub>k</sub>(<italic>t</italic>)<italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub>] within the individual’s life (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e024">Eq 14</xref>). Thus, skill can continue to grow after brain growth arrest if memory costs do not yet saturate the brain metabolic rate allocated to skills. When skill growth is determinate, an immediate prediction of the model is that adult skill level is proportional to adult brain mass. In particular, with determinate skill growth, the skill level that is asymptotically achieved [from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e048">Eq 24b</xref> setting <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e075"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e075g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e075" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M75"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e076"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e076g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e076" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M76"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>] is
<disp-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e077"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e077g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e077" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="block" id="M77"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac> <mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives> <label>(34)</label></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e078"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e078g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e078" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M78"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the asymptotic skill level, <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e079"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e079g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e079" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M79"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi> <mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the adult brain mass, <italic>s</italic><sub>k</sub> is the fraction of brain metabolic rate allocated to energy-extraction skills, and <italic>B</italic><sub>b</sub> is the brain mass-specific maintenance cost. Hence, adult skill level is proportional to adult brain mass in the model (1) because of saturation with skill maintenance of the brain metabolic rate allocated to skills and (2) because adult brain metabolic rate is found to be proportional to adult brain mass given energy conservation and the assumptions on the parameters [setting <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005380.e080"><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi.1005380.e080g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.e080" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M80"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi> <mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo> <mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi></mml:msub> <mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow> <mml:mo>=</mml:mo> <mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e022">Eq (12)</xref> yields <italic>B</italic><sub>rest,b</sub>(<italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub>) = <italic>x</italic><sub>b</sub>(<italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub>)<italic>B</italic><sub>b</sub>]. Weak correlations between cognitive ability and brain mass have been identified across taxa including humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref014">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref103">103</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref106">106</xref>]. Since skill level is here broadly understood to refer to cognitive abilities, this result offers an explanation for these correlations in terms of saturation of brain metabolic rate with skill maintenance (memory).</p>
<p>In section 8.2.3 of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>, we relax the assumption that maternal care is independent of maternal skill by allowing for such dependence (i.e., by letting maternal facilitation in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e070">Eq 33</xref> depend on maternal skill). Doing so yields the same results with exponential competence and a slightly faster body growth rate with power competence (section 8.2.3 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). The latter difference is only quantitative and arises because the chosen benchmark maternal facilitation for newborns (<italic>φ</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.6) is lower than the resulting newborn maternal facilitation (<italic>φ</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.8) when it is allowed to depend on maternal skill. In addition, the predicted adult body and brain mass are virtually the same with this relaxation for either the power or exponential competence (Fig H in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Hence, our results are robust to modification of our simplifying assumption of exogenous maternal care.</p>
<p>We now vary parameter values to assess what factors favor a large brain at adulthood in a me-vs-nature setting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>A large brain is favored by intermediate environmental difficulty, moderate skill effectiveness, and costly memory</title>
<p>We focus on varying the parameter values that were not estimated from empirical data to also assess how they impact predictions. For the switching times in the cases when the predicted adult body and brain mass are not zero, we find that the age of brain growth onset (<italic>t</italic><sub>b0</sub>) remains largely invariant to parameter change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5</xref> and Figs Q, S, U, and W in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Later ages at brain growth arrest (<italic>t</italic><sub>b</sub>) and at maturity (<italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub>) are favored by increasing environmental difficulty (increasing <italic>α</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5A</xref> and Fig S panel A in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>), decreasing skill effectiveness (decreasing <italic>γ</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5B</xref> and Fig S panel B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>), and costlier memory (increasing <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5C</xref> and Fig S panel D in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). A later age at adulthood (<italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub>) is also favored by environmental difficulty (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5A</xref> and Fig S panel A in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>) and skill ineffectiveness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5B</xref> and Fig S panel B in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>), but is favored by either small or large memory costs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5C</xref> and Fig S panel D in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). While the switching times (<italic>t</italic><sub>b0</sub>, <italic>t</italic><sub>b</sub>, <italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub>, <italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub>) vary quantitatively as parameter values change, the qualitative occurrence of an adolescence period after childhood persists (shaded regions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g005">Fig 5</xref> and Figs Q, S, U, and W in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1005380.g005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g005</object-id>
<label>Fig 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Predicted ages at brain growth onset (<italic>t</italic><sub>b0</sub>), brain growth arrest (<italic>t</italic><sub>b</sub>), maturity (<italic>t</italic><sub>m</sub>), and adulthood (<italic>t</italic><sub>a</sub>) as parameter values change with exponential competence.</title>
<p>Plots show the predicted ages (switching times) vs (A) environmental difficulty, (B) skill effectiveness, and (C) memory cost. The childhood stage is shaded in pink, and the adolescence stage is shaded in blue. For clarity in the figure, points where adult body or brain sizes are zero are not shown (such points are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6</xref>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>Regarding brain mass, a larger adult brain mass is favored by an increasingly challenging environment (increasing <italic>α</italic>; <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e069">Eq 32</xref>), but is <italic>disfavored</italic> by an exceedingly challenging environment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6A</xref>). Environmental difficulty favors a larger brain because a higher skill level is needed for energy extraction (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e069">Eq 32</xref>), and from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e024">Eq (14)</xref> a higher skill level can be gained by increasing brain metabolic rate in turn by increasing brain mass. Thus, a large brain is favored to energetically support skill growth in a challenging environment. However, with exceedingly challenging environments, the individual is favored to reproduce early without substantial body or brain growth because it fails to gain a sufficiently high skill level to maintain its body mass as maternal care decreases with age (Fig O in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi.1005380.g006" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g006</object-id>
<label>Fig 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Large adult brain mass and EQ are favored by environmental difficulty, moderate skill effectiveness, and costly memory.</title>
<p>Plots are the predicted adult body and brain mass, EQ, and skill vs parameter values with exponential competence. A-C show adult body mass (blue) and adult brain mass (red). D-F show adult EQ (green) and skill (orange). Vertical axes are in different scales. Dashed horizontal lines are the observed values in human females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref096">96</xref>].</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>A larger adult brain is favored by moderately effective skills. When skills are ineffective at energy extraction (<italic>γ</italic> → 0; <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e069">Eq 32</xref>), the brain entails little fitness benefit and fails to grow in which case the individual also reproduces without substantially growing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6B</xref>). When skill effectiveness (<italic>γ</italic>) crosses a threshold value, the fitness effect of brain becomes large enough that the brain becomes favored to grow. Yet, as skill effectiveness increases further and thus a lower skill level is sufficient for energy extraction, a smaller brain supports enough skill growth, so the optimal adult brain mass <italic>decreases</italic> with skill effectiveness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6B</xref>). Hence, adult brain mass is largest with moderately effective skill.</p>
<p>A larger brain is also favored by skills that are increasingly expensive for the brain to maintain (costly memory, increasing <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub>), but exceedingly costly memory prevents body and brain growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6C</xref>). Costly memory favors a large brain because then a larger brain mass is required to energetically support skill growth (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e024">Eq 14</xref>). If memory is exceedingly costly, skill level fails to grow and energy extraction is unsuccessful, causing the individual to reproduce without substantial growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6C</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Factors favoring a large EQ and high skill</title>
<p>A large EQ and high adult skill are generally favored by the same factors that favor a large adult brain, but there are some differences regarding memory and learning costs. First, the memory cost has a particularly strong effect favoring a large EQ because it simultaneously favors increased brain and reduced body mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6C and 6F</xref>). In contrast, increasing learning cost simultaneously reduces adult body and brain mass causing EQ to be invariant with respect to learning costs (Fig R panel D in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). That is, memory costs have a strong effect on EQ, but learning costs have little to no effect on it. Second, in contrast to its effect on EQ, increasing memory cost <italic>disfavors</italic> a high adult skill level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6F</xref>). That is, a higher EQ attained by increasing memory costs is accompained by a <italic>decrease</italic> in skill level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6C and 6F</xref>). The factors that favor a large brain, large EQ, and high skill are similar with either power or exponential competence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6</xref> and Figs R and T in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Importantly, although with the estimated parameter values the me-vs-nature setting can recover human growth patterns yielding adult body and brain mass of ancient humans, our exploration of the parameters that were not estimated from data suggests that the me-vs-nature setting cannot recover human growth patterns yielding adult body and brain mass of <italic>modern</italic> humans.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>By combining elements of life history and metabolic theories, we formulated a metabolically explicit mathematical model to study brain life history evolution that can yield testable quantitative predictions from predefined settings. We applied our model to a me-vs-nature setting where individuals have no social interactions except possibly with their mothers through maternal care, but the model can be implemented to study brain evolution more generally. Surprisingly, our results for the me-vs-nature case show that this setting can be sufficient to generate major human life history stages as well as adult brain and body mass of ancient human scale, all without social interactions, evolutionary arms races in cognition triggered by social conflict, or explicit cumulative culture. Overall, we find that in the model the brain is favored to grow to energetically support skill growth, and thus a larger brain is favored when (1) competence at energy extraction has a steep dependence on skill, (2) high skill is needed for energy extraction due to environmental difficulty and moderate skill effectiveness, and (3) skills are expensive for the brain to maintain but are still necessary for energy extraction.</p>
<p>We find that somatic tissue grows more than the other tissues because it contributes to body mass and it is the cheapest tissue to maintain. The reason for this stems from the physical constraint imposed by resting metabolic rate being a power law of body mass (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e041">Eq 21</xref>). This constraint implies that individuals with a larger body mass release more heat and thus must compensate their energy budget either by extracting more energy, storing less energy, burning less energy in activity, or leaving less energy unassimilated (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e043">Eq 22</xref>). Given the pervasiveness across living systems of the power law between resting metabolic rate and body mass, we assumed that individuals balance their energy budget this way (as is implicitly assumed by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref054">54</xref>]). If an individual balances its energy budget like this, then increasing any tissue’s mass can increase the energy available for growth, particularly if the tissue is cheap to maintain (so <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e044">Eq 23</xref> is positive). Thus, in our model all tissues have the implicit function of being able to increase the energy available for growth, given that individuals balance their energy budget as indicated, and this is why somatic tissue grows in our model.</p>
<p>The model correctly divides the individual’s lifespan into childhood, adolescence, and adulthood. The model also rightly predicts brain growth to occur only during childhood, although there is a delay in the predicted brain growth which may be due to the absence of social interactions or an underestimation of resting metabolic rate early in life by its power law approximation. Additionally, the predicted childhood stage finishes with a body growth spurt that ends at the age of maturity, as observed in human preadolescence and menarche. The model also recovers an adolescence stage with simultaneous allocation to growth and reproduction, which has been previously difficult to replicate with life history models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref032">32</xref>]. While the timing of these predicted life stages depends on the magnitude of parameter values, their relative sequence is robust to change in the parameter values that were not estimated from data. However, the childhood-adolescence-adulthood sequence may depend on the relative magnitude of metabolic costs of maintenance and production of the different tissues (i.e., on whether (1) <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> and (2) <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> for <italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic> ∈ {b, r, s}). Empirically guided refinement of both parameter values and the shape of energy-extraction efficiency is expected to allow for increasingly accurate predictions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref091">91</xref>]. Similarly, empirical data for non-human taxa should allow determining the model’s ability to predict diverse life histories and brain growth patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref107">107</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref109">109</xref>].</p>
<p>The model also offers a metabolic explanation for correlations between adult cognitive ability and brain mass observed in inter- and intraspecific studies in birds and mammals including humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref014">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref103">103</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref106">106</xref>]. The explanation is that when skills are costly for the brain to maintain (costly memory), the brain metabolic rate allocated to skills can become saturated by the energetic consumption of skill maintenance which causes adult skill level (or cognitive ability) to be proportional to brain mass (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e077">Eq 34</xref>). This proportionality between adult skill level and adult brain mass arises because the adult brain metabolic rate is found to be proportional to brain mass. This follows from energy conservation and our assumption that some of the brain (resting) metabolic rate is due to skill learning and memory (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e023">Eq 13</xref>), which does not make any assumptions about skill function. Consequently, the proportionality between adult skill level and brain mass is linear rather than non-linear: adding exponents to brain mass and skill level in Eqs (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e022">12</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e023">13</xref>) would remove the linear relationship between adult brain mass and adult skill, but it would also violate the assumption of energy conservation given the definitions of the accompanying parameters. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e077">Eq (34)</xref> also predicts that additional variation in correlations between cognitive ability and brain mass can be explained by variation in maintenance costs of brain and skill (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref110">110</xref>]), and by variation in brain metabolic rate allocation to skill. However, the proportionality between adult skill and adult brain mass arising from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005380.e077">Eq (34)</xref> assumes that the fraction of brain metabolic rate allocated to the skills of interest (<italic>s</italic><sub>k</sub>) is independent of brain mass (and similarly for <italic>B</italic><sub>b</sub> and <italic>B</italic><sub>k</sub>). So, the proportionality could break if any of these parameters depends on brain mass. Also, the model indicates that adult skill and brain mass need not be correlated since saturation with skill maintenance of the brain metabolic rate allocated to skills may not occur during the individual’s lifespan, for example if memory is inexpensive, so skill increases throughout life (Fig K panel E in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
<p>Predicted adult brain mass and skill have non-monotonic relationships with their predictor variables (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6</xref> and Figs R and T in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Consequently, conflicting inferences can be drawn if predictor variables are evaluated only on their low or high ends. For instance, increasingly challenging environments favor large brains up to a point, so that exceedingly challenging environments disfavor large brains. Thus, on the low end of environmental difficulty, the prediction that increasingly challenging environments favor large brains is consistent with ecological challenge hypotheses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref045">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref046">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref111">111</xref>]; yet, on the high end of environmental difficulty, the prediction that increasingly challenging environments disfavor large brains is consistent with constraint hypotheses according to which facilitation of environmental challenge favors larger brains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref046">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref112">112</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref114">114</xref>]. Counter-intuitively on first encounter, the finding that moderately effective skills are most conducive to a large brain and high skill is a consequence of the need of higher skill when skill effectiveness decreases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6B</xref>). Regarding memory cost, the strong effect of memory cost on favoring a high EQ at first glance suggests that a larger EQ than that observed in humans is possible if memory were costlier (see dashed lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6F</xref>). However, such larger memory costs cause a reduced adult skill level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1005380.g006">Fig 6F</xref>), and a substantial delay in body and brain growth that yields growth patterns that are inconsistent with those of humans (Figs L–N in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005380.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p>
<p>We have made a number of assumptions that, if modified, the predicted relationships may be qualitatively affected, as is known to occur with life history models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref033">33</xref>]. Assumptions whose modification may qualitatively affect predictions, as suggested by previous life-history models, include (1) different forms for the mortality rate (e.g., as a function of skills) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref069">69</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref115">115</xref>], (2) different modes of population regulation (e.g., through survival rather than through fecundity) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref069">69</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref115">115</xref>], and (3) allowing population size to change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref062">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref115">115</xref>]. Implementing modifications like these would allow to assess the level of generality of our results. Additionally, our model may be used to study allocation to tissue maintenance to address senescence.</p>
<p>Although our model does not include numerous details relevant to human life history, such as social interactions and cummulative social learning, our results are relevant for a set of hypotheses for human-brain evolution. In particular, food processing (e.g., mechanically with stone tools or by cooking) has previously been advanced as a determinant factor in human-brain evolution as it increases energy and nutrient availability from otherwise relatively inaccessible sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref007">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref116">116</xref>]. This is supported by archaeological evidence of mechanical food processing in early humans (1.5 mya in Kenya; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref116">116</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref117">117</xref>]), as well as archeological evidence of fire control in early humans with increasing certainty in younger strata (1.5 mya–130 kya; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref118">118</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1005380.ref120">120</xref>]). Our results, where individuals engage in energy extraction without considering the effects of social interactions, suggest that food processing alone could indeed have been sufficient to allow for a substantial brain expansion. In addition, food processing may help satisfy at least two of the three key conditions identified for large-brain evolution listed in the first paragraph of the Discussion. First, a shift in food-processing technology (e.g., from primarily mechanical to cooking) could create a steeper relationship between energy-extraction skill and competence by substantially facilitating energy extraction (relating to condition 1). Second, food processing (e.g., by building the required tools or lighting a fire) is a challenging feat to learn and may often fail (relating to condition 2). Yet, there are scant data allowing to judge the metabolic expense for the brain to maintain tool-making or fire-control skills (condition 3). Our results are thus consistent with the hypothesis of food processing as being a key factor in human brain expansion.</p>
<p>In sum, the model identifies various conditions favoring large-brain evolution, in particular steep competence with respect to skill, intermediate environmental difficulty, moderate skill effectiveness, and costly memory. As we did not consider social interactions, our application of the model cannot refute or support social brain hypotheses. However, application of our model to the social realm should allow for assessments of social hypotheses. Overall, our model is a step towards a quantitative theory of brain life history evolution yielding testable quantitative predictions as ecological, demographic, and social factors vary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1005380.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Appendix</label>
<caption>
<title>Appendix.</title>
<p>Analytical results, parameter estimation, numerical implementation, and supplementary numerical results.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1005380.s002" mimetype="application/zip" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005380.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Computer code</label>
<caption>
<title>Computer code.</title>
<p>MATLAB computer code for solutions using GPOPS.</p>
<p>(ZIP)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Tadeusz J. Kawecki and Michael B. Morrissey for helpful discussion, and Alexandre Courtiol and Jonathan Newton for critical comments on the paper.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref001">
<label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shettleworth</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <source>Cognition, Evolution, and Behavior</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref002">
<label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jolly</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lemur social behavior and primate intelligence</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1966</year>;<volume>153</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.153.3735.501" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.153.3735.501</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">5938775</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref003">
<label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jerison</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name>. <source>Evolution of the Brain and Intelligence</source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>1973</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref004">
<label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname> <given-names>NK</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The social function of the intellect</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Bateson</surname> <given-names>PPG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hinde</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Growing Points in Ethology</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>1976</year>. p. <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref005">
<label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Byrne</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whiten</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Machiavellian Intelligence</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>1988</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref006">
<label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Call</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández-Lloreda</surname> <given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hare</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomasello</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Humans have evolved specialized skills of social cognition: the cultural intelligence hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>317</volume>:<fpage>1360</fpage>–<lpage>1366</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1146282" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1146282</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17823346</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref007">
<label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wrangham</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <source>Catching Fire</source>. <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref008">
<label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaik</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burkart</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Social learning and evolution: the cultural intelligence hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc B</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>366</volume>:<fpage>1008</fpage>–<lpage>1016</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2010.0304" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstb.2010.0304</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21357223</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref009">
<label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Henrich</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <source>The Secret of our Success</source>. <publisher-name>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref010">
<label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fish</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lockwood</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dietary constraints on encephalization in primates</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.10136" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/ajpa.10136</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12541334</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref011">
<label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dunbar</surname> <given-names>RIM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shultz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution in the social brain</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>317</volume>:<fpage>1344</fpage>–<lpage>1347</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1145463" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1145463</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17823343</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref012">
<label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>MacLean</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrickman</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wall</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sociality, ecology, and relative brain size in lemurs</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2008.12.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jhevol.2008.12.005</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19410273</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref013">
<label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>MacLean</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandel</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oldenkamp</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hare</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Group size predicts social but not nonsocial cognition in lemurs</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e66359</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0066359" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0066359</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840450</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref014">
<label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>MacLean</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hare</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunn</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Addessi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amici</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The evolution of self-control</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>E2140</fpage>–<lpage>E2148</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1323533111" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1323533111</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24753565</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref015">
<label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jelbert</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Does absolute brain size really predict self-control? Hand-tracking training improves performance on the A-not-B task</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>20150871</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2015.0871" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rsbl.2015.0871</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26843555</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref016">
<label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matějů</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kratochvíl</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavelková</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavelková Řičánková</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vohralík</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Němec</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Absolute, not relative brain size correlates with sociality in ground squirrels</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>283</volume>:<fpage>20152725</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2015.2725" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2015.2725</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27009231</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref017">
<label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navarrete</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reader</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Street</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whalen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laland</surname> <given-names>KN</given-names></name>. <article-title>The coevolution of innovation and technical intelligence in primates</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc B</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>371</volume>:<fpage>20150186</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2015.0186" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstb.2015.0186</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26926276</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref018">
<label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cosmides</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tooby</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adaptive specializations, social exchange, and the evolution of human intelligence</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>9007</fpage>–<lpage>9014</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0914623107" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0914623107</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20445099</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref019">
<label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amodio</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frith</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meeting of minds: the medial frontal cortex and social cognition</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrn1884" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrn1884</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16552413</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref020">
<label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frith</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The social brain?</article-title> <source>Phil Trans R Soc B</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>362</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2006.2003" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstb.2006.2003</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17255010</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref021">
<label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez-Barbería</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunbar</surname> <given-names>RIM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence for coevolution of sociality and relative brain size in three orders of mammals</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>2811</fpage>–<lpage>2821</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.2007.00229.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2007.00229.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17908248</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref022">
<label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Finarelli</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain-size evolution and sociality in Carnivora</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>9345</fpage>–<lpage>9349</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0901780106" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0901780106</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474299</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref023">
<label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Babbitt</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fedrigo</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wall</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wray</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genomic signatures of diet-related shifts during human origins</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>961</fpage>–<lpage>969</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2010.2433" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2010.2433</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177690</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref024">
<label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kotrschal</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogell</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bundsen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Svensson</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zajitschek</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brännström</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Artificial selection on relative brain size in the guppy reveals costs and benefits of evolving a larger brain</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2012.11.058" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2012.11.058</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23290552</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref025">
<label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mathieson</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lazaridis</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohland</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mallick</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roodenberg</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Genome-wide patterns of selection in 230 ancient Eurasians</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>528</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature16152" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature16152</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26595274</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref026">
<label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Servedio</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandvain</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhole</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname> <given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Not just a theory—the utility of mathematical models in evolutionary biology</article-title>. <source>PLOS Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e1002017</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1002017" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.1002017</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25489940</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref027">
<label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>McElreath</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smaldino</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Replication, communication, and the population dynamics of scientific discovery</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0136088</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0136088" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0136088</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26308448</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref028">
<label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Healy</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>A critique of comparative studies of brain size</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2006.3748" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2006.3748</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17476764</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref029">
<label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Resource transfers and human life-history evolution</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Anthropol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>531</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-anthro-102214-013938" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-anthro-102214-013938</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref030">
<label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stearns</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Life-history tactics: a review of the ideas</article-title>. <source>Q Rev Biol</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/409052" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/409052</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">778893</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref031">
<label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stearns</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koella</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>. <article-title>The evolution of phenotypic plasticity in life-history traits: predictions of reaction norms for age and size at maturity</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>913</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2408752" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/2408752</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref032">
<label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kozłowski</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Optimal allocation of resources to growth and reproduction: implications for age and size at maturity</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0169-5347(92)90192-E" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0169-5347(92)90192-E</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21235937</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref033">
<label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stearns</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>. <source>The Evolution of Life Histories</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref034">
<label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roff</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <source>The Evolution of Life Histories</source>. <publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher-name>; <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref035">
<label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Charlesworth</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <source>Evolution in age-structured populations</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref036">
<label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aiello</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>The expensive-tissue hypothesis: the brain and the digestive system in human and primate evolution</article-title>. <source>Curr Anthropol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/204350" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/204350</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref037">
<label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laughlin</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Ruyter van Steveninck</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>. <article-title>The metabolic cost of neural information</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/236" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/236</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10195106</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref038">
<label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Isler</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaik</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Metabolic costs of brain size evolution</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>560</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2006.0538" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rsbl.2006.0538</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17148287</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref039">
<label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barrickman</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastian</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isler</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaik</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Life history costs and benefits of encephalization: a comparative test using data from long-term studies of primates in the wild</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2007.08.012" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jhevol.2007.08.012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18068214</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref040">
<label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roughgarden</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Shoot/root balance of plants: optimal growth of a system with many vegetative organs</article-title>. <source>Theor Popul Biol</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0040-5809(84)90007-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0040-5809(84)90007-8</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref041">
<label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roff</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predicting body size with life history models</article-title>. <source>BioScience</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>323</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1310236" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/1310236</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref042">
<label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perrin</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Optimal resource allocation and the marginal value of organs</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>1344</fpage>–<lpage>1369</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/285390" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/285390</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref043">
<label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Irie</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Optimal growth pattern of defensive organs: the diversity of shell growth among mollusks</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>165</volume>:<fpage>238</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/427157" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/427157</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15729653</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref044">
<label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Klug</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonsall</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Life history and the evolution of parental care</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>823</fpage>–<lpage>835</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.2009.00854.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2009.00854.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19796144</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref045">
<label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hurtado</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>. <article-title>A theory of human life history evolution: diet, intelligence, and longevity</article-title>. <source>Evol Anthropol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/1520-6505(2000)9:4%3C156∷AID-EVAN5%3E3.0.CO;2-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/1520-6505(2000)9:4%3C156∷AID-EVAN5%3E3.0.CO;2-7</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref046">
<label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robson</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The emergence of humans: the coevolution of intelligence and longevity with intergenerational transfers</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>10221</fpage>–<lpage>10226</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.152502899" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.152502899</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12122210</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref047">
<label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Arbilly</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grodzinskic</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>An arms race between producers and scroungers can drive the evolution of social cognition</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/beheco/aru002" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/beheco/aru002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24822021</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref048">
<label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Piantadosi</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Extraordinary intelligence and the care of infants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>6874</fpage>–<lpage>6879</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1506752113" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1506752113</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27217560</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref049">
<label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gavrilets</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Collective action and the collaborative brain</article-title>. <source>J R Soc Interface</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>20141067</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2014.1067" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rsif.2014.1067</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25551149</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref050">
<label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gavrilets</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vose</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The dynamics of Machiavellian intelligence</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>16823</fpage>–<lpage>16828</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0601428103" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0601428103</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17075072</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref051">
<label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>McNally</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cooperation and the evolution of intelligence</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2012</year>; <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2012.0206" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2012.0206</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22496188</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref052">
<label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kooijman</surname> <given-names>SALM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Energy budgets can explain body size relations</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0022-5193(86)80107-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0022-5193(86)80107-2</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref053">
<label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kooijmann</surname> <given-names>SALM</given-names></name>. <source>Dynamic Energy and Mass Budgets in Biological Systems</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref054">
<label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enquist</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>A general model for ontogenetic growth</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>413</volume>:<fpage>628</fpage>–<lpage>631</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/35098076" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/35098076</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11675785</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref055">
<label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moses</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woodruff</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Energy uptake and allocation during ontogeny</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>322</volume>:<fpage>736</fpage>–<lpage>739</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1162302" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1162302</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18974352</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref056">
<label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grady</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enquist</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dettweiler-Robinson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence for mesothermy in dinosaurs</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>344</volume>:<fpage>1268</fpage>–<lpage>1272</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1253143" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1253143</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24926017</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref057">
<label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richerson</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <source>Culture and the Evolutionary Process</source>. <publisher-name>Univ. Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>1985</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref058">
<label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Potts</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faith</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Alternating high and low climate variability: The context of natural selection and speciation in Plio-Pleistocene hominin evolution</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2015.06.014" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jhevol.2015.06.014</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26315724</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref059">
<label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>León</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Life histories as adaptive strategies</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0022-5193(76)90062-X" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0022-5193(76)90062-X</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">957718</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref060">
<label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Charnov</surname> <given-names>EL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trade-off-invariant rules for evolutionarily stable life histories</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>387</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/387393a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/387393a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9163423</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref061">
<label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>. <source>The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clarendon</publisher-name>; <year>1930</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref062">
<label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tuljapurkar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <source>Population Dynamics in Variable Environments</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>1980</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref063">
<label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eshel</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname> <given-names>MW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Initial increase of new mutants and some continuity properties of ESS in two-locus systems</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>631</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/284303" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/284303</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref064">
<label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrière</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gatto</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Lyapunov exponents and the mathematics of invasion in oscillatory or chaotic populations</article-title>. <source>Theor Popul Biol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/tpbi.1995.1024" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/tpbi.1995.1024</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref065">
<label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Metz</surname> <given-names>JAJ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Thoughts on the geometry of meso-evolution: collecting mathematical elements for a post-modern synthesis</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Chalub</surname> <given-names>FACC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, editors. <source>The mathematics of Darwin’s legacy. Mathematics and biosciences in interaction</source>. <publisher-loc>Basel</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Birkhäuser</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>. p. <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref066">
<label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rousset</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <source>Genetic Structure and Selection in Subdivided Populations</source>. <publisher-name>Princeton Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref067">
<label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leimar</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>. <article-title>Multidimensional convergence stability</article-title>. <source>Evol Ecol Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref068">
<label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mullon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akçay</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Cleve</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Invasion fitness, inclusive fitness, and reproductive numbers in heterogeneous populations</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1689</fpage>–<lpage>1702</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/evo.12980" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/evo.12980</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27282317</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref069">
<label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mylius</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diekmann</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>. <article-title>On evolutionarily stable life histories, optimization and the need to be specific about density dependence</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/3545651" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/3545651</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref070">
<label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dieckmann</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heino</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parvinen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>The adaptive dynamics of function-valued traits</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>241</volume>:<fpage>370</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2005.12.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jtbi.2005.12.002</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16460763</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref071">
<label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Metz</surname> <given-names>JAJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mylius</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diekmann</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>. <article-title>When does evolution optimize?</article-title> <source>Evol Ecol Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref072">
<label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Metz</surname> <given-names>JAJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staňková</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johanson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>The canonical equation of adaptive dynamics for life histories: from fitness-returns to selection gradients and Pontryagin’s maximum principle</article-title>. <source>J Math Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1125</fpage>–<lpage>1152</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00285-015-0938-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00285-015-0938-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26586121</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref073">
<label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ronce</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Promislow</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Kin competition, natal dispersal and the moulding of senescence by natural selection</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>3659</fpage>–<lpage>3667</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2010.1095" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2010.1095</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20591867</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref074">
<label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ziółko</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozłowski</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of body size: an optimization model</article-title>. <source>Math Biosci</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0025-5564(83)90032-9" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0025-5564(83)90032-9</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref075">
<label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blaxter</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <source>Energy Metabolism in Animals and Man</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref076">
<label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Mier</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tempel</surname> <given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perlmutter</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raichle</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changes in brain activity during motor learning measured with PET: effects of hand of performance and practice</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>2177</fpage>–<lpage>2199</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9772270</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref077">
<label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schiltz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bodart</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubois</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dejardin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roucoux</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Neuronal mechanisms of perceptual learning: changes in human brain activity with training in orientation discrimination</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/nimg.1998.0394" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/nimg.1998.0394</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9918727</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref078">
<label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shannona</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaishnavia</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vlassenkoa</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimonya</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutlina</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raichle</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain aerobic glycolysis and motor adaptation learning</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>E3782</fpage>–<lpage>E3791</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1604977113" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1604977113</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref079">
<label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nyberg</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Habib</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McIntosh</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tulving</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reactivation of encoding-related brain activity during memory retrieval</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>11120</fpage>–<lpage>11124</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.97.20.11120" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.97.20.11120</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11005878</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref080">
<label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname> <given-names>XN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Intrinsic resting-state activity predicts working memory brain activation and behavioral performance</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>3204</fpage>–<lpage>3215</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/hbm.22136" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/hbm.22136</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22711376</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref081">
<label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schniter</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gurven</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname> <given-names>NT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Skill ontogeny among Tsimane forager-horticulturalists</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthrop</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>158</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajpa.22757" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/ajpa.22757</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25921880</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref082">
<label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiber</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Body size and metabolism</article-title>. <source>Hilgardia</source>. <year>1932</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3733/hilg.v06n11p315" xlink:type="simple">10.3733/hilg.v06n11p315</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref083">
<label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kleiber</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <source>The Fire of Life</source>. <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>; <year>1961</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref084">
<label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name>. <source>The Ecological Implications of Body Size</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>1983</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref085">
<label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt-Nielsen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <source>Scaling</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>; <year>1984</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref086">
<label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkhoff</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Messerman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Itagaki</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ontogenetic Scaling of Metabolism, Growth, and Assimilation: Testing Metabolic Scaling Theory with <italic>Manduca sexta</italic> Larvae</article-title>. <source>Physiol Biochem Zool</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/664619" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/664619</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22418708</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref087">
<label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nagylaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <source>Introduction to Theoretical Population Genetics</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>; <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref088">
<label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>McGee</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsueh</surname> <given-names>AJW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Initial and cyclic recruitment of ovarian follicles</article-title>. <source>Endocrine Reviews</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1210/edrv.21.2.0394" xlink:type="simple">10.1210/edrv.21.2.0394</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782364</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref089">
<label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname> <given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soong</surname> <given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of the antral follicle count to predict the outcome of assisted reproductive technologies</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0015-0282(97)00557-8" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0015-0282(97)00557-8</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9531887</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref090">
<label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Skaperdas</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Contest success functions</article-title>. <source>Econ Theory</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF01213906" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF01213906</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref091">
<label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skaperdas</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaidya</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Contest functions: theoretical foundations and issues in estimation</article-title>. <source>Int J Ind Organ</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijindorg.2012.06.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ijindorg.2012.06.007</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref092">
<label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hirshleifer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Theorizing about conflict</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartley</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandler</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Handbook of Defense and Economics</source>. vol. <volume>1</volume>. <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>. p. <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref093">
<label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pontzer</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Energy expenditure in humans and other primates: a new synthesis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Anthropol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-anthro-102214-013925" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-anthro-102214-013925</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref094">
<label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sydsæter</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seierstad</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strom</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <source>Further Mathematics for Economic Analysis</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref095">
<label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name>. <article-title>GPOPS-II: A MATLAB Software for solving multiple-phase optimal control problems using hp-adaptive Gaussian quadrature collocation methods and sparse nonlinear programming</article-title>. <source>ACM Trans Math Softw</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2558904" xlink:type="simple">10.1145/2558904</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref096">
<label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzawa</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chugani</surname> <given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname> <given-names>LI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipovich</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muzik</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hof</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Metabolic costs and evolutionary implications of human brain development</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>13010</fpage>–<lpage>13015</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1323099111" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1323099111</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25157149</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref097">
<label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>McHenry</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tempo and mode in human evolution</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>6780</fpage>–<lpage>6786</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.91.15.6780" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.91.15.6780</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8041697</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref098">
<label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Froehle</surname> <given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Churchill</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Energetic competition between Neandertals and anatomically modern humans</article-title>. <source>PaleoAnthropology</source>. <year>2009</year>; p. <fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref099">
<label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ruff</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trinkaus</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holliday</surname> <given-names>TW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Body mass and encephalization in Pleistocene <italic>Homo</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>387</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/387173a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/387173a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144286</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref100">
<label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gluckman</surname> <given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution, development and timing of puberty</article-title>. <source>Trends Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tem.2005.11.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.tem.2005.11.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311040</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref101">
<label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname> <given-names>PI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morelli</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tronick</surname> <given-names>EZ</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Child caretakers of among the Efé foragers in the Ituri forest</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewlett</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Hunter-Gatherer Childhoods</source>. <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>. p. <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref102">
<label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relative brain size and basal metabolic rate in terrestrial vertebrates</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>293</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/293057a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/293057a0</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7266659</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref103">
<label>103</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Andreasen</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flaum</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swayze</surname> <given-names>V</given-names> <suffix>II</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Leary</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alliger</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Intelligence and brain structure in normal individuals</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1176/ajp.150.1.130" xlink:type="simple">10.1176/ajp.150.1.130</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8417555</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref104">
<label>104</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deaner</surname> <given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isler</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burkart</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaik</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overall brain size, and not encephalization quotient, best predicts cognitive ability across non-human primates</article-title>. <source>Brain Behav Evol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000102973" xlink:type="simple">10.1159/000102973</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510549</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref105">
<label>105</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pietschniga</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penke</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wicherts</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeiler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voracek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of associations between human brain volume and intelligence differences: How strong are they and what do they mean?</article-title> <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.09.017" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.09.017</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref106">
<label>106</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Benson-Amram</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dantzer</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stricker</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holekamp</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain size predicts problem-solving ability in mammalian carnivores</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>2532</fpage>–<lpage>2537</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1505913113" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1505913113</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26811470</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref107">
<label>107</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moses</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woodruff</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nekola</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Revisiting a model of ontogenetic growth: estimating model parameters from theory and data</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>171</volume>:<fpage>632</fpage>–<lpage>645</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/587073" xlink:type="simple">10.1086/587073</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18419571</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref108">
<label>108</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname> <given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Life history in comparative perspective</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Smuts</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheney</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seyfarth</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wrangham</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struhsaker</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Primate Societies</source>. <publisher-name>The Univ. of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>1987</year>. p. <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref109">
<label>109</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Leigh</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Brain growth, life history, and cognition in primate and human evolution</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajp.20012" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/ajp.20012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15027089</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref110">
<label>110</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olkowicz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kocourek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucǎn</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porteš</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitch</surname> <given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herculano-Houzel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Birds have primate-like numbers of neurons in the forebrain</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>7255</fpage>–<lpage>7260</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1517131113" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1517131113</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27298365</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref111">
<label>111</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vincze</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>. <article-title>Light enough to travel or wise enough to stay? Brain size evolution and migratory behavior in birds</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>2123</fpage>–<lpage>2133</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/evo.13012" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/evo.13012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27436482</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref112">
<label>112</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Austad</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Primate longevity: Its place in the mammalian scheme</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>261</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ajp.1350280403" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/ajp.1350280403</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref113">
<label>113</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hintze</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hertwig</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Janus face of Darwinian competition</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>13662</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep13662" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/srep13662</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26354182</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref114">
<label>114</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlap</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ragazzi</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krahe</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salazar</surname> <given-names>VL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predators inhibit brain cell proliferation in natural populations of electric fish, <italic>Brachyhypopomus occidentalis</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc B</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>283</volume>:<fpage>20152113</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2015.2113" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.2015.2113</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26842566</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref115">
<label>115</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Caswell</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <source>Matrix Population Models</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Sinauer</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref116">
<label>116</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zink</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lieberman</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of meat and Lower Palaeolithic food processing techniques on chewing in human</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>531</volume>:<fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature16990" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature16990</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26958832</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref117">
<label>117</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Keeley</surname> <given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Microwear polishes on early stone tools from Koobi Fora, Kenya</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1981</year>;<volume>293</volume>:<fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/293464a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/293464a0</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref118">
<label>118</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name>. <source>The Human Career</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-name>The Univ. of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref119">
<label>119</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roebroeks</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villa</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>On the earliest evidence for habitual use of fire in Europe</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>5209</fpage>–<lpage>5214</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1018116108" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1018116108</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21402905</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1005380.ref120">
<label>120</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Berna</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horwitz</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brink</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bamford</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Microstratigraphic evidence of in situ fire in the Acheulean strata of Wonderwerk Cave, Northern Cape province, South Africa</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>E1215</fpage>–<lpage>E1220</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1117620109" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1117620109</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22474385</object-id></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>