<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="article-commentary" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">pcbi</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="flc">plcb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0010059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">05-PLCB-PV-0225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plcb-01-06-06</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Science Policy</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Interdisciplinary research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>NIH Roadmap Interdisciplinary Research Initiatives</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">NIH Roadmap</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huerta</surname><given-names>Michael F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>Gregory K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilder</surname><given-names>Elizabeth L</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>Dushanka V</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>Patricia A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>David A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>Lawrence A</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mhuert1@mail.nih.gov</email></corresp><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="n102"><p>Michael F. Huerta is Associate Director, National Institute of Mental Health and co-leader of the National Institutes of Health Roadmap Interdisciplinary Research Consortia Initiative; Gregory K. Farber is Program Director, National Center for Research Resources and co-leader of the National Institutes of Health Roadmap Interdisciplinary Research Consortia Initiative; Elizabeth L. Wilder is Program Director, National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases and Coordinator of the National Institutes of Health Roadmap Interdisciplinary Research Initiatives; Dushanka V. Kleinman is Assistant Director for Roadmap Coordination, Office of the Director; Patricia A. Grady is Director, National Institute of Nursing Research and co-leader of the National Institutes of Health Roadmap Interdisciplinary Research Initiatives; David A. Schwartz is Director, National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences and co-leader of the National Institutes of Health Roadmap Interdisciplinary Research Initiatives; Lawrence A. Tabak is Director, National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research and co-leader of the National Institutes of Health Roadmap Interdisciplinary Research Initiatives, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e59</elocation-id><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Huerta et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Public Domain declaration which stipulates that, once placed in the public domain, this work may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose.</license-p></license></permissions><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts><!--===== Restructure custom-meta-wrap to custom-meta-group =====--><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Citation:</meta-name><meta-value>Huerta MF, Farber GK, Wilder EL, Kleinman DV, Grady PA, et al. (2005) NIH roadmap interdisciplinary research initiatives. PLoS Comput Biol 1(6): e59.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title/><p>A recent Perspective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0010059-b001">1</xref>] suggested that the National Institutes of Health (NIH) Roadmap interdisciplinary research initiatives (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nihroadmap.nih.gov/interdisciplinary/" xlink:type="simple">http://nihroadmap.nih.gov/interdisciplinary/</ext-link>) embrace interdisciplinary teams without recognizing the importance of interdisciplinary individuals, and that these initiatives recognize something other than scientific questions as drivers of interdisciplinary research. As representatives of the implementation work group for these initiatives, we welcome this opportunity to clarify the approach that the interdisciplinary portion of the NIH Roadmap is taking to support science conducted beyond the borders of individual disciplines.</p><p>The NIH Roadmap interdisciplinary research work group issued seven requests for applications (RFAs). Recognizing that interdisciplinary individuals require knowledge of multiple disciplines, the work group emphasized individual training in four of these RFAs. Together, the training initiatives represent a coherent trans-NIH effort to not only provide training opportunities to individuals, but in the process, nurture and cultivate interest and investment in interdisciplinary research at the organizations to which those grants were awarded. The driving forces behind which disciplines are intertwined and drawn upon in these training activities are the questions that those participating are interested in pursuing (and which are, of course, relevant to the mission of the NIH).</p><p>Support provided under two other RFAs is also aimed at individuals—in these cases, to facilitate the development and enhancement of methods that work across disciplines contributing to behavioral, social, and biomedical research. Again, the scientific questions that interest those being funded will determine the nature of this interdisciplinary activity.</p><p>Finally, one RFA encouraged projects comprising teams of investigators from different disciplines to begin to develop new ways of thinking about, and addressing, significant research problems in research relevant to health and illness. Grants awarded under this RFA were specifically meant to facilitate thoughtful planning for what were hoped to become long-term interdisciplinary research projects. Again, these efforts are driven by the scientific questions that interest the participating investigators.</p><p>Very recently, the National Academies published “Facilitating Interdisciplinary Research” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi-0010059-b002">2</xref>], a report that considered several aspects of this topic from many perspectives. We are delighted that the conceptualization and implementation of the NIH Roadmap interdisciplinary research initiatives conform well with the findings and recommendations presented in that report, including the importance of both individuals and teams in conducting such research.</p><p>It is clear that interdisciplinary research will play an increasingly significant role in improving human health. In recognition of this, the NIH is proceeding deliberately and rapidly to enhance its ability to advance this important and exciting paradigm. The Roadmap initiatives described above, which support both individual and team efforts and which are driven by the scientific questions that are of greatest interest to investigators and trainees, represent a major thrust in this direction.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>NIH</term><def><p>National Institutes of Health</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RFA</term><def><p>requests for application</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pcbi-0010059-b001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
					<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
					<year>2005</year>
					<article-title>“Antedisciplinary” science.</article-title>
					<source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
					<volume>1</volume>
					<elocation-id>e6.</elocation-id>
					<comment>DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0010006" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0010006</ext-link></comment>
				</element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi-0010059-b002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
					<collab xlink:type="simple">National Academy of Sciences</collab>
					<year>2005</year>
					<source>Facilitating interdisciplinary research</source>
					<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>
					<!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">306</size>
					<comment>p.</comment>
				</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>