<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="correction" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PBIOLOGY-D-14-00584</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001818</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correction</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Correction: The Sphingolipid Receptor S1PR2 Is a Receptor for Nogo-A Repressing Synaptic Plasticity</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">The <italic>PLOS Biology</italic> Staff</collab></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<elocation-id>e1001818</elocation-id><permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The PLOS Biology Staff</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="RA1" related-article-type="corrected-article" ext-link-type="uri" page="e1001763" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001763"> <article-title>The Sphingolipid Receptor S1PR2 Is a Receptor for Nogo-A Repressing Synaptic Plasticity</article-title></related-article><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In the legend for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001818-g001">Figure 4</xref>, there is a misspelling. The correct spelling is: 50 µm. The authors have provided a corrected version here.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001818-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001763.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>S1PR2 mediates Nogo-A-Δ20- and myelin-induced inhibition of cell spreading and neurite outgrowth.</title>
<p>(A,C) Representative pictures of 3T3 fibroblasts treated with JTE-013 or vehicle (DMSO) (A), or stably carrying a S1pr2 shRNA (sh-S1pr2) or empty vector (sh-Vec) construct (C) and plated on control, Nogo-A-Δ20 or myelin substrates. (B,D) Cell spreading quantification of (A) and (C). (E) Representative pictures of MEFs isolated from WT or S1PR2<sup>−/−</sup> mice and plated on control, Nogo-A- Δ20, or myelin substrates. (F) Cell spreading quantification of (E). Cells were stained with Alexa488-conjugated Phalloidin in (A, C, and E). (G,I) Representative pictures of P5–8 cerebellar granule neurons treated with JTE-013 or DMSO (G), or isolated from S1PR2<sup>−/−</sup> or WT mice (I) and plated on PLL (ctrl), Nogo-A-Δ20 or myelin substrates. (H,J) Normalized mean neurite length per cell quantification of (G) and (I). Neurons were stained with βIII-Tubulin in (G) and (I). Data shown are means ± SEM (n  =  3–6 experiments; *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001). Scale bars: 50 µm.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001818.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001818-g002">Figure 5</xref> is incorrect. Figure panel 5H was an inadvertent duplication of the figure panel 5G. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001818-g002">Figures 5G and H</xref> show ELISA quantifications of extra- (EC) and intracellular (IC) S1P levels in 3T3 cells (G) and cerebellar granule neurons (H) before and after 30 and 60 min incubation with Nogo-A-Δ20. The authors have provided a corrected version here.</p>
<fig id="pbio-1001818-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001763.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Nogo-A-Δ20 inhibition is mediated via the G13-LARG-RhoA signaling axis and can be modulated by exogenous S1P.</title>
<p>(A) 3T3 cells transfected with siRNAs against G12, G13, Gq, or Larg, or control (ctrl) siRNA were replated on a Nogo-A-Δ20 substrate and assessed for cell spreading. Gi/o was blocked with Pertussis Toxin (PTX) for which saline was used as control. JTE-013 was co-applied to G13-siRNA-treated cells to investigate a cumulative effect. (B) Transfection of DIV4 E19 cortical neurons with siRNA against G13 but not G12 similarly rescued Nogo-A-Δ20-induced neurite outgrowth inhibition. (C,D) Nogo-A-Δ20-induced RhoA activation was assessed in JTE-013- versus DMSO-treated cells (C) or in cells carrying a stable knockdown of S1PR2 (sh-S1pr2) versus control vector (sh-Vec) (D). (E,F) Relative quantification of (C) and (D), respectively. (G,H) Competitive ELISA quantifications of extra- (EC) and intracellular (IC) S1P levels in 3T3 cells (G) and cerebellar granule neurons (H) before and after 30 and 60 min incubation with Nogo-A-Δ20. (I) Quantification of Nogo-A-Δ20-mediated cell spreading inhibition in the presence of the SphK-specific blocker D,L-threo-dihydrosphingosine (DHS) or in SphK1−/− or SphK2−/− MEFs. (J,K) 3T3 cells were plated on a Nogo-A-Δ20 substrate in the presence of the function blocking anti-S1P antibody Sphingomab (J) or of exogenous S1P (K) and assessed for cell spreading. Co-application of JTE-013 significantly reversed the modulatory effects obtained by S1P (K) but not anti-S1P (J). Anti-BrdU antibody or methanol was used as control in (J) and (K). Data shown are means ± SEM (n  =  3–6 experiments; *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001818.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="pbio.1001818-Kempf1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kempf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tews</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arzt</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obermair</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The Sphingolipid Receptor S1PR2 Is a Receptor for Nogo-A Repressing Synaptic Plasticity</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>12(1)</volume>: <fpage>e1001763</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001763" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001763</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>