<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-14-00005</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant science</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Synthetic biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Systems biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Theoretical biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Model organisms</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Variability of Metabolite Levels Is Linked to Differential Metabolic Pathways in Arabidopsis's Responses to Abiotic Stresses</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Differential Pathways and Metabolite Variability</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Töpfer</surname><given-names>Nadine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scossa</surname><given-names>Federico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>Alisdair</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikoloski</surname><given-names>Zoran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Systems Biology and Mathematical Modeling Group, Max Planck Institute of Molecular Plant Physiology, Potsdam, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Central Metabolism Group, Max Planck Institute of Molecular Plant Physiology, Potsdam, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Consiglio per la Ricerca e la Sperimentazione in Agricoltura, Centro di ricerca per l'Orticoltura, Pontecagnano (Salerno), Italy</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugh</surname><given-names>Jason M.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>North Carolina State University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">nikoloski@mpimp-golm.mpg.de</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: NT. Performed the experiments: NT. Analyzed the data: NT ZN. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: NT ZN. Wrote the paper: NT ZN. Interpreted the findings: NT FS AF ZN.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003656</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Töpfer et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Constraint-based approaches have been used for integrating data in large-scale metabolic networks to obtain insights into metabolism of various organisms. Due to the underlying steady-state assumption, these approaches are usually not suited for making predictions about metabolite levels. Here, we ask whether we can make inferences about the variability of metabolite levels from a constraint-based analysis based on the integration of transcriptomics data. To this end, we analyze time-resolved transcriptomics and metabolomics data from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> under a set of eight different light and temperature conditions. In a previous study, the gene expression data have already been integrated in a genome-scale metabolic network to predict pathways, termed modulators and sustainers, which are differentially regulated with respect to a biochemically meaningful data-driven null model. Here, we present a follow-up analysis which bridges the gap between flux- and metabolite-centric methods. One of our main findings demonstrates that under certain environmental conditions, the levels of metabolites acting as substrates in modulators or sustainers show significantly lower temporal variations with respect to the remaining measured metabolites. This observation is discussed within the context of a systems-view of plasticity and robustness of metabolite contents and pathway fluxes. Our study paves the way for investigating the existence of similar principles in other species for which both genome-scale networks and high-throughput metabolomics data of high quality are becoming increasingly available.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>Organisms are usually exposed to changing environments and balance these perturbations by altering their metabolic state. Gaining a deeper understanding of metabolic adjustment to varying external conditions is important for the development of advanced engineering strategies for microorganisms as well as for higher plants. One tool which is particularly suited for investigating these processes is genome-scale metabolic models. These large-scale representations of the underlying metabolic networks enable the integration of experimental data and application of constrain-based mathematical approaches to estimate flux rates through the chemical reactions of the network under different environmental scenarios. However, for most of these approaches the assumption of a steady-state (flux balance) is indispensable and therefore precludes the prediction of metabolite concentrations. Here, we present a data-driven observation that relates results from a flux-centric constraint-based approach that is based on transcriptomics data to metabolite levels from the same experiments. Our observations suggest that constraint-based modeling approaches in combination with high-throughput data can be used to infer regulatory principles about the plasticity and robustness of metabolic behavior from the stoichiometry of the underlying reactions alone.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Max-Planck-Society (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mpg.de/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mpg.de/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Organisms, especially plants, are exposed to almost perpetually changing environments (<italic>e.g.</italic>, light intensity and quality, nutrient and water supply) to which they respond by readjusting their cellular setup to efficiently utilize available resources and to ensure viability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Dodd1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Kooke1">[6]</xref>. These transitions are often systemic in that they affect almost all levels of cellular organization, starting from gene expression to protein abundances and metabolite levels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Cramer1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Gechev1">[9]</xref>. Therefore, a systems-based analysis is particularly suited for understanding the responses of plants to changes in the environment. Such an approach offers the possibility to integrate data which were simultaneously collected across different cellular levels to identify dependence between processes and to aid in testing hypotheses concerning the behavior of individual components or pathways.</p>
<p>Constraint-based approaches provide a modeling framework which is particularly amenable for systems-based analyses, since they not only allow for the integration of high-throughput data, but also rely almost solely on the stoichiometry of the reactions included in the models. For instance, with the help of Flux Balance Analysis (FBA, for details see Material and Method section) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Varma1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Orth1">[11]</xref> condition-specific steady-state flux distributions and growth capabilities can be readily predicted <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Monk1">[12]</xref>. Moreover, recent studies have established that integration of high-throughput data can narrow down the space of feasible flux distributions and, therefore, results in improved predictions of biomass or contributes to more physiologically realistic engineering strategies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Lewis1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Hyduke1">[15]</xref>. The existing constraint-based approaches, which integrate data rely mostly on transcriptomics data and assume a relationship between the expression level of a given gene and the flux boundaries of the corresponding reaction in the metabolic network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Blazier1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Colijn1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-OBrien1">[17]</xref>.</p>
<p>However, one of the main drawbacks of most constraint-based approaches lies in the nature of their problem formulation, <italic>i.e.</italic>, the steady-state assumption, which precludes the integration and prediction of metabolite levels (detailed in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> section). Therefore, these approaches usually neglect the metabolome <italic>i.e.</italic>, the levels of all considered metabolites which, along with reaction fluxes, act as one of the most informative indicators of the cellular metabolic state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Fiehn1">[18]</xref>. Existing attempts to integrate metabolite levels/concentrations into constraint-based approaches are restricted to predictions of reaction directionality via thermodynamic analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Hamilton1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Kmmel1">[21]</xref> or require relaxation of the steady-state assumption <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Mahadevan1">[22]</xref>. In the current study, we ask whether (and if so, to what extent) we can make inferences about metabolite levels from a constraint-based analysis that is based on the integration of transcriptomics data.</p>
<p>In order to do so, we extend a previous study in which we used microarray data from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer2">[24]</xref> and integrated them in a metabolic network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-MintzOron1">[25]</xref> to predict flux capacities for a large set of pathways under eight different light- and temperature conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Caldana1">[26]</xref>. Furthermore, to make statistical statements, we compared the flux capacity profiles to those obtained from a biochemically meaningful data-driven null model. Based on this, we defined a pathway to be differential under a given condition if it exhibits a flux capacity profile that has an average absolute <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> greater that 2 with respect to the null model. Moreover, we introduced the concept of metabolic sustainers and modulators. Sustainers are metabolic functions that are differentially up-regulated with respect to the null model and sustain a certain functioning, whereas modulators are differentially down-regulated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer2">[24]</xref> to control a certain flux and modulate affected processes. A more detailed description of this study is given in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref> section.</p>
<p>Here, we present observations that link predictions made from the integration of transcriptomics data to metabolomics data from the same experiment. By doing so, we bridge the gap between flux- and metabolite-centric approaches. Most importantly, our findings demonstrate that under certain conditions, metabolites acting as substrates in pathways defined as modulators or sustainers of the metabolic state show a significantly lower temporal variation in comparison to the remaining metabolites. These observations are discussed within the context of a systems-view of plasticity and robustness of metabolite content as well as reaction/pathway fluxes. Taken together, our results demonstrate the power of transcriptomic data in predicting metabolic behavior in large-scale models and suggest an underlying regulatory principle governing metabolic stability.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Data integration in a constraint-based model to predict condition-specific differential metabolic functions</title>
<p>FBA's objective function has a large effect on the predicted flux distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Schuetz1">[27]</xref>. For microorganisms under ambient conditions, the maximization of growth is a widely used cellular objective <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Edwards1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Feist1">[29]</xref>. However, when modeling plants metabolism this assumed objective does not necessarily hold true. Plants are more complex than microorganisms. They have multiple compartments within the cell, different cell types, several tissues and organs, which make it difficult to define a single objective function for the entire plant. Defining such an objective becomes even more challenging under stress conditions which have been shown to drastically alter plant's cellular chemical composition (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Obata1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Urano1">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Cook1">[31]</xref> and references therein).</p>
<p>In consideration of the absence of a reasonable biological objective function for plants experiencing stress, in our previously presented approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref> we did not attempt to make predictions about actual fluxes through a metabolic pathway but rather aimed at predicting flux capacities. These capacities are derived from the integration of transcriptomics data into a large-scale metabolic model and represent maximum fluxes which certain pathways can carry under certain environmental conditions. While this concept can also be applied to single reactions of a network, we relied on the investigation of the functional units, the pathways, or in a more generic terminology, the metabolic functions.</p>
<p>We employed a transcriptomics dataset which captures the temporal response of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> to eight different light and temperature conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Caldana1">[26]</xref> and used the data to constrain the upper and lower flux boundaries of the reactions based on the E-Flux method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Colijn1">[16]</xref> in a recent compartmentalized genome-scale model of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-MintzOron1">[25]</xref>. Subsequently, we predicted the flux capacities through a set of 167 metabolic functions, from primary and secondary metabolism, for each time-point and each condition.</p>
<p>Furthermore, to make statistical statements about the metabolic functions under consideration we compared the resulting flux capacities to predictions from a null model as a reference state. This analysis was motivated by the need to determine behavior of a metabolic function in a particular condition irrespective of an artificially placed reference state, which may not be representative for the “naturally occurring environment” which the plant experiences in the field. The employed null model was based on the permutation of the assigned flux boundaries while keeping thermodynamic and exchange constraints unaltered. In this manner, we circumvented issues with the selection of a reference state and relied on the average behavior determined solely by the network structure and the imposed flux boundaries. We re-computed the flux capacities from the null model for 100 repetitions for each time point and condition. Based on this, a metabolic function was deemed differential if it showed an absolute <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> greater than 2 with respect to the expectation from the null model in at least one but not all conditions under consideration. Pathways that were differentially up-regulated were termed sustainers—sustaining a certain metabolic functioning, while those that were differentially down-regulated were referred to as modulators—modulating a certain metabolic functioning. A complete list of these pathways and their classification under the eight conditions considered is given in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Metabolites in metabolic functions</title>
<p>The working hypothesis of this study was motivated by the following: The determined modulators and sustainers exhibit flux capacities significantly different from the capacities expected by the null model. Furthermore, we observed that the direction of the differential behavior is unaltered across environmental conditions (<italic>i.e.</italic>, differential metabolic functions are robust, or in genetic terminology, canalized <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Siegal1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Flatt1">[33]</xref>). Therefore, we expected the likelihood for this observation to increase if the metabolites participating in these differentially behaving functions show persistently smaller fluctuations compared to metabolites involved in other functions. To test this hypothesis, we analyzed the metabolite profiles that were collected alongside with the transcriptomics data in the same experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Caldana1">[26]</xref>. A schematic representation of the overall workflow from the data mapping and integration to the statistical analysis is provided in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003656-g001">Figure 1</xref>. For each of the eight environmental conditions and set of investigated functions, we categorized the 65 mapped metabolites (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>) according to the following criteria: (1) participation in (non-)differentially behaving metabolic function and (2) metabolite, substrate, or product of a pathway. In addition, we made the distinction between substrates/products and initial substrates/initial products of the pathway.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003656-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Schematic representation of the analysis framework.</title>
<p>Transcriptomics and metabolomics data capturing <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>'s temporal response to eight different environmental conditions (combinations of different light and/or temperature regimes) are collected for a time-series of 24 hours. The transcriptomic data are used to constrain flux boundaries of the respective reactions in a large-scale network by assuming a correlation between the transcript abundance and the upper flux boundary through the respective enzyme-catalyzed reaction. Based on a model with randomized flux boundaries (null model), pathways are classified as differential for a given condition if they exhibit an absolute <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>2. Differentially up-regulated (down-regulated) pathways are termed sustainers (modulators) of the metabolic state, respectively. Independently from this categorization, the temporal variation of the metabolite profiles was determined. Under certain conditions, substrates in the differential pathways exhibit a significantly lower temporal variation with respect to other groups of metabolites.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We defined a substrate of a pathway as any metabolite that acts as a substrate in a reaction involved in the pathway but not as product/intermediate of the same pathway. Furthermore, an initial substrate is a substrate in the first reaction of the pathway. In an analogous manner: a product of a given pathway is defined as any metabolite acting as a product in a reaction of the pathway but not as a substrate/intermediate of the pathway. A product of the last reaction of the pathway is defined as a final product. For the metabolic function in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003656-g002">Figure 2</xref>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are substrates, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are initial substrates; moreover, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are products, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are final products.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003656-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Representation of a metabolic function and its metabolites.</title>
<p>Shown is a metabolic pathway with four reactions, represented by the arrows. The dots represent the metabolites, which are categorized as substrates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, intermediates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and products <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with the subgroup of initial substrates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and final products <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Variability of substrates in differential metabolic functions</title>
<p>We calculated the variability of each considered metabolite over the time course following the perturbation by calculating the coefficient of variation (CV) as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> section. In order to determine differences in the distribution of CVs over the considered categories of metabolites we employed the <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> rank-sum test (which also is applicable to non-normal distributions) at a significance level of 0.05. We considered the distribution of CVs across all metabolites, across products only, and across substrates only, in the following six comparisons of groups: modulators vs. all metabolites, sustainers vs. all metabolites, differentially behaving functions (<italic>i.e.</italic>, modulators and sustainers) vs. all metabolites, modulators vs. non-modulators, sustainers vs. non-sustainers, and differentially behaving functions vs. non-differentially behaving functions. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003656-t001">Table 1</xref>, this summed up to a total of 144 statistical tests for three categorizations of metabolites over six groupings under eight conditions. A list containing the numbers of tested metabolites for each scenario is given in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003656.s001">Supporting Information S1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1003656-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Significance test for the coefficients of variation (CVs) for different groups of <italic>metabolites</italic>, or <italic>products</italic>, or <italic>substrates</italic> across the considered environmental conditions.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003656-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolites/condition</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - dark</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - dark</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - dark</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">modulator vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.487</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.040</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sustainer vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.404</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.338</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.024</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">differential vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.303</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.264</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.330</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.019</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">modulator vs. non-modulator</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.427</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.370</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.504</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.408</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.420</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sustainer vs. non-sustainer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.606</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.489</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.377</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">differential vs. non-differential</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.590</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.364</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.311</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.401</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Products/condition</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">modulator vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.760</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.298</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.416</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sustainer vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.563</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">differential vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.715</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.509</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.563</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.178</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">modulator vs. non-modulator</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.469</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.761</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.328</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sustainer vs. non-sustainer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.608</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.376</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.729</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.311</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">differential vs. non-differential</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.668</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.526</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.448</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.435</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Substrates</bold>/<bold>condition</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">modulator vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.030</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.019</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sustainer vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.338</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.329</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.033</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">differential vs. all metabolites</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.033</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.026</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">modulator vs. non-modulator</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.046</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.037</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.294</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sustainer vs. non-sustainer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.371</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.273</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.405</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.291</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.046</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">differential vs. non-differential</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.043</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.033</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.046</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.029</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Given are <italic>Wilcoxon</italic>-test <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-values from testing for significantly lower CVs for <bold><italic>metabolites</italic></bold> or <bold><italic>products</italic></bold> or <bold><italic>substrates</italic></bold> in the given six comparisons, respectively. A <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes that the sample size was too small for a statistic test (0 or 1 product in the respective group). The table entries in bold mark the significant comparisons at level 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>First, considering the group of all metabolites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003656-t001">Table 1</xref> top), we found the mean CV of metabolites involved in differential metabolic functions to be smaller in comparison to the mean CV of all metabolites under one conditions, <italic>i.e.</italic>, high-light (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). This was also the case when considering the mean CV of metabolites in modulators and sustainers, separately (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively). Secondly, analyzing the group of products of the pathways, we did not observe any significant differences in the CVs in any of the tested groups under any of the eight conditions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003656-t001">Table 1</xref> middle). In contrast, investigating the third group—the substrates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003656-t001">Table 1</xref> bottom) — we found the mean CV of the substrates in modulators to be significantly smaller than the mean CV of all metabolites under two conditions, <italic>i.e.</italic>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Moreover, the mean CV of the substrates in sustainers was significantly smaller than the mean CV of all metabolites under one condition, <italic>i.e.</italic>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Altogether, the mean CV of the substrates in differentially behaving metabolic functions was significantly smaller than the mean CV of all metabolites under three conditions, namely, under <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Furthermore, the mean CV of the substrates in modulators was significantly smaller than the mean CV of substrates in non-modulators under two conditions, <italic>i.e.</italic>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), while the mean CV of sustainers was significantly smaller than the mean CV of substrates in non-sustainer under <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Finally, the mean CV of the substrates in differentially behaving metabolic functions was significantly smaller than the mean CV of substrates in all non-differential functions under four conditions, namely under <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-darkness (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003656-g003">Figure 3</xref> shows a histogram of the distribution of CVs for all measured metabolites and those that participate as substrates in the metabolic functions which were previously identified as sustainer or modulator over all eight investigated conditions. Histograms for each condition separately can be found in the Figure S2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003656.s002">Supporting Information S2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003656-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Histogram of temporal coefficient of variation for metabolites.</title>
<p>Distribution of CVs over all measured metabolites (green) and all metabolites identified as substrates in a differentially behaving functions for the respective conditions (red). The plot summarizes the distributions over all eight considered conditions.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Inspecting the list of mapped metabolites, we identified 15 out of 65 to act as substrates in a differential pathway in at least one of the considered conditions, namely: alanine, pyruvate, serine, threonine, aspartate, methionine, glutamine, 2-oxoglutarate, citrulline or arginine, spermidine, glycine, glutamate, ethanolamine, valine, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-alanine. The temporal profiles of these metabolites for those conditions in which they act as substrates in modulator or sustainer are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003656-g004">Figure 4</xref>. All of these metabolites are either amino acids or essential intermediates in central carbon or nitrogen metabolism. The differential pathways they belong to fall into the larger groups of primary nitrate assimilation (glutamate, glutamine, and 2-oxoglutarate), photorespiration (glycine, serine, and ethanolamine), TCA cycle (pyruvate and 2-oxoglutarate), amino acid metabolism (alanine, arginine, threonine, aspartate, methionine, and valine) and polyamine biosynthesis (spermidine and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-alanine). A discussion about the involvement of the respective differential pathways in stress responses to the eight environments investigated was already given in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>. Apart from their involvement as substrates in modulators and sustainers, these metabolites have also been implicated in various other stress responses, <italic>e.g.</italic>, anoxia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Krsteiner1">[34]</xref> or hypoxia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Miyashita1">[35]</xref>, oxidative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Baxter1">[36]</xref>, drought stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Bartels1">[37]</xref>, or general stress responses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Joshi1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Bohnert1">[39]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003656-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Time-series of the metabolites acting as substrates in differential metabolic functions.</title>
<p>Profiles of the relative metabolite content of those measured metabolites that act as substrates in a pathway classified as differential with respect to the null model under the respective condition. The horizontal line indicates time point 60-organization and transition into a new metabolic state.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Additionally, we tested if the described patterns of robustness in the metabolite profiles can also be found in the flux capacity profiles of the differential metabolic functions they belong to. Interestingly, only for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> we also observe the flux capacity profiles of the differential pathways to exhibit significantly lower CVs than the non-differential pathways (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Another general observation that we made is, that for all metabolic functions for which substrate measurements were available, the CVs of these substrates were significantly lower than the CVs of the respective flux capacity profile. These two observations further underline the none-trivial interconnection between flux rates and the levels of metabolites.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Substrates in differential metabolic functions are more connected</title>
<p>Next, we investigated whether the group of substrates in differential metabolic functions shows distinct characteristics with respect to the network topology. For the analysis we neglected evidently ubiquitous cofactors, such as: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, ADP, ATP, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, NAD(P)H, CoA, (pyro-)phosphate. This strategy has also been followed in other studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Fell1">[40]</xref>. Furthermore, to arrive at a value for the connectivity of each metabolite, <italic>i.e.</italic>, the number of reactions in which a metabolite is involved (as defined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Schuster1">[41]</xref>), we kept the compartmentalized structure of the network and considered the instances of a metabolite appearing in more than one compartment as different reactants. Based on the given stoichiometry we determined the number of reactions in which each metabolite participates. Interestingly, we find the group of measured substrates of differential pathways to be on average significantly more connected than the group of all metabolites—6.24 vs. 2.99 reactions (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> rank-sum test). Clearly, one has to keep in mind that our analysis is based on a generic compartmentalized network reconstruction. The connectivity values might vary in different tissues, due to the presence or absence of certain pathways. Nevertheless, we belief that the well-curated model we use in our study serves a good starting point for the analysis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Differential metabolic functions have less substrates</title>
<p>To further investigate which attributes are typical for differentially behaving pathways, we next investigated the number of (initial) substrates of the pathways. Cofactors of the considered reactions were neglected from the analysis (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003656.s003">Supporting Information S3</xref>). Counting the number of substrates, we found their average number in the differential pathways to be significantly smaller in comparison to all considered pathways/all non-differential pathways (2.6 and 3.3/3.5 substrates, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>/<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively). In contrast to this, when considering the number of initial substrates, we found that 29.7% of differential pathways have two initial substrates, while the remaining ones have only one substrate. In the whole group of metabolic pathways and the group of non-differential pathways this value is lower (25.5% and 26.2%, respectively) although not significant.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, we extended our earlier analysis of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>'s metabolic acclimation to varying light and/or temperature conditions which was based on transcriptomics data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer2">[24]</xref>. Here we considered metabolomics data from the same experiment and investigated the temporal variation of the metabolite profiles. Our findings from the integrative analysis include the following: (<italic>i</italic>) for specific environmental conditions, differential metabolic functions have substrates, which on average show a lower CV than other metabolite groups tested, (<italic>ii</italic>) when considering the network topology, these substrates are on average more connected than the remaining metabolites and (<italic>iii</italic>) differential metabolic pathways have on average fewer substrates than the other metabolic functions investigated.</p>
<p>Closer inspection of the environmental conditions that exhibit low substrate variability leads to the following hypothesis: substrate robustness can be observed under stressful environmental conditions. Yet, we do not observe substrate robustness, or in genetic terms canalization, under conditions which are not perceived as stress by the plant (<italic>e.g.</italic>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and moreover the canalization effect might get lost under those conditions which are too extreme or prolonged (<italic>e.g.</italic>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The latter scenario might cause a serious disturbance of the acclimation which could potentially lead to non-resilience, <italic>i.e.</italic>, non-recovery. Therefore, we believe that the observed substrate robustness is an inducible genetic mechanism, both depending on the metabolic network structure and the specific environmental condition. Determining the range of conditions that permit the observed robust behavior would be an interesting undertaking for future experimental testing.</p>
<p>Deriving flux values from transcriptomics data is a delicate issue. In recent years, a large set of methods have been proposed that use transcriptomics data to infer condition-specific networks, mainly applied on microorganisms (GIMME, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Becker1">[42]</xref>, iMat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Zur1">[43]</xref>, E-flux <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Colijn1">[16]</xref>, PROM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Chandrasekaran1">[44]</xref>, MADE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Jensen1">[45]</xref>, TEAM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Collins1">[46]</xref>). While most approaches rely on a discretization of the expression data and employ user-defined thresholds, the here applied E-flux method does not rely on these requirements. It assumes a relationship between the amount of a certain transcript and the upper flux boundary of the respective reaction. While mechanisms, such as post-transcriptional modification and hierarchical regulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-terKuile1">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Bruggeman1">[48]</xref> cannot be explicitly considered, they are implicitly accounted for by only restricting the upper flux boundary. In other words if a certain amount of transcript was measured the predicted flux can range between zero and the upper boundary; no enforcements on certain minimum flux values are made. Additionally, claims are even made with more reservation since the approach does not attempt to predict actual fluxes but flux capacities that are compliant with the data. Moreover, one needs to keep in mind that the employed metabolite data are not compartment-specific. In the analysis presented here, we assigned the same metabolite profile to each compartment-specific compound in the model. It would be interesting to investigate in future studies, when more compartment-or tissue specific metabolite data become available, if the observed patterns of substrate robustness are not only specific for certain environments, but also for particular compartments or tissues.</p>
<p>Finally, like any other modeling attempt, any results depend on the quality of the network as well as on the quality of the collected data. Here, we relied on the most recent and most comprehensive network reconstruction of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and a dataset that was collected with a single technology in a single laboratory to minimize technical artifacts.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Comparison to related studies</title>
<p>The principle of keeping levels of metabolites involved in important pathways from exhibiting fluctuations was recently discussed in another context. Reznik at al. used the dual formulation of a classical FBA problem, which uses the maximization of biomass as a cellular objective, to compute sensitivities of the objective value to flux imbalances, <italic>i.e.</italic>, deviations from the steady-state assumption <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Reznik1">[49]</xref>. The so-called shadow price of a given metabolite captures the influence of the metabolite's accumulation or depletion on the maximum value of the objective. Thereby, a negative shadow price implies that the corresponding metabolite is growth limiting. By using data from <italic>S. cerevisae</italic> under different nutrient limiting conditions the authors were able to show that the determined shadow prices negatively correlate with the growth limitation of the respective measured intracellular metabolites. Moreover, based on these findings, the authors argued that growth-limiting metabolites cannot exhibit large fluctuations. Using data from <italic>E. coli</italic>'s metabolic response to carbon and nitrogen perturbations, they further demonstrated that metabolites associated with a negative shadow price indeed show lower temporal variation in comparison to metabolites with zero shadow prices in a perturbed system.</p>
<p>What both approaches, ours and the one briefly described above, have in common is the principle that metabolites important for a particular function exhibit less temporal variation than other metabolites. In the latter, an important metabolite is defined as a metabolite with a negative shadow price with respect to the assumed cellular objective of growth maximization. In contrast to this, our analysis is driven by integration of transcriptomics data and does not assume a particular overall cellular objective. In our approach, we consider a metabolite relevant if it acts as a substrate in a metabolic pathway which behaves differentially in comparison to a condition-specific null model for flux capacities. These relevant metabolites may thus play a role in the plant acclimation to environmental changes.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>The role of substrates of differential metabolic functions in network topology</title>
<p>Additionally to the observed substrate robustness in differential pathways under certain abiotic stress conditions, we also showed that these substrates are on average more connected <italic>i.e.</italic>, involved in more reactions. The role of these highly connected metabolites has previously been discussed in terms of evolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Fell1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Barabsi1">[50]</xref>. In the latter, the authors identified among others, pyruvate, serine, aspartate, 2-oxoglutarate, and glutamate and put forward the hypothesis that the most highly connected metabolites should also be the phylogenetically oldest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Fell1">[40]</xref>. The connection between metabolites involved in core reaction of central carbon metabolism and their involvement in abiotic stress acclimation, together with the observation that they are on average more connected, extends this concept and puts the evolutionary structure of metabolic networks into a more dynamic context—one which also accounts for the changing environments affecting the organism.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>The role of substrates as systems input in terms of number and variability</title>
<p>Our third finding concerning the smaller number of substrates in differentially behaving metabolic functions has wide implications on the interplay between plasticity and robustness in metabolism. Most notably, our findings differ from claims made with respect to evolution of robustness and cellular stochasticity of gene expression. In a recent study, the author proposed that the degree to which varying cellular components combine to determine robust phenotypes may be predictive of the amount of their inherent variability. The basis for this claim is the observation that averaging over multiple independent inputs is a general way to reduce variability of molecular phenotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Frank1">[51]</xref>. This implies that the larger the number of variable inputs is, the smaller the variability of the phenotypic output will be. However, this observation does not apply to metabolic reactions which are governed by multiplicative (<italic>e.g.</italic>, mass action, as the simplest) rather than averaging laws. Here we observe that fewer input variables with smaller fluctuations, do not necessarily result in smaller fluctuations of the output (<italic>i.e.</italic>, the flux capacity in our case) but in robust differential behavior. Furthermore, our findings also showed that for all metabolic functions for which substrate measurements are available, the CVs of their substrates are significantly lower than the CVs of the respective flux capacity profile. This further highlights the particularities of regulation, variability, and robustness of metabolic pathways.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Further biological implications</title>
<p>Robustness of certain pathway fluxes and specific metabolite concentrations have long been documented. The concept of network rigidity has initially been proposed in <italic>S. cerevisae</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Stephanopoulos1">[52]</xref>. Subsequently it has been demonstrated to be functional in plant systems too, especially in the context of central metabolism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Rontein1">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Williams1">[54]</xref>. Moreover, considered evidence has also accrued for certain metabolite levels to be exceptionally stable, for example the levels of alanine, pyruvate, 2-oxoglutarate, glutamine and spermidine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Geigenberger1">[55]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Stitt1">[56]</xref>. Furthermore, it has been shown that levels of metabolites such as serine coordinately control the level of expression of genes which encode multiple steps of the pathway in which they themselves take part <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Timm1">[57]</xref>.</p>
<p>In our view, the high stability of a pool of primary metabolites, invariant to environmental heterogeneity, fulfills two major functions. On the one hand, it efficiently sustains a set of “core” reaction rates which are deemed essential for the plant's objective function across a wide range of different stresses. On the other hand, the observed substrate stability enables a tight conditional control on a set of metabolic functions to act as modulators or sustainers in response to specific stresses only.</p>
<p>Finally, the fact that the robust metabolites may well be the most biologically relevant for metabolic regulation is an important point since it is at odds with the manner in which the majority of the metabolomics community assesses their data. This fact additionally highlights the potential difficulties and challenges in interpreting data from a single level of the cellular hierarchy and thus provides further grounds for integrated models such as the one we present here.</p>
<p>Taken together, our findings show that the integration of large-scale modeling with high-throughput data can be used to infer regulatory principles from the stoichiometry of the underlying reactions alone. Furthermore, we presented an approach that bridges the gap between flux-centric and metabolite centric view of large-scale data. Therefore, our study paves the way for investigating the existence of similar principles relating plasticity of metabolic profiles and robustness of metabolic behavior across other species for which both genome-scale networks and high-throughput (time-resolved) metabolomics data of high quality are becoming increasingly available.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Data</title>
<p>The investigated data set captures the time-resolved response of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> to changing light and/or temperature conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Caldana1">[26]</xref>. The previously published data comprise time-series measurements for eight environmental conditions covering combinations of four different light intensities (ranging from high-light (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) to darkness) and three different temperatures (4, 21, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). A schematic representation of the combinations of abiotic stresses is provided in the Figure S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003656.s002">Supporting Information S2</xref>. In brief, wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> Columbia-0 plants were grown in soil under short-day-conditions for 4 weeks and then transferred to long-day-conditions for another 2 weeks. Subsequently, they were exposed to the following conditions: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Metabolite and transcript profiles were collected from samples harvested at 22 time points ranging from 0 to 24 hours after the stress application. Further details of the experimental procedures and data processing can be found in the original publication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Caldana1">[26]</xref>. Transcriptomics data are deposited in the array express repository (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress</ext-link>) under Arabidopsis light and temperature response ArrayExpress accession: E-MTAB-375 and they can be downloaded using the following link: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mpimp-golm.mpg.de/Supplementary-Materials-for-Publications/Caldana-et-al_Filtered-Affymetrix-Gene-Expression-Data.zip" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mpimp-golm.mpg.de/Supplementary-Materials-for-Publications/Caldana-et-al_Filtered-Affymetrix-Gene-Expression-Data.zip</ext-link>. Metabolomics data are provided on the following website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mpimp-golm.mpg.de/Supplementary-Materials-for-Publications/Caldana-et-al_Normalized-metabolic-data.zip" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mpimp-golm.mpg.de/Supplementary-Materials-for-Publications/Caldana-et-al_Normalized-metabolic-data.zip</ext-link>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Mapping of high-throughput data onto the model</title>
<p>From the total of 82 measured metabolites, 65 can be mapped onto the model. It must be noted that the metabolomics data are not compartment-specific and 61 out of 65 mapped metabolites appear in more than one compartment in the model. Due to a lack of this information, for those non-unique metabolites we assigned the same profile to each compartment-specific compound in the model. The mapping dictionary is given in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003656.s004">Supporting Information S4</xref>.</p>
<p>The mapping of the transcriptomics data from our previous study has a network coverage of 46%, <italic>i.e.</italic>, 627 out of 1363 reactions can be constrained by transcriptomics data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer2">[24]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Flux Balance Analysis</title><p>FBA is a constraint-based approach for predicting steady-state fluxes in a metabolic network independent of enzyme kinetics and metabolite concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Varma1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Orth1">[11]</xref>. The method solely relies on the physico-chemical constraints of the network (<italic>e.g.</italic>, the reaction stoichiometry, reversibility, and maximum uptake rates) and a putative biological objective of the organism under consideration (<italic>e.g.</italic>, biomass production for microorganisms under ambient conditions). A central element of the approach is the assumption of a steady-state which implies that each internal metabolite <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the network is produced and consumed at the same net rate if considering the system at a small time interval, or in a mathematical representation: <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003656.e095"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e095" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>which results in a decoupling of the flux predictions from the metabolite concentrations. Adding the above mentioned additional constraints and assumptions leads to the following linear program:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003656.e096"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e096" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003656.e097"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e097" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003656.e098"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e098" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the stoichiometric matrix of the system under consideration in which the rows denote the metabolites <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the columns represent the reactions of the model. The reaction fluxes are captured in the flux vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The respective lower and upper boundaries of the reaction are given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> encodes the ratios at which certain precursors (<italic>e.g.</italic>, amino acids, fatty acids, nucleotides, sugars) contribute to the objective function. For a detailed review of FBA and other related constraint-based optimization approaches see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Orth1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Lewis1">[13]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Metabolic functions</title>
<p>The analysis presented here extends results recently presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>. In brief: In our previous study we had simulated flux capacities through a set of a 167 metabolic functions. The simulation of metabolic functions has initially been proposed to demonstrate the quality of a metabolic reconstruction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Duarte1">[58]</xref> and it has also been used in the original model reconstruction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-MintzOron1">[25]</xref> to ensure model functionality. The set of selected pathways cover primary as well as secondary metabolism and is obtained from AraCyc/MetaCyc <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Zhang1">[59]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Caspi2">[61]</xref>. These databases incorporate community-wide efforts to integrate current biological knowledge and understanding of metabolic pathways. In our previous study we extended the proposed concept to simulate time-and condition-specific flux capacities by integrating transcriptomics data based on a modification of the E-flux method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Colijn1">[16]</xref>, which assumes a relationship between the amount of a certain transcript and the upper flux boundary of the respective reaction. Since the correspondence between transcript and protein abundance is crucial when using transcriptomics data to constrain flux boundaries, the approach only makes weak assumptions. Proteins are allowed to be present and active if the respective gene product is detected. In contrast, no enforcements on protein activities are made if the gene product was detected with certain abundance. Additionally, our claims are stated with even greater reservation since the approach does not attempt to predict actual fluxes but flux capacities that are compliant with the data. For details of the simulation and the list of metabolic functions refer to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003656-MintzOron1">[25]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Statistical methods</title>
<p>To determine the temporal variation of the metabolite profiles we used the coefficient of variation (CV) which is defined as the ratio of the standard deviation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the mean <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the observable: <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003656.e107"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.e107" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>We applied this statistic to the mapped metabolite profiles for each condition separately. While doing so, we neglected the data for the first hour (first six time points) after the stress application during which the system experiences the strongest effect, <italic>i.e.</italic>, differential regulation of pathways involved in the response. To ensure that the categorization of differential metabolic functions is robust to the removal of this time-interval we repeated the analysis of our previous study. Reassuringly, we find our results, <italic>i.e.</italic>, the classification as a sustainer or modulator of a given metabolic state, to be robust to the removal of up to six time points from the beginning of the time series.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003656.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Supporting Information S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>List of tested metabolites.</bold> Given is the number of metabolites in the respective group for each condition on which the <italic>Wilcoxon</italic>-test is based.</p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003656.s002" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Supporting Information S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Additional figures.</bold> Figure S1: Schematic representation of the eight environmental conditions. Plants were grown under ambient conditions and then transferred into one of the eight indicted conditions. Figure S2: Condition-specific distribution of the coefficients of variation (CVs) for all mapped metabolite profiles. Given are the distributions of CVs for all measured metabolites (green) and those that participate as substrates in the metabolic functions that were previously identified as sustainer or modulator (red) for all eight investigated conditions separately.</p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003656.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Supporting Information S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Metabolites regarded as cofactors or constant and neglected from the analysis.</bold> Given is the Metabolite ID, the AraCyc/PMN ID, the KEGG ID, the metabolite name, and the formula.</p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003656.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003656.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Supporting Information S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Metabolite dictionary.</bold> Given is the mapping of the metabolites between that data and the model. Some metabolites have two possible metabolites IDs in the model. Note that a metabolite ID is not unique and the same metabolite can participate in reactions in different compartments.</p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Dodd1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salathia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kévei</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tóth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plant circadian clocks increase photosynthesis, growth, survival, and competitive advantage</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Guy1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular responses of plants to cold shock and cold acclimation</article-title>. <source>Journal of molecular microbiology and biotechnology</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Mittler1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Abiotic stress, the field environment and stress combination</article-title>. <source>Trends in plant science</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Skirycz1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skirycz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inzé</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>More from less: plant growth under limited water</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Biotechnology</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Obata1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The use of metabolomics to dissect plant responses to abiotic stresses</article-title>. <source>Cellular and molecular life sciences: CMLS</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>3225</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Kooke1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kooke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keurentjes</surname><given-names>JJB</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Multi-dimensional regulation of metabolic networks shaping plant development and performance</article-title>. <source>Journal of experimental botany</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>3353</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Cramer1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delrot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pezzotti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effects of abiotic stress on plants: a systems biology perspective</article-title>. <source>BMC plant biology</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Baerenfaller1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baerenfaller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Massonnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baginsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bühlmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Systems-based analysis of Arabidopsis leaf growth reveals adaptation to water deficit</article-title>. <source>Molecular systems biology</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>606</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Gechev1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gechev</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tohge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sujeeth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of desiccation tolerance in the resurrection glacial relic Haberlea rhodopensis</article-title>. <source>Cellular and molecular life sciences: CMLS</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Varma1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Metabolic Flux Balancing: Basic Concepts, Scientific and Practical Use</article-title>. <source>Bio/Technology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>998</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Orth1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>What is flux balance analysis?</article-title> <source>Nature biotechnology</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Monk1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charusanti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Premyodhin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Genome-scale metabolic reconstructions of multiple Escherichia coli strains highlight strain-specific adaptations to nutritional environments</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>20338</fpage>–<lpage>20343</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Lewis1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Constraining the metabolic genotype-phenotype relationship using a phylogeny of in silico methods</article-title>. <source>Nature reviews Microbiology</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Blazier1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blazier</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>Ja</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Integration of expression data in genome-scale metabolic network reconstructions</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Physiology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Hyduke1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyduke</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Analysis of omics data with genome-scale models of metabolism</article-title>. <source>Molecular bioSystems</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Colijn1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colijn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zucker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lun</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Interpreting expression data with metabolic flux models: predicting Mycobacterium tuberculosis mycolic acid production</article-title>. <source>PLoS computational biology</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000489</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-OBrien1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyduke</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Genome-scale models of metabolism and gene expression extend and refine growth phenotype prediction</article-title>. <source>Molecular Systems Biology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Fiehn1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Metabolomics–the link between genotypes and phenotypes</article-title>. <source>Plant molecular biology</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Hamilton1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Quantitative Assessment of Thermodynamic Constraints on the Solution Space of Genome-Scale Metabolic Models</article-title>. <source>Biophysical Journal</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Hoppe1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holzhütter</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Including metabolite concentrations into flux balance analysis: thermodynamic realizability as a constraint on flux distributions in metabolic networks</article-title>. <source>BMC systems biology</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Kmmel1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kümmel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Putative regulatory sites unraveled by network-embedded thermodynamic analysis of metabolome data</article-title>. <source>Molecular systems biology</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>2006.0034</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Mahadevan1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Dynamic flux balance analysis of diauxic growth in Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>Biophysical journal</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>1331</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Töpfer N, Caldana C, Grimbs S, Willmitzer L, Fernie AR, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2013) Integration of Genome-Scale Modeling and Transcript Profiling Reveals Metabolic Pathways Underlying Light and Temperature Acclimation in Arabidopsis. The Plant cell <volume>25</volume> : tpc.112.108852–.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Tpfer2"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Töpfer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niokoloski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Large-scale modeling provides insights into Arabidopsis's acclimation to changing light and temperature conditions</article-title>. <source>Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e25480</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-MintzOron1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mintz-Oron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malitsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruppin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Reconstruction of Arabidopsis metabolic network models accounting for subcellular compartmentalization and tissue-specificity</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Caldana1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Degenkolbe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuadros-Inostroza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sulpice</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>High-density kinetic analysis of the metabolomic and transcriptomic response of Arabidopsis to eight environmental conditions</article-title>. <source>The Plant journal: for cell and molecular biology</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Schuetz1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuetz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuepfer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Systematic evaluation of objective functions for predicting intracellular fluxes in Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>Molecular systems biology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Edwards1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>In silico predictions of Escherichia coli metabolic capabilities are consistent with experimental data</article-title>. <source>Nature biotechnology</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Feist1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The biomass objective function</article-title>. <source>Current opinion in microbiology</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Urano1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Characterization of the ABA-regulated global responses to dehydration in Arabidopsis by metabolomics</article-title>. <source>The Plant journal: for cell and molecular biology</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1065</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Cook1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A prominent role for the CBF cold response pathway in configuring the low-temperature metabolome of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>15243</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Siegal1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegal</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Waddington's canalization revisited: developmental stability and evolution</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>10528</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Flatt1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flatt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The evolutionary genetics of canalization</article-title>. <source>The Quarterly review of biology</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Krsteiner1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kürsteiner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupuis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhlemeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The pyruvate decarboxylase1 gene of Arabidopsis is required during anoxia but not other environmental stresses</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>968</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Miyashita1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dolferus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ismond</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Good</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Alanine aminotransferase catalyses the breakdown of alanine after hypoxia in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>The Plant journal: for cell and molecular biology</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1108</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Baxter1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Redestig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Repsilber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The metabolic response of heterotrophic Arabidopsis cells to oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Bartels1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sunkar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Drought and Salt Tolerance in Plants</article-title>. <source>Critical Reviews in Plant Sciences</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Joshi1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Interdependence of threonine, methionine and isoleucine metabolism in plants: accumulation and transcriptional regulation under abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>Amino acids</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>933</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Bohnert1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Adaptations to Environmental Stresses</article-title>. <source>The Plant cell</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Fell1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The small world of metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nature biotechnology</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1121</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Schuster1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moldenhauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dandekar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Exploring the pathway structure of metabolism: decomposition into subnetworks and application to Mycoplasma pneumoniae</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Becker1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Sa</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Context-specific metabolic networks are consistent with experiments</article-title>. <source>PLoS computational biology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000082</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Zur1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruppin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shlomi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>iMAT: An Integrative Metabolic Analysis Tool</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3140</fpage>–<lpage>3142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Chandrasekaran1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Probabilistic integrative modeling of genome-scale metabolic and regulatory networks in Escherichia coli and Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>17845</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Jensen1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>Ja</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional integration of a metabolic network model and expression data without arbitrary thresholding</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Collins1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reznik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Segre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Temporal Expression-based Analysis of Metabolism</article-title>. <source>PLoS computational biology</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002781</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-terKuile1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>ter Kuile</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westerhoff</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome meets metabolome: hierarchical and metabolic regulation of the glycolytic pathway</article-title>. <source>FEBS Letters</source> <volume>500</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Bruggeman1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruggeman</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouwman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Time-dependent hierarchical regulation analysis: deciphering cellular adaptation</article-title>. <source>IEE Proceedings-Systems Biology</source> <volume>153</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Reznik1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reznik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Segrè</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Flux imbalance analysis and the sensitivity of cellular growth to changes in metabolite pools</article-title>. <source>PLoS computational biology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e1003195</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Barabsi1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barabási</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Emergence of Scaling in Random Networks</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Frank1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genetic variation of polygenic characters and the evolution of genetic degeneracy</article-title>. <source>Journal of evolutionary biology</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Stephanopoulos1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephanopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vallino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Network rigidity and metabolic engineering in metabolite overproduction</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>252</volume>: <fpage>1675</fpage>–<lpage>1681</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Rontein1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rontein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dieuaide-Noubhani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufourc</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rolin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The metabolic architecture of plant cells. Stability of central metabolism and flexibility of anabolic pathways during the growth cycle of tomato cells</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>43948</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Williams1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>TCR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miguet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masakapalli</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweetlove</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Metabolic network fluxes in heterotrophic Arabidopsis cells: stability of the flux distribution under different oxygenation conditions</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>704</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Geigenberger1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geigenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Response of plant metabolism to too little oxygen</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Stitt1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>From measurements of metabolites to metabolomics: an ‘on the fly’ perspective illustrated by recent studies of carbon-nitrogen interactions</article-title>. <source>Current opinion in biotechnology</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Timm1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Florian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittmiβ</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jahnke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Serine acts as a metabolic signal for the transcriptional control of photorespiration-related genes in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source> <volume>162</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Duarte1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Sa</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Global reconstruction of the human metabolic network based on genomic and bibliomic data</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>1777</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Zhang1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foerster</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tissier</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>MetaCyc and AraCyc. Metabolic pathway databases for plant research</article-title>. <source>Plant physiology</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Caspi1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foerster</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulcher</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkinson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingraham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>MetaCyc: a multiorganism database of metabolic pathways and enzymes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic acids research</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>D511</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003656-Caspi2"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dreher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foerster</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The MetaCyc database of metabolic pathways and enzymes and the BioCyc collection of Pathway/Genome Databases</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>D459</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>