<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-13-01031</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Decipher the Mechanisms of Protein Conformational Changes Induced by Nucleotide Binding through Free-Energy Landscape Analysis: ATP Binding to Hsp70</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Nucleotide Induced Conformational Change in Hsp70</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolaï</surname><given-names>Adrien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¤</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delarue</surname><given-names>Patrice</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Senet</surname><given-names>Patrick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Laboratoire Interdisciplinaire Carnot de Bourgogne, UMR 6303 CNRS-Université de Bourgogne, Dijon, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livesay</surname><given-names>Dennis R.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>UNC Charlotte, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">psenet@u-bourgogne.fr</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AN PD PS. Performed the experiments: AN PD PS. Analyzed the data: AN PD PS. Wrote the paper: AD PS.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤</label><p>Current address: Department of Physics, Applied Physics and Astronomy, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York, United States of America.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003379</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Nicolai et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>ATP regulates the function of many proteins in the cell by transducing its binding and hydrolysis energies into protein conformational changes by mechanisms which are challenging to identify at the atomic scale. Based on molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, a method is proposed to analyze the structural changes induced by ATP binding to a protein by computing the effective free-energy landscape (FEL) of a subset of its coordinates along its amino-acid sequence. The method is applied to characterize the mechanism by which the binding of ATP to the nucleotide-binding domain (NBD) of Hsp70 propagates a signal to its substrate-binding domain (SBD). Unbiased MD simulations were performed for Hsp70-DnaK chaperone in nucleotide-free, ADP-bound and ATP-bound states. The simulations revealed that the SBD does not interact with the NBD for DnaK in its nucleotide-free and ADP-bound states whereas the docking of the SBD was found in the ATP-bound state. The docked state induced by ATP binding found in MD is an intermediate state between the initial nucleotide-free and final ATP-bound states of Hsp70. The analysis of the FEL projected along the amino-acid sequence permitted to identify a subset of 27 protein internal coordinates corresponding to a network of 91 key residues involved in the conformational change induced by ATP binding. Among the 91 residues, 26 are identified for the first time, whereas the others were shown relevant for the allosteric communication of Hsp70 s in several experiments and bioinformatics analysis. The FEL analysis revealed also the origin of the ATP-induced structural modifications of the SBD recently measured by Electron Paramagnetic Resonance. The pathway between the nucleotide-free and the intermediate state of DnaK was extracted by applying principal component analysis to the subset of internal coordinates describing the transition. The methodology proposed is general and could be applied to analyze allosteric communication in other proteins.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>The precise biophysical characterization of the mechanisms of the protein conformational changes controlled by a nucleotide remains a challenge in biology. Molecular dynamics simulations of proteins in different nucleotide-binding states contain information on the nucleotide-dependent conformational dynamics. However, it is difficult to extract relevant information about the conformation-induced mechanism from the raw molecular dynamics data. Herein, we addressed this issue for the major ATP-dependent molecular chaperones Hsp70 s, which contribute to crucial cellular processes and are involved in several neurodegenerative diseases and in cancer. To function, Hsp70 undergoes several conformational changes controlled by the state of its nucleotide-binding domain. We demonstrated that the analysis of the effective free-energy landscape of the protein projected along the amino-acid sequence and computed from the molecular dynamics simulations of Hsp70 in different nucleotide-binding states, holds the key to identify the key residues of the conformational induced pathway. Identification of the key residues involved in the propagation of the structural changes induced by ATP binding offer alternative druggable specific sites other than the ligand binding clefts. The methodology developed for Hsp70 is general and can be adapted to any ligand induced conformational change in proteins.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by funds from the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, from the Conseil Regional de Bourgogne, and from the Ministère de l'Enseignement Supérieur et de la Recherche. Calculations were performed using High Performance Computing (HPC) resources from the Centre de Calcul de l'Université de Bourgogne (DSI-CCUB) and from the Centre Informatique National de l'Enseignement Supérieur (CINES). This work was granted to the HPC resources of CINES under the allocations 2011-c2011076161, 2012-c2012076161, and 2013-c2013076161 made by GENCI (Grand Equipement National de Calcul Intensif). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="20"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Biomolecular machines, as motor proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cecchini1">[1]</xref> and ATP-dependent molecular chaperones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Saibil1">[2]</xref>, undergo a major conformational change upon ATP binding and hydrolysis. In many cases, the ATP molecule regulates the protein function by an allosteric mechanism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Monod1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Tsai1">[7]</xref>: binding of ATP in the ATPase domain of these proteins transmits a conformational change to a distant binding site where the substrate binding propagates an analogous conformational change towards the nucleotide-binding site. The exact biophysical characterization of the mechanisms of propagation of a conformational change induced by ligand binding through a protein remains a major challenge in structural biology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Ihee1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Tzeng1">[9]</xref>. In biomolecular machines, as the ATP-dependent molecular chaperones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Horovitz1">[10]</xref>, crystallographic data of the different nucleotide-bound states do not provide generally a complete description of the mechanism by which the protein undergoes a conformational change, because the pathway between the different conformational states and the dynamical information are missing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Gunasekaran1">[5]</xref>.</p>
<p>In recent years, NMR, among other techniques, contributed to the characterization of allostery and protein dynamics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Ihee1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Tzeng1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Manley1">[11]</xref> including nucleotide-dependent conformational changes in molecular chaperones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva2">[13]</xref>. Conformational changes induced by a ligand can be mediated by perturbations of the mean protein conformation (enthalpic effect) as well as by changes of its fluctuations and dynamics (entropic effect) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Gunasekaran1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Tzeng1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Benkovic1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bakan1">[16]</xref>. Both enthalpic and entropic effects are encompassed in the free-energy landscape (FEL) of a protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Frauenfelder1">[17]</xref>. In solution, the FEL is best regarded as a multi-dimensional surface with multiple local minima separated by barriers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Frauenfelder1">[17]</xref>. Different protein-bound states correspond to different FELs, with different shapes and distributions of populations of conformers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kumar1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Gunasekaran1">[5]</xref>. Hence, the nucleotide binding and the nucleotide release in a biomolecular machine redistribute its conformational substates and modify its FEL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Swain1">[18]</xref>.</p>
<p>In many cases, how the dynamics contributes to the conformational transition at the different time-scales of the protein motions and how the FEL is modified upon nucleotide binding remain elusive. Nowadays, standard all-atom molecular dynamics (MD) simulations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-McCammon1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Dror1">[21]</xref> represent a powerful tool, complementary to experiments, for investigating the conformational sampling and nucleotide-dependent conformations of biomolecular machines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Morra1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Chiappori1">[25]</xref>. The fully unbiased all-atom MD simulations permit to monitor the sequence of <italic>spontaneous</italic> conformational changes at the atomic level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Sliozberg1">[26]</xref> and to translate the conformational fluctuations in terms of modified protein FEL. Although unbiased MD simulations of a fully solvated protein may extend to the millisecond range <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Shaw1">[27]</xref> with specific hardware <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Chow1">[28]</xref>, the current state-of-art of unbiased MD simulations correspond typically to 100 ns up to 1 µs time-scale for a system of several thousands of atoms in explicit solvent with the standard computational capabilities available to most of the research groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Duan1">[29]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola2">[31]</xref>. However, transition between active and inactive states in proteins occurs typically on the microsecond to the millisecond time-scales <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Volkman1">[32]</xref>. The complete conformational transition between different nucleotide-binding states of a molecular chaperone in fully unconstrained all-atom MD is thus still inaccessible <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola2">[31]</xref>. To overcome this time-scale restriction, different computational strategies were developed to shorten artificially the time-scale of the conformational transitions. Targeted MD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Ma1">[33]</xref>, accelerated MD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wereszczynski1">[34]</xref>, metadynamics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Pfaendtner1">[35]</xref> to cite a few allow the acceleration of the conformational sampling of all-atom MD by adding a bias potential. An alternative strategy consists to eliminate the fast degrees of freedom of the protein from the MD calculation by coarse-graining the protein structure. A recent application to the 70 kDa heat-shock protein (Hsp70), a key ubiquitous molecular chaperone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hartl1">[36]</xref>, allow us to observe a short-life time full transition between an ATP-like state and an ADP-like state using a coarse-grained model where the solvent and the nucleotides were implicit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Goa1">[37]</xref>. However, current coarse-grained models of proteins lack the description of the crucial explicit interactions between the nucleotide and the protein which can be only described accurately at the atomic level.</p>
<p>In spite the fact that all-atom unbiased MD simulations are not able to follow the full conformational change of a large ATP-dependent protein, as Hsp70 analyzed in the present work, MD simulations probing the structural fluctuations around the end points of a conformational transition are useful to understand the conformational changes. Normal mode analysis (NMA) has been also extensively applied to study the conformational transitions in proteins because the directions of the low-frequency vibrational modes provide the direction of the largest deformation at thermal equilibrium and can serve as collective coordinates to describe the conformational changes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Gerstein1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hayward1">[39]</xref>. Indeed, intrinsic low-frequency vibrational dynamics of proteins in different conformational states correlates with the structural changes between the different conformations induced by ligand binding or by protein-protein interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bakan1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Tobi1">[40]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cui1">[44]</xref>.</p>
<p>Aside the limited sampling issue of standard all-atom MD simulations of large conformational changes upon ligand binding, another issue is to extract from these data relevant information about the mechanism of propagation of a small perturbation at one ligand binding site to a different remote binding site. To get insight into the mechanisms, several analytical tools were applied to ATP-dependent conformational transitions such as the analysis of contact maps <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Daily1">[45]</xref> and of the correlations between the residue motions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Morra1">[22]</xref>. In NMA, relevant information is gained by projecting the direction of the low-frequency modes of a given conformation on the shortest path between the two end structures of a conformational transition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cecchini1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Tama1">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola3">[49]</xref>. None of these approaches is easily related simultaneously on the FEL of the protein and to mutagenesis experimental data.</p>
<p>In the present work, we addressed these two issues (MD sampling and relation between FEL and biochemical data) for the conformational change induced upon nucleotide binding to a molecular chaperone Hsp70 by using rather extensive unbiased MD simulations of the protein in three different nucleotide-binding states; nucleotide-free, ADP-bound and ATP-bound. Hsp70 is a key molecular chaperone which assists in the correct folding and refolding of proteins in all prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Saibil1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hartl1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bukau1">[50]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Young1">[53]</xref>. Hsp70 s contribute to other crucial cellular processes including the protein degradation, the translocation of peptides across the cell membrane, the formation of protein complexes, and the inhibition of the programmed cell death (apoptosis) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Parsell1">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schmitt1">[57]</xref>. Among the Hsp70 s, <italic>human</italic> Hsp70 (hHsp70) has attracted great interest because of its demonstrated implications in numerous misfolding diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Selkoe1">[58]</xref> (Parkinson, Alzheimer…) and in cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Garrido1">[59]</xref>. Hsp70 s of all species share common structural features and it is hypothesized that they perform their biological functions in a similar manner. Most mechanistic information about hHsp70 was derived from comparisons with the highly homologous bacterial <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 (DnaK) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s014">Table S1</xref>). It should be mentioned however that a high homology of sequence between two proteins does not guarantee that their allosteric mechanisms and residues involved are similar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Livesay1">[60]</xref>. In the present work, the calculations and analysis were performed for DnaK because a large set of structural and biochemical data are available (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref> sections for a comparison with the present results and their implications for hHsp70). In particular, the allosteric communication in Hsp70 s, i.e. how the binding of a ligand in the nucleotide-binding domain (NBD) modifies the conformation of the remote substrate-binding domain (SBD) of the protein, was extensively studied for DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Ha1">[61]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>. The structural model used in the present work is the two-domain structure of ADP-bound DnaK (residues 4–603, missing the C-terminal part) solved by NMR (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref>. Our first aim was to probe the conformational dynamics and the structural perturbations induced upon exchange of ADP by ATP and by the removal of ADP from this NMR model of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK on the micro-second time-scale at the atomic scale.</p>
<p>The sampling issue of the unbiased MD simulations of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK was addressed by considering two trajectories with different initial conditions of the protein in each of its nucleotide-binding states and more important by restricting the data to a <italic>subset</italic> of the conformational degrees of freedom for which the convergence between the two trajectories was reached. This was achieved by projecting the FEL of the protein along its amino-acid sequence by computing the free-energy profiles (FEPs) along the coarse-grained dihedral angles (CGDAs) <italic>γ</italic> defined from four consecutive C<sup>α</sup> atoms of the protein (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s003">Fig. S1</xref>) and describing the backbone motions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Senet1">[71]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cote1">[72]</xref>. Only the FEPs which were similar in the two trajectories of the protein in the same nucleotide-binding state were kept for the analysis of the allosteric communication, we named these FEPs the DATA. No information can be exploited from the other FEPs: they may or not be relevant to the conformational fluctuations of the protein (NO DATA set). With this approach, we were able to quantify how each FEP varies along the amino-acid sequence depending on the nucleotide-binding state of the protein and to relate the FEP modifications to biochemical data of wild-type or mutant <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK chaperones. Indeed, the comparison between the DATA sets of FEPs for <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK in different nucleotide-binding states lead finally to a subset of only 27 key dihedral angles involved in the conformational nucleotide-dependent transitions. The fluctuations of these 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> on their FEPs are subdiffusive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Senet1">[71]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cote2">[73]</xref>. The coupling between the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> can be revealed by analyzing the correlation of their motions using the dihedral principal component analysis (dPCA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Altis1">[74]</xref> allowing the definition of collective motions to which these degrees of freedom contribute the most, in a similar manner to principal component analysis in Cartesian coordinates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Amadei1">[75]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kitao1">[76]</xref> or to the full-correlation analysis based on the information theory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Lange1">[77]</xref>. The study of the FELs was complemented by an analysis of the long-life time contacts between residues present in ATP-DnaK trajectories and not present in the trajectories of the protein in the other nucleotide-binding states.</p>
<p>The paper is organized as follows. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref> are presented in the next section and are compared to available experimental data. The structure of Hsp70 s and the results of the unbiased all-atom MD simulations for <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK are shown. There, we described and compared to available experimental data an intermediate state found by MD upon ATP-binding, named ATP*-Hsp70, where the two domains of the protein are docked on a sub-microsecond time-scale. The construction of a map of persistent residue contacts in ATP-bound DnaK conformational dynamics is described and compared to available experimental data. Next, the methodology to cope with the limited sampling of the present unbiased MD simulations and to extract the key residues from the analysis of the FEPs along the amino-acid sequence is presented, as well as its application to the MD simulations of ATP-bound DnaK. Then, a comparison between the key residues extracted from this new methodology with biochemical and structural data on the allostery in Hsp70 s is discussed in detail. The paper ends with a short conclusion where the major results are summarized and with the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Conformational changes of <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 (DnaK)</title>
<sec id="s2a1">
<title>Conformations of Hsp70 s from experiments</title>
<p>All homologous Hsp70 s share a common architecture composed of a 45 kDa N-terminal NBD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Flaherty1">[78]</xref> which catalyzes ATP hydrolysis, and of a 25 kDa C-terminal domain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhu1">[79]</xref> which is divided into SBD, which binds to non-native or unfolded substrate proteins, and a C-unstructured terminal domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 A</xref>). The N-terminal 45-kDa NBD is divided into two rather symmetrical lobes, I and II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 A</xref>), each divided into two subdomains A and B <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Flaherty1">[78]</xref>. The SBD is composed of a β-sandwich subdomain (SBD-β), which has a hydrophobic peptide binding pocket, and of a α-helical “lid” subdomain (SBD-α), which regulates the access of the substrate to the SBD-β <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhu1">[79]</xref>. The NBD and the SBD are connected by a conserved hydrophobic linker <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hunt1">[80]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Nucleotide-dependent conformational states of Hsp70 s.</title>
<p>A: Cartoon diagram of the experimental NMR structure of <italic>E. coli</italic> ADP-Hsp70 (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> used as input structure for the MD simulations. B: Cartoon diagram of the experimental X-ray structure of <italic>E. coli</italic> ATP-Hsp70 (PDB ID: 4B9Q) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>. C: Schematic representation of the conformational transition as expected from experimental data and observed in MD simulations of ATP-Hsp70, starting from the closed conformation of Hsp70. The color code is the following: NBD-IA (residues 4–37, 112–182 and 363–383; red), NBD-IB (residues 38–111; green), NBD-IIA (residues 183–227 and 311–362; blue), NBD-IIB (residues 228–310; yellow), linker (residues 384–393; black), SBD-β (residues 394–502; magenta) and SBD-α (residues 503–603; cyan). These figures were prepared with PyMOL [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>].</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Hsp70 s occur in two main conformations to perform their chaperone function, we named closed conformation (with ADP bound to the NBD or without nucleotide = APO, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 A</xref>) and open conformation (with ATP bound to the NBD, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 B</xref>). In the nucleotide-free Hsp70 and in ADP-bound Hsp70, the SBD is assumed to be closed with low binding and release rate of the protein substrate. However, recent experiments shown that the complete closure of the SBD is not strictly required in the chaperone protein interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schlecht1">[81]</xref>. In absence of ATP, the SBD and the NBD are undocked and the inter-domain linker is exposed to solvent, as shown by low-resolution Small Angle X-ray Scattering (SAXS) data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Shi1">[83]</xref>, Förster resonance energy transfer (FRET) data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Mapa1">[84]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Marcinowski1">[85]</xref> and by the two-domain Hsp70 NMR derived-structure (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 A</xref>). In ATP-bound Hsp70, the SBD is open with fast binding and release of the protein substrate, and the SBD and NBD are docked, as shown by SAXS data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Shi1">[83]</xref> and FRET data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Mapa1">[84]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Marcinowski1">[85]</xref> and suggested by the X-ray structure of an ATP-Hsp110 homolog <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Liu1">[86]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schuermann1">[87]</xref> and by a new open conformation of an ATP-bound DnaK mutant (PDB ID: 4B9Q) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref> stabilized by introducing disulphide bridges at specific positions deduced from the structure of the ATP-Hsp110 homolog (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 B</xref>).</p>
<p>The transition between the open and the closed structural states of Hsp70 is triggered by the ATP binding to the NBD which induces a conformational change of the inter-domain linker and the opening of the SBD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Ha1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Moro1">[62]</xref>, through an allosteric mechanism which is not fully elucidated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Ha1">[61]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Vogel2">[68]</xref>. The ATP hydrolysis restores the closed conformation of the SBD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Garrido1">[59]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Livesay1">[60]</xref>. In <italic>vivo</italic>, the ATP hydrolysis and the nucleotide exchange rates are increased by co-chaperones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kampinga1">[88]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2a2">
<title>Unbiased MD simulations of the APO and ADP-bound DnaK reveal that the SBD is moving freely around the NBD whereas MD simulations of the ATP-bound DnaK reveal the docking of the SBD onto the NBD</title>
<p>To get insights into the mechanism of the conformational dynamics of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK, we focused here on the spontaneous conformational transition, i.e. from the closed to the open conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 C</xref>), induced by the binding of ATP to the NBD of DnaK in absence of protein substrate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Ha1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Moro1">[62]</xref>. We performed 2 unbiased all-atom MD simulations in explicit solvent with different initial conditions in each nucleotide-binding state of the NBD, i.e. nucleotide-free (APO state), ADP-bound and ATP-bound for a total simulation time of 1.9 µs. The six MD trajectories (APO1, APO2, ADP1, ADP2, ATP1, and ATP2) are described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section.</p>
<p>First, MD simulations of the nucleotide-free and the ADP-bound DnaK revealed that the SBD is moving freely around the NBD. Indeed, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2</xref> clearly shows that the different conformational sub-states of APO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2 A</xref>) and ADP-DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2 B</xref>) correspond to different orientations of the SBD relative to the NBD. Structures of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK upon ADP-binding and without nucleotide are elongated with no strong interactions between the two main domains, as expected by comparison with experimental data and particularly SAXS experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Shi1">[83]</xref>. In addition, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Figs. 2 A and 2 B</xref> agree with the hypothesis of a SBD diffusing around a cone, as suggested from residual dipolar coupling NMR data of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref>. By contrast, MD simulations of ATP-bound DnaK reveal conformational changes. Indeed, significant structural changes and particularly the docking of the SBD onto the NBD (more precisely on the lobe I of the NBD) were found upon the binding of ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2 C</xref>) in the two MD runs ATP1 and ATP2. In addition, differences between the MD runs ATP1 and ATP2 were observed. Actually, it seems that there are (at least) two different binding positions of the SBD onto the lobe I of the NBD, more precisely there are two orientations of the SBD, bound to the NBD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2 C</xref>). The time-scale of the present MD simulations is too short to observe the full conformational change between the ADP-bound and the ATP-bound states of Hsp70: in other words, the opening of the substrate binding domain was not observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2 C</xref>). However, we found that the ATP-binding to the NBD of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK induces the docking of a closed SBD onto the NBD (we named this intermediate state ATP*) whereas this docking was not observed for ADP-bound DnaK and for APO-DnaK.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Cartoon representation of the representative structures obtained by MD simulations.</title>
<p>A: MD runs APO1 (red) and APO2 (firebrick). B: MD runs ADP1 (blue) and ADP2 (light blue). C: MD runs ATP1 (green) and ATP2 (pale green). The NMR-derived structure used as starting point for the MD simulations (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> is shown in transparent gray. Representative structures are extracted from a dPCA on the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section). These figures were prepared with PyMOL [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>].</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2a3">
<title>Comparison of ATP*-DnaK structure with experimental and MD data</title>
<p>In spite of the fact that the SBD of ATP*-DnaK remains closed on the time-scale of the present MD simulations, its structural properties are compatible with SAXS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Shi1">[83]</xref>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3</xref>. In all SAXS experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Shi1">[83]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Johnson1">[89]</xref>, the structure of ATP-Hsp70 was more compact than the structure of ADP-Hsp70: the difference between their radius of gyration, <italic>ΔR<sub>g</sub></italic> = <italic>R<sub>g</sub>(ADP)</italic>−<italic>R<sub>g</sub>(ATP)</italic>, was about 5 Å for <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Shi1">[83]</xref> and between 2 and 7 Å for bovine Hsc70 (bHsc70) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Johnson1">[89]</xref>. In our MD simulations of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK, <italic>ΔR<sub>g</sub></italic> varies between 3.6 Å and 6.8 Å in good agreement with SAXS data. The distribution of the distance <italic>r</italic> between two heavy atoms, <italic>P(r)</italic>, in ATP-bound DnaK and ADP-bound DnaK computed from MD simulations are also in good agreement with the distribution <italic>P(r)</italic> of Hsp70 homologs measured by SAXS and with the distribution <italic>P(r)</italic> of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK computed from the experimental X-ray <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref> and NMR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> resolved 3D structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). In MD, <italic>P(r)</italic> has only one peak at about 30 Å for ATP-DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3 A</xref>), in agreement with the distribution extracted from the SAXS data of ATP-bHsc70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3 B</xref>) and from the X-ray data of ATP-DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3 A</xref>). On the contrary, the functions <italic>P(r)</italic> extracted from SAXS data of ADP-bHsc70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3 B</xref>) and from NMR data of ADP-DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3 A</xref>) and the one calculated from the MD simulations of ADP-DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g003">Fig. 3 A</xref>) show two peaks: one at 30 Å and a distinct shoulder at 60 Å, reflecting the bilobal shape of the protein in this nucleotide-binding state.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Comparison between the simulated and experimental distance distribution functions <italic>P(r)</italic> of Hsp70 s.</title>
<p>A: Distance distribution function <italic>P(r)</italic> of the ATP-bound (green lines) and ADP-bound (blue lines) of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK computed from MD simulations (solid lines) and computed from the experimental X-ray (PDB ID: 4BQ9) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref> and NMR-derived (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> structures (dashed lines), respectively. B: Distance distribution function <italic>P(r)</italic> of the ATP-bound (green line) and ADP-bound (blue line) of bHsc70. The function <italic>P(r)</italic> of bHsc70 in the ATP and ADP states were digitized from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Figure 4</xref> of Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1">[82]</xref>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The intermediate structure of ATP*-DnaK is different from the very recent crystallized triple mutant ATP-bound DnaK (E47C, T199A, F529C) in an <italic>open</italic> conformational state with a SBD-α covalently bound to the NBD through a disulphide bridge 47C-529C (PDB ID: 4B9Q) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>. In ATP*, as in ATP-bound DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1 B</xref>), the linker forms a β strand interacting with the loop between the strands β2 and β2' of the SBD-β. However, the position of the linker in ATP-bound DnaK is shifted relative to the one in ATP*: a contact is formed between D393 and I418 in ATP-bound structure whereas a contact is formed between D393 and N415 in ATP* (see next subsection) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>.</p>
<p>Recent NMR studies suggest that DnaK occur in at least three states: a closed conformation (ADP-bound with a flexible linker as the NMR-derived structure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref>), an open conformation (ATP-bound with the linker bound between the subdomains IA/IIA of the NBD and the NBD/SBD docked as in the crystallized structure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>), and an intermediate allosteric active state (where the closed SBD <italic>bound to a substrate</italic> and the NBD domains interact with the linker bound to the NBD). This intermediate state is however different from ATP*-DnaK found in MD as it occurred when both ATP and the protein substrate are bound to the NBD and to the SBD, respectively.</p>
<p>The intermediate state ATP*-DnaK was the most frequent SBD/NBD transient docked state found in our recent intensive coarse-grained MD simulations of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK using a completely unrelated force-field <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Goa1">[37]</xref>. On the contrary, in the recent all-atom MD simulations of DnaK by Chiappori et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Chiappori1">[25]</xref> using the same force-field used in the present work, the authors did not observe the docking of the SBD onto the NBD. They did find however a motion of the SBD towards the NBD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2</xref> in Ref. 25) which resembles to the one leading to the ATP*-DnaK intermediate state found here. It is worth noting however that the number and the duration of the MD simulations in Ref. 25 were much smaller than the present ones: the trajectories were typically of about 50–100 ns of duration with the longest duration being 225 ns for an ATP-bound DnaK trajectory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Chiappori1">[25]</xref>. The absence of ATP* in the calculations of Ref. 25 may arise simply from the too short duration used in this earlier work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Chiappori1">[25]</xref> for the random initial condition chosen.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Specific contacts in ATP-bound DnaK</title>
<p>In order to characterize the interdomain interactions leading to the ATP*-DnaK intermediate state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2 C</xref>), as well as the interactions between the nucleotide and the NBD of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK, the contact maps (CMs) of ADP and ATP-bound DnaK and the contact map difference (CMD) ATP/ADP were computed for the MD trajectories of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK in these two different nucleotide-binding states (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section for the calculations of CM and CMD).</p>
<p>The CM of ATP-bound DnaK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s004">Fig. S2 A</xref>), which is composed of 1994 contacts, contains only 6 interdomain contacts (contacts between NBD/linker, linker/SBD or NBD/SBD): R167-L390, R167-L391, L391-T417, L391-P419, L392-T416 and D393-N415 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4 A</xref>). The CM of ADP-bound DnaK has no interdomain contacts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s004">Fig. S2 B</xref>), which means that the interdomain contacts are unique to the ATP* intermediate state, as revealed by the CMD ATP/ADP (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s004">Fig. S2 C</xref>). In MD, this major difference about the interdomain contacts in ADP-bound and in ATP-bound DnaK arises from a different interaction between the NBD and the linker in these two nucleotide-binding states, as shown by the different distances R167-L390 and R167-L391 in these two states (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Contact maps from ATP-bound and ADP-bound MD trajectories.</title>
<p>A: Interdomain interactions extracted from the contact map difference ATP/ADP (see text for details). Residues involved in the interdomain interactions are shown in stick representation. The color code is the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. B: Interactions between the ATP nucleotide and the NBD of DnaK from ATP-bound MD trajectories. C: Three-dimensional representation of the interactions between ATP and the NBD. Residues of the NBD in contact with ATP are shown in stick representation. The color code of the protein structure is the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. These figures were prepared with PyMOL [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>].</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003379-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>List of the interdomain interactions and their corresponding average distances extracted from the contact map difference ATP/ADP (see text for details).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003379-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residues</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Distance (Å)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADP</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NBD/Linker</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R167-L390</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R167-L391</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linker/SBD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L391-T417</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L391-P419</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L392-T416</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D393-N415</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>The comparison between MD results for ADP-bound and ATP-bound DnaK shows that the communication between the NBD, the linker and the SBD involves the residue R167 of the subdomain IA of the NBD, the residues L390 and L391 of the linker and the residues 415–419 of the subdomain β of the SBD. These residues were identified to be crucial for the interdomain communication in DnaK. Indeed, the mutation R167A induces a loss of allosteric coupling between the NBD and the SBD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Vogel1">[64]</xref> and the mutations K414I <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Montgomery1">[90]</xref> and N415G <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref> eliminate and attenuate allostery, respectively. The residues L390, L391 and L392, which belong to the VLLL motif of the linker (highly conserved between the different species of Hsp70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kumar2">[67]</xref>), was shown essential for <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK's <italic>in vivo</italic> functions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kumar2">[67]</xref>. In addition, it has been proposed that ATP binding to the ATPase domain causes a bending of the C-terminal part of the linker of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK at D393, in order to facilitate an insertion of the linker between the NBD and the SBD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Vogel1">[64]</xref>. In the present MD simulations, the coupling between the NBD and the SBD confirms the insert of the linker upon ATP binding between the two domains through the interactions R167/L390 and D393/N415.</p>
<p>The contacts between ATP and the NBD were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4 B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4 C</xref>). This network of contacts is formed by 12 residues which belong to the subdomains IA, IIA and IIB of the NBD: T11, T12 and N13 (IA); G195, G196, G197, G198 and T199 (IIA); I271 (IIB); G341, G342 and R345 (IIA). Among these 12 residues, the CMD ATP/ADP reveals that only 6 are unique to the ATP-bound state of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK and were not found in the APO and ADP-DnaK MD simulations performed in the present work (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4 B and C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s004">Fig. S2 C</xref>): T11, G197, G198, T199, I271 and G341.</p>
<p>The contacts depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4</xref> for the intermediate state ATP*-DnaK can be compared qualitatively with those observed in the very recent crystallized triple mutant ATP-bound DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>. Although the structure of the intermediate state found in MD and the crystallized open conformation of DnaK are quite different as discussed above, many contacts between ATP and the NBD found in ATP*-DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4 B and C</xref>) are also found in the experimental structure of ATP-bound DnaK (PDB ID: 4B9Q) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>. Except D195-ATP, at a contact distance (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section) of 4.9 Å in the open X-ray structure, all contacts found in MD between the NBD and ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4 B</xref>) occur also in the ATP-bound experimental structure. However, contacts between ATP and the NBD observed in the fully open structure are missing in ATP* intermediate state: in particular the residue K70, which is at 2.8 Å from ATPγ in the experimental structure, is at about 4.2 Å in ATP*-DnaK. A contact occurs however between K70 and E171 both in the ATP*-DnaK MD trajectory (average distance K70-E171 = 2.4 Å) and in the experimental open conformation but not in the ADP-DnaK trajectories (average distance ADP K70-E171 = 8.6 Å). Because the metastable position of the linker is different in ATP* compared with the position of the linker in the open conformation of DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>), different interdomain contacts were found experimentally in particular R167-D481, I168-D481, N415-D326 and D393-N170.</p>
<p>The analysis of the contact maps provides only a static representation of the MD data and of the influence of ATP binding on the conformations of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK. The modifications of the protein dynamics induced by the nucleotide and the correlations between the different structural modifications along the DnaK amino-acid sequence are not easily interpreted from this sole analysis. As stated in the introduction, the FEL holds the key to understand how a nucleotide modifies the properties and populations of the protein conformers. To provide the link between the FEL and the global conformational change observed in ATP-bound MD trajectories, we analyze next the free-energy profiles (FEPs) of the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s003">Fig. S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e001">Eq. 1</xref>) along the amino-acid sequence of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Analysis of the main-chain FEPs along the amino-acid sequence to detect key residues involved in the conformational changes</title>
<p>In order to identify which residues are involved in the nucleotide signal propagation along the backbone of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK, we examined which of the 597 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> have a FEP depending on the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD. However, the FEPs of DnaK in a given nucleotide-binding state computed from the present unbiased MD trajectories are effective FEPs. The effective FEP differs from the actual FEP, which is an equilibrium thermodynamic property and should be computed from a large ensemble of trajectories of the protein in the same nucleotide state. However, the size of the system simulated (about 500000 atoms) and our computing capabilities limited the number of trajectories to only two trajectories of several hundred of nanoseconds per nucleotide-binding state of the NBD. Because of this limited sampling issue, only the FEPs which are similar in different trajectories in a given nucleotide-binding state were considered.</p>
<sec id="s2c1">
<title>Convergence of the FEPs</title>
<p>For each <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic>, the similarity index <italic>H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> computed from two MD trajectories of DnaK in the same nucleotide-binding state of the NBD was calculated, i.e. <italic>H(γ<sub>i</sub>)<sup>APO1/APO2</sup></italic>, <italic>H(γ<sub>i</sub>)<sup>ADP1/ADP2</sup></italic> and <italic>H(γ<sub>i</sub>)<sup>ATP1/ATP2</sup></italic> (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e002">Eq. 2</xref>). For the APO state, 471 of 597 FEPs were similar (“converged”) in the two MD trajectories representing 79% of all <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> angles (defining the DATA for the APO state ≡ <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>APO</sub></italic>). For the ADP and ATP bound states, 449 of 597 (DATA ADP ≡ <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ADP</sub></italic>) and 447 of 597 (DATA ATP≡<italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ATP</sub></italic>) FEPs were similar (“converged”), respectively. The similar FEPs are located all along the amino-acid sequence, both in secondary-structures and in loops, and have various shapes from strongly harmonic FEPs to multiple-minima FEPs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Senet1">[71]</xref>. Only the CGDAs <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> belonging to the subset DATA for each nucleotide-binding state of the NBD of DnaK, i.e. <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>APO</sub></italic>, <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ADP</sub></italic> and <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ATP</sub></italic>, were considered to be “converged” within the time-scale of the present MD simulations. From these DATA subsets, we defined an average PDF for each nucleotide-binding state of the NBD by combining the two MD trajectories 1 and 2 with different initial conditions i.e. <italic>P<sub>APO</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>, <italic>P<sub>ADP</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> and <italic>P<sub>ATP</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> (<italic>P(γ<sub>i</sub>)≡[p<sub>1</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)+p<sub>2</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)]/2</italic>) and recomputed the FEPs <italic>V(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> of each <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> of the DATA subsets from these average PDFs <italic>P(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>, as shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e001">Eq. 1</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c2">
<title>Identifying a small network of residues influenced by the nucleotide binding from the FEPs</title>
<p>To identify the key residues influenced by the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD, the <italic>dissimilarity</italic> index, defined by <italic>1-H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e002">Eq. 2</xref>), was computed between the average FEPs (see above) <italic>V<sub>APO</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>) V<sub>ADP</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>, and <italic>V<sub>ATP</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>, for the CGDAs common to the different DATA sets (388 <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> for <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>APO</sub></italic>∩<italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ADP</sub></italic>, 379 <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> for <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>APO</sub>∩{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ATP</sub></italic> and 363 <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> for <italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ADP</sub></italic>∩<italic>{γ<sub>i</sub>}<sub>ATP)</sub></italic>). The results for the dissimilarity <italic>1-H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> along the amino-acid sequence are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g005">Fig. 5</xref> (on the structure) and in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s005">Fig. S3</xref> (along the sequence). For each comparison, APO/ADP, APO/ATP and ADP/ATP, the FEPs were divided in three sets according to the influence of the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD of DnaK: a set of FEPs strongly influenced (<italic>1-H</italic>&gt;0.7), a set of FEPs significantly influenced (0.3≤<italic>1-H</italic>&lt;0.7) and a set of FEPs weakly influenced (<italic>1-H</italic>≤0.3) by the nucleotide. Most of CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> of DnaK have FEPs weakly influenced by the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD (more than 300 in the three comparisons, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g005">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s005">Fig. S3</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t002">Table 2</xref>) showing that the large conformational changes induced by a nucleotide could be due to a small network of residues. For example, only 9 FEPs, which are distributed all along the structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g005">Fig. 5</xref>) and along the amino-acid sequence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s005">Fig. S3</xref>), are strongly influenced by the nucleotide between the ADP and the ATP-bound states of DnaK (<italic>1-H</italic>&gt;0.7) and 25 FEPs are significantly influenced (0.3≤<italic>1-H</italic>&lt;0.7). Similar results were observed for the other comparisons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g005">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s005">Fig. S3</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Analysis of 1-D FEPs of CGDAs <italic>γ</italic>.</title>
<p>Mapping of the dissimilarity index <italic>1-H</italic> between the FEPs of APO/ADP (top panel), APO/ATP (middle panel) and ADP/ATP (bottom panel) onto the structure of DnaK (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref>. Residues belonging to the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> which are strongly influenced (<italic>1-H</italic>&gt;0.7), significantly influenced (0.3≤<italic>1-H</italic>&lt;0.7) and weakly influenced by the nucleotide (<italic>1-H</italic>≤0.3) are shown with large red, medium yellow and small cyan spheres, respectively. The color code of the protein structure is the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. These figures were prepared with PyMOL [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>].</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003379-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Statistical analysis of the dissimilarity [<italic>1-H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>] of the FEPs between concatenated MD runs in different nucleotide-binding states.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003379-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subset</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APO/ADP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APO/ATP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADP/ATP</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Strongly influenced</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{6}/{388} (1.6%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{6}/{379} (1.6%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{9}/{363} (2.5%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Significantly influenced</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{41}/{388} (10.6%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{26}/{379} (6.9%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{25}/{363} (6.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Weakly influenced</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{341}/{388} (87.8%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{347}/{379} (91.5%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">{329}/{363} (90.6%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p><italic>1-H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>&gt;0.7, 0.3&lt;<italic>1-H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>≤0.7 and <italic>1-H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>≤0.3, respectively.  The notation is the following: {number of residues in the subset}/{number of residues compared}. Subset strongly, significantly and weakly influenced correspond to </p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The combination of the three different comparisons reveals common CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> for which the FEP is significantly influenced by the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s005">Fig. S3</xref>). For example, <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic> in the linker has a FEP weakly influenced by the nucleotide in the comparison APO/ADP (<italic>1-H(γ<sub>387</sub>)<sup>APO/ADP</sup></italic> = 0.26) and strongly influenced in the comparisons APO/ATP (<italic>1-H(γ<sub>387</sub>)<sup>APO/ATP</sup></italic> = 0.99) and ADP/ATP (<italic>1-H(γ<sub>387</sub>)<sup>ADP/ATP</sup></italic> = 0.98) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s005">Fig. S3</xref>). It means that <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic> has a specific FEP in ADP-bound DnaK or in nucleotide-free DnaK but another FEP in ATP-bound DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). We named hereafter <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic> an ATP-specific angle. Another example is <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic> which has a FEP weakly influenced by the nucleotide in the comparison APO/ATP (<italic>1-H(γ<sub>98</sub>)<sup>APO/ATP</sup></italic> = 0.18) but strongly influenced in the comparisons APO/ADP (<italic>1-H(γ<sub>98</sub>)<sup>APO/ADP</sup></italic> = 0.75) and ADP/ATP (<italic>1-H(γ<sub>98</sub>)<sup>ADP/ATP</sup></italic> = 0.78), as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s005">Fig. S3</xref>. It means that <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic> has a specific FEP in ATP-bound DnaK or in nucleotide-free DnaK but another specific FEP in ADP-bound DnaK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s006">Fig. S4</xref>). We named hereafter <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic> an ADP-specific angle.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>FEPs <italic>V(γ)</italic> for <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic> in <italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic> unit.</title>
<p><italic>V(γ)</italic> computed from APO, ADP-bound and ATP-bound MD simulations of DnaK are colored in red, blue and green respectively.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Finally, 7 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> are APO specific (for example <italic>γ<sub>213</sub></italic>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s006">Fig. S4</xref>), 6 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> are ADP specific, 9 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> are ATP specific and 5 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> are specific to each different nucleotide-bound state (for example <italic>γ<sub>465</sub></italic>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s006">Fig. S4</xref>). These 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>) correspond to 91 residues (15% of the total residue number) which contribute to the communication between the SBD and the NBD of DnaK through nucleotide binding in the present MD simulations. The 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> are localized along the whole structure, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>, and more precisely, 11 are located in the NBD (1 in the subdomain IA; 4 in the subdomain IB; 3 in each subdomain IIA and IIB), 1 in the linker and 15 in the SBD (11 in the SBD-β and 4 in the SBD-α).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Overview of the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic>.</title>
<p>A: NBD+linker. B: SBD. Each CGDA <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> is represented by a sphere centered on the C<sup>α</sup>(i) atom. The color code of the protein structure is the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. These figures were prepared with PyMOL [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>].</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pcbi-1003379-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>List of the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> revealed by analysis of 1-D FEPs of DnaK in different nucleotide-binding states and their corresponding amino acids.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003379-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGDA <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corresponding residues</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APO/ADP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APO/ATP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADP/ATP</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Refs.</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G212-E213-K214-T215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.19</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Chiappori1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Swain2">[65]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">432<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D431-N432-Q433-S434</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.54</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.53</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Rist1">[98]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Burkholder1">[100]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">463<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I462-N463-P464-A465</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.45</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.64</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Davis1">[102]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">490</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K489-D490-K491-N492</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.49</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.36</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">492</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K491-N492-S493-G494</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.57</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.62</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">494<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S493-G494-K495-E496</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.64</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.53</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">504</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A503-S504-S505-G506</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.41</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.64</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R76-F77-Q78-D79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.32</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.16</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Johnson1">[89]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-OBrien1">[96]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D97-N98-G99-D100</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.25</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.22</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A101-W102-V103-E104</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.35</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.61</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Buchberger1">[97]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V192-Y193-D194-L195</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.63</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.66</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Chiappori1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L252-R253-N254-D255</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.63</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.70</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Liu2">[99]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I338-L339-V340-G341</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.46</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.34</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T11-T12-N13-S14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.46</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.40</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Sousa1">[95]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q248-G249-I250-D251</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.48</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.28</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Liu2">[99]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G249-I250-D251-L252</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IIB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.37</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.26</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Liu2">[99]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">387<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V386-K387-D388-V389</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">linker</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.02</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Swain2">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kumar2">[67]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Rist1">[98]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G406-V407-M408-T409</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.43</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.43</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Burkholder1">[100]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">408<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V407-M408-T409-T410</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.52</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.62</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Burkholder1">[100]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">448<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R447-A448-A449-D450</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.67</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.54</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Rist1">[98]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Aponte1">[103]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">508</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L507-N508-E509-D510</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.67</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.59</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">524<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A523-E524-A525-D526</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.56</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.59</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Aponte1">[103]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N64-T65-L66-F67</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.53</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.45</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.12</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Johnson1">[89]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-OBrien1">[96]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">†</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G443-E444-R445-K446</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.64</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.19</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.68</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Burkholder1">[100]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">464<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N463-P464-A465-P466</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.49</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.49</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.56</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">465<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P464-A465-P466-R467</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.65</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.50</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.63</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">519<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">‡</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D518-A519-E520-A521</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.22</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.65</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.05</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Davis1">[102]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Aponte1">[103]</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>† and ‡ indicate amino acids which have been depicted to be allosterically relevant from biochemical and bioinformatics methods, respectively. Characters in bold in the table represents strongly and significantly influenced FEPs (<italic>H</italic>&lt;0.7, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t002">Table 2</xref> and text for more details). </p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Two-dimensional free-energy surface (FES) built from the collective motions of the key residues in ATP-bound DnaK</title>
<sec id="s2d1">
<title>Two-dimensional FES of ATP-bound DnaK</title>
<p>The comparison of the FEPs of CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> of the backbone of DnaK in different nucleotide-binding states reveals that the nucleotide influences at least 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> located both in the NBD and in the SBD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). In other words, the modification of the (unknown) FEL of DnaK upon ligand binding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kumar1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Tsai1">[7]</xref> can be represented here quantitatively by its projection over 27 dimensions. Obviously, these 27 coordinates are not independent and the local motions of the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> upon nucleotide-binding are coupled to each other. In order to understand how the binding of ATP to the NBD of DnaK induces the docking of its SBD onto its NBD, we established the relation between these 27 local motions <italic>γ</italic> and the global motions (domains) of ATP-DnaK by applying dPCA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Altis1">[74]</xref>.</p>
<p>The dPCA was carried on the subset of 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> using the MD trajectories of ATP-DnaK (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section for more details). <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref> for the MD trajectory ATP1 are shown (the results for the MD trajectory ATP2 lead to the same conclusions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4">[92]</xref>). Only modes 1 and 2 contribute significantly to the <italic>MSF</italic> of the 27 CGDAs. Indeed, for the MD run ATP1, <italic>λ<sup>1</sup></italic> contributes 74% of the total covariance of the system and <italic>λ<sup>2</sup></italic> 8% whereas for the MD run ATP2, <italic>λ<sup>1</sup></italic> contributes 85% of the total covariance of the system and <italic>λ<sup>2</sup></italic> 3%; justifying to use only the two collective modes 1 and 2 as the minimal representation of the free-energy landscape of ATP-DnaK.</p>
<p>The projections of the vectors <italic>u<sub>n</sub>(t)</italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e004">Eq. 4</xref>) extracted from the MD trajectory along the eigenvectors of modes 1 and 2 defined the collective coordinates <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup>(t)</italic> and <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup>(t)</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e012">Eq. 7</xref>). From the two-dimensional PDF of <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup></italic> computed from the MD trajectory, i.e. <italic>P(dPC<sup>1</sup><sub>,</sub>dPC<sup>2</sup>)</italic>, the effective FES <italic>V<sub>1,2</sub> = -k<sub>B</sub>T ln[P(dPC<sup>1</sup><sub>,</sub>dPC<sup>2</sup>)]</italic>, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g008">Fig. 8</xref>, was calculated. The largest motions defined by the first and second <italic>dPCs</italic> can be interpreted in terms of specific features of the two-dimensional FES <italic>V<sub>1,2</sub></italic> because the dPCA method is converged <italic>in the subspace</italic> of the 27 dihedral angles considered (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section and Refs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hess1">[93]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hess2">[94]</xref>). The FES of the MD run ATP1 shows 5 global minima <italic>A<sub>i</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g008">Fig. 8</xref>) defined from the isolines of free-energy (≤3 <italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic>). The minima <italic>A<sub>i</sub></italic> are ordered according to the chronology of the MD trajectory, from <italic>i</italic> = 1 to 5. The most probable structure within each minimum <italic>A<sub>i</sub></italic> of the MD run ATP1 is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s007">Fig. S5</xref>: the structure corresponding to the minimum <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic> is an elongated structure, without interactions between the NBD and the SBD and closely similar to the initial one (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref>. In the basin corresponding to the minimum <bold><italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic></bold>, the SBD rotates around the linker and get close to the NBD but without strong interactions between the two main domains. In the structure of the global minimum <bold><italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic></bold> of the MD run ATP1, the SBD is docked to the lobe I of the NBD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s007">Fig. S5</xref>). Note that the lid of the SBD (SBD-α) is docked in the subdomain B of the lobe I of the NBD. Structures corresponding to the minima <bold><italic>A<sub>4</sub></italic></bold> and <bold><italic>A<sub>5</sub></italic></bold>, are characterized by the docking of the two domains, as observed in the minimum <bold><italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic></bold>, but with local conformational changes in the SBD (for example of the CGDA <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s008">Fig. S6</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Dihedral principal component analysis applied to MD simulations of ATP-bound DnaK.</title>
<p>FES computed for the MD run ATP1. Minima are shown with gray (green for the most probable one) diamonds and the isolines (black lines) are drawn every <italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic> unit. The color scale for the free-energy is in <italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic> units.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>In the representative structure of the global minimum of the MD run ATP2, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, the SBD is docked to the lobe I of the NBD but in a different position, compared to the global minimum of the MD run ATP1. Although the two end points of the ATP-bound DnaK trajectories are different, the ground-state (on the time-scale of our simulations) is identical in the space of the subset of CGDAs with a similar FEP. Indeed, each of the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> is in the same local conformation in the structures corresponding to the global minimum of the FESs computed from the MD runs ATP1 and ATP2, as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s008">Fig. S6</xref>.</p>
<p>Because the dPCA catches the most important fluctuations occurring in a MD trajectory, the application of the dPCA analysis to the APO and ADP-bound DnaK trajectories produce different behaviors. The FES of the ADP-bound DnaK trajectories (computed from the <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup></italic> on the 27 dihedral angles) shown no transition state between the initial and final conformations of the protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4">[92]</xref>. The FES of the nucleotide-free (APO) DnaK trajectories (computed from the <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> on the 27 dihedral angles) shown three basins: a small basin corresponding to the initial state, a transition state, and a final basin corresponding to the final state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4">[92]</xref>. The transition state corresponds to an intermediate state where the SBD starts to rotate on a cone due to a change of the linker conformation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4">[92]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d2">
<title>Free-minimum energy path on the two-dimensional FES of ATP-bound DnaK</title>
<p>The initial <bold><italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic></bold> and final <bold><italic>A<sub>5</sub></italic></bold> conformations are located at the bottom of two “basins” of the FES (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g008">Fig. 8</xref>) which can be connected by a pathway of minimum energy (PME) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 A</xref>). The PME for the transitions <bold><italic>A<sub>1</sub>→A<sub>2</sub>→A<sub>3</sub>→A<sub>4</sub>→A<sub>5</sub></italic></bold> on the FES of the MD run ATP1 was computed as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section. The PME was divided into 74 steps (from <italic>s<sub>0</sub></italic> to <italic>s<sub>73</sub></italic>) with minima <bold><italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic></bold>, <bold><italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic></bold>, <bold><italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic></bold>, <bold><italic>A<sub>4</sub></italic></bold> and <bold><italic>A<sub>5</sub></italic></bold> at respectively <italic>s<sub>0</sub></italic>, <italic>s<sub>14</sub></italic>, <italic>s<sub>36</sub></italic>, <italic>s<sub>63</sub></italic> and <italic>s<sub>73</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 A and B</xref>). The PME shows 4 saddle points for each transition: at <italic>s<sub>9</sub></italic> for the transition <bold><italic>A<sub>1</sub>→A<sub>2</sub></italic></bold>; at <italic>s<sub>18</sub></italic> for the transition <bold><italic>A<sub>2</sub>→A<sub>3</sub></italic></bold>; at <italic>s<sub>54</sub></italic> for the transition <bold><italic>A<sub>3</sub>→A<sub>4</sub></italic></bold> and at <italic>s<sub>68</sub></italic> for the transition <bold><italic>A<sub>4</sub>→A<sub>5</sub></italic></bold>. The largest free-energy barrier along this pathway is observed for the transition <bold><italic>A<sub>3</sub>→A<sub>4</sub></italic></bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 B</xref>) and is larger than 4.0 <italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic> (≈2.5 <italic>kcal/mol</italic>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>Analysis of the FEL of ATP-bound DnaK.</title>
<p>A: FES generated from dPCA of MD run ATP1. Minima and saddle points are shown with gray (green for the most probable one) and red diamonds, respectively. The PME is represented by the red line. B: Free-energy <italic>V<sup>PME</sup></italic> along the PME for the transition <bold><italic>A<sub>1</sub>→A<sub>2</sub>→A<sub>3</sub>→A<sub>4</sub>→A<sub>5</sub></italic></bold>. C: <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Results</xref> of the clustering along the PME. Each frame is represented at the corresponding time <italic>t</italic> observed in the MD trajectory.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>From the FES (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 A</xref>), we extracted the coordinates of the bin (<italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic>; <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup></italic>) of each step <italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic> along the PME. Each step <italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic> of the PME, which is a bin of the FES (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section), represents a number <italic>N(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic> of frames of the corresponding MD trajectory. For example, the step <italic>s<sub>1</sub></italic> corresponds to the bin (<italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> = −1.53; <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.64) and to <italic>N(s<sub>1</sub>)</italic> = 87 frames of the MD run ATP1. From the <italic>N(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic> frames, we computed the 1-D FEPs <italic>V<sub>j</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> of the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> used in the dPCA, and we defined the value <italic>γ<sub>i</sub>(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic> as the minimum of the FEP <italic>V<sub>j</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> (the most probable value of the CGDAs <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> at each step <italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic>). Finally, for each of the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic>, we projected the trajectory <italic>γ<sub>i</sub>(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic> along the PME and along its corresponding one-dimensional FEP <italic>V(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> (shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s008">Fig. S6</xref>) to visualize the coupling between the local and the global collective motions described by <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup></italic> (as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>). The CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> with the largest changes along the PME are the CGDAs having multiple-minima FEPs (except for <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>), corresponding also to those having a significant influence (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e010">Eq. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s010">Fig. S8</xref>) in the <italic>dPC</italic> modes [<italic>Δ<sub>i</sub><sup>1</sup></italic> (mode 1) and <italic>Δ<sub>i</sub><sup>2</sup></italic> (mode 2)&gt;10%], i.e. <italic>γ<sub>77</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>213</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>407</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>464</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>519</sub></italic>. In addition, others CGDAs <italic>γ</italic><sub>i</sub> show smaller changes along the PME, for example <italic>γ<sub>250</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>432</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>444</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>465</sub></italic> or <italic>γ<sub>492</sub></italic>. In total, these 13 <italic>γ</italic><sub>i</sub> CGDAs correspond to 49 residues.</p>
<p>At <italic>s<sub>0</sub></italic>, corresponding to the minimum <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic> on the FES (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g008">Fig. 8</xref>), the structure is still elongated and without interactions between the NBD and the SBD and is closely similar to the initial structure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>). From <italic>s<sub>0</sub></italic> to <italic>s<sub>9</sub></italic> (corresponding to the saddle point of the transition <italic>A<sub>1</sub>→A<sub>2</sub></italic>), we observed the rotation of the SBD around the linker (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>), due to the relaxation of <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>465</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>492</sub></italic> towards the minimum of their FEPs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>), involving a reorganization of subdomains IB of the NBD and of the SBD-β (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>). The system goes through this saddle point from <italic>s<sub>9</sub></italic> to <italic>s<sub>14</sub></italic> as a consequence of jumps of <italic>γ<sub>213</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>432</sub></italic> to local minima of their FEPs and last but not least <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic> jumps to its most probable conformation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>). These changes involve a large rotation of the SBD of ATP-DnaK around the linker, which becomes close to the NBD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>) at <italic>s<sub>14</sub></italic>, corresponding to the minimum <italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic>. The rotation of the SBD is thus related to the relaxation of dihedral angles <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>465</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>492</sub></italic> involving a reorganization of subdomains IB of the NBD and of the SBD-β (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>). The angle <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic> is located within the NBD and coupled to the 27 other dihedral angles, in particular to <italic>γ<sub>12</sub></italic> built on the residues T11, T12, N13 which are in contact with ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g004">Fig. 4</xref>) providing a physical link between the SBD rotation and the ATP/NBD interactions. For the transition <italic>A<sub>2</sub>→A<sub>3</sub></italic> (from <italic>s<sub>14</sub></italic> to <italic>s<sub>36</sub></italic>), <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>444</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>519</sub></italic> change their conformation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>), allowing the system to go through the saddle point at <italic>s<sub>18</sub></italic>, which involves a rotation of the subdomain SBD-α of ATP-DnaK, which becomes close to subdomain IB of the NBD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>). Then, the system relaxed to a state where the SBD is finally docked to the lobe I of the NBD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>) at <italic>s<sub>36</sub></italic> with changes of <italic>γ<sub>77</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>213</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>250</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>432</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>), and adopted its most stable structure in the MD trajectory ATP1, corresponding to the global minimum <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic> of the FES (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g008">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
<p>In the MD trajectory ATP1 (on the contrary to trajectory ATP2, data not shown), the system did not end in its most stable state (<italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic>) but escaped from this minimum because of changes of <italic>γ<sub>213</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>464</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>465</sub></italic> which jumps to local metastable states of their FEPs, which allows the system to climb the highest energy barrier (4 <italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic>) along the PME at <italic>s<sub>54</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 B</xref>). The system goes through this saddle point of the transition <italic>A<sub>3</sub>→A<sub>4</sub></italic> at <italic>s<sub>54</sub></italic> with changes of <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>407</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>) which jump to local minima of their FEPs and the system relaxed to the minimum <italic>A<sub>4</sub></italic>. The structure corresponding to the minimum <italic>A<sub>4</sub></italic> is still characterized by a docking of the two domains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>) but with local changes in the SBD, particularly in the SBD-β. Finally, the last transition which occurred is the transition <italic>A<sub>4</sub>→A<sub>5</sub></italic>, with a saddle point at <italic>s<sub>68</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 B</xref>). The system goes through the saddle point by a change of <italic>γ<sub>407</sub></italic> coupled with a change of <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic> up to the second most probable state along the PME, namely <italic>A<sub>5</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s009">Fig. S7</xref>). The structure in <italic>A<sub>5</sub></italic> is characterized by the docking of the SBD on the NBD but with structural changes within the SBD and particularly within the SBD-β compared with the representative structure of the minimum <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s011">Fig. S9</xref>). Combination of the global (<italic>dPC</italic>) and local (<italic>γ</italic>) coordinates allow us to decipher the mechanistic process by which the protein undergoes a conformational change upon ATP binding along the PME.</p>
<p>Another point to figure out is the relation between the PME on the two-dimensional FES and the MD trajectory or in other terms, the relation between the step <italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic> of the PME and the time <italic>t</italic> of the different events observed in the MD trajectory. As explained in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section, each step <italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic> of the PME is characterized by a number of frames <italic>N(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic> of the MD trajectory. So we extracted and plotted the time <italic>t</italic> for each frame <italic>i</italic>, <italic>i</italic> = 1 to <italic>N(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 C</xref>). Starting from the minimum <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic>, the MD trajectory reaches the docked state, which corresponds to the minimum <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic> after 150 ns. The basin corresponding to this minimum is explored during the major time period of the MD trajectory (up to 400 ns). The “X” shaped of the graph during this period (between 150 and 400 ns) shows us that it exists different attempts to escape this minimum <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic> (there are in fact three entrances/exits into/from this state) but this only happens when all the conditions given previously in the text about local conformational changes are reached (at <italic>t</italic> = 400 ns). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9 A</xref>, it is due to the existence of the highest barrier between the minima <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic> and <italic>A<sub>4</sub></italic>. Finally, the system reaches the minimum <italic>A<sub>5</sub></italic> at <italic>t</italic> = 500 ns and stay in the corresponding basin up to the end of the trajectory.</p>
</sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The analysis of the FEPs, as shown in the previous section, revealed the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK influenced by the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>). The 91 residues associated to these 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>) are involved in the long-range (on about 5–10 nm) propagation of the conformational fluctuations between the NBD and the SBD of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK. Starting from <italic>γ<sub>12</sub></italic> in the NBD, which corresponds to residues in direct contacts with the ATP nucleotide, the signal induced by the nucleotide binding is propagated up to <italic>γ<sub>524</sub></italic>, in the SBD, through <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic>, located in the inter-domain linker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Experimentally, X-ray crystallography, NMR spectroscopy, biophysical and biochemical techniques have contributed to understand such an allosteric communication in Hsp70 s (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>). A large comparison between the residues elucidated from the analysis of the FEPs similarity computed from the MD simulations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>) and the experimental database of key residues relevant for the communication in DnaK available in the literature, shows that most of the residues identified by our methodology have been found to be experimentally relevant for the allosteric communication in Hsp70 s and that new residues can be proposed to play a role according to the present MD calculations.</p>
<p>In more detail, the comparison in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref> can be summarized as follows. In the NBD, mutation of residue T13 in bovine Hsc70 (T11 in <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK) to S13 completely abrogated the communication between the NBD and the SBD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Sousa1">[95]</xref>. Residue T13 was indeed found from the analysis of the FEP of <italic>γ<sub>12</sub></italic>, which belongs to the nucleotide-binding pocket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Mutation in bHsc70 of residue K71 (K70 in <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK), which is the only residue of subdomain IB in contact with the ATP molecule, affects the ATP hydrolysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-OBrien1">[96]</xref> and also abrogated the ATP-induced conformational changes determined by SAXS experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Johnson1">[89]</xref>. In the network extracted from our analysis, several CGDAs <italic>γ</italic>, having a significant role for signal propagation, belong to subdomain IB of the NBD and particularly <italic>γ<sub>65</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>77</sub></italic>, which enclosed residue K70 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). In addition, fluorescence of W102, the only tryptophan residue of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Buchberger1">[97]</xref> is directly dependent on the ADP/ATP conformational changes in the NBD and was identified from the analysis of the FEP of <italic>γ<sub>102</sub></italic> in the present MD simulations. In the NBD, the interface between the subdomains IA and IIA plays a key role in Hsp70, acting as a cleft for the binding of the interdomain linker <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Swain2">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Liu1">[86]</xref> in the ATP-bound state (open structural state) of Hsp70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Swain2">[65]</xref>. The analysis of the FEPs of DnaK reveals the important role of CGDA <italic>γ<sub>213</sub></italic>, which is precisely localized in subdomain IIA, and of the CGDA <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic>, which is part of the linker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>).</p>
<p>The linker is the physical link between the NBD and the SBD and was identified early as a key region for the allosteric communication in Hsp70 s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Vogel1">[64]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Swain2">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kumar2">[67]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Rist1">[98]</xref>. The linker is flexible and solvent exposed in the nucleotide-free and in the ADP-bound DnaK and is docked in the IA/IIA cleft of the NBD in the ATP-bound state. In the present MD simulations, the CGDA <italic>γ<sub>387</sub></italic> belonging to the linker occurs in a specific conformation in ATP-DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g006">Fig. 6</xref>), confirming that ATP binding lead to a conformational change in the linker region (even if the SBD stays closed in the present ATP-bound DnaK trajectories).</p>
<p>Finally, the dynamics of the subdomain IIB of the NBD, and particularly its rotation, is known to be allosterically relevant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bhattacharya1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Liu2">[99]</xref>. The rotation of the subdomain IIB occurs upon nucleotide exchange from ADP to ATP and the binding of ATP involves the opening of the nucleotide-binding cleft relative to an ADP-bound NBD. These findings are confirmed by our analysis of the FEPs which revealed that <italic>γ<sub>249</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>250</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>253</sub></italic> are influenced by the nucleotide; these CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> are localized in the loop between two α-helices of the subdomain IIB of the NBD for which large changes in the NMR chemical-shifts between the ADP-bound and the ATP-bound NBD of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK were observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1">[12]</xref></p>
<p>Most of the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> located in the SBD of DnaK influenced by the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD are located in the SBD-β subdomain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). These CGDAs are related to residues previously identified experimentally. Indeed, <italic>γ<sub>408</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>432</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>444</sub></italic> involve residues M408, D431 and E444 which modify the substrate binding and affinity to <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Burkholder1">[100]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Swain3">[101]</xref>. In addition, residue I462, belonging to <italic>γ<sub>463</sub></italic>, has been shown to be allosterically relevant due to the fact that the dual DnaJ and peptide-binding defects were observed in I462T <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Davis1">[102]</xref>. In addition, amide hydrogen exchange experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Rist1">[98]</xref> revealed that the binding of ATP in the NBD of Hsp70 involves local structural changes in the segments 413–437 (which encloses the CGDA <italic>γ<sub>432</sub></italic> found in the analysis of the FEPs) and 439–457 (which encloses the CGDA <italic>γ<sub>448</sub></italic> found in the analysis of the FEPs) of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>).</p>
<p>Other CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> revealed by our analysis (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>) such as <italic>γ<sub>98</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>339</sub></italic>, located in the NBD, <italic>γ<sub>490</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>492</sub></italic>, located in the SBD-β, or <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>508</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>524</sub></italic> located in the SBD-α provide new hypothesis for the residues relevant for the allosteric communication in Hsp70. Interestingly, the residue N98 contacts G506 in the crystal form of ATP-bound DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>. The mutation V337F, a residue preceding the residues defining <italic>γ<sub>339</sub></italic> strongly reduces the capacity of DnaK to refold luciferase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Aponte1">[103]</xref>. Finally, <italic>γ<sub>524</sub></italic> includes the residue D526 forming a highly conserved ionic pair with R445 which stabilizes the SBD-α/SBD-β interactions through an ionic network including also K446 (precedes <italic>γ<sub>448</sub></italic>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>), D518 (belonging to <italic>γ<sub>519</sub></italic>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>) and D450 (belonging to <italic>γ<sub>448</sub></italic>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-FernndezSiz1">[104]</xref>. Two GCDAs <italic>γ</italic> are located at the interface between the SBD-β and the SBD-α, namely <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>508</sub></italic> and one is located in the kink between the helices A and B of the SBD-α, namely <italic>γ<sub>524</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). This demonstrates that even if the SBD remains closed in ATP*-DnaK, local conformational changes within the SBD were observed in MD.</p>
<p>The conformational changes of the SBD induced by ATP binding in MD can be related to recent experimental data. Indeed, EPR spectroscopy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schlecht1">[81]</xref> has been recently used to investigate the conformations of the SBD-α relative to those of the SBD-β of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK. Distance distributions between the residues E430 and R547 of the nucleotide-free DnaK and of ATP-bound DnaK were extracted from the EPR spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10</xref>). The E430/R547 distance distribution measured in nucleotide-free DnaK shows two interacting spin populations, one around 12 Å and one with a broader population between 16 Å and 20 Å (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 A</xref>, black arrows). Only a small fraction of the labeled residues was not interacting (fraction of non-interacting spins, <italic>f<sub>NI</sub></italic> = 0.09), corresponding to residues distant by more than 20 Å. Upon ATP binding, the short-distance population disappeared and almost 80% of the spin labeled residues was separated by more than 20 Å, whereas in 20% of the molecules, the distance was in a range similar to the nucleotide-free state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 C and D</xref>, black arrows).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003379-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>Comparison between MD data and EPR experiments.</title>
<p>Histograms of the distance E430-R547 computed from the MD simulations in the APO state (panels A and C, red) and in the ATP-bound state (panels B and D, green). Panels A and B represent the distributions up to 20 Å, as in the EPR experiments and panels C and D represents the same distributions up to 40 Å. Each subpopulation in the distance distribution was fitted with a Gaussian function shown with black lines. The black arrows in panels A and B represent the experimental results from Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schlecht1">[81]</xref>. FEP <italic>V(γ<sub>504</sub>)</italic> computed from different subpopulations relative to the distance E430/R547 distribution function in the APO state (panel E) and in the ATP state (panel F). <italic>&lt;d&gt;</italic> represents the mean value of the Gaussian distributions shown in panel C for the APO-DnaK and D for the ATP-DnaK.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To compare with EPR data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schlecht1">[81]</xref>, we computed the probability distribution of the distance between the centers of mass of the side chains of E430 and R547 from the MD trajectories of APO-DnaK and ATP-DnaK. Up to 20 Å, the distance distribution of nucleotide-free DnaK shows two populations; a broad distribution centered at 14.6 Å and a narrower distribution centered at 18.7 Å (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 A</xref>). Note that the MD simulations provide information on the E430/R547 distance distribution for distances inaccessible to EPR (&gt;20 Å): in the case of the nucleotide-free DnaK, a third population is observed and is characterized by a broad distribution centered at 24.7 Å (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 C</xref>). The fraction of distances larger than 20 Å in MD of the nucleotide-free DnaK (<italic>f<sub>NI</sub></italic>) is about 45%. Upon ATP binding, the population of the shortest distance observed in the nucleotide-free DnaK (centered at 14 Å) disappears (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 B</xref>), as observed in EPR experiments, and the distance distribution shows two peaks centered at 20.5 Å and 23.1 Å, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 D</xref>). Consequently, the fraction of distances larger than 20 Å increases up to 73%, as observed in EPR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 C and D</xref>). These MD results show that the addition of ATP increases the distances between the SBD-β and the SBD-α even if the SBD remains closed. In addition, the MD simulations provide a possible structural origin for the disappearance of the population of molecules with the shortest E430/R547 distance upon ATP-binding in the experiment. Indeed, we performed a clustering of the <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK structures within each subpopulation of the distance distributions shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 B and D</xref> and computed the FEPs of each of the CGDA <italic>γ</italic> selected previously and which belong to the SBD (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>). From these calculations, we found that <italic>only</italic> the FEP of <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic> was different in each subpopulation of molecules having a different E430/R547 distance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 E and F</xref>). In the APO state, the structures belonging to the shortest distance population have a most probable value of <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic> equal to 71.5° whereas it is 55.5° for the structures in the 2 largest subpopulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 E</xref>). In the ATP state, <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic> moves more freely compared with the APO state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g010">Fig. 10 F</xref>), meaning that the lid is more mobile in this nucleotide-binding state compared with the nucleotide-free state, which could explain that the shortest distance population distribution observed for the nucleotide-free DnaK disappears for the ATP-bound DnaK.</p>
<p>A statistical analysis of 926 Hsp70 sequences pointed to interdomain sectors that might mediate the allosteric communication between the NBD and the SBD of Hsp70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>. Although it is unclear that the allosteric mechanism and residues can be extracted from the sole comparison of sequences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Livesay1">[60]</xref>, we found that these sectors correspond to key CGDAs found from the present analysis of the FEL of DnaK. The sectors comprise the residues 11, 12 and 14 (<italic>γ<sub>12</sub></italic>); residues 192 and 195 (<italic>γ<sub>193</sub></italic>); residue 406 (<italic>γ<sub>407</sub></italic>); residues 431 and 433 (<italic>γ<sub>432</sub></italic>); residues 443 to 445 (<italic>γ<sub>444</sub></italic>); residue 450 (<italic>γ<sub>448</sub></italic>); residues 462, 463, 464, 466 and 467 (<italic>γ<sub>463</sub></italic>, <italic>γ<sub>464</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>465</sub></italic>); residue 494 (<italic>γ<sub>494</sub></italic>) and finally residue 519 (<italic>γ<sub>519</sub></italic>) (where the CGDAs in the brackets are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t003">Table 3</xref>). In total, 19 residues (involved in 10 CGDAs) out of 91 residues (involved in 27 CGDAs) revealed by the present MD simulations were also found by a statistical analysis of Hsp70 sequences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Smock1">[91]</xref>. Due to the importance and relevance of hHsp70 in diseases, it is instructive to examine to which extent the residues identified in the allosteric mechanism of DnaK by MD are conserved in hHsp70. In order to answer this question, we performed the alignment of the sequence of <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 (Uniprot ID: P0A6Y8) on the sequence of the human inducible Hsp70 (Uniprot ID: P08107) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s014">Table S1</xref>). On the 91 residues of <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 found to be relevant in the nucleotide-induced conformational change, 59/91 [65%] are positives [with similar physical and chemical properties] among which 44/91 [48%] are identical, i.e. conserved in the human form. Only 2/91 are gaps [2%]. In addition, at least one residue of each CGDA found to be dependent on the nucleotide-binding state of the NBD of DnaK is common between human and the <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 s. However, one emphasizes that the conservation of the residues involved in the conformational changes of DnaK do not necessarily guarantee that the allosteric mechanisms of DnaK and hHsp70 are similar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Livesay1">[60]</xref>.</p>
<p>Residues involved in the dynamics of the conformational change of DnaK are also largely conserved in hHsp70. In DnaK, 49 residues are involved in the collective modes 1 and 2 computed from the dPCA of the MD trajectories as identified by their influence (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e010">Eq. 5</xref>) <italic>Δ<sub>i</sub><sup>1</sup></italic> (mode 1) and <italic>Δ<sub>i</sub><sup>2</sup></italic> (mode 2) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s010">Fig. S8</xref>) and by their dynamics along the PME (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9</xref>). To identify these residues in hHsp70, we aligned the sequences of DnaK and hHsp70 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s014">Table S1</xref>) and reported the results of the alignment in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t004">Table 4</xref>. On 49 residues identified in this manner, 2 are gaps and 33 are positives (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t004">Table 4</xref>). As stated in the introduction, the low-frequency vibrational modes of proteins are generally correlated with the reaction coordinates of their conformational changes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola3">[49]</xref>. Based on all-atom normal modes of hHsp70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola3">[49]</xref>, we identified 64 residues having the largest influences in the low-frequency vibrational modes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4">[92]</xref> of hHsp70 which are compared to those deduced from dPCA in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t004">Table 4</xref>. Comparison between the NMA and dPCA shows that 12 residues are identical in both methods, namely F78, K100, K250, K251, G408, V409, A467, P468, R469, K493, S494 and T495 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003379-t004">Table 4</xref>). The most important differences between the two approaches were observed in the subdomain IIA of the NBD, in the linker and in the SBD-α where we did not find residues common to the two analyses. The differences observed are expected because NMA describes the structural fluctuations of the protein in the vicinity of the minimum of the free-energy basin characterizing its native state (harmonic approximation) whereas the dPCA analysis include jumps between minima of the protein FEL.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1003379-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>List of residues found to be relevant for conformational dynamics of <italic>human</italic> Hsp70 deduced from NMA of human Hsp70 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola3">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4">[92]</xref> and from dPCA of <italic>E. coli</italic> MD trajectories (present work) after sequence alignment of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK on human Hsp70 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s014">Table S1</xref>).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003379-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NMA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dPCA</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NBD IA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NBD IB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L50- <bold>F78</bold>-<bold><italic>K100</italic></bold>-<italic>Y107</italic>-K108-E110-<italic>K112</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K77-<bold>F78</bold>-<italic>G79</italic>-D80-D99-<bold><italic>K100</italic></bold>-<italic>P101-K102</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NBD IIA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G215-<italic>I216</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NBD IIB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R247-<italic>H249</italic>-<bold><italic>K250</italic></bold><bold>-</bold><bold><italic>K251</italic></bold>-<italic>S254</italic>-<italic>Q255</italic>-R299</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>K250</italic></bold>-<bold><italic>K251</italic></bold>-D252-I253</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">linker</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V388-Q389-D390-L391</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-β</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>G408-V409</bold>-T429-<italic>Y431</italic>-<italic>S432</italic>-<italic>Q441</italic>-<italic>S462</italic>-I464-<bold>A467</bold>-<bold>P468</bold>-<bold>R469</bold>-G470-V471-P472-Q473-D492-<bold>K493</bold>-<bold>S494</bold>-<bold>T495</bold>-K497-<italic>A498</italic>-N499-K500</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>G408</bold>-<bold>V409</bold>-M410-T411-D433-N434-Q435-<italic>P436</italic>-G445-E446-R447-<italic>A448</italic>-<italic>P465</italic>-P466-<bold>A467</bold>-<bold>A468</bold>-<bold>R469</bold>-<bold>K493-S494-T495</bold>-G496</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBD-α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Y525</italic>-<italic>K526</italic>-<italic>Q532-R533</italic>-<italic>R535-Y545-K559</italic>-K561-<italic>S563-E564-A565</italic>-D566-K567-<italic>K568-K569-K573</italic>-<italic>W580</italic>-E588-K589-<italic>D590</italic>-<italic>E591-F592-H594-R596</italic>- K597-Q601</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N505-D506-K507</italic>-G508-E521-A522-E523-<italic>K524</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Residues common to the two analyses are in bold. Residues of hHsp70 which are not identical in <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 are in italic font.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s3a">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In summary, all-atom MD simulations of Hsp70-DnaK in different nucleotide-binding states in explicit solvent were performed. We observed the docking of the SBD of DnaK onto the lobe I of its NBD upon ATP-binding: the structure found is an intermediate plausible ATP-bound state, named ATP*, which is compared to several experimental data. A strategy was presented in which the FEL computed from unbiased MD simulations is represented by FEPs of CGDAs of the main chain along the amino-acid sequence of the protein. The FEPs can be quantitatively compared in different nucleotide-binding states by using a similarity index. The analysis of the FEPs allowed us to identify a small network of 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic>. The coupling between these 27 CGDAs was deciphered by using dihedral principal component analysis. The conformational change induced by ATP binding was represented by a pathway of minimum energy on the FES built from the two lowest dihedral principal components of the ATP-bound DnaK trajectories. The 27 coordinates correspond to 91 residues which are involved in the interdomain communication upon nucleotide binding to DnaK. Most of these 91 residues revealed by MD were shown experimentally to be relevant for the communication between the NBD and the SBD in the Hsp70 chaperone cycle. The present work also suggests 26 new key residues that could be tested experimentally. For example, the residues A503 to G506, defining <italic>γ<sub>504</sub></italic>, belonging to the kink between SBD-α and SBD-β, seem to play a key role in the dynamics of the docking as well as for the intrinsic dynamic of the SBD. We found that the conformation of these residues influences the distribution of the distance E430/R547 explaining the structural origin of the variations of this distance observed in EPR upon ATP binding to <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schlecht1">[81]</xref>. The strategy developed to analyze the long-range effect of ATP binding on the structure and dynamics of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK is general and could be applied to decipher allosteric communication in other proteins.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>MD simulations</title>
<p>All unbiased all-atom MD simulations in explicit water of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK using the NMR-derived structure (PDB ID: 2KHO in which the missing atoms of ARG and TYR were added) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> were carried out with the GROMACS software package <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-VanderSpoel1">[105]</xref> and the GROMOS96 ffG43a1 force field <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Gunsteren1">[106]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Scott1">[107]</xref>. The time step used in all simulations was 0.001 ps and the list of neighbors was updated every 0.005 ps with the ‘grid’ method and a cut-off radius of 1 nm. The coordinates of all the atoms in the simulation box were saved every 2 ps. The initial velocities were chosen randomly. We used the NPT ensemble with a cubic box. The temperature and pressure were kept to the desired value by using the Berendsen method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Berendsen1">[108]</xref> and an isotropic coupling for the pressure (<italic>T</italic> = 300 K, <italic>τ<sub>T</sub></italic> = 0.1 ps; P0 = 1 bar, coupling time <italic>τ<sub>P</sub></italic> = 0.5 ps). The electrostatic term was computed by using the particle mesh Ewald algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Darden1">[109]</xref> (with a radius of 1 nm) with the Fast Fourier Transform optimization (on 140 points for DnaK, with an order equal to 4 for the interpolation). The “cut off” algorithm was applied for the non-coulomb potentials with a radius of 1 nm. The system was warmed up for 40 ps and equilibrated for 600 ps with lower restraints, finishing with no restraints at 300 K. We performed 6 MD runs, 2 in each nucleotide-binding state (APO1, APO2, ADP1, ADP2 and ATP1, ATP2), as described in the following subsections. The stability of the protein structure in each MD trajectory was monitored by computing the Root-Mean-Square-Deviation (<italic>RMSD</italic>) between the molecular structure every 2 ps and the initial structure (as done before <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s012">Fig. S10 A</xref>). To reduce the computational cost, the APO and ADP-bound DnaK MD runs were stopped when the <italic>RMSD</italic> was converged to a constant value with a standard deviation lower than 0.5 Å (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s012">Fig. S10 B</xref>) during at least 50 ns, resulting in six MD runs of different durations. The 2 MD runs of ATP-DnaK were continued after convergence of the <italic>RMSD</italic> up to 0.5 µs in order to explore a possible opening of the SBD which did not occur however on that time-scale.</p>
<sec id="s4a1">
<title>MD runs of APO-Hsp70</title>
<p>The initial structure of the nucleotide-free DnaK (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> was solvated in a cubic box with 136508 SPC water molecules keeping a minimum distance of 0.9 nm between the solute and each face of the box. We used periodic boundary conditions with an initial value of the box side of 16.112 nm. The charge of the system was neutralized by adding 25 Na<sup>+</sup> counter-ions. The energy of the system was first optimized with the “steepest descent minimization” algorithm and then by using a “conjugate gradient” algorithm. We performed two runs with different initial conditions. The total simulation time was 151 ns for the MD run APO1 and 360 ns for the MD run APO2.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4a2">
<title>MD runs of ADP-Hsp70</title>
<p>The topology files of the ADP and ATP molecules were constructed with the PRODRG program (version 2.5 BETA) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Schttelkopf1">[110]</xref>. We added one ADP molecule and one divalent ion (Ca<sup>2+</sup>) to the nucleotide-free DnaK (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref>. The initial coordinates of the ADP molecule were extracted from those of the ADP molecule in the X-ray structure of the isolated NBD of ADP-bound hHsp70 (PDB ID: 1HJO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Osipiuk1">[111]</xref>) after alignment of the backbone atoms of the residues 5 to 377 of the hHsp70 NBD on those of the DnaK NBD (PDB ID: 2KHO) by using the VMD software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Humphrey1">[112]</xref>. The protein was solvated with 136488 SPC water molecules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Berendsen2">[113]</xref> in a cubic box of the same dimensions as in the MD runs APO (see above), and 26 Na<sup>+</sup> counterions were added to neutralize the system. The ADP-bound DnaK initial structures were relaxed during 600 ps with the protein structure restrained to the experimental structure (PDB ID: 2KHO) and with no constraints on the solvent and on the ligands (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s001">Dataset S1</xref> in supporting information). We performed two MD runs ADP1 and ADP2 with different initial conditions. The total simulation time was 164 ns for the MD run ADP1 and 151 ns for the MD run ADP2.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4a3">
<title>MD runs of ATP-Hsp70</title>
<p>The ATP-Hsp70 structure was built using the NMR-derived structure of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK (PDB ID: 2KHO) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref> with ADP and one divalent ion inserted as described above. The initial coordinates of the ATP molecule was built by adding a phosphate group to the ADP molecule in the free-space available within the NBD of the ADP-bound DnaK structure. The precise initial location of the third phosphate group was not crucial because the ATP-bound DnaK structure was relaxed during 600 ps with the protein structure restrained to the experimental structure (PDB ID: 2KHO) and with no constraints on the solvent and on the ligands (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s002">Dataset S2</xref> in supporting information). We compared the ATP-bound construct relaxed after 600 ps with available X-ray structures of isolated NBD of hHsp70 bound to ADP and PO<sub>4</sub> (PDB IDs: 1S3X <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Sriram1">[114]</xref>, 3AY9 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Arakawa1">[115]</xref>, 3JXU <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Wisniewska1">[116]</xref>). The relaxation of the ATP molecule using the present force-field displaced the added phosphate group to a position close to the experimental position of the PO<sub>4</sub> group in the isolated NBD of hHsp70. Comparison with the new published X-ray full-length ATP-bound <italic>open</italic> structure (PDB ID: 4B9Q) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1">[69]</xref>, confirmed that the initial relaxed position of the ATP molecule (which mimic the ATP binding position in the full-length <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 in a <italic>closed</italic> state) is realistic. The protein was solvated with 136485 SPC water molecules <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Berendsen2">[113]</xref> in a cubic box of the same dimensions as in the MD runs APO and ADP (see above), and 27 Na<sup>+</sup> counterions were added to neutralize the system. We performed two MD runs ATP1 and ATP2 with different initial conditions. The total simulation time was 553 ns for the MD run ATP1 and 560 ns for the MD run ATP2. The MD runs confirmed that the very precise initial locations of the nucleotides are not so crucial. The X-ray structures provide indeed only a static picture of the binding mode of ADP and ATP. The NBD is dynamics and the nucleotides are fluctuating within the NBD pocket. In the ATP-bound Hsp70 MD simulations, we found that the terminal phosphate groups of ATP and ADP are fluctuating relative to the nucleic base with a <italic>RMSD</italic> varying between 2 Å and 9 Å for ATP and between 2 Å and 6 Å for ADP. The position of the nucleotide fluctuates relative to the NBD (which is itself dynamics) with a <italic>RMSD</italic> varying between 3 Å and 4 Å both for ADP and ATP MD trajectories.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Definition of the coarse-grained dihedral angles (CGDAs) <italic>γ</italic> and of their free-energy profiles (FEPs)</title>
<p>The conformational fluctuations of the main chain of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK were monitored by recording the fluctuations of the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Senet1">[71]</xref>. The CGDA <italic>γ</italic> for a residue <italic>i</italic> is the dihedral angle formed by the vectors (virtual bonds) joining 4 successive C<sup>α</sup> atoms (<italic>i−1, i, i+1 and i+2</italic>) along the amino-acid sequence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s003">Fig. S1 A</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nishikawa1">[117]</xref>. The first dihedral angle along the sequence is <italic>γ<sub>2</sub></italic> and the last is <italic>γ<sub>N-2</sub></italic>, where <italic>N</italic> is the total number of residues. Each CGDA <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> is a local probe of the FEL along the amino-acid sequence of the protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Senet1">[71]</xref>.</p>
<p>The FEP of each <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> is computed from the usual Boltzmann formula:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003379.e001"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <italic>k<sub>B</sub></italic> is the Boltzmann constant, <italic>T</italic> the temperature (300 K) and <italic>p(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> is the probability distribution function (PDF) of the CGDA <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> computed from the MD trajectory (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s003">Fig. S1 B</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Senet1">[71]</xref>. Note that the experimental NMR structure of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK is comprised of 600 residues, starting from residue 4 to residue 603 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1">[70]</xref>, and is described by 597 angles <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic>, from index <italic>i</italic> = 5 to index <italic>i</italic> = 601.</p>
<p>To quantify the convergence between two FEPs of a same CGDA <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> in two MD trajectories with the same nucleotide-binding state but with different initial conditions, we computed the similarity index <italic>H</italic> between their associated PDFs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cote1">[72]</xref>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003379.e002"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>where <italic>p<sub>1</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> and <italic>p<sub>2</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> are two PDFs of the same CGDA <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> computed from two MD trajectories 1 and 2.</p>
<p>The similarity index <italic>H</italic> varies between 0 (dissimilar) and 1 (identical). Two FEPs, <italic>v<sub>1</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> from the MD trajectory 1 and <italic>v<sub>2</sub>(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic> from the MD trajectory 2, are considered similar (“converged”) if the index <italic>H</italic> is larger than 0.5.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Contact map (CM) and contact map difference (CMD)</title>
<p>Distances between all pairs of atoms of the 600 residues were calculated every 2 ps for each MD run (APO1, APO2, ADP1, ADP2, ATP1 and ATP2). The distance matrix between the residues was built by retaining only the smallest atomic distance between the atoms of each residue pair. If this smallest distance was smaller than 4 Å, the residues were said in contact (contact matrix element is 1) and not in contact otherwise (contact matrix element is 0). For each nucleotide-binding state (APO, ADP and ATP), only contacts with at least 50% of occupancy in the two MD runs of <italic>E. coli</italic> DnaK in the same nucleotide-binding state (for example ATP-bound DnaK) and for which the average distance was similar in the two MD runs (for example MD runs ATP1 and ATP2) within 0.5 Å were finally considered, defining the contact map (CM, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s004">Fig. S2 A and B</xref>) of a nucleotide-binding state (for example ATP). In addition, the difference between the contact maps, the contact map difference (CMD, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s004">Fig. S2 C</xref>) was computed. For example, the CMD ATP/ADP is the difference between the contact matrices ATP and ADP defined above, and thus reveals the atomic contacts present in the ATP nucleotide-binding state of DnaK, but not in its ADP nucleotide-binding state.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Dihedral Principal Component Analysis (dPCA)</title>
<p>In dPCA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Altis1">[74]</xref>, the correlated internal motions of a protein are quantified by a covariance matrix <italic>C<sub>ij</sub></italic> [<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e003">Eq. (3)</xref>] of the Cartesian components of the two-dimensional vectors <bold><italic>u</italic></bold><italic>(t)</italic> [<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e004">Eq. (4)</xref>] representing the CGDAs:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003379.e003"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.e003" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where &lt;…&gt; denotes the average over all sampled conformations and<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003379.e004"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.e004" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>
    
    The diagonalization of the covariance matrix <italic>C<sub>ij</sub></italic> gives 2<italic>N</italic> ( = number of CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> eigenvalues <italic>λ<sup>k</sup></italic>, ordered by decreasing value: <italic>λ<sup>1</sup></italic>&gt;<italic>λ<sup>2</sup></italic>&gt;…&gt;<italic>λ<sup>2</sup></italic> and eigenvectors <bold><italic>e</italic></bold><italic><sup>k = </sup>{</italic><bold><italic>e<sub>1</sub></italic></bold><italic><sup>k</sup>,</italic><bold><italic>e<sub>2</sub></italic></bold><italic><sup>k</sup>,…,</italic><bold><italic>e<sub>27</sub></italic></bold><italic><sup>k</sup>}<sup>T</sup></italic>, with <bold><italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic></bold><italic><sup>k</sup> = {e<sub>i</sub><sup>k</sup>(X);e<sub>i</sub><sup>k</sup>(<italic>Y</italic>}</italic> where <italic>e<sub>i</sub><sup>k</sup>(X)</italic> is the Cartesian component <italic>x</italic> of the projection of the eigenvector <bold><italic>e</italic></bold><italic><sup>k</sup></italic> on the <italic>i<sup>th</sup></italic> CGDA (similarly for <italic>e<sub>i</sub><sup>k</sup>(Y)</italic>).</p>
    
    
<p>The contribution of each CGDA <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> to a mode <italic>k</italic> is the so-called influence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Altis1">[74]</xref>:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003379.e010"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.e010" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>The mean-square fluctuation (<italic>MSF<sub>i</sub></italic>) of each vector <bold><italic>u</italic></bold><italic><sub>i</sub></italic> can be decomposed into collective modes:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003379.e011"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.e011" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>The eigenmodes with the largest eigenvalues <italic>λ<sup>k</sup></italic> (named slow modes) correspond to the collective modes contributing the most to the <italic>MSF</italic> of the protein [see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e011">Eq. (6)</xref>]. Therefore, <italic>λ<sup>1</sup></italic> is the eigenvalue of the collective mode which contributes the most to the structural fluctuations of the CGDAs <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> in an MD run <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cote1">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Altis1">[74]</xref>. Finally, the projection of the MD trajectory on the <italic>k</italic><sup>th</sup> eigenvector <bold>e</bold><sup>k</sup> is named the dihedral principal component <italic>dPC<sup>k</sup></italic>,<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003379.e012"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.e012" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>More details can be found in Refs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Cote1">[72]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Altis1">[74]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Maisuradze1">[118]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Maisuradze2">[119]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4e">
<title>Free-energy surface (FES) from dPCA</title>
<p>The effective two-dimensional FES shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g008">Fig. 8</xref> was computed from the two-dimensional probability density of <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup></italic> computed from the covariance matrix of the <italic>subset</italic> of the 27 dihedral angles involved in the conformational change of DnaK (all shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). The two-dimensional FES computed from the covariance matrix of <italic>all</italic> dihedral angles is indeed irrelevant due to a lack of convergence sampling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hess2">[94]</xref>. Indeed, some dihedral angles are in a diffusive regime. As shown in Refs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hess1">[93]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hess2">[94]</xref>, the diffusive regime of the internal degrees of freedom of a protein can be measured by the cosine content (CC) of the principal components. A large value (close to 1.0) of the CC means that some of the degrees of freedom are fluctuating as the variables of free random walks on the time-scale of the present MD simulations. The FES built on principal components with CC close to 1.0 shows artifacts, i.e. basins which are signatures of the cosine shape of the principal components and not of an actual minimum of the FES <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hess1">[93]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Hess2">[94]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Maisuradze2">[119]</xref>. We computed the cosine content of each principal component <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4">[92]</xref>. The values of the cosine content computed for <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>dPC<sup>2</sup></italic> calculated from the covariance matrix in the space of the 27 dihedral angles having a converged FEP are very small (CC<sub>1</sub> = 0.11 and CC<sub>2</sub> = 0.16 for ATP1 trajectory for example). On the contrary, the cosine content of the principal component <italic>dPC<sup>1</sup></italic> computed in the space of all dihedral angles is very large (CC<sub>1</sub> = 0.69 for ATP1 trajectory for example).</p>
</sec><sec id="s4f">
<title>Pathway of minimum energy</title>
<p>The <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s013">Fig. S11</xref> A shows an example of a free-energy surface (FES) generated by projecting a MD trajectory on the essential plane defined by two principal components [<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003379.e012">Eq. (7)</xref>]. In this example, the FES has two minima <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic>. The pathway that connects the two minima <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic> by traveling along the “valleys” of the FES and going over the “passes” (which are saddle-points on the surface and correspond to the transition states) in order to minimize the free-energy difference while moving, is commonly referred to the Pathway of Minimum Energy (PME) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003379-No1">[120]</xref>. To find the PME for the transition <italic>A<sub>1</sub>→A<sub>2</sub></italic>, we applied the following methodology. First, an initial guess of the path is made, here the straight interpolation line <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> from <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic> to <italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic>. Secondly, we move from <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic> along the direction <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> by 0.1 (which is the bin size defined for the calculation of FES) and draw a segment <italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic> perpendicular to the direction <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic>. Note that the size of the segment <italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic> is chosen to belong to a circle of diameter <italic>A<sub>1</sub>A<sub>2</sub></italic>. Finally, we search along the segment <italic>p<sub>1</sub></italic> the bin with the minimum of free-energy, named <italic>s<sub>1</sub></italic>. This bin is also considered as the first step of the PME. We repeat the algorithm by constructing a straight interpolation line <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> from <italic>s<sub>1</sub></italic> to <italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic>. The algorithm ends after <italic>N</italic> steps when the distance between <italic>s<sub>N</sub></italic> and <italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic> is smaller than the size of the bin defined for the calculation of FES. The PME corresponds to the <italic>ensemble {s<sub>j</sub>}<sub>j = 1,..,N</sub></italic> and to the corresponding free-energy profile <italic>V<sup>PME</sup>(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s013">Fig. S11 B</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s001" mimetype="text/plain" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Dataset S1</label><caption>
<p>Cartesian coordinates of the nucleotide and of the protein for the initial structures of the ADP1 and ADP2 trajectories (Protein Data Bank format is used).</p>
<p>(TXT)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s002" mimetype="text/plain" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Dataset S2</label><caption>
<p>Cartesian coordinates of the nucleotide and of the protein for the initial structures of the ATP1 and ATP2 trajectories (Protein Data Bank format is used).</p>
<p>(TXT)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s003" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Definition of the coarse-grained dihedral angles (CGDAs) </bold><bold><italic>γ</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> A: Each angle <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> is built from the positions of 4 successive C<sup>α</sup> atoms. The CGDA <italic>γ</italic> varies between −180° and +180° with <italic>γ</italic> = 0° being chosen when C<sup>α</sup>(<italic>i−1</italic>) is <italic>cis</italic> to C<sup>α</sup>(<italic>i+2</italic>), and the clockwise rotation of C<sup>α</sup>(<italic>i+1</italic>)−C<sup>α</sup>(<italic>i+2</italic>) being positive when looking from C<sup>α</sup>(<italic>i</italic>) to C<sup>α</sup>(<italic>i+1</italic>). B: Free-Energy Profile (FEP) of <italic>γ<sub>213</sub></italic>.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s004" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Contact maps computed from the MD simulations.</bold> A: ATP-bound DnaK. B: ADP-bound DnaK. C: Contact map difference ATP/ADP (See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> section).</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s005" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Dissimilarity index between 1-D FEPs of CGDAs </bold><bold><italic>γ</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> Histograms showing FEP dissimilarity (<italic>1-H(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic>) along the amino-acid sequence (from <italic>γ<sub>5</sub></italic> to <italic>γ<sub>597</sub></italic>). FEPs of the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> strongly influenced (<italic>1-H</italic>&gt;0.7), significantly influenced (0.3≤<italic>1-H</italic>&lt;0.7) and weakly influenced (<italic>1-H</italic>≤0.3) by the nucleotide are colored in red, yellow and cyan, respectively. Top panel shows dissimilarities between the FEPs in the APO and the ADP-bound states; middle panel shows dissimilarities between the FEPs in the APO and the ATP-bound states, and the bottom panel shows dissimilarities between the FEPs in the ADP and the ATP-bound states. Subdomain boundaries are indicated with dashed lines.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s006" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Effective FEPs </bold><bold><italic>V(γ)</italic></bold><bold> of DnaK in </bold><bold><italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic></bold><bold> units in the three different nucleotide-binding states computed from MD simulations.</bold> Only the network of the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> revealed by the FEP analysis is represented here. The color code is the following: APO, red; ADP, blue and ATP, green.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s007" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p><bold>Representative structure of each minimum </bold><bold><italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic></bold><bold>, </bold><bold><italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic></bold><bold>, </bold><bold><italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic></bold><bold>, </bold><bold><italic>A<sub>4</sub></italic></bold><bold> and </bold><bold><italic>A<sub>5</sub></italic></bold><bold> extracted from the FES for the MD run ATP1.</bold> C<sup>α</sup> atoms belonging to the CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> with large influences are represented by spheres. The color code of the protein structure is the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. These figures were prepared with PyMOL [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>].</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s008" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S6</label><caption>
<p><bold>Effective FEPs </bold><bold><italic>V(γ)</italic></bold><bold> of ATP-bound DnaK in </bold><bold><italic>k<sub>B</sub>T</italic></bold><bold> units for the network of 27 CGDAs </bold><bold><italic>γ</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> The values of <italic>V(γ)</italic> for the most probable representative structure extracted from the MD runs ATP1 (<italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic>) and ATP2 (<italic>B<sub>3</sub></italic>) are shown with diamonds and triangles, respectively. The FEPs <italic>V(γ)</italic> were translated between −180° and +180° compared with <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003379.s006">Fig. S4</xref>.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s009" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S7</label><caption>
<p><bold>Trajectory along the PME (for the MD run ATP1) of each CGDA </bold><bold><italic>γ<sub>i</sub>(s<sub>j</sub>)</italic></bold><bold> and their corresponding FEP </bold><bold><italic>V(γ<sub>i</sub>)</italic></bold><bold>.</bold> Minima and saddle points along the PME (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003379-g009">Fig. 9</xref>) are represented by gray and red diamonds, respectively. The green diamond corresponds to the minimum <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic>.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s010" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S8</label><caption>
<p><bold>Dihedral principal component analysis applied to MD simulations of ATP-bound DnaK.</bold> Influences <italic>Δ<sub>i</sub><sup>1</sup></italic> and <italic>Δ<sub>i</sub><sup>2</sup></italic> of the 27 CGDAs <italic>γ</italic> extracted from dPCA of the MD run ATP1. The dashed line represents an influence of 10%.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s011" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s011" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S9</label><caption>
<p><bold>Representative structures of the minima and of the saddle points observed along the PME on the FES computed from dPCA applied to the MD run ATP1.</bold> At each step <italic>s<sub>j</sub></italic>, the CGDAs <italic>γ<sub>i</sub></italic> which have the same conformation as observed in the minimum <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic> are represented by green spheres and the others by red spheres. The ATP nucleotide is shown in blue spheres. These figures were prepared with PyMOL [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>].</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s012" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s012" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S10</label><caption>
<p><bold>Convergence analysis of MD trajectories.</bold> A: C<sup>α</sup> <italic>RMSD</italic> with respect to the initial structure computed for the MD runs APO1 (red), ADP1 (blue) and ATP1 (green) up to 250 ns. B: Variance σ of the C<sup>α</sup> <italic>RMSD</italic> with respect to the initial structure computed for the MD runs APO1 (red), ADP1 (blue) and ATP1 (green) on time windows of 10 ns and up to 250 ns.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s013" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s013" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S11</label><caption>
<p><bold>Pathway of minimum energy (PME) for the transition </bold><bold><italic>A<sub>1</sub>→A<sub>2</sub></italic></bold><bold>.</bold> A: FES generated for the MD run ATP1 from dPCA. Minima are shown with grey diamonds. The PME is shown with black cross and a red line. Interpolated lines <italic>d</italic> (dashed blue lines) and perpendicular lines <italic>p</italic> (dot-dashed green lines) are shown for the first three steps only. Empty black squares show the intersection between <italic>d</italic> and <italic>p</italic>. B: Free-energy profile <italic>V<sup>PME</sup></italic> along the PME shown in panel A.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003379.s014" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003379.s014" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Sequence alignment of human and </bold><bold><italic>E. coli</italic></bold><bold> Hsp70 s from BLASTp program.</bold> Identities are shown in bold and positives in italic. Residues of <italic>E. coli</italic> Hsp70 relevant for interdomain communication and extracted from the FEL analysis are underlined.</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Dr. Carmen Garrido and her team of the Centre de Recherche U866 de l'Institut National de la Santé et de la Recherche Médicale (INSERM), Dijon, for fruitful discussions on Heat-Shock proteins.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Cecchini1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cecchini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Houdusse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Allosteric Communication in Myosin V: From Small Conformational Changes to Large Directed Movements</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000129</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000129" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000129</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Saibil1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saibil</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Chaperone machines in action</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sbi.2007.11.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.sbi.2007.11.006</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Monod1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wyman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Changeux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title>On the nature of allosteric transitions: A plausible model</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Kumar1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nussinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Folding and binding cascades: dynamic landscapes and population shifts</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1110/ps.9.1.10" xlink:type="simple">10.1110/ps.9.1.10</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Gunasekaran1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunasekaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nussinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Is allostery an intrinsic property of all dynamic proteins?</article-title> <source>Proteins</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/prot.20232" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/prot.20232</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Monod2"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Changeux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Allosteric proteins and cellular control systems</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Tsai1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Del Sol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nussinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Protein allostery, signal transmission and dynamics: a classification scheme of allosteric mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Mol Biosyst</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/b819720b" xlink:type="simple">10.1039/b819720b</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Ihee1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ihee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajagopal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Šrajer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pahl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Visualizing reaction pathways in photoactive yellow protein from nanoseconds to seconds</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>7145</fpage>–<lpage>7150</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0409035102" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0409035102</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Tzeng1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>S-R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalodimos</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Protein dynamics and allostery: an NMR view</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sbi.2010.10.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.sbi.2010.10.007</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Horovitz1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horovitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willison</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Allosteric regulation of chaperonins</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>646</fpage>–<lpage>651</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sbi.2005.10.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.sbi.2005.10.001</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Manley1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loria</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>NMR insights into protein allostery</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source> <volume>519</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.abb.2011.10.023" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.abb.2011.10.023</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuravleva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Allosteric signal transmission in the nucleotide-binding domain of 70-kDa heat shock protein (Hsp70) molecular chaperones</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>6987</fpage>–<lpage>6992</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1014448108" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1014448108</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Zhuravleva2"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuravleva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clerico</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>An interdomain energetic tug-of-war creates the allosterically active state in Hsp70 molecular chaperones</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>1296</fpage>–<lpage>1307</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2012.11.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2012.11.002</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Benkovic1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benkovic</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammes-Schiffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Enzyme Motions Inside and Out</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>312</volume>: <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1127654" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1127654</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-HenzlerWildman1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henzler-Wildman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Dynamic personalities of proteins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>450</volume>: <fpage>964</fpage>–<lpage>972</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature06522" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature06522</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Bakan1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The intrinsic dynamics of enzymes plays a dominant role in determining the structural changes induced upon inhibitor binding</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>14349</fpage>–<lpage>14354</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0904214106" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0904214106</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Frauenfelder1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frauenfelder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Conformational Substates in Proteins</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Biophysics and Biophysi Chem</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>479</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.bb.17.060188.002315" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.bb.17.060188.002315</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Swain1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The changing landscape of protein allostery</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sbi.2006.01.003" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.sbi.2006.01.003</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-McCammon1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gelin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of folded proteins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>267</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/267585a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/267585a0</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Karplus1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular dynamics simulations of biomolecules</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>646</fpage>–<lpage>652</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nsb0902-646" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nsb0902-646</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Dror1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dror</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dirks</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Biomolecular Simulation: A Computational Microscope for Molecular Biology</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Biophysics</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-biophys-042910-155245" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-biophys-042910-155245</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Morra1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verkhivker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Modeling Signal Propagation Mechanisms and Ligand-Based Conformational Dynamics of the Hsp90 Molecular Chaperone Full-Length Dimer</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000323</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000323" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000323</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Nicola1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolaï</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delarue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Human Inducible Hsp70: Structures, Dynamics, and Interdomain Communication from All-Atom Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title>. <source>J Chem Theory Comput</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>2501</fpage>–<lpage>2519</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ct1002169" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/ct1002169</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Skjaerven1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skjaerven</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teigen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Conformational Sampling and Nucleotide-Dependent Transitions of the GroEL Subunit Probed by Unbiased Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002004</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002004" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002004</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Chiappori1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiappori</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merelli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milanesi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular Mechanism of Allosteric Communication in Hsp70 Revealed by Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002844</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002844" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002844</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Sliozberg1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sliozberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Spontaneous Conformational Changes in the E. coli GroEL Subunit from All-Atom Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1906</fpage>–<lpage>1916</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1529/biophysj.107.108043" xlink:type="simple">10.1529/biophysj.107.108043</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Shaw1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maragakis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindorff-Larsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dror</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Atomic-level characterization of the structural dynamics of proteins</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>330</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1187409" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1187409</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Chow1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Chow E, Klepeis JL, Rendleman CA, Dror RO, Shaw DE (2012) 9.6 New Technologies for Molecular Dynamics Simulations. In: Edward H. Egelman, editor. Comprehensive Biophysics. Amsterdam: Elsevier. pp. 86–104. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9780123749208009085" xlink:type="simple">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9780123749208009085</ext-link>. Accessed 4 April 2013.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Duan1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kollman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Pathways to a protein folding intermediate observed in a 1-microsecond simulation in aqueous solution</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>282</volume>: <fpage>740</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Adcock1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adcock</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Molecular Dynamics: Survey of Methods for Simulating the Activity of Proteins</article-title>. <source>Chem Rev</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1589</fpage>–<lpage>1615</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/cr040426m" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/cr040426m</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Nicola2"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolaï</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delarue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Conformational dynamics of full-length inducible human Hsp70 derived from microsecond molecular dynamics simulations in explicit solvent</article-title>. <source>J Biomol Struct Dyn</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1111</fpage>–<lpage>1126</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/07391102.2012.726190" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/07391102.2012.726190</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Volkman1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkman</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wemmer</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Two-state allosteric behavior in a single-domain signaling protein</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>291</volume>: <fpage>2429</fpage>–<lpage>2433</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.291.5512.2429" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.291.5512.2429</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Ma1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sigler</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A dynamic model for the allosteric mechanism of GroEL</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>302</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/jmbi.2000.4014" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/jmbi.2000.4014</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Wereszczynski1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wereszczynski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCammon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Nucleotide Dependent Mechanism of Get3 as Revealed by Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>240a</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2011.11.1324" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bpj.2011.11.1324</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Pfaendtner1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfaendtner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Branduardi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voth</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide-dependent conformational states of actin</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>12723</fpage>–<lpage>12728</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0902092106" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0902092106</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Hartl1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>FU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bracher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Molecular chaperones in protein folding and proteostasis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>475</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature10317" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature10317</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Goa1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gołaś</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisuradze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ołdziej</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czaplewski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Simulation of the Opening and Closing of Hsp70 Chaperones by Coarse-Grained Molecular Dynamics</article-title>. <source>J Chem Theory Comput</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1750</fpage>–<lpage>1764</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ct200680g" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/ct200680g</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Gerstein1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A database of macromolecular motions</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>4280</fpage>–<lpage>4290</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Hayward1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berendsen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Systematic analysis of domain motions in proteins from conformational change: new results on citrate synthase and T4 lysozyme</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Tobi1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Structural changes involved in protein binding correlate with intrinsic motions of proteins in the unbound state</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>18908</fpage>–<lpage>18913</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0507603102" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0507603102</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Dobbins1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbins</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lesk</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>MJE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Insights into protein flexibility: The relationship between normal modes and conformational change upon protein-protein docking</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>10390</fpage>–<lpage>10395</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0802496105" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0802496105</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Nashine1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nashine</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammes-Schiffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benkovic</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Coupled motions in enzyme catalysis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Chem Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>–<lpage>651</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cbpa.2010.07.020" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cbpa.2010.07.020</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Louet1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Louet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perahia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Floquet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A concerted mechanism for opening the GDP binding pocket and release of the nucleotide in hetero-trimeric G-proteins</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>411</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2011.05.034" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2011.05.034</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Cui1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karplus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A normal mode analysis of structural plasticity in the biomolecular motor F(1)-ATPase</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>340</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>372</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2004.04.044" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2004.04.044</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Daily1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daily</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhyaya</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Contact rearrangements form coupled networks from local motions in allosteric proteins</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/prot.21800" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/prot.21800</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Tama1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tama</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanejouand</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Conformational change of proteins arising from normal mode calculations</article-title>. <source>Protein Eng</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/protein/14.1.1" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/protein/14.1.1</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Gaillard1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dejaegere</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stote</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of beta3 integrin I-like and hybrid domains: insight from simulations on the mechanism of transition between open and closed forms</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>994</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/prot.22404" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/prot.22404</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Gaillard2"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>San Sebastian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cossío</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Comparative normal mode analysis of LFA-1 integrin I-domains</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>374</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2007.07.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2007.07.006</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Nicola3"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Nicolaï A, Delarue P, Senet P (2013) Low-Frequency, Functional, Modes of Proteins: All-Atom and Coarse-Grained Normal Mode Analysis. In: Liwo A, editor. Computational Methods to Study the Structure and Dynamics of Biomolecules and Biomolecular Processes. Springer Series in Bio-/Neuroinformatics. Springer Berlin Heidelberg. pp. 483–524. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-642-28554-7_15" xlink:type="simple">http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-642-28554-7_15</ext-link>. Accessed 19 September 2013.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Bukau1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horwich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Molecular chaperones and protein quality control</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2006.04.014" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2006.04.014</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Bukau2"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deuerling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pfund</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Getting Newly Synthesized Proteins into Shape</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80806-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80806-5</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Hartl2"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>FU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular Chaperones in the Cytosol: from Nascent Chain to Folded Protein</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>295</volume>: <fpage>1852</fpage>–<lpage>1858</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1068408" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1068408</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Young1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agashe</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siegers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>FU</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Pathways of chaperone-mediated protein folding in the cytosol</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrm1492" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrm1492</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Parsell1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The function of heat-shock proteins in stress tolerance: degradation and reactivation of damaged proteins</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genet</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>496</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ge.27.120193.002253" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ge.27.120193.002253</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Young2"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barral</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich Hartl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>More than folding: localized functions of cytosolic chaperones</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tibs.2003.08.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.tibs.2003.08.009</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Mayer1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Hsp70 chaperones: cellular functions and molecular mechanism</article-title>. <source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>670</fpage>–<lpage>684</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00018-004-4464-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00018-004-4464-6</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Schmitt1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehrmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Multhoff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Intracellular and extracellular functions of heat shock proteins: repercussions in cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1189/jlb.0306167" xlink:type="simple">10.1189/jlb.0306167</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Selkoe1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Folding proteins in fatal ways</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>426</volume>: <fpage>900</fpage>–<lpage>904</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature02264" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nature02264</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Garrido1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zermati</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Heat shock proteins 27 and 70: anti-apoptotic proteins with tumorigenic properties</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>2592</fpage>–<lpage>2601</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Livesay1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livesay</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreth</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fodor</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A critical evaluation of correlated mutation algorithms and coevolution within allosteric mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source> <volume>796</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage> <comment>doi:_<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-61779-334-921" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/978-1-61779-334-9_21</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Ha1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Kinetics of nucleotide-induced changes in the tryptophan fluorescence of the molecular chaperone Hsc70 and its subfragments suggest the ATP-induced conformational change follows initial ATP binding</article-title>. <source>Biochem</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>11635</fpage>–<lpage>11644</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Moro1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Saiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The allosteric transition in DnaK probed by infrared difference spectroscopy. Concerted ATP-induced rearrangement of the substrate binding domain</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1110/ps.051732706" xlink:type="simple">10.1110/ps.051732706</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-McCarty1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchberger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The role of ATP in the functional cycle of the DnaK chaperone system</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>249</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/jmbi.1995.0284" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/jmbi.1995.0284</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Vogel1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Allosteric regulation of Hsp70 chaperones involves a conserved interdomain linker</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>38705</fpage>–<lpage>38711</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M609020200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M609020200</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Swain2"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dinler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sivendran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stotz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Hsp70 chaperone ligands control domain association via an allosteric mechanism mediated by the interdomain linker</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2007.02.020" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2007.02.020</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Bhattacharya1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kurochkin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>GNB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertelsen</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Allostery in Hsp70 chaperones is transduced by subdomain rotations</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>388</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>490</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2009.01.062" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2009.01.062</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Kumar2"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vorvis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarbeng</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabra Ledesma</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The four hydrophobic residues on the Hsp70 inter-domain linker have two distinct roles</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>411</volume>: <fpage>1099</fpage>–<lpage>1113</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2011.07.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2011.07.001</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Vogel2"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Allosteric regulation of Hsp70 chaperones by a proline switch</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2005.12.017" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2005.12.017</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Kityk1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kityk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinning</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Structure and dynamics of the ATP-bound open conformation of Hsp70 chaperones</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>863</fpage>–<lpage>874</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2012.09.023" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2012.09.023</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Bertelsen1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertelsen</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gestwicki</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuiderweg</surname><given-names>ERP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Solution conformation of wild-type E. coli Hsp70 (DnaK) chaperone complexed with ADP and substrate</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>8471</fpage>–<lpage>8476</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0903503106" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0903503106</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Senet1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Senet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisuradze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foulie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delarue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheraga</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>How main-chains of proteins explore the free-energy landscape in native states</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>19708</fpage>–<lpage>19713</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0810679105" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0810679105</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Cote1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delarue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisuradze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheraga</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Anomalous diffusion and dynamical correlation between the side chains and the main chain of proteins in their native state</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>10346</fpage>–<lpage>10351</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1207083109" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1207083109</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Cote2"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Senet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delarue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisuradze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheraga</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nonexponential decay of internal rotational correlation functions of native proteins and self-similar structural fluctuations</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>19844</fpage>–<lpage>19849</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1013674107" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1013674107</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Altis1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hegger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Dihedral angle principal component analysis of molecular dynamics simulations</article-title>. <source>J Chem Phys</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>244111</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.2746330" xlink:type="simple">10.1063/1.2746330</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Amadei1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amadei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linssen</surname><given-names>ABM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berendsen</surname><given-names>HJC</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Essential dynamics of proteins</article-title>. <source>Proteins: Structure, Function, and Bioinformatics</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>412</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/prot.340170408" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/prot.340170408</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Kitao1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Investigating protein dynamics in collective coordinate space</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0959-440X(99)80023-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0959-440X(99)80023-2</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Lange1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grubmüller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Full correlation analysis of conformational protein dynamics</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1294</fpage>–<lpage>1312</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/prot.21618" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/prot.21618</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Flaherty1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeLuca-Flaherty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Three-dimensional structure of the ATPase fragment of a 70 K heat-shock cognate protein</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>346</volume>: <fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>628</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/346623a0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/346623a0</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Zhu1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burkholder</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gragerov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Structural analysis of substrate binding by the molecular chaperone DnaK</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>272</volume>: <fpage>1606</fpage>–<lpage>1614</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Hunt1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Conserved features of eukaryotic hsp70 genes revealed by comparison with the nucleotide sequence of human hsp70</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>6455</fpage>–<lpage>6459</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Schlecht1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlecht</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erbse</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mechanics of Hsp70 chaperones enables differential interaction with client proteins</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nsmb.2006" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nsmb.2006</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Wilbanks1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilbanks</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuruta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Solution small-angle X-ray scattering study of the molecular chaperone Hsc70 and its subfragments</article-title>. <source>Biochem</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>12095</fpage>–<lpage>12106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Shi1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Conformational characterization of DnaK and its complexes by small-angle X-ray scattering</article-title>. <source>Biochem</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>3297</fpage>–<lpage>3308</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/bi951984l" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/bi951984l</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Mapa1"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mapa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sikor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kudryavtsev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waegemann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalinin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The conformational dynamics of the mitochondrial Hsp70 chaperone</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2010.03.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.03.010</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Marcinowski1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcinowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Höller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feige</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baerend</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Substrate discrimination of the chaperone BiP by autonomous and cochaperone-regulated conformational transitions</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nsmb.1970" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nsmb.1970</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Liu1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Insights into Hsp70 Chaperone Activity from a Crystal Structure of the Yeast Hsp110 Sse1</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2007.08.039" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cell.2007.08.039</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Schuermann1"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuermann</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuellar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Llorca</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Structure of the Hsp110:Hsc70 nucleotide exchange machine</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>232</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2008.05.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.05.006</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Kampinga1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kampinga</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The HSP70 chaperone machinery: J proteins as drivers of functional specificity</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrm2941" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/nrm2941</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Johnson1"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Mapping the role of active site residues for transducing an ATP-induced conformational change in the bovine 70-kDa heat shock cognate protein</article-title>. <source>Biochem</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>10823</fpage>–<lpage>10830</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/bi990816g" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/bi990816g</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Montgomery1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Mutations in the substrate binding domain of the Escherichia coli 70 kda molecular chaperone, DnaK, which alter substrate affinity or interdomain coupling</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>–<lpage>932</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/jmbi.1998.2514" xlink:type="simple">10.1006/jmbi.1998.2514</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Smock1"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smock</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivoire</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russ</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leibler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An interdomain sector mediating allostery in Hsp70 molecular chaperones</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>414</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/msb.2010.65" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/msb.2010.65</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Nicola4"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Nicolaï A. (2012) Conformational dynamics and free-energy landscape of human and E. coli Hsp70 chaperones from all-atom and coarse-grained numerical simulations [PhD thesis]. Dijon: Université de Bourgogne.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Hess1"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Similarities between principal components of protein dynamics and random diffusion</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>8438</fpage>–<lpage>8448</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.62.8438" xlink:type="simple">10.1103/PhysRevE.62.8438</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Hess2"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Convergence of sampling in protein simulations</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>031910</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.65.031910" xlink:type="simple">10.1103/PhysRevE.65.031910</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Sousa1"><label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The hydroxyl of threonine 13 of the bovine 70-kDa heat shock cognate protein is essential for transducing the ATP-induced conformational change</article-title>. <source>Biochem</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>15392</fpage>–<lpage>15399</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/bi981510x" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/bi981510x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-OBrien1"><label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Lysine 71 of the chaperone protein Hsc70 Is essential for ATP hydrolysis</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>15874</fpage>–<lpage>15878</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Buchberger1"><label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchberger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theyssen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schröder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCarty</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Virgallita</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide-induced conformational changes in the ATPase and substrate binding domains of the DnaK chaperone provide evidence for interdomain communication</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>16903</fpage>–<lpage>16910</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Rist1"><label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rist</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Amide Hydrogen Exchange Reveals Conformational Changes in Hsp70 Chaperones Important for Allosteric Regulation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>16493</fpage>–<lpage>16501</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M600847200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M600847200</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Liu2"><label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bahar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Role of Hsp70 ATPase Domain Intrinsic Dynamics and Sequence Evolution in Enabling its Functional Interactions with NEFs</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1000931</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000931" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000931</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Burkholder1"><label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkholder</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrickson</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gragerov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Mutations in the C-terminal fragment of DnaK affecting peptide binding</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>10632</fpage>–<lpage>10637</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Swain3"><label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gierasch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Direct comparison of a stable isolated Hsp70 substrate-binding domain in the empty and substrate-bound states</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>1605</fpage>–<lpage>1611</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M509356200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M509356200</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Davis1"><label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voisine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Intragenic suppressors of Hsp70 mutants: interplay between the ATPase- and peptide-binding domains</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>9269</fpage>–<lpage>9276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Aponte1"><label>103</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aponte</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Directed evolution of the DnaK chaperone: mutations in the lid domain result in enhanced chaperone activity</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>399</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2010.03.060" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2010.03.060</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-FernndezSiz1"><label>104</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Sáiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arizmendi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acebrón</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Ionic contacts at DnaK substrate binding domain involved in the allosteric regulation of lid dynamics</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>7479</fpage>–<lpage>7488</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M512744200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M512744200</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-VanderSpoel1"><label>105</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Van der Spoel D, Lindhal E, Hess B, van Buuren AR, Apol E, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2011) Gromacs User Manual version 4.5.5. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gromacs.org" xlink:type="simple">www.gromacs.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Gunsteren1"><label>106</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gunsteren WFV (1996) Biomolecular Simulation: GROMOS 96 Manual and User Guide. Verlag der Fachvereine Hochschulverlag AG an der ETH Zurich. 1044 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Scott1"><label>107</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WRP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hünenberger</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tironi</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billeter</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The GROMOS Biomolecular Simulation Program Package</article-title>. <source>J Phys Chem A</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>3596</fpage>–<lpage>3607</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/jp984217f" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/jp984217f</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Berendsen1"><label>108</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berendsen</surname><given-names>HJC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>JPM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Gunsteren</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiNola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Molecular dynamics with coupling to an external bath</article-title>. <source>J Chem Phys</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>3684</fpage>–<lpage>3690</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1063/1.448118" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1063/1.448118</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Darden1"><label>109</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>York</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Particle mesh Ewald: An Nlog(N) method for Ewald sums in large systems</article-title>. <source>J Chem Phys</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>10089</fpage>–<lpage>10092</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1063/1.464397" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1063/1.464397</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Schttelkopf1"><label>110</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schüttelkopf</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Aalten</surname><given-names>DMF</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>PRODRG: a tool for high-throughput crystallography of protein–ligand complexes</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr Section D Biol Crystallogr</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1355</fpage>–<lpage>1363</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S0907444904011679" xlink:type="simple">10.1107/S0907444904011679</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Osipiuk1"><label>111</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osipiuk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joachimiak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Structure of a new crystal form of human Hsp70 ATPase domain</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>1105</fpage>–<lpage>1107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Humphrey1"><label>112</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>VMD: Visual molecular dynamics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Graphics</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0263-7855(96)00018-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0263-7855(96)00018-5</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Berendsen2"><label>113</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Berendsen HJC, Postma JPM, van Gunsteren WF, Hermans J (1981) Intermolecular Forces. Intermolecular Forces. Dordrecht: D. Reidel. p. 331.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Sriram1"><label>114</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sriram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osipiuk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joachimiak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Human Hsp70 molecular chaperone binds two calcium ions within the ATPase domain</article-title>. <source>Structure</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Arakawa1"><label>115</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arakawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Handa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shirouzu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Biochemical and structural studies on the high affinity of Hsp70 for ADP</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1367</fpage>–<lpage>1379</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/pro.663" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/pro.663</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Wisniewska1"><label>116</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wisniewska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karlberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehtiö</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotenyova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Crystal structures of the ATPase domains of four human Hsp70 isoforms: HSPA1L/Hsp70-hom, HSPA2/Hsp70-2, HSPA6/Hsp70B', and HSPA5/BiP/GRP78</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e8625</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0008625" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0008625</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Nishikawa1"><label>117</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Momany</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheraga</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Low-Energy Structures of Two Dipeptides and Their Relationship to Bend Conformations</article-title>. <source>Macromolecules</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>797</fpage>–<lpage>806</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ma60042a020" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/ma60042a020</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Maisuradze1"><label>118</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisuradze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leitner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Free energy landscape of a biomolecule in dihedral principal component space: sampling convergence and correspondence between structures and minima</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>569</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/prot.21344" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/prot.21344</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-Maisuradze2"><label>119</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisuradze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liwo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheraga</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Principal component analysis for protein folding dynamics</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>385</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2008.10.018" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jmb.2008.10.018</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003379-No1"><label>120</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Noé</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ille</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Automated computation of low-energy pathways for complex rearrangements in proteins: application to the conformational switch of Ras p21</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>534</fpage>–<lpage>544</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/prot.20422" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/prot.20422</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>